<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schimmels</surname></persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">710B85FC60FA81A3709CA4A43828C31E</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T04:53+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Eigenscrew Decomposition of Spatial Stiffness Matrices Shuguang Huang, Member, IEEE, and Joseph M. Schimmels, Member, IEEE Abstract-In this paper, the structure of spatial stiffness is investigated by evaluating the stiffness matrix "primitives"-the rank-1 matrices that compose a spatial stiffness matrix.</p><p>Although the decomposition of a rank-2 or higher stiffness matrix into the sum of rank-1 matrices is not unique, one property of the set of matrices is conserved. This property, defined as the stiffness-coupling index, identifies how the translational and rotational components of the stiffness are related. Here, we investigate the stiffness-coupling index of the rank-1 matrices that compose a spatial stiffness matrix. We develop a matrix decomposition that yields a set of rank-1 stiffness matrices that identifies the bounds on the stiffness-coupling index for any decomposition. This decomposition, referred to as the eigenscrew decomposition, is shown to be invariant in coordinate transformation. With this decomposition, we provide some physical insight into the behavior associated with a general spatial stiffness matrix.</p><p>Index Terms-Multidimensional impedance, spatial compliant behavior, spatial stiffness and compliance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>I N THIS paper, we address the structure of general spatial stiffness matrices. In our investigation, a manipulator system is modeled as a kinematically unconstrained rigid body suspended by elastic devices. If each individual elastic device is linear and the mechanism deflection from its equilibrium position is small, the spatial force-deflection behavior of the model is characterized by a 6 6 positive semidefinite (PSD) matrix, the spatial stiffness matrix.</p><p>This work is motivated by the improved reliability in automated assembly that can be attained through the proper design of a robot manipulator's multidirectional impedance (frequency-dependent stiffness behavior) and the related synthesis problem. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, the space of multidirectional spatial impedances that improve robot relative positioning capability has been identified. More recently <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, procedures for the synthesis of any prescribed spatial stiffness behavior have been presented. Each of the synthesis procedures is based on a decomposition of a stiffness matrix into rank-1 matrices. Here, we evaluate the bounds on the stiffness behavior associated with the rank-1 matrices obtained in any decomposition.</p><p>This work is also motivated by the desire for a better physical appreciation of spatial compliant behavior. Although the structure of a purely translational or a purely rotational nonspatial stiffness is well known, the structure of a general spatial stiffness is not. For example, if a purely translational system (a particle suspended by a system of springs) is considered, the force/deflection relationship can be equivalently and uniquely represented by a set of three line springs obtained by an eigenvalue decomposition of the stiffness matrix. These springs have the following properties: 1) the spring directions (determined by the three eigenvectors of the stiffness matrix) are orthogonal to each other; 2) the spring stiffnesses (determined by the three eigenvalues) in these directions identify the extreme stiffness values (i.e., the most "stiff" axis is along one direction of the three springs and the most "compliant" axis is along another); and 3) the largest of the three stiffnesses identifies the upper bound on the stiffness constants that may be used to realize the stiffness matrix with any set of springs. This interpretation is intuitive and uniquely describes the structure of the system compliance. However, as shown in this paper, it cannot be directly generalized to the spatial case.</p><p>In this paper, the structure of system compliance is analyzed by decomposing the spatial stiffness matrix into its simplest spatial components-rank-1 spatial stiffness matrices. A unique (coordinate system invariant) decomposition based on a modified stiffness eigenvalue problem is developed. This decomposition (the eigenscrew decomposition) identifies the basic structure of the stiffness and provides a physical interpretation of spatial elastic behavior. Although performed differently, this eigenscrew decomposition yields results analogous to those associated with the eigenvalue decomposition for the purely translational case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Related Work</head><p>Many authors have investigated the compliance or stiffness characteristics of a rigid body suspended by elastic devices. A review of existing spatial stiffness analysis and synthesis methods is provided below.</p><p>General spatial stiffness behavior was first analyzed in 1900 when Ball <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> introduced the theory of screws and used it to describe the motion of a rigid body in a general spatial potential field. He showed that, for a body with degrees of freedom in a potential field, there exist principal screws that are real and reciprocal.</p><p>Later, Dimentberg <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> applied screw theory to the analysis of the static and dynamic behavior of an elastically suspended body. The elastic behavior of the suspended body was characterized by six screws obtained by unit translations of the body along three mutually perpendicular directions and unit rotations of the body about three given axes parallel to them. In his description of the stiffness mapping, ray coordinates were assigned to both the wrench (force and torque) and the twist (angular displacement and translational displacement). As a consequence, the stiffness matrix is neither symmetric nor positive definite.</p><p>In more recent work using screw theory, Griffis and Duffy <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and Patterson and Lipkin <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> have evaluated nonsingular spatial stiffness behavior. In their work, the stiffness mapping normally parameterizied by a 6 6 symmetric positive definite stiffness matrix (using ray coordinates and axis coordinates to describe the wrench and twist, respectively) was transformed into an asymmetric stiffness matrix (using axis (ray) coordinates for both the wrench and twist). It was shown that, with this transformation, the symmetric stiffness matrix becomes Dimentberg's asymmetric stiffness matrix. Analysis of the resulting asymmetric matrix showed that its eigenvalues and eigenvectors are preserved in coordinate transformation. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, the eigenvectors were shown to be the principle screws of Ball <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, and a number of propositions which characterize the eigenstructure of the stiffness/compliance matrix were proved. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, stiffness behavior was classified based on results obtained from the modified eigenvalue problem.</p><p>Loncaric also has analyzed spatial stiffness/compliance matrices, but used Lie algebra rather than screw theory. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, Loncaric showed that, in the generic case, a stiffness matrix can be expressed in a "normal form" (for which rotational and translational aspects are maximally decoupled) if an appropriate coordinate frame is chosen. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, he showed that the space of stiffness matrices that can be achieved with a parallel connection of line springs is restricted.</p><p>In previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, we showed that the space of spatial stiffnesses achieved with line springs and torsional springs connected in parallel is bounded (a 20-dimensional hyperplane in the PSD matrix cone) and provided a procedure for the realization of any matrix on the hyperplane. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, we showed that, in a decomposition of an arbitrary spatial stiffness matrix, there must exist some rank-1 components that couple translational and rotational stiffness along an axis and that no more than three such components are required for the realization of an arbitrary spatial stiffness matrix.</p><p>Here, we investigate the structure of general spatial stiffnesses (including singular cases). We investigate the properties of the stiffness matrix "primitives," the rank-1 PSD matrices that compose the spatial stiffness matrix, using a decomposition of the stiffness matrix based on the modified stiffness eigenvalue problem posed by Griffis and Duffy <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and Patterson and Lipkin <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Overview</head><p>In this paper, we investigate the coordinate system invariant properties of a spatial stiffness matrix. The primary contributions of this work are as follows: 1) the development of a unique decomposition of a spatial stiffness matrix that identifies the extremes in the translational/rotational coupling behavior of the stiffness matrix and 2) a physical appreciation of the results.</p><p>Section II addresses the decomposition of a spatial stiffness matrix into rank-1 stiffness matrices. A coordinate system in-variant quantity that identifies the translational/rotational coupling behavior, the "stiffness-coupling index," is defined. The limitations of the conventional eigenvalue decomposition of a matrix in developing a physical appreciation of its spatial stiffness behavior are identified.</p><p>Section III develops a new decomposition of a stiffness matrix based on the modified stiffness eigenvalue problem. It is shown that any rankstiffness matrix can be decomposed into rank-1 stiffness matrices associated with the eigenstiffnesses and eigenscrews (the eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the modified stiffness eigenvalue problem, respectively). A physical appreciation of this decomposition is provided.</p><p>In Section IV, the "extremal" properties of the eigenstiffnesses associated with any specified stiffness matrix are identified. It is shown that the stiffness-coupling indices of the rank-1 stiffness matrices that compose a specified stiffness matrix are bounded by the eigenstiffnesses of the specified stiffness matrix. Section V presents a numerical example of the spatial stiffness eigenscrew decomposition and its associated extremal characteristics.</p><p>Section VI relates the results obtained from the eigenscrew decomposition to the results obtained from the eigenvalue decomposition of a purely translational matrix and presents a summary of this work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. STIFFNESS MATRIX DECOMPOSITION</head><p>It is known that any rank-PSD matrix can be decomposed into a sum of rank-1 PSD matrices, i.e., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> where each is a rank-1 symmetric PSD matrix. For a stiffness matrix with rank , the rank-1 decomposition is not unique <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Here, we seek to find a decomposition that uniquely describes the physical characteristics of the stiffness matrix. To achieve our objective, the description of its behavior must not change as a result of coordinate frame transformation.</p><p>In this section, the properties of the rank-1 matrices obtained in a rank-1 decomposition of a spatial stiffness matrix are reviewed. An important property that reflects the "coupling" behavior of the stiffness translational and rotational components, the "stiffness-coupling index," is identified and shown to be an invariant to coordinate system transformation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Rank-1 PSD Matrices</head><p>If in ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) is a rank-1 PSD matrix, then can be represented in the form <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> where is a constant and is a unit wrench defined as the spring wrench <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. For a rank-1 , this expression is unique except for a sign change of .</p><p>We have shown <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> that every rank-1 stiffness matrix can be uniquely represented by the spatial force-deflection characteristics of a single spring that allows six degrees of freedom but provides compliant constraint along one degree of freedom. This representation is independent of coordinate frame or length scaling used to describe the stiffness matrix. The representation also identifies a means of realizing any rank-1 stiffness matrix with a single spring.</p><p>If the spring wrench is represented by , , , and a small deflection from the spring equilibrium position is represented by , then the wrench associated with deflection obtained from the spatial forcedeflection relation is</p><p>In can be seen that the translational component and rotational component can be totally decoupled if and only if, in an appropriate coordinate frame, or . This decoupling condition is equivalent to the condition that the spring wrench is isotropic, i.e., satisfies</p><p>where ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>)</p><p>This condition can be equivalently imposed on any rank-1 PSD matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> as</p><p>Physically, this condition indicates that the wrench due to this spatial compliant behavior is always a pure force or a pure couple, and this property is invariant to coordinate transformation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Stiffness-Coupling Index</head><p>Since the quantity reflects the translation-rotation coupling characteristics of a rank-1 stiffness matrix , we define it here as the stiffness-coupling index of .</p><p>The stiffness-coupling index of a rank-1 stiffness matrix has the following properties.</p><p>1) If ( ), then identifies its stiffness-coupling index, an invariant to coordinate transformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>2) If a rank-1 PSD matrix is represented by a single spring with stiffness constant and unit spring wrench , then the stiffness-coupling index is , where <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Since a rank-1 stiffness matrix can be uniquely represented by a single spring with stiffness and coupling between force and torque indicated by , we define the stiffness-coupling index of as the stiffness-coupling index of the spring that realizes . It was shown <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> that if the stiffness-coupling index is zero, the matrix can be realized with a simple spring, a conventional line spring, or conventional torsional spring; if the stiffness-coupling index is nonzero, the matrix can be realized with a screw spring, a spring that provides a force and a torque in the same direction, and is the pitch of the spring wrench. Since the stiffness-coupling index of a rank-1 stiffness matrix is , the stiffness-coupling index of a rank-1 stiffness matrix is equal to twice the force caused by a unit rotation about the spring wrench axis. As such, the stiffness-coupling index of a spring measures the force applied to the spring when the displacement is a unit rotation about the spring axis.</p><p>The concept of stiffness-coupling index can be generalized to a stiffness matrix of arbitrary rank. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, the following was shown.</p><p>1) The quantity is an invariant for any PSD matrix, i.e., is independent of coordinate frame used to describe the stiffness matrix.</p><p>2) The quantity vanishes if and only if can be decomposed into the sum of rank-1 matrices that have zero stiffness-coupling indices. As such, for a PSD matrix of arbitrary rank, we define as the stiffness-coupling index, an invariant property of the spatial stiffness matrix.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Rank-1 Decomposition</head><p>As stated previously, the decomposition of a rank-2 or higher PSD matrix into the sum of rank-1 PSD matrices is not unique. The most common method for decomposing a general PSD matrix is the conventional eigenvalue decomposition obtained using the eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the PSD matrix.</p><p>If is a rank-symmetric PSD, then it must have positive eigenvalues . If are the corresponding unit eigenvectors of , then can be expressed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> Thus, the stiffness matrix is decomposed into the sum of rank-1 PSD matrices.</p><p>As the eigenvectors of are orthogonal, it can be seen that every two rank-1 matrices in ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) satisfy <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> Conversely, it can be proved that if a PSD matrix is decomposed into the sum of rank-1 PSD matrices that satisfy <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, the decomposition must be the eigenvalue decomposition of <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> Although unique for any given description of a PSD matrix, the eigenvalue decomposition depends on the coordinate frame used to describe the stiffness matrix. In a specified coordinate frame, the stiffness mapping is expressed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> where is a small change in position/orientation (twist), and is the force/torque (wrench) associated with . If a coordinate transformation is performed, then in the new coordinate frame, the stiffness matrix is <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> where has the form <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> where is a 3 3 rotation matrix and is the 3 3 antisymmetric matrix associated with translation.</p><p>The coordinate transformation of ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) is a congruence transformation. Since is, in general, not orthogonal, the stiffness matrix does not preserve the eigenvalues and eigenvectors in coordinate transformation.</p><p>The main limitation of the eigenvalue decomposition is that because the decomposition changes if the coordinate frame changes, the conventional eigenvalue decomposition does not identify any fundamental physical properties of the stiffness matrix. Another limitation is that although the eigenvectors obtained from the conventional eigenvalue problem of are orthogonal in the six-vector space , they are not necessarily reciprocal as screws.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. EIGENSCREW DECOMPOSITION</head><p>In this section, a new decomposition of a stiffness matrix of arbitrary rank is developed based on a modified eigenvalue problem. Unlike the conventional eigenvalue decomposition, this decomposition is uniquely determined by the compliance relationship of the system (for the generic case) and is independent of the coordinate frame used to describe the stiffness matrix.</p><p>Below, we do the following: 1) identify the modified stiffness eigenvalue problem (the eigenscrew problem) on which this unique decomposition (eigenscrew decomposition) is based; 2) define the eigenscrew decomposition for the full-rank case; 3) define the eigenscrew decomposition for the singular case; and 4) identify the uniqueness and physical significance of this decomposition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Stiffness Eigenscrew Problem</head><p>First, the modified stiffness eigenscrew problem presented by Griffis and Duffy <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and Patterson and Lipkin <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> is reviewed below.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>, is a twist deformation in axis coordinates, while is a wrench in ray coordinates. Both Griffis and Duffy <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and Patterson and Lipkin <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> noted that for coordinate frame independence, the formulation of the eigenvalue problem should have both quantities represented in the same coordinates to preserve the integrity of the units. To accomplish this, a transformation between the axis coordinates and ray coordinates is used.</p><p>The transformation matrix defined in (4) interchanges the first and last three components of a screw, thus changes a screw in axis coordinates to a screw in ray coordinates. Also, for any coordinate transformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, it is readily shown that or equivalently . Hence, for the stiffness matrix This means and are similar and thus have the same eigenvalues. Therefore, preserves the eigenvalues under coordinate transformation. As such, the eigenscrew problem of the spatial stiffness matrix is formulated as <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> The eigenvalue in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> was defined by Griffis and Duffy <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> as the eigenstiffness of the stiffness matrix and the six-vector (screw) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> was defined as its corresponding eigenscrew of . Patterson and Lipkin <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> observed that if is full-rank, the eigenscrew problem of (11) yields the following properties:</p><p>1) has three positive and three negative eigenstiffnesses; 2) has a full set of eigenscrews with nonzero, finite pitches; 3) the eigenscrews of are reciprocal, i.e., , ; 4) the pitch of an eigenscrew has the same sign as the corresponding eigenstiffness. It is important to understand the relationship between the stiffness-coupling index of a stiffness matrix and its corresponding eigenstiffnesses. For an arbitrary stiffness matrix, the stiffness-coupling index is the sum of all eigenstiffnesses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Eigenscrew Decomposition</head><p>Below, a decomposition based on the eigenscrew problem ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>) is developed. First, the decomposition of a full-rank spatial stiffness matrix is presented. The result is then generalized to a spatial stiffness matrix of arbitrary rank.</p><p>1) Eigenscrew Decomposition of a Full-Rank Stiffness Matrix: Let be a full-rank stiffness matrix and be the eigenscrews corresponding to eigenstiffnesses , , obtained from the eigenscrew problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>. Below, we prove that With some additional modification, the decomposition in ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>) can be represented as the stiffness and pitch weighted sum of the dyads involving the spring wrench.</p><p>If we denote then, since is nonisotropic, . Then and where is a unit screw with pitch . Therefore and the stiffness-coupling index of can be obtained Therefore, for any full-rank stiffness matrix, we have the following eigenscrew decomposition.</p><p>Eigenscrew Decomposition: Let be a full-rank stiffness matrix with eigenstiffnesses and corresponding unit eigenscrews , and let be the pitch of , . Then can be decomposed into the form <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> where ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) is a rank-1 PSD matrix with stiffness-coupling index of .</p><p>The eigenscrew decomposition states that any full-rank stiffness matrix can be decomposed into six rank-1 stiffness matrices involving the dyads of the six eigenscrews. Each rank-1 component in the decomposition has the stiffness-coupling index identical to the corresponding eigenstiffness. In fact, is the only nonzero eigenstiffness of , and is the only nontrivial eigenscrew (except for a scalar multiple) of associated with . Due to the reciprocal property of eigenscrews, any two rank-1 components and in the eigenscrew decomposition must satisfy (15) Conversely, it is readily proved that if a full-rank stiffness matrix is decomposed into a sum of rank-1 matrices (16) with every combination of two components and satisfying (15), then the decomposition of ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) must be identical to the eigenscrew decomposition of (13), i.e., the number of rank-1 components in (16) must be 6 (</p><p>) and each rank-1 PSD matrix must be identical to the rank-1 matrix defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>. This property of the eigenscrew decomposition is analogous to that of the conventional eigenvalue decomposition of (6).</p><p>As the eigenstiffnesses and eigenscrews of a stiffness matrix are independent of coordinate frame, the eigenscrew decomposition of a full-rank stiffness matrix is uniquely determined by the spatial compliant behavior.</p><p>2) General Stiffness Matrices: The decomposition of ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) can be generalized to a PSD stiffness matrix of arbitrary rank. If a PSD matrix is rank-, then has at most nonzero eigenvalues. Unlike the conventional eigenvalue problem of a symmetric matrix, a nonzero nonsymmetric stiffness matrix (</p><p>) may have all of its eigenvalues equal to zero. Results of the analysis of this special case are summarized below.</p><p>If is a PSD matrix with all of its eigenstiffnesses equal to zero, then the following can be proved <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>:</p><p>1) ; 2) any decomposition of into a sum of rank-1 PSD matrices yields a set of matrices in which each is isotropic and is an eigenscrew of associated with a zero eigenstiffness. It can be seen that any PSD component in a decomposition of must have a zero-valued stiffness-coupling index. Since the decomposition of is not unique for , any decomposition of preserves this property no matter how the stiffness matrix is decomposed.</p><p>In general, some of the eigenstiffnesses may be zero, but most are not. It can be proved <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> that if the algebraic multiplicity of a nonzero eigenstiffness is , then there exist independent eigenscrews associated with the eigenstiffness. Thus, if a stiffness matrix has nonzero eigenstiffnesses, it must have independent eigenscrews, and these eigenscrews are reciprocal.</p><p>Suppose that is a rank-PSD matrix with nonzero eigenstiffnesses and ( ) zero eigenstiffnesses; and that is the unit eigenscrews with pitch corresponding to . If we denote (17) then, the following can be proved <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>:</p><p>1) is a PSD matrix with rank ; 2) all eigenstiffnesses of are zero; 3) if is decomposed into the sum of , then each is an eigenscrew of associated with its zero eigenstiffness. Therefore, if is decomposed to the sum of rank-1 PSD matrices (18) then each is isotropic and is an eigenscrew of associated with one of its zero eigenstiffnesses (regardless of how is decomposed). An easy way to decompose is to use the conventional eigenvalue decomposition used in Section II-C.</p><p>The following decomposition is valid for any spatial stiffness matrix.</p><p>Generalized Eigenscrew Decomposition: If a rank-PSD matrix has nonzero eigenstiffnesses , and are the corresponding unit eigenscrews with pitch , then has isotropic eigenscrews associated with its zero eigenstiffnesses such that can be decomposed into the form (19)</p><p>The generalized eigenscrew decomposition states that a rank-stiffness matrix can be decomposed into rank-1 components of which components have nonzero stiffness-coupling indices and are along the nonisotropic eigenscrews ; while the other components have zero stiffness-coupling indices and are along isotropic eigenscrews associated with its zero eigenstiffnesses.</p><p>It is proved <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> that every combination of two rank-1 matrices in this decomposition (19) satisfies (15). Also, like the full-rank case, it can be proved that if a rank-stiffness matrix is decomposed into the sum of rank-1 PSD matrices ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) with every two rank-1 matrices satisfying (15), then the decomposition must be an eigenscrew decomposition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Uniqueness of the Eigenscrew Decomposition</head><p>The eigenscrew decomposition of a stiffness matrix is based on the eigenscrews and eigenstiffnesses of the stiffness matrix. Since the eigenscrews and eigenstiffnesses of a stiffness matrix are unique for the generic case, the eigenscrew decomposition is unique for "almost all" stiffness matrices. A of all cases is provided below.</p><p>Let be a rank-stiffness matrix with nonzero eigenstiffnesses and zero eigenstiffnesses. First, we discuss the rank-1 components associated with nonzero eigenstiffnesses.</p><p>If the nonzero eigenstiffnesses are distinct, then the eigenscrew subspace corresponding to each eigenstiffness is one-dimensional (scalar multiple of the same eigenvector). Thus, each unit eigenscrew in ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>) is unique. This means that each rank-1 component associated with a nonzero eigenstiffness is unique.</p><p>If is an eigenstiffness of multiplicity ( ), then, as we stated previously, there are corresponding independent eigenscrews that span the eigenscrew subspace. Any vector in this subspace is an eigenscrew of associated with . Thus, the eigenscrews associated with are not unique. This means that the rank-1 components in (19) are not unique.</p><p>For the stiffness matrix , suppose that the nonzero eigenstiffnesses are distinct, then 1) if (the generic case), the eigenscrew decomposition is unique; 2) if , the eigenscrew decomposition is also unique; 3) if , the eigenscrew decomposition is nonunique. The first statement is obvious from (17) in which must be the zero matrix. The second statement also can be obtained from (17) in which is rank-1 and cannot be decomposed further. In the third case, since the rank of is greater than 1, the decomposition of is not unique. The decomposition is nonunique iff .</p><p>In application, full-rank stiffness matrices are of most interest. Since a full-rank stiffness matrix always has six nonzero eigenstiffnesses <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> that in the generic case are distinct, the eigenscrew decomposition is unique.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Physical Significance of the Eigenscrew Decomposition</head><p>Below, the physical significance of the eigenscrew decomposition for a generic stiffness matrix is established.</p><p>Consider a rank-( ) stiffness matrix , for the generic case, has nonzero eigenstiffnesses (i.e., ). Let be the pitch of corresponding eigenscrew, then . If we denote then by the generalized eigenscrew decomposition (20) Since are unit wrenches, (20) indicates that can be interpreted by a body suspended by screw springs <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> each with spring wrench and spring constant . It can be seen that the stiffness constant of each screw spring is independent of the coordinate frame used to describe the stiffness matrix. Also, the stiffness-coupling index of each screw spring (</p><p>) identifies the corresponding eigenstiffness of ( ). This provides the physical appreciation of the eigenscrews and eigenstiffnesses of .</p><p>In summary, we have the following.</p><p>In the generic case, a rank-stiffness matrix can be uniquely represented by a rigid body suspended by screw springs. Each screw spring has a spring wrench identical to the unit eigenscrew and has a stiffness constant uniquely determined by the corresponding eigenstiffnesses and pitch of the eigenscrew. Since any full-rank stiffness matrix has six nonzero eigenstiffnesses, this interpretation of a stiffness matrix is valid for all full-rank stiffness matrices. Next, we prove that among all the rank-1 decompositions of a stiffness matrix, the stiffness-coupling indices obtained in the eigenscrew decomposition take "extremal" values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. BOUNDS ON THE STIFFNESS-COUPLING INDICES</head><p>In this section, the "extremal" property of the eigenscrew decomposition is investigated. We show that, if a stiffness matrix is decomposed into the sum of rank-1 PSD matrices, the stiffness-coupling index of each rank-1 matrix must be bounded by the eigenstiffnesses of .</p><p>It is well known that the eigenvalues of a symmetric PSD matrix indicate extremal values of the matrix properties (as in the spring constants for the purely translational stiffness matrix). Here, we show that the eigenvalues of a nonsymmetric matrix also indicate extremal properties. To do this, we first transform the eigenvalue problem on the nonsymmetric matrix into an eigenvalue problem on a symmetric non-PSD matrix. Next, the extremal properties of the eigenvalues obtained from the symmetric matrix are investigated. The analysis of a full-rank stiffness matrix is presented. Extension of these results to the nonfull-rank case is discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Transformation of the Eigenvalue Problem</head><p>As previously noted, although both and are symmetric, is not, in general, symmetric. However, because is a symmetric PSD matrix, it can be written as . This property enables us to transform the nonsymmetric eigenvalue problem into a symmetric one. In fact, we have the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 4.1: If a PSD matrix is expressed as , where</p><p>, then the symmetric matrix and have the same nonzero eigenvalues. Proof: It can be shown <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> that for any </p><p>Therefore, a decomposition yields a rank-1 decomposition of (and vice versa). Since the rank-1 decomposition of a PSD matrix is not unique, the matrix is not unique. Theorem 4.1 states that, no matter what decomposition is conducted to , the eigenvalue problem of the symmetric matrix always yields the same nonzero eigenstiffnesses of . It should be noted that the matrix is not a PSD matrix in general.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Full-Rank Case</head><p>Below, we prove that the stiffness-coupling index of each rank-1 matrix in the decomposition of a full-rank stiffness matrix is bounded by the matrix eigenstiffnesses regardless of the type of decomposition performed.</p><p>A full-rank stiffness matrix has three positive and three negative eigenstiffnesses. Since sign and relative magnitude are important in subsequent analysis, we sort the eigenstiffnesses of as follows:</p><p>(23) Suppose a full-rank stiffness matrix is decomposed into the sum of ( ) rank-1 PSD (24)</p><p>where each has stiffness-coupling index . Below, we identify the bounds on the coupling indices for the following: 1) any single rank-1 component, 2) any two rank-1 components, and 3) any combination of rank-1 components.</p><p>1) Extremal Stiffness-Coupling Index for a Single Rank-1 Component: Let be the stiffness-coupling index for each rank-1 matrix in (24). We prove that and . Also, it can be proved <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> that in the generic case , a stiffness-coupling index of a rank-1 PSD in the decomposition (24) achieves the upper bound only if the matrix is along the corresponding eigenscrew , i.e.,</p><p>The same is true for the lower bound in the generic case, . </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Generalization</head><p>The results for full-rank stiffness matrices can be generalized to a spatial stiffness matrix of arbitrary rank.</p><p>Unlike full-rank stiffness matrices that have three positive and three negative eigenstiffnesses, a general PSD matrix has six eigenstiffnesses (some of which may be zero). However, it can be shown <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> that for any PSD matrix, the number of nonzero eigenstiffnesses that have the same sign is no greater than 3. This means that a PSD matrix always has three nonnegative and three nonpositive eigenstiffnesses. Therefore, we can use the notation , and to designate the six eigenstiffnesses of such that Using the same notation and the generalized eigenscrew decomposition, the results in Theorem 4.2 can be generalized to a stiffness matrix of arbitrary rank. The strict proof can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. NUMERICAL EXAMPLE</head><p>In this section, we provide a numerical example to illustrate the eigenscrew decomposition. The stiffness matrix considered is This stiffness matrix has been used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> as an example to illustrate the synthesis of stiffness matrix with a parallel connection of springs. With a procedure presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, is realized with six springs, among which three are simple springs (with stiffness-coupling indices of 0) and the other three are screw springs (with stiffness-coupling indices of 12, 6, and</p><p>). Here, we apply the eigenscrew decomposition to the same .</p><p>By solving the eigenvalue problem of (11) for the given , the six eigenstiffness , the six corresponding unit eigenscrews , and the eigenscrew pitches obtained are shown in (26), at the bottom of the page.</p><p>Since each of 's is nonisotropic, by the procedure addressed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, six screw springs are obtained. For each screw spring, the spring constant is determined by , the geometrical connection of the spring of springs is determined by the eigenscrew (spring wrenches)</p><p>, and the pitch of helical joint (in length/rotation) used in the screw spring is determined by . The physical properties and geometrical connections of these six screw springs are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref>. Each screw spring is defined by its spring constant , helical joint pitch (in length/rotation), and geometrical connection parameters ( and ), where (a unit vector) indicates the direction of the spring axis and identifies the direction and distance to the line of action. Table I also includes the stiffness-coupling index for each spring.</p><p>The six screw springs system yielded by the eigenscrew decomposition reflects the eigenstructure of the stiffness matrix: the six spring wrenches are reciprocal, and the largest and the smallest stiffness-coupling indices of the six screw springs take the extremal values for all the stiffness-coupling indices of springs that realize the same stiffness matrix. Unlike the other procedures represented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, the eigenscrew decomposition always generates the same six screw springs no matter what coordinate frame is chosen to describe . Note that, in this example, the stiffness-coupling indices for the springs obtained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> are bounded by the minimum and maximum stiffness-coupling indices ( 22.5805 and 30.1683, respectively) obtained by the eigenscrew decomposition. These are the bounds on the stiffness-coupling indices for any decomposition of this .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. DISCUSSION AND SUMMARY</head><p>This paper provides a description of spatial stiffness structure based on an evaluation of the primitive components of a general stiffness matrix. The principal result of this paper is the development of a unique decomposition of a spatial stiffness matrix that identifies the extremes in the translational/rotational coupling behavior of the stiffness matrix. This result provides the basis for a better physical appreciation of a general stiffness mapping. Below, we provide this by noting the analogies between purely translational stiffness behavior and general spatial stiffness behavior.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Comparison of Translational and Spatial Stiffness</head><p>Consider again the general purely translational compliant behavior associated with a particle suspended by an arbitrary number of line springs. For this case, the stiffness is characterized by a 3 3 PSD matrix. The stiffness relationship, for the generic case, can be interpreted by three specific springs [illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1(a)</ref>] with the following properties:</p><p>1) the directions of the three springs are orthogonal and the geometries and stiffness constants of the three springs are uniquely determined by the eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the stiffness matrix;</p><p>(26) 2) any motion along the axis of a single spring leads to a force along the same axis (the other two springs are not involved); 3) the most "stiff" and the most "compliant" axes must be along two directions of the three springs; 4) if a set of springs realizes a specified stiffness matrix, then the spring constant of any spring in the set must be bounded by , the largest stiffness constant of the three springs. This interpretation is obvious and intuitive, since only translational displacement and force are involved in this system. These properties, however, cannot be directly generalized to spatial stiffnesses.</p><p>Spatial stiffness differs from the purely translational stiffness in two significant ways. First, in the spatial case, the compliance resists force and torque along/about the same axis. As a consequence, a general spatial stiffness cannot be achieved with only simple springs connected in parallel. Second, the conventional eigenvalue problem cannot be applied to spatial cases. The direction of a twist is determined by its rotational component (the last three elements), while the direction of a wrench is determined by its force component (the first three elements). Therefore, the fact that two six-vectors and are in the same direction in does not necessarily mean the two screws are collinear in physical space.</p><p>Using the results developed here, an interpretation of spatial stiffness analogous to that obtained for the purely translational case is obtained. Instead of considering simple springs and their spring constants, we consider screw springs and their stiffness-coupling indices (i.e., , the product of spring constant and pitch of the spring wrench<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">1</ref> ). Thus, in the generic case, the spatial stiffness relationship for any given 6 6 stiffness matrix can be interpreted by six specific screw springs with the following properties:</p><p>1) the six spring wrenches are reciprocal, and the geometry and stiffness-coupling index of each spring are uniquely determined by the eigenscrews and eigenstiffnesses of the stiffness matrix; 2) any motion (twist) along one spring wrench only leads to a wrench along the same screw (the other five screw springs are not involved); 3) the maximum and minimum values of the stiffness-coupling indices are along two spring wrenches of the six screw springs; 4) if a set of springs realizes a specified stiffness matrix, then the quantity of any spring in the set must be bounded by and of the six screw springs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Summary</head><p>In this paper, we have done the following:</p><p>• developed a decomposition of a spatial stiffness matrix based on the stiffness eigenscrew problem that indicates the relationship between the eigenstiffnesses, the eigenscrews, and the stiffness matrix; • investigated the "extremal" property of the eigenstiffness and found that the eigenstiffnesses of a stiffness matrix established the bounds on the stiffness-coupling indices of rank-1 PSD components that compose a specified stiffness matrix; • provided a physical interpretation of a spatial stiffness which is analogous to that of a simple purely translational case. The results we presented here are valid for all spatial stiffness matrices (including singular matrices).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>are independent, is of full rank. Because the eigenscrews of are reciprocalare full-rank matrices Because is a diagonal matrix with diagonal entries ( ), the above equation yields (12) immediately.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of a matrix. Since and are characteristic polynomials for and , respectively, they must have the same nonzero roots (including repetitions). Therefore, and have the same nonzero eigenvalues, and the algebraic multiplicities of a nonzero in and are identical. It should be clear that, since the dimensions of and may be different, the two matrices may have a different number of eigenvalues. The matrix always has six eigenvalues; while [ ] has eigenvalues. For instance, if is of full-rank, has six nonzero eigenvalues; then and has the same six eigenvalues with all other ( ) eigenvalues being zero. If we denote as the th column of , then</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>discussed in Section II-B If we denote then is symmetric, and, by Theorem 4.1, has the same six nonzero eigenvalues as , . In the following, we use the notation to designate the th largest eigenvalue of a symmetric matrix. Thus, for any symmetric matrix If we denote as the th leading principal minor of the matrix and as the th largest eigenvalue of , then, by the interlacing property of [3], we have But therefore To obtain the lower bound, we consider the matrix , then are nonzero eigenvalues of , and , thus For , exchange the positions of and in (25) to obtain the same result. Hence, we have: Since identifies the stiffness-coupling index of , the above equation means that any stiffness-coupling index is bounded by</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>2 )</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Extremal Stiffness-Coupling Index for Any Two Rank-1 Components: Below, we prove the sum of any two coupling indices is bounded by and . Since the six nonzero eigenstiffnesses of are eigenvalues of and all other eigenvalues of (if any) are zero, must be the second largest eigenvalue of . By the interlacing property of , we have But, since thus The lower bound can be obtained by considering the symaddition of and is bounded by and . Since we can arrange any and to the positions of and , this inequality holds for all . 3) Extremal Stiffness-Coupling Index for Any Combination of Rank-1 Components: Let ( numbers arbitrarily chosen from , by the same procedure as in Section IV-B-2, it can be shown that Since has three positive eigenvalues and three negative eigenvalues, and the remaining eigenvalues are zero, for . Therefore Applying the same procedure to yields This states that an addition of stiffness-coupling indices (no matter how many) is bounded by and . 4) Summary: In summary, the results obtained in Sections IV-B-1-IV-B-3 can be stated as the following theorem. Theorem 4.2: If a full-rank stiffness matrix is decomposed into a sum of ( ) rank-1 PSD matrices with stiffnesscoupling indices</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Comparison of spatial stiffness with the pure translational case. (a) Illustrates an interpretation of translational compliant behavior. The particle is suspended by three translational springs associated with the eigenvectors and eigenvalues of the stiffness matrix. (b) Illustrates an interpretation of spatial compliant behavior. The rigid body is suspended by six screw springs associated with the eigenscrews and eigenstiffnesses of the stiffness matrix.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE I INTERPRETATION</head><label>I</label><figDesc>OF K BASED ON EIGENSCREW DECOMPOSITION. SIX SCREW SPRINGS ARE ALONG THE SIX EIGENSCREWS OF K</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Manuscript received January 8, 1998; revised October 5, 1998. This paper was recommended for publication by Associate Editor J. Wen and Editor S. Salcudean upon evaluation of the reviewers' comments.The authors are with the Department of Mechanical and Industrial Engineering, Marquette University, Milwaukee, WI 53201-1881 USA (e-mail: j.schimmels@marquette.edu).Publisher Item Identifier S 1042-296X(00)03428-5.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_1"><p>For simple springs, the spring wrenches are isotropic, s = 0.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>S'90-M'91) received the B.S. degree in mechanical engineering from Marquette University, Milwaukee, WI, in 1981, and the M.S. and Ph.D. degrees in mechanical engineering from Northwestern University, Evanston, IL, in 1988 and 1991, respectively.</p><p>From 1981 to 1987, he was with Exxon Production Research Company, Houston, TX, as a Reservoir Engineer. In 1991, he became an Assistant Professor in the Department of Mechanical and Industrial Engineering, Marquette University, where he is presently an Associate Professor. His general research interests are in the assessment, analysis, and design of desirable multidirectional and nonlinear dynamic behavior (spatial mechanical impedances). Current applications in the robotics area focus on manufacturing tasks such as assembly and material removal.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Treaties on the Theory of Screws</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ball</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1900">1900</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, U.K.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The screw calculus and its applications in mechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dimentberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>FTD-HT-23-1632-67</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Foreign Technology Division</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
			<pubPlace>Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, OH, Doc</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Golub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F V</forename><surname>Loan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Matrix Computations</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Baltimore, MD</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The Johns Hopkins Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinestatic control: A novel theory for simultaneously regulating force and displacement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Griffis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Duffy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mech. Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="508" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-12">Dec. 1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the cone of positive semidefinite matrices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Waters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Linear Algebra Applicat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The analysis and synthesis of spatial compliance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<pubPlace>Milwaukee, WI</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Marquette Univ.</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Achieving an arbitrary spatial stiffness with springs connected in parallel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schimmels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mech. Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="520" to="526" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The bounds and realization of spatial stiffnesses achieved with simple springs connected in parallel</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="475" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-06">June 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Geometrical analysis of compliant mechanisms in robotics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Loncaric</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Harvard Univ.</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Normal forms of stiffness and compliance matrices</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-12">Dec. 1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A classification of robot compliance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Patterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lipkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mech. Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="581" to="584" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-09">Sept. 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of robot compliance</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mech. Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="576" to="580" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-09">Sept. 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A linear space of admittance control laws that guarantees force-assembly with friction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schimmels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="656" to="667" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-10">Oct. 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Admittance matrix design for force guided assembly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schimmels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Peshkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-04">Apr. 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He worked as an Assistant Professor in the Department of Engineering Mechanics at Tsinghua University</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shuguang</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">respectively, and the Ph.D. degree in mechanical engineering from Marquette University</title>
		<title level="s">M&apos;98) received the B.S. degree in mechanics the M.S. degree in theoretical me</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Beijing, China; Milwaukee, WI; Beijing, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984. 1986. 1998. 1986 to 1993</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>chanics from Peking University ; Research Assistant Professor in the Department of Mechanical and Industrial Engineering, Marquette University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>His general interests are classical mechanics, dynamics, and control of robotic systems</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
