<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">When a City Tells a Story: Urban Topic Analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Felix</forename><surname>Kling</surname></persName>
							<email>felix.kling.2012@nuim.ie</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">National Centre for Geocomputation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National University of Ireland Maynooth</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Co. Kildare</addrLine>
									<country key="IE">Ireland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexei</forename><surname>Pozdnoukhov</surname></persName>
							<email>alexei.pozdnoukhov@nuim.ie</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">National Centre for Geocomputation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National University of Ireland Maynooth</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Co. Kildare</addrLine>
									<country key="IE">Ireland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">When a City Tells a Story: Urban Topic Analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A4656071732ED18931C646DBD24F52E0</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T04:47+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>H</term>
					<term>2</term>
					<term>8 [Database Management]: Database Applicationsdata mining location-based social networks, urban dynamics</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper explores the use of textual and event-based citizengenerated data from services such as Twitter and Foursquare to study urban dynamics. It applies a probabilistic topic model to obtain a decomposition of the stream of digital traces into a set of urban topics related to various activities of the citizens in the course of a week. Due to the combined use of implicit textual and movement data, we obtain semantically rich modalities of the urban dynamics and overcome the drawbacks of several previous attempts. Other important advantages of our method include its flexibility and robustness with respect to the varying quality and volume of the incoming data. We describe an implementation architecture of the system, the main outputs of the analysis, and the derived exploratory visualisations. Finally, we discuss the implications of our methodology for enriching location-based services with real-time context.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Digital traces of citizen activities in a city contain abundant detail on various aspects of urban dynamics. The space-time dynamics imprinted in such streams originate from a mixture of processes inherent to complex technosocial systems. A comprehensive analysis of these processes would need to bring together research in social networks, human mobility, of individual behaviours and spatial interaction and, finally, natural language models for semantic content extraction and representation. This paper investigates space-time dynamics of check-in information from services such as Foursquare <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> , distributed over the micro-blogging service Twitter<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> . These time-stamped and geo-tagged events can be used to quantify the intensities of urban activities within a particular area and time period. They also contain user generated content and venue information from the check-in services, which can be used to determine the semantics behind these activities.</p><p>We have applied probabilistic topic modelling to obtain a decomposition of the stream of digital traces of citizens into a set of city-scale activities which we call urban topics. We argue that understanding the semantic content of what makes the reason for a visit or check-in at a particular destination is central both to the fundamental studies of space-time dynamics of cities <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr">8]</ref> and for building efficient semantic data structures behind location-based city information systems. Due to the combined use of implicit textual and location data, we obtain semantically rich modalities of urban dynamics.</p><p>The novelty of this study and its main findings can be summarised as follows:</p><p>• Probabilistic topic modelling <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1]</ref> was applied to the combined data on check-in events and text messages as described in Section 4.</p><p>• A topic model was trained on an averaged week activity for a data set of several months collected for New York area, USA. Several interpretable topics in space and time were identified and analysed (Section 5). The extension of the analysis of city areas usage with temporally varying profiles which characterise the intensities of within-day activities is the first of its kind.</p><p>• A post-processing scheme was introduced to compute and visualise the functional profile diagrams of the neighbourhoods (Section 5.4). The use of the diagrams to define a similarity metric for enhancing locationbased services is discussed.</p><p>• Clustering of city areas and visualisation of the functional structure of the neighbourhoods was proposed as a city exploratory tool. This representation overcomes certain limitations of the previous approaches as discussed in Section 5.5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">TOPIC MODELS</head><p>We hypothesise that citizen-generated data that captures urban dynamics can be represented in a form of topics that are characterised by particular space-time regularities in the co-occurrence of individual actions of the city dwellers. Regularly co-occurring check-ins at a given set of venues within particular hours with associated textual comments containing food related content indicate the "lunch break" activity in a given space-time interval. It is natural to assume that these activities co-exist and several such activities are usually going on within every area of a city. Moreover, every venue, as well as any given word used by a users to describe their actions can be associated with several activities.</p><p>A baseline and powerful topic model is Latent Dirichlet Allocation (LDA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1]</ref>. It is a Bayesian probabilistic model of documents that assumes a collection of K "topics" defined as a multinomial distribution over the given vocabulary. No restriction is implied on the nature of the vocabulary which may consist of discrete events of arbitrary etymology. Topics are assumed to have been drawn from a Dirichlet distribution, β k ∼ Dirichlet(η) and are defined as a distribution over the vocabulary entries. Documents d are assumed to be generated from the topics with the following generative process. First a distribution is drawn over topics θ d ∼ Dirichlet(α). Then, for each entry i in the document, a topic index z di ∈ {1, ...K} is drawn from the topic weights z di ∼ θ d and finally the observed entry (a "word") w di ∼ θz di is drawn from the selected topic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">DATA</head><p>Foursquare allows users to share their location publicly or with friends, by letting them check in at venues. Users can connect their Twitter account with Foursquare to let an automatic message be sent on their behalf whenever they check in.</p><p>The dataset used in this study contains about 740, 000 tweets, both user-and automatically generated by Foursquare, in the area of New York City subtracted from a dataset described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref>. There are a total of 38, 300 unique venues and 20, 500 unique users in the dataset which spans from August to mid December 2010.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>Both the word per topic probabilities derived from LDA training and topic proportions in the documents obtained from LDA inference are used for the analysis of Section 5. An implementation described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> was used in the experiments. LDA hyper-parameters α and β which control the sparsity of topics and words mixtures, and the "optimal" number of topics K are related, as by increasing sparsity in representation (decreasing β) one would also require more topics to account for this variation. A relevant strategy described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref> is to fix the values of α and β and vary the number of topics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Dictionary and documents composition</head><p>Every check-in action at a particular venue can be considered as a "word" within a document. Co-occurrence of check-in events would mean that they are semantically close in terms of urban dynamics: all restaurants and night clubs would appear within the same topic while check-ins at venues co-occurring around midday may indicate their prevalence to be popular places for a lunch break. Venues can be a part of several topics as well as words of natural language. We included the location ID of each check-in as a word into the dictionary and corresponding documents without making any distinctions between check-in IDs and the words of natural language at model training and inference stages.</p><p>LDA expects a set of documents (a corpus) to learn from. We aggregated all tweets into a time frame of one "average" week and considered a set of samples within each hour as a single document. The analysis of the evolution of topics in the course of a week will provide us with an idea of the dynamics of various modalities of a city over time.</p><p>It is through the analysis of words one can reveal semantic behind the topics, give them names and associate with particular events. In our case the topic is defined as a distribution over words of the natural language as well as a set of geo-referenced check-in venues. Therefore, the topics can be analysed both in space-time as well as via word clouds. The membership of a check-in location in a particular topic can help to contextualise place recommendation systems with real-time information on how a particular venue is being used by city dwellers and not a default static category as assigned in a POI database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">EXPERIMENTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Timeline</head><p>Each hour of the week is considered to be a document. By inferring on the training data, we get to know the topic distribution per hour. The number of topics defines the granularity with which the city dynamics are explored. Previous studies have shown that an exploration of a large number of topics can reveal localised events from the Twitter stream <ref type="bibr">[8]</ref>. In this work we are interested in generic modalities and large-scale activities regularly shared by a majority of citizens. With a small number of topics, we are able to get a general view on the space-time dynamics. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> show the topic distribution per hour for five topics.</p><p>Both cases show a day-night pattern and a periodicity for each topic. The topic intensities and durations on the weekend are clearly distinct from the weekdays. This suggest a shift of activities which coincides with expectations from common sense.</p><p>A more detailed analysis with five topics reveals a decomposition of daily activities into morning (Topic 5), midday/lunch time (Topic 2) and evening (Topic 1) activities. We can also see two topics with lower intensities and substantial intensity changes during the time of the day or day of the week (Topic 3 and 4). This leads to the assumption that the contents of these topic is less situational depended, which will be verified by the semantic analysis of the words with strong membership in these topics. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Word Clouds</head><p>Although the time analysis uncovers promising temporal patterns, a semantic analysis is necessary to confirm the validity of the topic distribution. That is, during the different times of the day, we expect to see different frequencies of distinctive words, which can be reasonably related to the characteristic activities in these time periods. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows the word clouds 3 for the morning topic (Topic 5). The size of each word is proportional to the probability of it belonging to the given topic.</p><p>The trend of each topic is evident and coincides with our expectations from the time analysis. In the morning, where people typically commute to work, we can find words related to transportation, such as "station", "airport" and "mta", but also morning activities, such as drinking a "coffee".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Heat maps</head><p>To examine the spatial extent and variations of topics throughout the city, we arrange the locations people tweeted from or checked in on a heat map. The probability distribution of all topics over all locations is used as intensity of the particular location in the heat map.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> on the left shows a heat map of the "morning" topics. In accordance to our observations of the word clouds, locations of transportation facilities are associated with the "morning" topic. The "evening" heat map shows a higher intensity in East Village, Manhattan, which is popular for its night-life opportunities. Also within our expectations is the spatial pattern of the "noise" . The noise does not show any temporal variations, does not form a coherent subject and is not restricted to certain geographical area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Functional diagrams</head><p>Running inference for check-ins collected at particular localities in a time interval helps uncovering functional profiles of the area. That is, we aim to uncover how a given locality is being used by city dwellers: whether it is a night life area, an office district or a residential suburb, or a mixture of the latter, and, if so, when the area is being predominantly used in a particular way. To speed up the processing we have done inference from a global model and used locally weighted word-per-topic probabilities to estimate topic mixture in particular localities of 250 meters in an hourly time segment. We then presented the daily evolution of area usage with an alluvial diagram, a visualisation technique we derived inspired by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>.</p><p>The following principle is applied to construct a diagram. Every time slice consists of a set of locations which at the current moment in time belong to a given topic. A sequence of topic membership in time is presented as a wide stripe.</p><p>Transitions between topics (links between stripes in a diagram) indicate that a given proportion of venues in the area have switched their function between respective topics (that is, a situation when a coffee shop popular for coffee in the morning is also selling sandwiches during a lunch break). Such diagram can be constructed to highlight a particular features in transition between disjoint time periods or a difference between weekday and weekday profiles for the same area. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> illustrates a profile for the Staten Island area for particular hours of the day on a weekday and weekend.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Functional regions</head><p>Despite some limitations discussed in the introduction, clustering of city areas into functional regions can appear to be a useful representation. For example, one could be interested in delineating the areas similar in terms of activities therein at a given time period on a weekend or weekday. It can be obtained by applying a clustering method to the functional profiles described above. Clustering has to be performed in the functional diagram space according to the query of interest. For example, the Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> presents the results of spectral clustering <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref> applied to the 38, 000 profiles (as presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>) computed for all the areas centred at popular venues. One can notice both spatially contiguous and disjoint clusters indicating areas of similar usage at various localities. Analogous results can be obtained to represent areas of a similar function for particular time periods on a weekday/weekend according to the query of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have shown how patterns in structure and function of urban areas can be extracted from the crowdsourced data of citizen activities using a probabilistic topic model. High temporal granularity and large volume of check-in data available through Twitter stream allowed us to step beyond traditional spatial zoning representation of the land use. We have derived functional diagrams for city areas which characterise its dynamics in a course of the day. This representation was found to be useful both to derive advanced visualisations and to serve to introduce a similarity metric to enrich location-based services. Explicit use of user-generated textual content has enhanced the interpretability and usability of the observed urban topics.</p><p>A number of pathways could be investigated to improve the methodology. Several extensions to the baseline LDA model were developed recently for tracking temporally-varying content (for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12]</ref>). With these methods, one would avoid the pre-defined temporal aggregation used for document composition and derive continuous time models which better account for the temporal variations of topics. The baseline topic model could be elaborated in more detail to account for the impact of spatial heterogeneity in behaviours and mobility of citizens. While a global model was found to perform well experimentally, there is distinct spatial stratification both in social structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref> and mobility flows <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref> which could be accounted for within an advanced probabilistic topic models framework.</p><p>Since we revealed how city modalities change over time and space, the step beyond an offline analysis to a real time online analysis seems to be reasonable. That is, given sufficient data volumes, one could infer the composition of the current state of a city in real time using the derived topic model, which can also be updated as new data becomes available to accommodate long-term temporal drift.</p><p>In conclusion, we believe that besides uncovering new opportunities in enhancing location-based services the developed approach will find its use in the quantitative datadriven fundamental studies of structure and dynamics of cities.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Five topics: temporal evolution.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,328.41,54.00,215.75,63.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Heatmap and a word cloud for the "morning" topic.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,276.97,75.54,243.95,86.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>3Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Temporal profiles of topic intensities in the Staten Island area on a typical weekday (top) and a weekend (bottom).</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://foursquare.com/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>http://www.twitter.com</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>Research presented in this paper was funded by Marie-Curie ITN GEOCROWD, a Strategic Research Cluster grant (07/SRC/I1168) and the 11/RFP.1/CMS/3247 award by Science Foundation Ireland under the National Development Plan. The authors gratefully acknowledge this support.</p><p>We also thank Fergal Walsh and Aonghus Lawlor for their help with software.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>References</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Latent dirichlet allocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Blei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Jordan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mach. Learn. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="993" to="1022" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Figure 4: Clustering results for the Manhattan area. Clusters of similar functional profiles are shown in the same colour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Caverlee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Sui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on Weblogs and Social Media. AAAI</title>
		<meeting>the 5th International Conference on Weblogs and Social Media. AAAI</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Exploring millions of footprints in location sharing services</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting urban patterns from location-based social networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ferrari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mamei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zambonelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 3rd ACM SIGSPATIAL International Workshop on Location-Based Social Networks</title>
		<meeting>the 3rd ACM SIGSPATIAL International Workshop on Location-Based Social Networks</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="16" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding scientific topics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Griffiths</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Steyvers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">Suppl 1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5228" to="5235" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-04">Apr. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking trends: Incorporating term volume into temporal topic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Davison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM SIGKDD: Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Diego, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pervasive Urban Applications workshop (PURBA&apos;12) at PERVASIVE</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lawlor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Coffey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mcgrath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pozdnoukhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">June 2012. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Stratification structure of urban habitats</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plda+: Parallel latent dirichlet allocation with data placement and pipeline processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://code.google.com/p/plda" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Transactions on Intelligent Systems and Technology, special issue on Large Scale Machine Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Space-time dynamics of topics in streaming text</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pozdnoukhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kaiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 3rd ACM SIGSPATIAL International Workshop on Location-Based Social Networks, LBSN &apos;11</title>
		<meeting>the 3rd ACM SIGSPATIAL International Workshop on Location-Based Social Networks, LBSN &apos;11<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping change in large networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rosvall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bergstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8694</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Normalized cuts and image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="888" to="905" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial structure and dynamics of urban communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pozdnoukhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The First Workshop on Pervasive Urban Applications (PURBA)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-06">June 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuous time dynamic topic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Blei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Heckerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-06">June 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
