<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Trust and conflict within virtual inter-organizational alliances: a framework for facilitating knowledge sharing</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2004-05-18">18 May 2004</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Niki</forename><surname>Panteli</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bath</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>BA2 7AY</postCode>
									<settlement>Bath</settlement>
									<region>England</region>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Siva</forename><surname>Sockalingam</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Business Information Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Caledonian Business School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Glasgow Caledonian University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cowcaddens Road</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Glasgow Caledonian University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G4 0BA</postCode>
									<settlement>Glasgow</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Trust and conflict within virtual inter-organizational alliances: a framework for facilitating knowledge sharing</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2004-05-18">18 May 2004</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BE4A492A3C91D628A5A6EE1E84962327</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.dss.2004.03.003</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T12:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Conflict</term>
					<term>Knowledge sharing</term>
					<term>Trust</term>
					<term>Virtual alliances</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Trust and conflict are inherent issues of any organizational arrangement and central for knowledge sharing; yet they have received limited attention in the literature. In this paper, we undertake an investigation of both phenomena within the context of virtual alliances. A generic framework for understanding the dynamics of trust and conflict within the context of virtual interorganizational arrangements is presented, followed by an examination of three distinct structural forms of virtual alliances, and strategies for generating trust and minimizing dysfunctional conflict. The paper concludes with an identification of avenues for further research.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Today's complex, competitive and dynamic business environment necessitates adaptive, flexible and responsive organizations. Accordingly, organizations are often compelled to form alliances with other organizations to survive and prosper. An expectation of such inter-organizational arrangements is the increased access to a wider pool of resources, in particular that of knowledge. While these knowledge-based inter-organizational arrangements have received an overwhelming attention in recent management and organizational literature, often over-looked is the fact that this fertile mechanism for nurturing knowledge sharing and knowledge creation can become sterile and even pathological when trust between partners is lacking and conflict is poorly managed. While trust and conflict are fundamental considerations for effective knowledge-based interorganizational arrangements, in particular those of a virtual nature, both bodies of literature have largely evolved independently of each other.</p><p>This paper addresses this gap focusing on three different forms of virtual inter-organizational arrangements. It commences by presenting the case for the consideration of both trust and conflict within the context of virtual inter-organizational arrangements. The paper then reviews the literature on trust and conflict and explores their dialectical nature and the compounded implications for knowledge sharing. Subsequently, a generic framework for understanding the dynamics of trust and conflict within the context of virtual inter-organizational arrangements is presented, followed by an examination of the three distinct structural forms of virtual alliances, and strategies for generating trust and minimizing dysfunctional conflict. The paper concludes with an identification of avenues for further research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Virtual inter-organizational alliances</head><p>Virtual inter-organizational alliances are defined as a network organization consisting of independent enterprises (organizations, groups, individuals) that come together to explore a business and/or market opportunity <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. Such inter-organizational arrangements often result from the convergence of two trends: firstly, technological advancements, which revolutionize communication between firms by establishing linkages for value-laden shared knowledge and secondly, the growing recognition of the importance of knowledge and innovation for networked organizations <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[69]</ref>. The business motivation for such arrangements is the potential for increased value added and competitive advantage from the enhanced knowledge stock and core competencies, which are deemed to accrue to such networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b87">88]</ref>.</p><p>Given the reciprocal dependencies, collaboration is an implicit feature of inter-organizational arrangements <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68]</ref>. Alliance partners are expected to share their skills, expertise and competencies for mutual benefit. Such partnerships therefore rely on trust, which often needs to evolve swiftly due to tight deadlines. Indeed, trust has been found to be positively related to the performance of inter-organizational partnerships <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and a potential source for competitive advantage <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. When trust prevails, opportunistic behavior is limited; partners are more confident that the knowledge shared will be used for the benefit and advancement of the alliance. Moreover, trust enables conflict to be used constructively; to explore differences, promote greater knowledge sharing and more importantly stimulate knowledge creation, which stems from learning and leads to innovation <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>. Open debate is the medium through which opposing views, assumptions and constraints are examined, valued and reconstituted towards creative solutions responsive to several points of view <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>. Further, Tjosvold <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">[78]</ref> contends that: ''Conflict when well managed, breathes life and energy into our relationships and strengthens our inter-dependence and makes us more innovative and productive'' (p. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23)</ref>. Thus, well-managed conflict in turn engenders stronger relationships and trust development, which can facilitate greater knowledge sharing and increased potential for knowledge creation during subsequent interactions. But when conflict is poorly managed or avoided, people remain aloof, sceptical and angry and become rigid, fixated and ambivalent <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>. Consequently, relationships weaken and trust disintegrates. Given its disposition for neutrality, when trust shrinks, mistrust takes over <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. The ensuing unconstructive interactions and the diminishing certainty of non-opportunistic behavior curtails value-adding knowledge sharing and the potential for new knowledge creation, which can have detrimental implications for both the performance of the alliance and its sustainability.</p><p>Accordingly, the main proposition of the paper is that knowledge sharing is positively related to interorganizational arrangements so long as the parties exhibit a trust type that permits the conflict to be heard, considered and effectively resolved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Trust and conflict</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Trust</head><p>Trust has been defined as a state of a positive, confident though subjective <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> expectation regarding the behavior of somebody or something in a situation which entails risk to the trusting party <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. Various forms of trust have been identified in the literature. The tendency of an individual to trust, e.g. due to faith in humanity, is widely known as dispositional trust <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>. However, even though individuals may have a natural tendency to trust others, they may not do so in certain situations and under different circumstances <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Trust, in such cases, becomes dependent on the situational cues that modify the expression of generalised tendencies to trust and is labelled as situational trust <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">[86]</ref>. Other types of trust are conditional and unconditional <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. Conditional trust is commonly found at the initial stages of relationships when there are no obvious grounds for distrust. Given its provi-sional nature, conditional trust is fragile. However, as relationships mature and familiarity increases, conditional trust can transform into the more enduring unconditional trust. The latter is considered to be more supportive of synergistic relationships that are essential for superior performances <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref> as it stems from first-hand knowledge and experience of, and confidence in, the other party.</p><p>With particular reference to temporary work arrangements, Meyerson et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> present the concept of swift trust, which may flourish even though the traditional antecedents may be absent. They suggest that swift trust could be strong and 'resilient' enough to survive the life of the temporary group as it is founded upon the competent and faithful enactment of clear roles and members' associated duties. This type of trust presumes that roles are clear and that each member has a good understanding of others' roles and responsibilities. Furthermore, in order to cope with uncertainty, this type of trust falls back on predispositions, categorical assumptions and theories, which are independent of the object of perception. It has been proposed that, in temporary teams, members tend to relate with each other based on roles rather than individuals and as such, swift trust is founded more on professionalism rather than character <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>; ''This potentially 'cool' form of trust places less emphasis on feeling and commitment and more on action and cognition'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> p. 135). Jarvenpaa and Leidner <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> have found evidence of swift trust in their study of global virtual teams, and note that this trust is very fragile and temporal, and is further dependent upon the communication behavior of team members. Regardless of the initial levels of trust, this study has shown that only a small number of teams saw an improvement in the levels of trust over time.</p><p>Following Boon and Holmes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and Shapiro et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref>, Lewicki and Bunker <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45]</ref> argue that trust is dynamic and distinct in character at different stages of any relationship (professional or personal). They propound that ''this is a fundamentally different perspective on trust from the view that the essence of trust cannot be captured by a single, 'static' definition of its key elements and attributes. Trust is viewed as a dynamic phenomenon that takes on a different character in the early, developing, and 'mature' stages of a relationship'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, p. 118). Thus, trust changes with the passage of time as individuals begin to feel more comfortable with one another and develop improved awareness of others' integrity and competence. They propose that an awareness of trust development can help better understand how professional relationships change and evolve over time. Accordingly, they suggest three types of trust, each corresponding to a different stage of the relationship: Calculus-Based Trust, Knowledge-Based Trust and Identification-Based Trust (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>), which are ''linked in a sequential iteration in which the achievement of trust at one level enables the development of trust at the next level'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, p. 118). The movement from one type of trust to another begins at points J (J1 and J2) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>). However, this movement may not always develop smoothly and some relationships may not progress beyond the initial stage of the relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>.</p><p>Calculus-based trust (CBT) is grounded in the rewards to be derived from pursuing and preserving a relationship, and fear of punishment for the violation of trust. Lewicki and Bunker <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> emphasise that deterrence elements such as sanctions act as more dominant motivators of trustworthy behavior rather than rewardseeking elements. Potential sanctions in professional relationships may include the loss of repeat business or of reputation. Accordingly, this partial and rather fragile trust tends to foster only limited levels of knowledge sharing necessary to fulfil the expectations of trustworthy behavior. Given the limited potential for shared understanding and the focus on adherence to partners' expectations, the nature of the knowledge shared is more likely to be of a formal and an explicit nature. However, in exceptional situations, partners may choose to exceed these minimal expected levels of knowledge sharing for a variety of reasons such as image enhancement or strengthening of future relationships with selected partners.</p><p>Knowledge-based trust (KBT) relies on information about involved parties, which is developed through interactions over time. The assumption is that the more information based on experience one has about others, the more able one is to predict their actions: ''Regular communication puts a party in constant contact with the other, exchanging information about wants, preferences, and approaches to problems. Without regular communication, one can 'lose touch' with the other --not only emotionally but in the ability to think alike and predict the reactions of the other'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, p. 121). Accordingly, KBT is much stronger than CBT and more tolerant of inconsistent behavior and its related cost, if understanding between partners can be developed. This stronger trust in turn facilitates a higher level of knowledge sharing. Further, the enhanced scope for the development of shared values and understanding, in turn enables more effective knowledge sharing (as it facilitates the sharing and understanding of the more personal and intuitive tacit knowledge), and simultaneously provides a mechanism to measure the value of a given piece of shared knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref>. Nevertheless, Lewicki and Bunker propose that, ''the parties may not move past CBT if: a) the relationship does not necessitate more than 'business' or 'arms-length' transactions, b) the inter-dependence between the parties is heavily bounded and regulated, c) the parties have already gained enough information about each other to be aware that any further gathering is unnecessary [. . .] or d) one or more violations of CBT have occurred'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, pp. 124 -125).</p><p>Identification-based trust (IBT) is characterised by mutual understanding amongst all parties to the point that each can effectively act for the other. In this case, ''the other can be confident that his or her interests will be fully protected and that no surveillance or monitoring of the actor is necessary'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, p. 122). IBT is generated by shaping and moulding identities in ways that increase identification between the parties <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>. With IBT, partners develop a shared identity (needs, preferences, thoughts and behavior patterns) that facilitates the development of strong inter-relationships, which enable the alliance to work in complex harmony; maximising collective strengths and minimizing individual weaknesses to create a collective that is superior than the sum of its individual parts <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. Accordingly, the potential for effective, value-adding knowledge sharing is greatest with IBT. The common ground facilitates the sharing and understanding of greater levels of valuable tacit knowledge and diverse sets of knowledge, while the robust trust built over time enables the sharing of more classified knowledge, which can enhance the potential for new knowledge creation (creative integration of existing sets of knowledge and learning, new insight development and exploration), vital for competitive advantage.</p><p>It is clear from the preceding discussion that trust not only influences the nature of professional relationships, but more importantly, the extent and nature of the knowledge shared.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Conflict</head><p>Conflict is defined as ''an expressed struggle between at least two inter-dependent parties who perceive incompatible goals, scarce rewards, and interference from the other party in achieving their goals'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Its source can vary from power differentials, competition over scarce resources, tendencies to differentiate, negative inter-dependence between work units, ambiguity over responsibility or jurisdiction, to denial of one's self-image or characteristic identifications including values and sensitivities <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</p><p>For well over a decade, genuine interest in the study of organizational conflict has developed. Researchers have made significant strides in understanding and describing the mechanics of the organizational conflict phenomenon. What sets these studies apart from earlier studies are: (1) the ethos that conflict is a phenomenon omnipresent in organizational life and simply inevitable; it is the nature of complex organizations and central to what an organization is, and (2) the underlying notion that conflict is a twin twinedged sword with the potential to be both functional and dysfunctional <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>. Thus, the emergent view of conflict is that it is both an enemy and a friend on the perpetual expedition to organizational efficiency and effectiveness <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">[83]</ref>.</p><p>The organizational conflict literature has identified three common forms of conflict: relationship conflict or affective conflict, task or cognitive conflict and process conflict.</p><p>Relationship conflict tends to be emotional and focused on inter-personal incompatibilities or disputes <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref> and typically provokes hostility, distrust, cynicism, apathy and other negative emotions <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33]</ref>. Theory suggests that relationship conflict has negative implications on team and organizational functioning as it can: promote inefficiency and ineffectiveness <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, lead to a loss of perspective regarding the task <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, inhibit individuals' cognitive functioning in assessing new information provided <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref> and processing complex information <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">[75]</ref>, encourage stereotype listening (e.g. ''There goes techie again'') and induce the freezing out of iconoclasts from important discussions <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>. Moreover, Amason et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> found that relationship conflict diminished decision creativity and quality, eroded team unity and commitment, and curtailed decision acceptance and support. Accordingly, relationship conflict can promote divide, diminish trust and weaken relationships, which in turn curtails open communication, value-adding knowledge sharing, learning and ultimately knowledge creation.</p><p>Task conflict is generally task oriented and is focused on judgmental differences on the best solution to achieve organizational objectives <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref>. It is a condition in which individuals disagree about task issues including goals, key decision areas, and the appropriate choice for action <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref>. Based on empirical research, it has been argued that functional background diversity is the key source for task conflict and has the greatest potential to influence performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref>. Research shows that task conflict elicits divergent thinking, which facilitates multiple perspectives being brought to bear on decision making and the consideration of diverse aspects of the issue under debate <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58]</ref>. Hence, well well-managed task conflict facilitates value-adding knowledge sharing, development of common contextual understanding, learning and knowledge creation <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>. This is achieved through critical, focused, creative, and investigative <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref> interaction, which is aided by frank communication of varied perspectives, and open discussion and challenge of viewpoints and traditional paradigms, without threat, anger, resentment or retribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, as it is the merit of ideas that drive decision making <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. Such well well-managed task conflict leads to better scanning of the environment, greater flexibility and higher responsiveness to external change <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref>. Besides, it is a valuable mechanism for strengthening relationships and trust <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[73]</ref>.</p><p>Process conflict concerns an ''awareness of controversies about aspects of how task accomplishment will proceed'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, p. 239). This form of conflict arises from differences of opinion regarding roles, responsibilities, time schedules and resource requirements. Unlike task conflict, process conflict tends to be associated with decreased productivity through ineffective task performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, and dissatisfaction that can promote a desire amongst members to abandon the team <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. Despite its propensity for dysfunctionality, a level of process conflict at the early stages of an alliance (or project) is crucial for success, as it allows processes, role and resource issues to be discussed, agreed and accepted <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">[80]</ref>, which is vital for nurturing shared understanding and commitment to final decisions. Well-managed process conflict provides the foundation for relationships and trust between partners to develop, which is critical for harnessing the benefits of task conflict and minimizing the dysfunctional effects of relationship conflict.</p><p>Despite clear theoretical distinctions between the three common forms of conflict, in practice, there is a strong inter-relationship between each form. Task conflict may be taken personally and thus generate relationship conflict, or conversely, relationship conflict may prompt individuals to criticise each other's ideas <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">66]</ref>. Further, it has been found that mismanaged process conflict interferes with task issues resulting in misdirected focus on irrelevant discussions such as members' ability <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. Accordingly, while task conflict promotes knowledge sharing, learning, creativity and knowledge creation, mismanaged relationship conflict and process conflict can weaken inter-organizational alliances, curtail open sharing of knowledge, distort debate and thus undermine success.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Trust, conflict and knowledge sharing</head><p>The emergent knowledge management literature reflects a fundamental shift from being techno-centric to acknowledging the value of people, connectivity and social dynamics: ''Unlike first-generation knowledge management, in which technology always seems to provide the answer, second-generation thinking is more inclusive of people, process and social initiatives.'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>, p. 4). The rationale for this shift is that learning, knowledge sharing and knowledge creation are social processes. Thus, relationships are central for effective knowledge sharing and creation.</p><p>Unsurprisingly, trust has been recognised as being ''at the heart of knowledge exchange'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, p. 35) and ''the gateway to successful relationships'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">[85]</ref>, p. 5). Several researchers have found that trust is a 'need to have' quality in business interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50]</ref> and teamwork activities <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref>. High levels of trust are key to effective communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> as trust ''improves the quality of dialogue and discussions. . .[which,] facilitates the sharing of. . .knowledge'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, p. 200), and committed relationships. Trust is also essential for minimizing risks that stem from exposure to opportunistic behavior by partners, uncertainty, ambiguity and incomplete information, which typify inter-organizational arrangements. Nevertheless, trust is a risky investment; it exposes entities to the potential for opportunistic behavior by others.</p><p>In inter-organizational arrangements, trust is positively related to conflict resolution <ref type="bibr" target="#b80">[81]</ref>, and further facilitates harnessing the manifold benefits of conflict -the ''spark'' that ignites valuable innovation <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref>. But conflict is a double-edged sword. Given its complex nature, if the different forms and their interrelationships are poorly understood and managed, it can undermine trust and even generate mistrust, which will damage relationships and the potential for knowledge sharing, learning and knowledge creation. However, when well managed, conflict can engage individuals, strengthen relationships and trust, and facilitate knowledge sharing, challenge, debate and learning, which lead to knowledge creation and innovation.</p><p>Accordingly, there is a dialectical relationship between trust and conflict. Poorly managed conflict cannot only damage relationships, limit cognitive functioning (and learning), and engender apathy, but it can also accentuate the negative influences of diminished trust or mistrust. In contrast, when conflict is well managed, it facilitates the development of genuine trust, which in turn enables the benefits of both conflict and trust to be harnessed for competitive advantage. For example, well-managed conflict and trust can engender strong open relationships between alliance partners, which enables the exploitation of the more rewarding social forms of governance (adherence to commonly agreed values, principle and code of conduct) rather than reliance on the more prescriptive, counterproductive and expensive formal governance mechanisms such as hierarchical governance and control <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Further, partners are able to engage in more open and effective knowledge sharing, higher levels of challenge, debate and learning, share risks and explore opportunities otherwise not possible. Such alliances are not only rare, but are difficult to emulate, thus enhancing the alliances' potential to innovate and sustain their relative competitive advantage <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">The framework: trust, conflict and knowledge sharing</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Theoretical basis and justification</head><p>The preceding discussion has shown that an exploration and understanding of the complexities of knowledge sharing within the context of inter-organi-zational arrangements is vital. This is primarily because knowledge sharing in such networks can be a critical source of competitive advantage <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. In practice, different types of alliances exist that may have different requirements on the type and intensity of knowledge shared. Some alliances are more focused on structured tasks, which when effectively managed, enable these alliances to capture niche markets and create competitive advantage through the sharing of limited explicit knowledge. In contrast, others focus on unstructured tasks requiring problem solving with few set procedures and a high degree of uncertainty. These alliances benefit from the sharing of high levels of both explicit and tacit knowledge, and rely on the diversity of knowledge sets between partners to engender learning and knowledge creation through the integration of existing sets of knowledge and new idea generation.</p><p>In both extremes, knowledge sharing is vital for the fulfilment of common goals and sustaining competitive advantage; yet alliances continue to encounter problems in practice. Little is known about the implications of the inter-relationship between trust and conflict for effective knowledge sharing in situations involving networks that transcend organizational boundaries and involve recurring relationships that extend over a period of time.</p><p>The proposed framework integrates Lewicki and Bunker's trust development model with the conflict literature. This model has previously been applied in inter-personal relationships (e.g., Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>). However, given the intent to explore the complexities of trust and conflict in recurring professional relationships, Lewicki and Bunker's model, which appears to be the most well-recognised model that considers trust as anything other than static <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, is deemed relevant to the case of virtual inter-organizational arrangements. Moreover, though this model has been popular in the traditional organizational literature, its relevance has not been explored in the virtual organizational literature. This may be attributed to the fact that this literature has so far concentrated on temporary organizational arrangements, an environment with no history and no future <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>.</p><p>Despite the passage of time, Jehn and Chatman's ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, p. 56) observation that the recent conflict literature has tended to focus on the ''absolute level. . .of conflict [and] influences. . .[on] performance'' and thus ''fails to fully depict the nature and effects of conflict'', remains significant. They comment: ''researchers rarely consider the combined effects of [the three different] types of conflict, particularly the types of conflict relative to other types and the overall profile of conflict types in a group'' (p. 56). Further, the literature on the different forms of conflict has tended to focus on teams or groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">73]</ref>. The proposed framework takes into account the need to understand both the distinct and combined effects of the three different forms of conflict identified by Jehn and Mannix <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, and extends these insights and that of Sockalingam and Panteli <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[73]</ref> to recurring relationships within the context of virtual inter-organizational alliances.</p><p>Accordingly, the framework presented in the following section is embryonic and exploratory, not just by virtue of the integration of two distinct sets of literature and extension of existing theory, but also given the focus (knowledge sharing) and context (virtual alliances). Nevertheless, it has benefited to some extent from theoretical validation through attention to existing theory. The framework is intended to stimulate further discussion and exploration, both theoretical and empirical.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">The generic framework: description and elucidation</head><p>The framework for understanding trust and conflict over time is depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Alliance formation and CBT stage</head><p>At the initial stage of a virtual inter-organizational alliance, given the limited familiarity between partners and the professional makeup of the alliance, trust will tend to take the form of CBT. The motivation for CBT is the promise of rewards (e.g. increased sales and reputation) compounded by fear of punishment for trust violation. The propensity for relationship conflict will be minimal as individuals have little experience and knowledge of their counterparts and have come together based on their expertise for collaboration leading to mutual benefit <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[73]</ref>. Further, given the newness of the alliance, partners tend to be cautious in the manner in which they present themselves, in establishing relationships with fellow partners, and their position within the alliance <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[73]</ref>. The propensity for process conflict tends to be high at the CBT stage as the prime concern amongst partners is establishing clear guidelines for operation including partners' roles and responsibilities, resource availability and requirements, work norms, timescales and processes to be adopted <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>.</p><p>The propensity for task conflict at this stage would tend to depend on the nature of core task of the alliance. In situations where the task is relatively structured, the propensity for task conflict tends to be limited as the opportunity for strong differences in opinion, and concentrated debate concerning task issues is comparatively limited. In such alliances, the tasks are generally performed independently by individual partners, but the outputs from the tasks require coordination. However, if the task is unstructured (e.g. exploration for innovation), and thus requires problem solving with few set procedures and a high degree of uncertainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">[82]</ref>, the propensity for task conflict will tend to be high, once partners establish their initial positions within the alliance and agree upon the framework for operation. Such alliances are formed to bring together diverse knowledge sets and expertise for the benefit of the whole, and as noted elsewhere, functional background diversity is the key source for task conflict <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref>.</p><p>How the potential for high process conflict and, in some cases, task conflict are managed can affect the dynamics of both trust and conflict in subsequent stages of the alliance, as process conflict while vital for effective performance has the potential to be dysfunctional. If process conflict is poorly managed, it can trigger and escalate relationship conflict and compromise the fragile CBT. For example, if discussions concerning process issues such as responsibilities and resources are poorly managed with certain partners assuming control, it can lead to the perception of inequitable distribution of responsibilities and resources amongst others and alienation. This poorly managed process conflict in turn can trigger the dysfunctional relationship conflict. Once relationship conflict creeps into the alliance, it can cause division and hostility amongst members, apathy and disinterest in discussions and also erode the fragile CBT amongst members. This can damage the interaction between members when they progress to consider task issues and hinder vital knowledge sharing, discussion, debate and learning, in particular in alliances with a high potential for task conflict. Such an environment goes against the essence of collaboration and compromises the ability of the alliance to reap its true potential.</p><p>Nevertheless, empirical evidence on the impact of relationship conflict to date remains contradictory <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">71]</ref>. Relationship conflict diminished decision quality, eroded unity and commitment, curtailed decision acceptance and support <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, engendered demotivation, disinterest, prejudiced evaluation and blinkered understanding <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref> and distorted perceptions of other's ideas <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. However, Jehn <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> discovered that while relationship conflict was dysfunctional, it did not affect performance as negatively as suggested by theory, while Pelled et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref> found no evidence that relationship conflict impaired performance; individuals were able to manage the negative effects effectively without affecting performance. Accordingly, given the potential for rewards, aggrieved partners may choose to remain in the alliance but only engage in limited knowledge sharing and fulfil the minimum expectations of fellow partners. Thus, the potential for CBT to develop within the alliance is significantly curtailed. The limited trust in turn may prompt the need for formal mechanisms to protect partners' interests and compound the problems for knowledge sharing. If relationship conflict amongst members escalates, it may even prompt members to seek alternative strategies to gain the rewards sought and ultimately leave the alliance. In extreme cases, it may deter partners from considering joining other alliances.</p><p>However, if the high process conflict is well managed through open discussion, involvement by all partners and fair process, where the merit of ideas drive decision making <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41]</ref>, it cannot only engage partners and secure their commitment and buy-in, but also provide a foundation to develop shared values, trust and relationships. Active involvement in discussions elicits a sense of self-affirmation and accomplishment that leaves people feeling more integrated, adjusted and competent <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">[78,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">84]</ref>. Partners feel unique and independent and simultaneously connected to others, trust each other more, and develop confidence that joint efforts will pay dividend <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b77">78]</ref>. The potential to go the extra mile for the benefit of the alliance is much greater in such scenarios. Accordingly, when partners move on to the task stage, the propensity for knowledge sharing is enhanced; this is due to the development of shared context and values, which facilitates the sharing and understanding of tacit knowledge. Moreover, the development of a secure and stimulating environment increases the likelihood of harnessing the positive potential of task conflict and fulfilling or even exceeding the business goals of the alliance. The success of its first project is more likely to draw partners together again for subsequent projects that may be of a similar nature or perhaps even more challenging, given the prior experience. This in turn can strengthen relationships and develop trust.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">KBT stage</head><p>As trust between partners develops over time, the nature of the trust can evolve from CBT to KBT. Given the stronger form of trust based on knowledge and experience of partners, it is likely that relationship conflict will be low, as relationship conflict is associated with diminished trust.</p><p>Further, the stronger KBT can encourage partners to be more open and challenging in their discussions about task issues. Hence, task conflict although dependent on the task type will tend to be moderate or high. In structured task scenarios, the level of task conflict will tend to be moderate. Pelled et al.'s <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref> findings indicate that when tasks are routine and under-stimulating, individuals tend to seek arousing experiences by seeking task debates with dissimilar others based on background differences. Other studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b76">77]</ref> show that some level of task conflict can increase the re-evaluation of current ideas and operating standards, and thus result in improved quality and performance. In unstructured task scenarios, task conflict tends to be high, given the nature of the task as previously discussed. Well-managed high-task conflict within the context of the stronger KBT can encourage the sharing of greater levels of knowledge, which enhances the alliance's collective stock of knowledge. Debate promotes learning; members realise the inadequacy of their original ideas, appreciate the value of opposing ones, solve issues and generate creative solutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>. The experience can leave members feeling more integrated, valued, competent, powerful and efficacious, which leads to increased motivation, high levels of performance, and ownership of, and commitment to, the alliance <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>.</p><p>The potential for process conflict is dependent on the nature of the alliance at the KBT stage. In situations where the general framework and remit of the alliance remains largely unchanged, the potential for process conflict is low, as process issues such as roles, responsibilities, resource requirements and processes remain unaffected. However, in situations where there is a need for fundamental change, the potential for process conflict can be high. This is likely to typify unstructured tasks, where each project is unique and hence may require varied resources and processes. However, given the existence of KBT, low relationship conflict, stronger relationships between partners and their prior experience of managing process conflict effectively, it is likely that the high process conflict will not have any major dysfunctional influences on the alliance.</p><p>With the passage of time, as the well-managed conflict and developing trust cements relationships and encourages greater knowledge sharing between partners, the likelihood of success of the alliance is considerably enhanced. Partners may be more likely to consider novel options that may be more challenging and risky, given the trust that exists. Further, the need for formal mechanisms to protect individual partners' interest and control other partners' actions may diminish. In the case that such a scenario unfolds, there is a potential for trust to evolve into IBT. This is more likely to happen in unstructured tasks, given the generally high levels of classified and tacit knowledge that is required to be shared in such cases, and the potential to value-adding knowledge creation. However, alliances crippled by relationship conflict will tend not to progress onto the KBT or IBT stages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.">IBT</head><p>Achieving IBT is rare in practice. In many alliances, such high levels of trust are not required for its effective functioning. Nevertheless, at this stage, the potential for relationship conflict is minimal. As previously discussed, the potential for process conflict will tend to be low, unless the framework for, and remit of, the alliance changes fundamentally. The potential for task conflict is expected to be high, as we posit that only alliances that engage in unstructured tasks generally need and are able to develop IBT. This framework is based on the assumption that the composition of the alliance remains unchanged over time. However, in reality, the composition may change if new partners are invited into the alliance. The implications of such complexities are not addressed in this paper.</p><p>The following section examines the framework within the context of specific inter-organizational arrangements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Virtual inter-organizational models: trust and conflict</head><p>Virtual alliances can take numerous forms and structures with some being more permanent, interactive, knowledge-intensive or complex than others. For the purpose of this paper, we draw on three models of virtual inter-organizational arrangements developed by Burn et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>: star-alliance, value-alliance and co-alliance. The star-alliance model is typified by one dominant player collaborating with other peripheral organizations. The value-alliance model refers to an alliance between a core organization and others that deliver inter-related products and services within the industry value chain. Finally, the co-alliance model is a collective of organizations that make equal contribution of resources, competencies, and knowledge to the alliance. These alliances are not expected to collaborate on a continuous basis, but tend to come together when a need arises for specific projects and then disassemble.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> summarises the salient features and potential trust and conflict dynamics for each model analysed, and forms the basis for subsequent discussion in this section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Trust and conflict in a star-alliance virtual arrangement</head><p>The star-alliance consists of a dominant core partner surrounded by various satellite partners who are only called upon to play a role in the virtual organization when a need arises. Satellites rely on the dominant partner for leadership, and allocation and direction of work. The power differential in this model is distinct and affects task allocation, process specification and information distribution. CCAA, an auto-mobile association in Australia, which brings in satellite partners as required for a wide range of breakdown services, is an example of this type of virtual alliance <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>. Based on prior performance and contribution of individual satellite partners, the core partner has the power to decide whether or not to reward them with further projects. As such, there is a potential for some partners to develop closer and stronger relationship with the dominant partner than others. Given the nature of the alliance, the dominant form of knowledge shared tends to be explicit. For example, in the event of a vehicle break down caused by engine failure, the central CCAA helpline operator will contact its partner located nearest to the location of its client with formal, codified and easily transmittable information (explicit knowledge) such as the vehicle registration number and nature of the client's problem. There is a limited need in such scenarios to share tacit knowledge.</p><p>Following from our earlier discussion, the propensity for task conflict will tend to be low given the rather structured nature of the core task of this type of alliance. At the same time, the propensity for relationship conflict at the alliance formation stage will also tend to be low in view of the existence of CBT and the potential for mutual rewards. Nevertheless, the potential for process conflict at the early stage of the star-alliance is high as this is the stage that the framework for operation is agreed and accepted by all partners. The management of process conflict is critical for the effectiveness of the alliance in particular, given the strong power differentials between the dominant partner and its satellite partners.</p><p>If the dominant partner adopts the domination approach for managing the process conflict, which prohibits meaningful discussion and results in the suppression of conflict-culminating in the victory of one party over another <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, it can accentuate relationship conflict. Or if some partners sense preference being shown towards other partners, it can generate a perception of inequity, which again can trigger the potential for relationship conflict to develop between satellites, and between satellites and the dominant partner. Further, if the dominant partner withholds, or is perceived to be withholding information, this too can generate relationship conflict. If relationship conflict creeps into the alliance, it can threaten the fragile CBT, limit the extent of knowledge shared and thus curtail the development of KBT.</p><p>However, this scenario can be avoided through the effective management of the potential for high process conflict. The dominant partner generally tends to be the most informed partner in the alliance, in particular regarding its purpose and expectations Such an environment cannot only result in superior decision quality, but also help engender clear understanding of salient issues, commitment to, and acceptance of, final decisions, given the joint decision making process, and unity amongst partners. While such discussion may be time consuming, it can minimize the potential for negativity caused by the poor management of process conflict and the generation of relationship conflict. Such efforts are vital in the star-alliance given the tendency for the ensuing arms-length interaction between partners, and the limited control over task allocation by other satellite partners. Further, such interactions also serve to strengthen relationships and establish a platform for the development of trust. Clarity of roles and understanding of the rational for task allocation and associated processes are vital for the stabilization and development of CBT over time.</p><p>In some cases, despite the predominantly armslength nature of the interaction between partners and the structured nature of the task, which requires limited sharing of largely explicit knowledge, trust can develop over time from CBT to KBT, provided the potential for conflict is effectively managed. At the KBT stage, it is likely that relationship conflict is low, given the length of the relationship and the development of trust. Similarly, process conflict tends to be low as long as the framework for operation remains largely unchanged. However, if the higher levels of trust prompts partners to reconsider the operational framework, it can escalate the potential for process conflict to moderate levels. Given the experiential knowledge of partners and the stronger levels of trust, it is likely that such conflict will be managed effectively without detrimental implications for the alliance. Further, with process-based change, there may also be a potential for task conflict to increase to moderate levels to address the task changes required.</p><p>Nevertheless, the predominantly arms-length interaction and limited need for extensive knowledge sharing, limits the potential for the development of trust within the star-alliance from KBT to IBT.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Trust and conflict in a value-alliance virtual arrangement</head><p>The value-alliance model is a network that comprises a group of partners providing a range of interrelated products and services, based on an industry value chain. It is a reinvention of the traditional valuechain, which permits an efficient, demand-pull operation that results in increased customer satisfaction. An example of this alliance is Benetton, which relies on a global virtual value chain to coordinate the production and shipment of garments and materials via a global distribution network: ''[this] virtual value chain passes through a number of suppliers generating textiles, designing and manufacturing clothing, and providing distribution services to retailing establishments'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74]</ref>, pp. 268 -269).</p><p>Unlike the star-alliance, in the value-alliance model all parties are needed and expected to make a contribution in all the projects undertaken by the alliance. As with the star-alliance model, there is a central partner whose role is to disseminate explicit knowledge from clients to associated partners and coordinate the entire process. The central partner needs to ensure that each partner has a clear understanding of not just their respective roles and contribution, but also that of other partners and of the entire process. Like the star-alliance, the propensity for relationship conflict at the value-alliance formation stage is low and the propensity for task conflict is also low. Similar arguments for the low propensity for both forms of conflict in the star-alliance also apply to the valuealliance model.</p><p>The propensity for process conflict at the CBT stage in turn is high. While the sources for process conflict and the strategies for minimizing its dysfunctional effects are similar to that of the star-alliance, the value alliance is distinguished by two additional features which have varied implications for process and relationship conflict. Firstly, unlike the star-alliance, the value-alliance model benefits from guaranteed task allocation, which minimizes the risk of misunderstandings between partners concerning the fairness of task allocation by the dominant central partner. Secondly, the continuous dependencies between all partners in the value-alliance creates further complexities that can further intensify the potential for process conflict during the CBT stage, which in turn can result in the escalation of relationship conflict. For example, if a clothing manufacturing partner fails to meet its obligations to other dependent partners and thus compromise the efficiency of the entire alliance through a continual lack of timely information from the central partner, it can trigger relationship conflict between partners. Such relationship conflict has a greater potential to escalate within the value-alliance given the inter-dependencies between partners. The problem can be compounded by a lack of acknowledgement and awareness raising amongst partners, by the central partner of the source of the problem, and challenges faced, resources invested and efforts expanded by the affected partner. Such escalated levels of dysfunctional conflict can compromise the cohesiveness of the entire alliance and the development of trust. However, this limitation of the value-alliance can also become a potential of strength for the alliance, if process conflict is effectively managed. The interactive nature of this alliance, which necessitates relatively close and continuous working relationships between partners, enables partners to learn about each other from personal experience and thus provides greater opportunities for the development of KBT than the star-alliance model.</p><p>At the KBT stage, the potential for the various types of conflict can be expected to be similar to that of the star-alliance at the same stage, given the similar structured nature of the task and the dependency on explicit knowledge. Accordingly, the potential for the development of IBT is also limited, as the nature of the interaction and knowledge shared do not facilitate the development of deep mutual understanding amongst all partners to enable them to effectively act on behalf of others.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Trust and conflict in a co-alliance virtual arrangement</head><p>The co-alliance model relies on the notion of shared partnerships with each partner bringing different expertise and making equal contribution to the alliance. This model can be best illustrated using the case of Perth Consulting Services (PCS), a virtual organization that provides consulting work on strategic IS planning <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>. Even though PCS has adequate expertise to manage its own assignments, it often collaborates with three other independent consultancy organizations and benefit from their diverse knowledge and skills. During such collaborative endeavours, all parties are required to invest equal levels of commitment and effort. This virtual alliance comes together when required for specific projects, then disperses at the end of such projects to focus on other projects independent of one another. With the passage of time, given its recurring work relationship and intensity of collaborative efforts, parties in the alliance are able to develop a sense of mutuality and belonging, which can lead to commitment and improves cooperation.</p><p>This model is quite distinct from the previous models discussed in several ways. Firstly, there is no dominant party; all parties are equally powerful and responsible for the outcome of respective projects. Secondly, the level of knowledge sharing is intensive and knowledge sharing needs to be multidirectional (i.e. to be exchanged amongst all parties involved). Thirdly, such alliances are reliant on the sharing of both tacit and explicit knowledge, which necessitates the development of shared contextual understanding, for the effective transfer of knowledge between partners. Finally, the focus is on creative thinking and knowledge creation; the core task is unstructured.</p><p>Nevertheless, at the alliance formation stage the propensity for relationship conflict is low, as in the case of the two previous models. Similarly, the propensity for process conflict is high. The fundamental difference in this model is that partners wield equal power and are jointly responsible for fashioning the framework for operation. Open sharing of knowledge, discussion and debate are vital to nurture shared understanding, commitment to, and acceptance of final decisions. If process conflict is poorly managed, it can be catastrophic, as discussion can easily become personal given the balanced power structure, and trigger relationship conflict. To compound matters, such alliances also experience high levels of task conflict as the nature of the work is unstructured and is dependent on the creative integration of diverse sets of knowledge, exploration of the inevitable differences, and learning, to develop new insight and knowledge. If relationship conflict is rife at the CBT stage, it can damage the creative and investigative interaction that is required and negate the benefits of task conflict; the high-task conflict can disintegrate into high relationship conflict. In such cases, the project may suffer a relatively high risk of failure, the development of trust will be curtailed and the future of the alliance will be threatened.</p><p>On the other hand, if the process conflict is effectively managed, the potential for relationship conflict can be minimized, which in turn enhances the potential for the benefits of high-task conflict to be harnessed for the mutual gain of the alliance and its partners. Further, the intensity of the collaboration and the concomitant mutual reliance on the diverse knowledge sets, renders the potential for the alliance to move swiftly from CBT to KBT, and for the development of IBT, where each party has the ability to represent each other individually and collectively. The degree of continuity of this partnership, as well as the level and frequency of interaction amongst all parties concerned, will determine whether KBT can develop to IBT.</p><p>At both the KBT and IBT stages, task conflict continues to be high given the unstructured nature of the task. However, given the strong bonding and trust, relationship conflict tends to be low. The level of process conflict is dependent on the structure of the framework for operation. Given the unstructured nature of the task, there is likelihood that the process requirements for each individual project may be unique and thus requires formalisation at the start of each new project. In such instances, process conflict can be expected to be high. However, in instances where the framework for operation does not require significant attention, process conflict can be expected to be low. Regardless of the level of process conflict, given the existence of either KBT or IBT and the alliance's prior experience in managing process conflict effectively, it would be reasonable to anticipate that such conflict would be appropriately managed for the benefit of the alliance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Generating IBT in virtual alliances</head><p>It follows from the discussion so far, that the coalliance model provides more opportunities for developing a knowledge-intensive environment than the star-alliance and value-chain models. Co-alliance makes the sharing of tacit knowledge vital for the success of the virtual organization and is therefore the most likely model that would enable the development of IBT. To address the question of how IBT can be generated in the virtual, technology-mediated environment, two issues are identified as important: (a) familiarity with all partners and (b) alliance's identity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.">Familiarity with all partners</head><p>Familiarity with partners is a key prerequisite for trust development. In the virtual era, information and communication technologies with collaborative potentials are increasingly used in organizations to enable their members and partners to communicate and become familiar with each other and therefore potentially offer many of the same advantages as trust <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. However, despite these collaborative potentials, access to technology alone is not sufficient to encourage familiarity and build collaboration <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61]</ref>. Technology is not an antecedent to effective trusting relations. ''. . .You may receive many emails, voice mails, and phone calls, but you are missing significant amounts of data that would normally be available to you in faceto-face working relationships'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref>, p. 41). Face-toface communication is the preferred means of communication at the start and end of each work process as it is valuable for establishing real shared understanding of task requirements and joint achievements, while technology-mediated communication is more suited to the middle period when the task context is well established <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">[87]</ref>. Even video-conferencing systems, which have the capability for face-to-face though distant (and video-mediated) communication, have been found to be more suitable for structured communication exchanges, where participants know each other well, rather than for creative and innovative meetings where trust and rapport are yet to be established <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref>. Video-conferencing systems could be effective means for sharing explicit knowledge within the star-alliance and value-alliance models.</p><p>It seems therefore that if communication is restricted to just technology-mediated, the potential for the development of IBT will be limited in virtual settings. Accordingly, a combination of face-to-face and technology-mediated communication is vital to enable parties to increase familiarity with each other not only for enhancing their knowledge base, but also for harnessing opportunities for building a mutual understanding of each other and the alliance that they represent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">Identity</head><p>Due to the nature of the co-alliance model and mainly the lack of a central player, trust relationships need to be jointly developed by all parties involved, constituting a type of trust relationship that is mutually negotiated, enacted, reinforced and even renegotiated. This conceptualisation of trust is based on the situated identity theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, which argues that parties perform a recognised action in a socially defined setting. This action, however, is neither predetermined nor is it random. It is rather '''an emergent property of moment-by-moment interactions between actors, and between actors and the environment of their action'' ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">[76]</ref>, p. 179). IBT emerges within such situated identities and develops through regular interaction between parties, and is sustained through (re)negotiations.</p><p>Accordingly, IBT in a co-alliance virtual environment will not be based on a shared collective identity <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">70]</ref> nor will it be merely based on a complementary and mutual understanding amongst the parties that their identities are different <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>, but rather on an identity that is situated. This situated identity will act as a prerequisite for social conduct <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and in turn will help in building and maintaining an interactive social situation every time the parties get together and will last throughout the duration of the virtual alliance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Conclusions and implications for further research</head><p>In accordance with the recent shift in the knowledge management literature and by recognising the centrality of human interaction for both knowledge sharing and creation, we posit that the emergence of new forms of virtual organizing require a careful repositioning of trust types, an appreciation of the varied potential for the different forms of conflict and an understanding of the dialectical relationship between both phenomena. Accordingly, the key proposition explored in this paper is that knowledge sharing is positively related to inter-organizational arrangements so long as the partners exhibit a trust type that discourages dysfunctional conflict and simultaneously promotes an environment to harness the potential of functional conflict. This was achieved using Lew-icki and Bunker's trust development model to map the potential forms of trust that can emerge in professional relationships over time against the propensity for the varied forms of conflict at different stages of trust development within the context of virtual alliances. This in turn enabled an exploration of the complex inter-relationship between both phenomena over time.</p><p>The primary insight offered is that the dynamics between trust and conflict are vital considerations for success in virtual inter-organizational arrangements. At the early stages of an alliance when trust is weak (CBT) and motivated by rewards and punishment, the effective identification and management of the three common forms of conflict are critical for strengthening relationships between partners and engender trust development. Process conflict, which arises from a need to understand and/or influence process issues such as roles, responsibilities, sequences and time scales, when well managed can engender shared understanding, acceptance and allegiance, which is vital for the enrichment of fragile trust and to harness the benefits of task conflict that follows. Well-managed task conflict in turn enhances the trust development process and enables partners to be more open in the level and nature of knowledge shared, debate and challenge engaged in, and thus more capable of learning and knowledge creation. The invigorating experience and increased potential for joint success can leave members feeling more integrated, valued, competent, powerful and efficacious, which leads to increased motivation, high levels of performance, and commitment to the alliance <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>. Such recurring interaction can contribute to the development of trust from CBT to KBT and in some cases even to IBT, which has positive influences on knowledge sharing and creation. However, if the high propensity for process conflict is poorly managed at the early stages of the alliance, when trust is fragile, it cannot only deviate discussions from the core issues and generate dissatisfaction, but also trigger the potentially dysfunctional relationship conflict. Relationship conflict can dissolve common ties and generate mistrust, which can threaten the success and survival of the alliance.</p><p>In exploring these connections, several contributions are made. Firstly, the proposed framework facilitates an understanding of how the different forms of conflict may impact upon one another and simultaneously influence the development or weakening of trust, within the context of virtual organizations. This in turn enabled an exploration of their distinct and combined implications for knowledge sharing and creation. Secondly, such understanding provided a basis for developing strategies for generating trust and managing conflict for different models of virtual inter-organizational arrangements. It is hoped that such an understanding and the proposed strategies may assist enterprises interested in exploring such emergent forms of operations to enhance their potential of reaping the full benefits of their joint endeavours. Thirdly, the paper sensitises researchers to the complex dynamics of virtual organizational arrangements, and in doing so carries forward an important debate in the era of virtuality. The focus on trust and conflict within different virtual alliance models further enabled a limited consideration of the power dynamics. An understanding of the interaction between trust, conflict and power is critical and yet is lacking in both the knowledge management literature and the information systems literature.</p><p>It is readily acknowledged that what has been attempted here is only an exploration of contingencies to provide a better understanding of trust and conflict within the knowledge-intensive virtual environment. Accordingly, the framework is simplistic in parts and does not do justice to the complexity of reality. Further research is required to advance and validate the conceptual ideas explored in this embryonic framework.</p><p>In particular, the following research agenda is proposed. Firstly, the inter-relationships between trust and conflict require exploration in the context of diverse forms of alliances, other than the three models considered in this paper. As the concept of alliances gains currency in the global arena, new models with composite features are beginning to emerge, which in turn have implications for the trust--conflict dynamics. For example, Dell's virtual integration model <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> displays features that typify both the star and valuechain models.</p><p>Secondly, even though this paper identified other types of trust such as dispositional, swift, conditional and unconditional, these did not feature in the analysis. The relationship between these trust types and conflict needs to be explored in order to gain a better understanding of the dynamics and complexities of virtual inter-organizational arrangements.</p><p>Thirdly, this paper focused on trust relationships at the organizational level. In the virtual era, trust relationships exist at multiple levels: between organizations, between individuals and between individuals and organizations <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>. Further research is required to consider the implications of multiple level interactions on the development of trust and the compounded implications for conflict, knowledge sharing, knowledge creation and the sustainability of alliances.</p><p>Fourthly, in this paper, we explored the star-alliance model that is typified by structural core tasks. However, such alliances may also engage in unstructured tasks. Accordingly, an in-depth investigation of trust development process and its inter-relationship with the different types of conflicts in specific virtual alliances and even specific projects undertaken within the alliance is required.</p><p>Finally, a detailed analysis of the power dynamics within alliances, along with that of trust and conflict is warranted, given that power has the potential to influence the dynamics of both trust and conflict <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">[79]</ref>.</p><p>The above form part of a research agenda that, when tackled, will advance the understanding of the inter-relationship between trust and conflict, which are crucial elements in facilitating knowledge sharing within virtual alliances. Such research is necessary for organizations to exploit the full potential of virtual interactions.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>0167-9236/$ -see front matter D 2004 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. doi:10.1016/j.dss.2004.03.003</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. The stages of trust development ([45], p. 124).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Conflict propensity and trust development in virtual alliances-a generic framework.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Trust and conflict in virtual alliances</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Star-alliance</cell><cell>Value-alliance</cell><cell>Co-alliance</cell></row><row><cell>Nature</cell><cell>Single dominant party</cell><cell>Single dominant party</cell><cell>All parties share equal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>for task allocation</cell><cell>for process coordination</cell><cell>status/responsibility</cell></row><row><cell>Dominant Knowledge</cell><cell>Explicit</cell><cell>Explicit</cell><cell>Tacit and Explicit</cell></row><row><cell>Type Transferred</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Trust Development</cell><cell>CBT to KBT</cell><cell>CBT to KBT</cell><cell>CBT to KBT to IBT</cell></row><row><cell>Trust and Conflict: Dynamics</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>and Development</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>-CBT</cell><cell>Low-Task Conflict</cell><cell>Low-Task Conflict</cell><cell>High-Task Conflict</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Low Relationship Conflict</cell><cell>Low Relationship Conflict</cell><cell>Low Relationship Conflict</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(but has potential to escalate</cell><cell>(but has potential to escalate</cell><cell>(but has potential to escalate</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>to Moderate/High)</cell><cell>to Moderate/High)</cell><cell>to Moderate/High)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>High Process Conflict</cell><cell>High Process Conflict</cell><cell>High Process Conflict</cell></row><row><cell>-KBT</cell><cell>Moderate Task Conflict</cell><cell>Moderate Task Conflict</cell><cell>High-Task Conflict</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Low Relationship Conflict</cell><cell>Low Relationship Conflict</cell><cell>Low Relationship Conflict</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Low/Moderate Process Conflict</cell><cell>Low/Moderate Process Conflict</cell><cell>Low/High Process Conflict</cell></row><row><cell>-IBT</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>High-Task Conflict</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>Low RC</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>Low/High Process Conflict</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>N. Panteli, S. Sockalingam / Decision Support Systems 39 (2005) 599-617</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We are grateful to the anonymous referees of this DSS Special Issue for their constructive and insightful comments.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Review: knowledge management and knowledge management systems: conceptual foundations and research issues</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Leidner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MIS Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-03">2001 March</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lauderdale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Situated identities and social influence</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="233" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinguishing the effects of functional and dysfunctional conflict on strategic decision making: resolving a paradox for top management teams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Amason</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-02">1996 Feb</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Harrison, Conflict: an important dimension in successful management teams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Amason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hochwarter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizational Dynamics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Autumn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Interpersonal Competence and Organizational Effectiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Argyris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">I11</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Dorsey, Homewood</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust and performance in cross-border marketing partnerships: a behavioral approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Aulakh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kotabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sahay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Business Studies, Special Issue</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1005" to="1032" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dangerous liaisons: trust, distrust, and information technology in american American work organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Baba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="346" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trustworthiness as a source of competitive advantage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Barney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positive effects of conflict: a cognitive perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Employee Responsibilities and Rights Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dynamics of interpersonal trust: resolving uncertainty in the face of risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Boon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cooperation and Prosocial Behavior</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hinde</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Groebel</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="211" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social judgement theory and the analysis of interpersonal conflict</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Brehmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="985" to="1003" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">E-business Strategies for Virtual Organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Burn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Marschall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<pubPlace>Butterworth-Heinemann, Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New work attitudes measures of trust: organizational commitment and personal need fulfilment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Occupational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cognitive conflict and goal conflict effects on task performance, Organizational Behavior and Human Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cosier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="391" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Measuring trust between organization boundary role persons, Organization Behavior and Human Decision Processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Currall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="170" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Working Knowledge: How Organizations Manage What They Know</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Davenport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Prusak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>Harvard Business School Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Virtual Corporation: Structuring and Revitalising the Corporation of the 21st Century</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Davidow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Malone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<pubPlace>Harper Collins, New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Numerical support, information processing and attitude change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K W</forename><surname>De Dreu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vries</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="647" to="662" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conflicts: productive and destructive</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Deutsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Exploring Interpersonal Trust in the Entrepreneurial Venture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dibben</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<pubPlace>Macmillan, London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning, trust and technological collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dodgson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Relations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Politics of strategic decision making in high-velocity environments: towards a midrange theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Eisenhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bourgeois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="737" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How management teams can have a good fight</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eisenhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kahwajyand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bourgeois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iii</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-07">1997 July -August</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conflict and performance in R&amp;D organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Evan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Industrial Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Prophet of Management: A Celebration of Writings from the 1920s</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Follett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Mary Parker Follett</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>Harvard Business School Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">68</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Beyond Contract: Work, Power and Trust Relations, Faber and Faber</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust and the virtual organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Handy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-05">1995 May -June) 40 -50</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Camping on seesaws: prescriptions for a self-designing organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hedberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nystrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Starbuck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administrative Science Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hocker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wilmot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Interpersonal Conflict</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>William C. Brown, Dubuque, IA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>second edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge and the concept of trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Huemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Krogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Knowing in Firms: Understanding, Managing and Measuring Knowledge</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Krogh</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kleine</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="145" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge enablers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ichijo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Krogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nonaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Knowing in Firms: Understanding, Managing and Measuring Knowledge</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Krogh</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kleine</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="203" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Communication and trust in global virtual teams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Jarvenpaa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Leidner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organization Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="815" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing effectiveness: an investigation of advantages and disadvantages of value-based intragroup conflict</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Conflict Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multi method examination of the benefits and detriments of intragroup conflict</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administrative Science Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-06">1995 June</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of proportional and perceptual conflict composition on team performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chatman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Conflict Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dynamic nature of conflict: a longitudinal study of intragroup conflict and group performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mannix</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why differences make a difference: a field study of diversity, conflict, and performance in workgroups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Northcraft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Neale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administrative Science Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="741" to="763" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The experience and evolution of trust: implications for cooperation and teamwork</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="546" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Communicating trustworthiness and building trust in interorganizational virtual organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kasper-Fuehrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ashkanasy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Personal Relationships: their Structure and Prophecies</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Erlbaum, Hillsdale, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fair process: managing in the knowledge economy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mauborgne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-07">1997 July -August</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whither trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tyler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Trust in Organizations: Frontiers of Theory and Research</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tyler</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Thousand Oaks, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge management enables, processes, and organizational performance: an integrative view and empirical investigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Summer</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust relationships: a model of trust development and decline</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lewicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bunker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Conflict, Cooperation and Justice</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bunker</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="173" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing and maintaining trust in working relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lewicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bunker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Trust in Organizations: Frontiers of Theory and Research</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tyler</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Thousand Oaks, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="139" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust development in negotiation: proposed actions and a research agenda</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lewicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stevenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Business &amp; Professional Ethics Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1 -3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The power of virtual integration: an interview with Dell computer&apos;s Michael Dell</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Magretta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harvard Business Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-03">1998 March -April</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When &apos;Silence=Death&apos;, keep talking: trust, control and the discursive construction of identity in the Canadian HIV/AIDS treatment domain, Organization Studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Maguire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Special Issue</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="310" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Burn, Structure, strategy and success factors for the virtual organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Marschall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mckay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">E-Commerce and V-Business</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Butterworth -Heinemann, Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="192" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrative model of organizational trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Schorman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="709" to="734" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mcelroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The New Knowledge Management: Complexity, Learning, and Sustainable Innovation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Butterworth-Heinemann, Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Initial trust formation in new organizational relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mcknight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cummings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chervany</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="490" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-07">1998 July</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Swift trust and temporary groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Meyerson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Weick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Trust in Organizations: Frontiers of Theory and Research</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tyler</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Thousand Oaks, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="195" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social and Economic Transformation in the Digital Era, Idea Group</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nandhakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Panteli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vidgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>G. Doukides, N. Mylonopoulos, N. Pouloudi</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<pubPlace>Hershey, PA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Trust in the digital era</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dissent as driving cognition, attitudes and judgements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nemeth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minority influence, divergent thinking and detection of correct solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nemeth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kwan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal Of of Applied Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="786" to="797" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The tradeoffs of control and innovation in groups and organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nemeth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Staw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Experimental Social Psychology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Berkowitz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="210" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exposure to dissent and recall information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nemeth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Mayseless</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sherman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust and inter-organizational networking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Newell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Swan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Relations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1287" to="1328" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nonaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Takeuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Knowledge Creating Company</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Video-conferencing meetings: changing patterns of business communication, new technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Panteli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Work and Employment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-07">2001 July</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Repositioning interpersonal trust within virtual teams, paper to BIT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Panteli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dibben</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Business Information Technology Management: E-futures, 10th Annual Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Manchester, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-11-01">2000. 2000 November 1 -2</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intentional breakdowns and conflict by design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Pascale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Planning Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-05">1994 May -June</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surfing the edge of chaos</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Pascale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sloan Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Demographic diversity, conflict, and work group outcomes: an intervening process theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Pelled</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organization Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="615" to="631" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the black box: an analysis of work group diversity, conflict and performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Pelled</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eisenhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Xin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administrative Science Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual teaming: where is everyone?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Platt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal for Quality and Participation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structuring cooperative relationships between organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Van De</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ven</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strategic Management Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Facilitating inter-organizational learning with information technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Management Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Fall</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Business on a handshake</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sheppard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cheraskin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Negotiation Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="377" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Discontinuity in Change: An Exploration of the Role of Conflict in Business Process Reengineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sockalingam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<pubPlace>UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Glasgow Caledonian University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A conflict strategy for BPR</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sockalingam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Doswell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Fifth European Conference on Information Systems (ECIS &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>the Fifth European Conference on Information Systems (ECIS &apos;97</meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conflict and trust: a framework for knowledge-intensive project teams, Paper to BIT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sockalingam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Panteli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Business Information Technology Management: Constructing the IS Futures, 11th Annual Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Manchester, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-10-30">2001. 2001 October 30 -31</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual management of global marketing relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Speier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of World Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="276" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Staw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sandelands</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Threat-rigidity effects in organizational behavior: a multilevel analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="501" to="526" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Plans and Situated Actions: The the Problem of Human Machine Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Suchman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Conflict-Positive Organization: Stimulate Diversity and Create Unity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tjosvold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Houston</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tjosvold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Conflict within interdependence: its value for productivity and individuality</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K W</forename><surname>De Dreu</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van De Vliert</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="37" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Using Conflict in Organizations</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Back to basics: shared goals and developing trust in global virtual teams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Panteli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Organizational Information Systems in the Context of Globalization</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Korpela</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Montealegre</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Poulymenakou</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishing</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="98" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development sequences in small groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Tuckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="399" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inter-organizational conflict resolution: the effects of power and trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Twomey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-08">1995 August</date>
			<publisher>Academy of Management Proceedings</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determinants of coordination modes within organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Van De Ven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Delbecq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Koenig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Sociological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="322" to="338" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effectiveness of mixing problem solving and forcing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van De Vliert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nauta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Euwema</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Janssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Using Conflict In Organizations</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K W</forename><surname>De Dreu</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van De Vliert</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="52" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Superiors&apos; conflict management strategies and subordinate outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weider-Hatfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hatfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Communication Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring value in relationship development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jantrania</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 9th IMP Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 9th IMP Conference<address><addrLine>Bath</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="25" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sept</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust and distrust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Worchel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Social Psychology of Intergroup Relations</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Austin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Worchel</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Broks/ Cole, Monterey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactivity and communication mode choice in ongoing management groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Systems Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The extended enterprise -creating value from virtual spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Zigurs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Qureshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Information Technology and the Future Enterprise: New Models for Managers</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dickson</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Desanctis</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New Jersey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="143" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Siva Sockalingam is a Lecturer in Knowledge Management and is the Director of The Metis Studio for Knowledge and Business Transformation at Caledonian Business School, Glasgow Caledonian University. She completed her PhD in Business Process Reengineering and her work has been published in The Journal of Corporate Transformation and the Journal of Knowledge and Process Management. Her current research interests include the influence of social dynamics on knowledge transfer, creativity, learning and knowledge creation</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Division of Business Information Management</title>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Niki Panteli is a Lecturer in Information Systems at the University of Bath School of Management ; European Journal of Information Systems; Futures; New Technology, Work and Employment ; Caledonian Business School, Glasgow Caledonian University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Dr. Sockalingam can be. Cowcaddens Road, Glasgow G4 0BA, UK, or via E-mail: s.sockalingam@gcal.ac.uk</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
