<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2000</postCode>
									<settlement>Sorrento</settlement>
									<region>June</region>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Communication Systems and Technologies Labs</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>60196</postCode>
									<settlement>Mo-torola Labs, Schaumburg</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engi-neering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>93106</postCode>
									<settlement>Santa Barbara</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">828C3B689BB5659697AA30DB0C269B6D</idno>
					<note type="submission">received April 17, 2000; revised February 2, 2001.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T08:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Space-time coding [1]- <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, which provides diversity in a fading environment. This does not require any knowledge of the spatial channel on the part of the transmitter.</p><p>2) Transmit beamforming, which assumes that the transmitter has accurate knowledge of the channel through feedback from the Manuscript</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Space-Time Transmit Precoding With Imperfect Feedback</head><p>Eugene Visotsky, Member, IEEE, and Upamanyu Madhow, Senior Member, IEEE Abstract-The use of channel feedback from receiver to transmitter is standard in wireline communications. While knowledge of the channel at the transmitter would produce similar benefits for wireless communications as well, the generation of reliable channel feedback is complicated by the rapid time variations of the channel for mobile applications. The purpose of this correspondence is to provide an information-theoretic perspective on optimum transmitter strategies, and the gains obtained by employing them, for systems with transmit antenna arrays and imperfect channel feedback. The spatial channel, given the feedback, is modeled as a complex Gaussian random vector. Two extreme cases are considered: mean feedback, in which the channel side information resides in the mean of the distribution, with the covariance modeled as white, and covariance feedback, in which the channel is assumed to be varying too rapidly to track its mean, so that the mean is set to zero, and the information regarding the relative geometry of the propagation paths is captured by a nonwhite covariance matrix. In both cases, the optimum transmission strategies, maximizing the information transfer rate, are determined as a solution to simple numerical optimization problems. For both feedback models, our numerical results indicate that, when there is a moderate disparity between the strengths of different paths from the transmitter to the receiver, it is nearly optimal to employ the simple beamforming strategy of transmitting all available power in the direction which the feedback indicates is the strongest. Index Terms-Antenna arrays, fading channels, feedback communication, space-time codes, spatial diversity, transmit beamforming, wireless communication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Antenna arrays, at the receiver or at the transmitter, are widely recognized as an effective means of improving the capacity and reliability of a wireless communication link. In a typical cellular or personal communication system, size and complexity limitations preclude deployment of an antenna array at the mobile, usually a small, hand-held unit. On the other hand, it is reasonable to assume that the base station is equipped with an antenna array. In such a setting, the use of transmit antenna arrays provides a powerful method for increasing downlink (base-to-mobile) capacity. There are two key techniques that have been proposed in the literature for exploiting transmit antenna arrays. receiver, and can, therefore, perform spatial matched filtering or (in a multiuser context) interference suppression <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>These two strategies are based on two different, and extreme, assumptions regarding the channel feedback available at the transmitter: space-time coding requires no feedback, whereas beamforming requires accurate feedback. Clearly, there are situations where neither of these assumptions is valid, and one would expect that the transmitter strategy in such situations would be some blend of space-time coding and beamforming. Our purpose in this correspondence is to make this intuition precise by providing information-theoretic insights into the appropriate transmitter strategies when the channel feedback available to the transmitter is imperfect.</p><p>Characterization of the information-theoretic capacity of channels with imperfect feedback is the subject of several recent publications. The approach in this correspondence is motivated by the results obtained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, which provide forward and converse coding theorems for certain channels with imperfect feedback. A similar feedback model is adopted in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, where optimum transmission strategies with perfect and imperfect feedback are examined and classified. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, a given transmission strategy is classified according to the rank of its input spatial covariance matrix. For instance, a beamforming strategy corresponds to a rank-one matrix while a covariance matrix with full rank indicates a diversity strategy. Such a classification is also adopted in this correspondence. With perfect channel feedback, it is shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> that the optimal strategy entails transmission in a single direction specified by the feedback (beamforming strategy). Conversely, with no channel feedback, it is shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> that the optimum strategy is to transmit equal power in orthogonal independent directions (diversity strategy). Many practical diversity transmission strategies are analyzed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Optimum power control and variable-rate transmission strategies when the same side information is available to transmitter and receiver, as well as when the side information is available only to receiver, are analyzed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The remainder of this correspondence is organized as follows. Section II contains the system model and formal problem statement. Section III contains our main results. Numerical results are presented in Section IV. Section V contains a discussion of these results and of possible directions for future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. MODELING AND OVERVIEW</head><p>It is assumed that the transmit antenna has M elements, and that the receive antenna has a single element. The channel coefficients from the M transmit elements to the receive element are denoted by the M 21 complex vector h h h. We consider the following abstraction to model par- tial knowledge of the channel at the transmitter. The corresponding system model is depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Problem Setup: The input to the channel is given by the M 2  6) is assumed to be a proper<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> complex Gaussian random vector, so that its distribution is completely specified by and 6 6 6.</p><p>If h h h is not a proper complex Gaussian vector, then the problem needs to be reformulated in terms of real-valued variables. Our main results, Theorems 3.1 and 3.2, apply to real as well as complex-valued channels.</p><p>The preceding maximization problem can be simplified as follows.</p><p>Let p o (x x</p><p>x) be the maximizing input distribution with covariance matrix Q Q Q and power Efkx x xkg 2 =tracefQ Q Qg = P . For fixed h h h, the channel is an additive Gaussian noise channel, with input distribution constrained to have covariance Q Q Q. As shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, the maximum mutual informa-</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">tion of this channel is log(h h h H Q Q Qh h h= 2 + 1</formula><p>) and the maximizing input distribution is proper complex Gaussian, p o (x x x) = N(0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">0; Q Q Q). Since p o (x x</formula><p>x) is not a function of h h h, it also maximizes I(x x</p><p>x; y jh h h ). The optimization problem is now one of finding the optimum choice of the covariance matrix Q Q Q o maximizing the mutual information I(x x</p><p>x; y jh h h) for power constraint P . The problem can be stated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">max Q Q Q E h h h log h h h H Q Q Qh h h 2 + 1 (1)</formula><p>subject to the power constraint tracefQ Q Qg = P , where 2 is variance of the additive circularly symmetric complex Gaussian noise. Note that the expectation in (1) is computed using distribution h h h N( ; 6 6 6).</p><p>A given transmission strategy is completely characterized by its covariance matrix Q Q Q. The strategy consists of transmitting independent complex circular Gaussian symbols along the corresponding directions specified by the eigenvectors of Q Q Q, with the corresponding eigenvalues specifying the powers allocated in each direction. Adapting definitions in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, a transmission strategy is defined as beamforming if the rank of Q Q Q is one, and as q-fold diversity if rankfQ Q Qg = q. In other words, beamforming is a strategy where transmission is performed only in a single direction, while q-fold diversity utilizes q transmit directions. Under this definition, the space-time coding techniques recently proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> can be viewed as attempting to provide full (M -fold) diversity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Discussion</head><p>When the channel feedback f f f is a deterministic function of the channel realizations h h h, recent results by Caire and Shamai <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> and by</p><p>Viswanathan <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> imply that an achievable information transfer rate between the input and the output in the preceding system model can be computed in the following two steps.</p><p>1) At time t, based on the "instantaneous" information provided by the current channel feedback vector f f f(t), find the optimum input y 0</p><p>)(y y y 0 ) g = 0 0 0.</p><p>distribution which maximizes the mutual information, subject to an instantaneous power constraint Efkx x x(t)k 2 g P (t).</p><p>2) Based on the solution to Step 1), and on the joint distribution of the channel and the feedback, find the optimum power profile fP(t); 0 t &lt; 1g.</p><p>While the results reported in this correspondence may be viewed as solving Step 1) of the preceding approach in a specific setting, such an interpretation would not hold in most practical situations, where the feedback may be noisy. In this case, maximization of the mutual information based on the instantaneous feedback as outlined in Step 1) need not be optimal, since knowledge of the feedback values at multiple times can help combat the randomness in the feedback. However, the framework of this correspondence can form the basis for a practical, albeit suboptimal, design in such situations. For example, the transmitter may derive a (possibly suboptimal) estimate of and <ref type="bibr">6 6 6</ref> based on more than one value of the feedback, and may then (again suboptimally) use the problem setup in (1) to find a strategy that maximizes the long-term information transfer rate.</p><p>Presently, the general solution to the optimization problem in (1) for the general form of h h h N( ; 6 6 6) is not known. The following special cases have been previously considered in the literature.</p><p>1) The optimum covariance for the special case of no feedback, h h h N(0 0 0; I I I), is derived by Telatar in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. In that case, the diversity strategy with power distributed equally in orthogonal independent transmit directions is optimum.</p><p>2) The optimum transmission strategy in the low signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) regime ( ! 1) for the special case h h h N(0 0 0; 6 6 6)</p><p>is found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. It is shown that beamforming in the direction corresponding to the largest eigenvalue of the channel covariance matrix 6 6 6 is asymptotically optimum as the SNR tends to zero.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Summary of Results</head><p>In this correspondence, the optimum distribution is characterized in the following two cases. In practice, these quantities could be computed at the transmitter based on knowledge of the joint statistics of h h h and f f f. An example of such a computation is given in Section IV as part of the numerical results for mean feedback.</p><p>The quality of the mean feedback depends on the feedback SNR k k 2 =, and this ratio is zero when no feedback is available. Our results show that the optimum solution is to use beamforming along (Q Q Q is unit rank) when the feedback SNR is larger than a threshold, and to use M-fold diversity (Q Q Q is full rank) oth- erwise. In the latter case, the power is distributed according to a water pouring strategy between the direction and the remaining M 0 1 orthogonal directions, which receive equal powers.</p><p>2) Covariance Feedback: The channel distribution known to the transmitter is h h h N(0 0 0; <ref type="bibr">6 6 6)</ref>. This models a situation in which the channel may be varying too rapidly for the feedback to give an accurate estimate of the current channel value. However, the relative geometry of the propagation paths changes more slowly, and is reflected in the covariance matrix 6 6 6. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> for a physical channel model justifying these assumptions.</p><p>In practice, the covariance matrix could be computed at the receiver via long-term time averaging of the channel realizations and reliably transmitted to the transmitter through a low data rate feedback channel. For covariance feedback, our results show that the optimum solution consists of independent Gaussian inputs along the M eigenvectors of 6 6 6. The solution resembles water pouring, in that eigenvectors corresponding to larger eigenvalues receive more power (the power along some of the eigenvectors may be zero, so that the optimal diversity order may be less than M).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. RESULTS</head><p>Notation: Theorems 3.1 and 3.2 characterize the optimum strategies for mean and covariance feedback, respectively. Proofs of both theorems follows the same general outline: first, we "guess" the optimum transmission directions; next, we project the channel realizations onto these directions; finally, convex optimization arguments are invoked to prove that the guessed directions are indeed optimum. Proof: Consider the optimization problem of (1), which can be equivalently expressed as </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Let U U U A A A3 3 3 A A AU U U H A A A denote</formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">max Q Q Q E h h h log h h h H Q Q Qh h h + 2</formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">E h h h h h h H (W W W 0 W W W o )h h h h h h H W W W o h h h + 2 0:<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Consider a projection of the channel h h h onto the "guessed" directions, given by v</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">v v = U U U H h h h.</formula><p>The components of v v v are independent with proper complex Gaussian distributions v v v[i] N(0; ), for i = 21 11M, and v v v [1] N(k k; ). Performing this change of variables in (3), we obtain an equivalent necessary condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">Ev v v v v v H (3 3 3 W W W 0 3 3 3 W W W )v v v v v v H 3 3 3 W W W v v v + 2 0 (4)</formula><p>where 3 3 3 W W W is any diagonal matrix with nonnegative entries satisfying the power constraint.</p><p>It is now shown that W W W o is also optimum for the unrestricted opti- mization problem, i.e., Q Q </p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Q o = W W W o .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">W o is f(W W W o ; Q Q Q 0 W W W o ) 0</formula><p>for all nonnegative definite matrices Q Q Q satisfying the power constraint.</p><p>Equivalently, the sufficient condition can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">E h h h h h h H (Q Q Q 0 W W W o )h h h h h h H W W W o h h h + 2 0:<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Again, making the substitution v v v = U U U H h h h, we obtain as the sufficient condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">E v v v v v v H Q Q Q 0 3 3 3 W W W v v v v v v H 3 3 3 W W W v v v + 2 0 (6)</formula><p>where </p><formula xml:id="formula_12">Q Q Q = U U U H Q Q QU U U is related to Q Q Q by</formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">E v v v v v v H D D D 0 3 3 3 W W W v v v v v v H 3 3 3 W W W v v v + 2 + E v v v v v v H Q Q Qv v v v v v H 3 3 3 W W W v v v + 2 0: (7)</formula><p>The first summand in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_14">Ev v v v v v[i] 3 v v v[j] v v v H 3 3 3 W W W v v v + 2 0 i 6 = j:<label>(8)</label></formula><p>Note that the M-dimensional probability distribution of v v v is symmetric with respect to all axes, excluding the v v v <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> axis (due to the nonzero mean of v v v <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>). Furthermore, the function under the expectation in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_14">8</ref>) is antisymmetric. We conclude that the expectation in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_14">8</ref>) is zero, so that the sufficient condition in  constraint is convex. Hence, these parameters can be numerically determined by the projected gradient descent algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, which in this case is guaranteed to converge to the global minimum. The mean feedback model was previously considered in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, where a similar computation is performed for two antenna elements (M = 2).</p><p>Specifically, the optimum transmit directions established analytically in Theorem 3.1 are determined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> by numerical simulations, and a sufficient condition on feedback SNR k k 2 = for the beamforming strategy to be optimum is given. 6. That is, the optimal strategy is to employ independent complex circular Gaussian inputs along the eigenvectors of 6 6 6.</p><p>Proof: For conciseness, only an outline of the argument is presented, since, with slight modifications, arguments used to prove Theorem 3.1 also apply here. In this case, our "guess" for the optimum transmit directions is given by the columns of U U U 6 6</p><p>6 . After projecting the channel onto the "guessed" directions as</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">v v v = U U U H 6 6</formula><p>6 h h h, the optimization problem in (1) can be equivalently expressed as To establish the theorem, it suffices to show that the maximizing covariance matrix in ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) is diagonal.</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">max Q Q Q E v v v log v v v H Q Q Qv v v + 2</formula><p>As in the proof of Theorem 3.1, consider a restricted optimization problem, where the search is restricted to only diagonal nonnegative definite matrices satisfying the power constraint in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>. By the convexity of the restricted optimization problem, there exists a unique di- Similarly to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, it is sufficient to establish that D D D o satisfies the fol- lowing inequality for all nonnegative complex matrices Q Q Q satisfying the power constraint   Let h h h(t) be an AR(1) random process with forgetting factor a, h h h(t) = ah h h(t 0 1) + w w w(t), where w w w(t) is an M 2 1 vector of independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) circularly symmetric Gaussians, each of variance 2 w . The feedback channel is modeled as a lossless channel with delay d: at time t, the transmitter observes f f f(t) = h h h(t 0 d) at the output of the feedback channel. It is straightforward to show that,</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">E v v v v v v H D D D 0 D D D o v v v v v v H D D D o v v v + 2 + E v v v v v v H Q Q Qv v v v v v H D D D o v v v + 2 0 (</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. NUMERICAL RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mean Feedback:</head><formula xml:id="formula_18">conditioned on f f f(t); h h h N( ; I I I), where = a d h h h(t 0 d) and = 2 w (1 0 2d )=(1 0 a 2 ). The distribution of f f f(t) = h h h(t 0 d) is</formula><p>the same as that of h h h(t) and is given by f f f N(0 0 0; 2 w =(1 0 a 2 )I I I). Hence, can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">= Efkh h hk 2 g(1 0 a 2d )=M:</formula><p>Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">3</ref><ref type="figure">4</ref>display information transfer rate (in bits per transmission) achievable with beamforming, diversity and the optimum transmission strategy for a two-element antenna array. The information transfer rate achieved by a given transmission strategy is obtained by substituting an appropriate covariance matrix Q Q Q into (1) and removing conditioning on the feedback. The optimum transmission strategy uses the covariance matrix Q Q Q o computed according to Theorem 3.1, where o 1 and o are numerically optimized using the projected gradient descent algorithm, as described in the note following Theorem 3.1. Since optimization of the instantaneous input power, given by tracefQ Q Qg, is not undertaken, tracefQ Q Qg is set equal to one for all transmission strategies without loss of generality. The input covariance matrix for the beamforming strategy, where beamforming is performed in the direction specified by the conditional mean, is then given by Q Q When a d = 0:9, the quality of the feedback is relatively high, which means that the channel estimate specified by the conditional mean is close to the true channel. This results in the beamforming strategy performing identical to the optimum strategy. The diversity strategy in this case is too conservative, losing about 2 dB in performance over a wide range of SNRs as compared to the beamforming strategy. With a d = 0:6, the conditional mean conveys less accurate information about the state of the channel. Nevertheless, the performance of the beamforming and optimum strategies is almost identical. This result is somewhat surprising, and highlights the robustness of the beamforming strategy to imperfections in the feedback. Of course, the gap between the performance of the diversity and optimum strategies is smaller than in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>. Finally, the channel feedback quality is poor when a d = 0:3.</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">Q B = H =k k 2 , while Q Q Q D =<label>(</label></formula><p>This case turns out roughly equivalent to the case of no feedback, in that the diversity strategy performs close to the optimum strategy, while the beamforming strategy performs about 1 dB worse than the optimum at high SNRs. Let i denote the ith eigenvalue (in this case the ith diagonal entry) of 6 6 6. Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> displays the information transfer rate (bits per transmission) achieved by the transmission strategies with M = 3, 1 = 2 = 3 . In this case, the performance of the diversity strategy is optimum, while the transmit beamforming strategy (equivalent here to using a single transmit antenna element) performs less than 1 dB worse than the optimum over a wide range of SNR values. Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> displays the performance of the transmission strategies for M = 3, 1 = 2 = 1 = 3 = 2.</p><p>In this case, there is a single direction which is 3 dB stronger than the other directions specified by <ref type="bibr">6 6</ref> 6. Somewhat surprisingly, the beam- forming strategy transmitting in the stronger direction achieves the performance of the optimum strategy for all displayed values of SNR.</p><p>Hence, no penalty is incurred for not utilizing the lower power direc-tions, leading us to conjecture that, in general, such a beamforming strategy is close to being optimal for small M , when 6 6 6 has at least a moderate eigenvalue spread.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>For a single transmit element, prior work <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> has shown that, in terms of information-theoretic limits, there is little to be gained by exploiting knowledge of the channel at the transmitter for a single transmit antenna element. As our numerical results indicate, for transmit antenna arrays, the gain through even partial knowledge of the channel can be substantial. For mean feedback, the beamforming strategy performs close to the optimal strategy when the feedback is of reasonable quality. The beamforming strategy performs close to the optimal strategy for covariance feedback when there is a stronger path present which can be exploited by the beamforming. Overall, the beamforming strategy appears to be a viable transmission strategy when meaningful channel feedback is present. Furthermore, the use of the beamforming strategy simplifies operation at the mobile, since only a single data stream needs to be decoded. The optimum transmission strategies presented in this work are based on random coding arguments. Hence, future work in this area includes design of practical coding strategies for exploiting partial knowledge of the spatial channel.</p><p>A possible extension of the information-theoretic approach taken in this correspondence is to consider optimum transmission strategies in the context of the multiuser system model. The problem can be formulated as a search for the optimum transmission strategies in a broadcast channel as a function of the quality of channel feedback at the transmitter. Such optimum strategies, if found, would provide a valuable benchmark for the performance of the practical transmit beamforming strategies, such as those proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>The current emphasis on constant-envelope spread-spectrum modulations has caused engineers to ignore one design, which has considerable potential, namely pulse-position hopping (PPH), also known as time hopping. Under the names impulse radio multiple access (IRMA) and ultra-wide bandwidth (UWB) transmission, this modulation is proposed and analyzed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. PPH transmission has several benefits, such as coherent reception and low transmit power density.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, the basics of the technology for generation of the narrow pulses of duration less than 1 ns and the very low spectral density is thoroughly described. The study of the capacity of a binary pulse position modulation (PPM) IRMA system <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> shows that it can reach an order of several thousands of active users per cell. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, an experimental design is described and measurements of the multipath channel are presented. There are several patents covering receiver structures, see for instance <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, and systems, see for instance <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. We will study a slightly different modulation method in comparison to <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, namely, binary on-off modulation. In this correspondence, we will present an information-theoretical analysis of a PPH code-division multiple-access (CDMA) system and will present a lower bound to the overall effective capacity of the system in the downlink and the uplink directions. Our approach follows classical information-theoretical analysis methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>; similar methods were applied for analysis of directsequence CDMA (DS-CDMA) and frequency-hopping CDMA (FH-CDMA) systems in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>The remaining part of this correspondence is organized as follows. In Section II, the system model is described, in Sections III and IV, the effective capacity of the uplink and downlink system is estimated, and in Section V conclusions and future work are discussed. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. System model.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,38.16,62.28,251.04,127.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Mean Feedback: In this case, the channel distribution is modeled at the transmitter as h h h N( ; I I I), where the mean may be interpreted as an estimate of the channel based on the feedback, and may be interpreted as the variance of the estimation error.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the spectral decomposition of a nonnegative definite matrix A A A, where 3 3 3 A A A is a diagonal matrix containing the eigenvalues of A A A, and U U U A A A is a unitary matrix containing as columns the eigenvectors of A A A. Likewise, U U U o 3 3 3 o (U U U o ) H is the spectral decomposition of the optimum covariance matrix Q Q Q o and o i ; i = 11 1 1 M, denote the optimum eigenvalues. Let A A A[i] denote the ith column of matrix A A A, and a a a[i] denote the ith component of column or row vector a a a.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Theorem 3 . 1 (</head><label>31</label><figDesc>Mean Feedback): Let h h h N( ; I I I). Then, the maximizing covariance matrix in (1) is given by U U U o [1] = =k k, and U U U o [2]; . . . ; U U U o [M] are arbitrarily chosen, except for the restriction that U U U o [1]; . . . ; U U U o [M] are orthonormal. Furthermore, o 2 = 1 11 = o min o where o = (P 0 o 1 )=(M 0 1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>( 2 )</head><label>2</label><figDesc>subject to the power constraint tracefQ Q Qg = P . Let U U U denote an or- thonormal matrix such that U are orthonormal and arbitrary. Matrix U U U contains as columns our choice for the transmitting directions of the optimum strategy. Below we establish that this choice is globally optimum, that is, U U U = U U U o . First, consider a restricted optimization problem where the optimization is restricted to only nonnegative definite matrices W W W satisfying the power constraint, such that U P as our constraint. The constraint set of the restricted problem is convex and compact, while the cost function is strictly concave in W W W . Hence, there exists a unique matrix W W W o (with U U U W W W = U U U ) which solves the restricted optimization problem. The matrix W W W o must satisfy the necessary op- timality condition f(W W W o ; W W W 0 W W W o ) 0 for all matrices W W W in the restricted constraint set, where f(W W W o ; W W W 0 W W W o ) is a Frechet differential [14, p. 178] of the cost function f in the direction W W W 0 W W W o , evaluated at W W W o . Differentiating, the necessary condition can be ex- pressed as</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>In view of the strict concavity of the cost function and the convexity of the constraint region, a sufficient condition for the overall optimality of</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>an orthonormal transforma- tion, and hence is nonnegative definite with the same trace, so that it also satisfies the power constraint. Decomposing Q Q Q into a sum of ma- trices D D D and Q Q Q containing diagonal and off-diagonal terms, respec- tively, expression (6) is rewritten as</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>is less than or equal to zero by the necessary condition for optimality given in (4), since matrix D D D satisfies the power constraint (tracef D D Dg =tracef Q Q Qg = P ), and is diagonal and nonnegative. The second sum can be decomposed into a weighted sum of the terms of the form</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>( 7 )</head><label>7</label><figDesc>is indeed satisfied by W W W o . It remains to be shown that the eigenvalues o 2 through o M are equal. This easily follows from substituting W W W o into the cost function and noticing that the cost function is symmetric with respect to the eigenvalues of interest. An application of the Jensen's inequality yields the desired result. To complete the solution, it remains only to specify the value of o 1 . Computation of o 1 in Theorem 3.1: The power constraint implies that o 1 lies in the range 0 o 1 P . Although a closed-form analytic solution for this quantity does not appear to be available, o 1 can be determined numerically by a one-dimensional search over the range. Another possibility is to use the observation that, as a function of the two parameters o 1 and o , the cost function is concave, while the power</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Information transfer rate achievable with the optimum, pure diversity and beamforming strategies, h h h N( ; I I I), M = 2, a = 0:9. The curves for</figDesc><graphic coords="4,99.12,62.28,392.16,310.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Theorem 3 . 2 (</head><label>32</label><figDesc>Covariance Feedback): Let h</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>( 9 )</head><label>9</label><figDesc>subject to the power constraint tracefQ Q Qg = P , where v v v N</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>agonal matrix D D D o , with real nonnegative entries, which solves the re- stricted optimization problem. Furthermore, D D D o satisfies the necessary condition optimality the restricted constraint set which is used to show its overall optimality.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>diagonal and off-diagonal terms of Q Q Q, re- spectively. Following arguments identical to those used to show that (7) holds, the proof of the theorem is concluded.Computation of the Optimum Distribution in Theorem 3.2: It follows from Theorem 3.2 that, for = 0 0 0, the transmit directions are precisely the eigenvectors of the channel covariance matrix 6 6 6. To com- pletely specify the transmission strategy, one needs to solve for the M transmit powers given by the diagonal entries of D D D o . This is an M-di- mensional water pouring problem which can be solved by a number of numerical algorithms, such as the projected gradient descent algorithm<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Intuitively, higher power should be transmitted in the directions of the larger eigenvalues of 6 6 6, since large eigenvalues correspond to stronger, and hence more reliable, channels.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Information transfer rate achievable with the optimum, pure diversity and beamforming strategies, h h h N( ; I I I), M = 2, a = 0:6.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,99.90,62.28,393.60,310.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>To obtain numerical results for this case, the following Rayleigh fading channel model is simulated.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1=M )I I I specifies the input covariance matrix for diver- sity transmission. In Figs. 2-4, the information transfer rate is plotted versus SNR (in decibels), where SNR = Efkh h hk 2 g= 2 ; Efkh h hk 2 g = 1 and a d = 0:9; 0:6; and 0:3, respectively. Parameter a d indicates the feedback quality and, more precisely, can be related to the average feedback SNR per antenna element as Efk k 2 g=M = a 2d =(1 0 a 2d ):</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Fig. 4 .6 6 6 ,</head><label>46</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Information transfer rate achievable with the optimum, pure diversity and beamforming strategies, h h h N( ; I I I), M = 2, a = 0:3.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,99.72,62.28,390.96,309.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Information transfer rate achievable with the optimum, pure diversity and beamforming strategies, h h h N(0 0 0; 6 6 6), M = 3, = = . The curves</figDesc><graphic coords="7,100.74,62.28,391.92,309.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> </figDesc><table><row><cell>complex vector x x x. The receiver knows h h h, and receives</cell></row><row><cell>y = x x x H h h h + n</cell></row><row><cell>where n N(0; 2 ) is circularly symmetric complex Gaussian noise with variance 2 =2 per dimension, and where a a a H denotes conjugate transpose of vector a a a. The transmitter receives channel feedback f f f from the receiver. Given f f f, the transmitter knows that the channel h h h is dis-tributed according to a complex Gaussian distribution N( ; 6 6 6); where and 6 6 6 denote the mean and covariance of h h h. Note that both and 6 6 6 can be functions of f f f. Problem: For h h hN ( ; 6 6 6), what is the input distribution p(x x x) that maximizes the mutual information I(x x x; y jh h h ), subject to Efkx x xk 2 g P .</cell></row><row><cell>0018-9448/01$10.00 © 2001 IEEE</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Manuscript received October 30, 1999; revised November 16, 2000. This work was supported in part by the Swedish Foundation for Strategic Research-Personal Computing and Communication (PCC), Ericsson Mobile Communications, and by the Royal Swedish Academy of Science in cooperation with the Russian Academy of Science. The material in this correspondence was presented in part at the International Symposium on Information Theory, Sorrento, Italy, June 2000. O. Wintzell and K. Sh. Zigangirov are with the Department of Information Technology, Lund University, 221 00 Lund, Sweden (e-mail: ola.wintzell@it.lth.se; kamil.zigangirov@it.lth.se). D. K. Zigangirov is with the Institute for Problems of Information Transmission, Moscow, 101447 Russia (e-mail: zig@iitp.ru). Communicated by M. L. Honig, Associate Editor for Communications.</figDesc><table /><note><p>Publisher Item Identifier S 0018-9448(01)05454-2. 0018-9448/01$10.00 © 2001 IEEE</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>As defined in<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, a complex Gaussian vector y y y with mean is proper if Ef(y y</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors wish to thank B. Hajek and M. Medard for helpful discussions.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported by Motorola under the University Partnerships in Research Program and by the National Science Foundation under Grants NCR96-24008 (CA-REER) and CCR99-79381.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Space-time codes for high data rate wireless communication: Performance criterion and code construction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tarokh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Seshadri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Calderbank</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="744" to="765" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-03">Mar. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unitary space-time modulation for multiple-antenna communications in Rayleigh flat fading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hochwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Marzetta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">36th Annu. Allerton Conf. Communication, Control and Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-09">Sept. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Noncoherent communication in space and time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Warrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Madhow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Conf. Information Sciences and Systems</title>
		<meeting>Conf. Information Sciences and Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-03">Mar. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transmit beamforming and power control for cellular wireless systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rashid-Farrokhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tassiulas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Select. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1437" to="1450" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-10">Oct. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimum beamforming using transmit antenna arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Visotsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Madhow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE 49th Vehicular Technology Conf., VTC&apos;99</title>
		<meeting>IEEE 49th Vehicular Technology Conf., VTC&apos;99</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-05">May 1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="851" to="856" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capacity of Markov channels with receiver CSI and delayed feedback</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Viswanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="744" to="765" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-03">Mar. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the capacity of some channels with channel state information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Caire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shamai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Shitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2007" to="2019" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-09">Sept. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient use of side information in multiple-antenna data transmission over fading channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Narula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lopez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Select. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1423" to="1436" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-10">Oct. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance limits of coded diversity methods for transmitter antenna arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Narula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2418" to="2433" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-11">Nov. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Capacity of multi-antenna Gaussian channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Telatar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>BL0112170-950615-07TM</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>AT&amp;T Bell Labs</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capacity of fading channels with channel side information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goldsmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Varaiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986-1992, Nov. 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proper complex random processes with applications to information theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Nesser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Massey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1293" to="1302" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-07">July 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive transmitting antenna methods for multipath environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gerlach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Paulraj</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE GLOBECOM&apos;94</title>
		<meeting>IEEE GLOBECOM&apos;94</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-03">Mar. 1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="429" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Luenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Optimization by Vector Space Methods</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear Programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bertsekas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Athena Scientific</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<pubPlace>Belmont, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
