<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">MINIMUM VOLUME SIMPLEX ANALYSIS: A FAST ALGORITHM TO UNMIX HYPERSPECTRAL DATA</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jun</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">José</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bioucas-Dias</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto de Telecomunicac ¸ões</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Instituto Superior Técnico</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Technical University of Lisbon</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lisboa</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">MINIMUM VOLUME SIMPLEX ANALYSIS: A FAST ALGORITHM TO UNMIX HYPERSPECTRAL DATA</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">748C3E00FF27AA90B57F277DD331A19F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T04:18+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Hyperspectral unmixing</term>
					<term>Minimum volume simplex</term>
					<term>Source separation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper presents a new method of minimum volume class for hyperspectral unmixing, termed minimum volume simplex analysis (MVSA). The underlying mixing model is linear; i.e., the mixed hyperspectral vectors are modeled by a linear mixture of the endmember signatures weighted by the correspondent abundance fractions. MVSA approaches hyperspectral unmixing by fitting a minimum volume simplex to the hyperspectral data, constraining the abundance fractions to belong to the probability simplex. The resulting optimization problem is solved by implementing a sequence of quadratically constrained subproblems. In a final step, the hard constraint on the abundance fractions is replaced with a hinge type loss function to account for outliers and noise.</p><p>We illustrate the state-of-the-art performance of the MVSA algorithm in unmixing simulated data sets. We are mainly concerned with the realistic scenario in which the pure pixel assumption (i.e., there exists at least one pure pixel per endmember) is not fulfilled. In these conditions, the MVSA yields much better performance than the pure pixel based algorithms.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Hyperspectral unmixing is a source separation problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1]</ref>. Compared with the canonical source separation scenario, the sources in hyperspectral unmixing (i.e., the materials present in the scene) are statistically dependent and combine in a linear or nonlinear fashion. These characteristics, together with the high dimensionality of hyperspectral vectors, place the unmixing of hyperspectral mixtures beyond the reach of most source separation algorithms, thus fostering active research in the field <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref>.</p><p>Given a set of mixed hyperspectral vectors, linear mixture analysis, or linear unmixing, aims at estimating the number of reference materials, also called endmembers, their spectral signatures, and their abundance fractions <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4,</ref><ref type="bibr">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6]</ref>. The approaches to hyperspectral linear unmixing can be classified as statistical and geometrical based. The former addresses spectral unmixing as an inference problem, often formulated under the Bayesian framework, whereas the latter exploits the fact that the spectral vectors, under the linear mixing model, are in a simplex set whose vertices represent the sought endmembers.</p><p>This work was supported by the European Commission Marie Curie training grant MEST-CT-2005-021175. Email:{jun, bioucas}@lx.it.pt</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1.">Statistical approach to spectral unmixing</head><p>Modeling the abundance fractions (sources) statistical dependence in hyperspectral unmixing is a central issue in the statistical framework. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref>, the abundance fractions are modeled as mixtures of Dirichlet densities. The resulting algorithm, termed DECA, for dependent component analysis, implements an expectation maximization iteratative scheme for the inference of the endmember signatures (mixing matrix) and the density parameters of the abundance fractions.</p><p>The inference engine in the Bayesian framework is the posterior density of the entities to be estimated, given the observations. Accorging to the Bayes law, the posterior includes two factors: the observation density, which may account for additive noise, and a prior, which may impose constraints on the endmember matrix (e.g., nonnegativity of its elements) and on the abundance fractions (e.g., to be in the probability simplex) and model spectral variability. Works <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">9]</ref> are representative of this line of attack.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2.">Geometrical approach to spectral unmixing</head><p>The geometrical approach exploits the fact that, under the linear mixing model, hyperspectral vectors belong to a simplex set whose vertices correspond to the endmembers. Therefore, finding the endmembers is equivalent to identify the vertices of the referred to simplex.</p><p>If there exists at least one pure (i.e., containing just one material) pixel per endmember, then unmixing amounts to find the spectral vectors in the data set corresponding to the vertices of the data simplex. Some popular algorithms taking this assumption are the the N-FINDR <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref>, the the pixel purity index (PPI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref>, the Automated Morphological Endmember Extraction (AMEE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>, the vertex component analysis (VCA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref>, and the simplex growing algorithm (SGA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>.</p><p>If the pure pixel assumption is not fulfilled, what is a more realistic scenario, the unmixing process is a rather challenging task, since the endmembers, or at least some of them, are not in the data set. A possible line of attack, in the vein of the seminal ideas introduced in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>, is to fit a simplex of minimum volume to the data set. Relevant works exploiting this direction are the non-negative least-correlated component analysis (nLCA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref>, the alternating projected subgradients <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>, and the nonnegative matrix factorization minimum volume transform (NMF-MVT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>. We consider that the NMF-MVT algorithm is representative of the state-of-the-art in the minimum volume simplex fitting approaches.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3.">Proposed approach</head><p>We introduce the minimum volume simplex analisys (MVSA) algorithm for unsupervised hyperspectral linear unmixing. As the name suggests, MVSA belongs to the minimum volume class, and thus is able to unmix hyperspectral data sets in which the pure pixel assumption is violated.</p><p>Fitting a simplex of minimum volume to hyperspectral data is a hard nonconvex optimization problem, which may end up in a local minimum. To avoid poor quality local minima, a good initialization is of paramount importance. We initialize MVSA with an inflated version of the simplex provided by VCA <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref>, a pure pixel based algorithm. Although this initialization may be far from the optimum, we have observed that it is systematically in the attraction basin of a good quality local minimum. Furthermore, since VCA yields a simplex defined by spectral vectors existing in the data set, we can discard all the spectral vectors that are inside this simplex, what accelerates the algorithm. Moreover, by carefully choosing the inflating factor, the large majority of constraints related with the abundance source fractions become inactive, what contributes to speeding up the algorithm, as well.</p><p>Minimum volume simplex algorithms are very sensitive to outliers. To make MVSA robust to outliers and noise, we run a final step in which the abundance fraction positivity hard constraint is replaced by a hinge type soft constraint. This step, applied after having found the minimum volume simplex, preserves the good quality of local minima.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows. Section 2 introduces the core of MVSA algorithm. Section 3 illustrates aspects of the performance of MVSA approach with simulated data, and Section 4 ends the paper by presenting a few concluding remarks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">MINIMUM VOLUME SIMPLEX ANALYSIS ALGORITHM (MVSA)</head><p>Let Y ≡ [y1, . . . , yN ] ∈ R p×n be a matrix holding in its columns the spectral vectors yi ∈ R p , for i = 1, 2, . . . , n, of a given hyperspectral data set. Although not strictly necessary, we assume in this version of the algorithm that a dimensionality reduction step (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>) has been applied to the data set and the vectors yi ∈ R p are represented in the signal subspace spanned by the endmember spectral signatures. Under the linear mixing model, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Y = MS s.t.: S 0, 1 T p S = 1 T n ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where M ≡ [m1, . . . , mp] ∈ R p×p is the mixing matrix (mi denotes the ith endmember signature and p is the number of endmembers), and S ∈ R p×n is the abundance matrix containing the fractions ([S]i,j denotes the fraction of material mi at pixel j). For each pixel, the fractions should be no less than zero, and sum to 1, that is, the fraction vectors belong to the probability simplex. Therefore, the spectral vectors yi belong, as well, to a simplex set with vertices mi, for i = 1, . . . , p.</p><p>Given Y , and inspired by the seminal work <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>, we infer matrices M and S by fitting a minimum volume simplex to the data subject to the constraints in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(1)</ref>. This can be achieved by finding the matrix M with minimum volume defined by its columns under the constraints in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(1)</ref>. It can be formulated as the following optimization problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">M * = arg min M | det(M )| s.t. : QY 0, 1 T p QY = 1 T N ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where Q ≡ M -1 . Since det(Q) = 1/ det(M ), we can replace the problem (2) with the following:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Q * = arg max Q log | det(Q)| s.t. : QY 0, 1 T p QY = 1 T N .</formula><p>(</p><p>Optimizations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">3</ref>) are nonlinear, although the constraints are linear. Problem ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>) is non-convex and has many local minima. So, problem (3) is non-concave and has many local maxima. Therefore, there is no hope in finding systematically the global optima of (3). The MVSA algorithm, we introduce below aims at "good" sub-optimal solutions of optimization problem (3). Our first step is to simplify the set of constraints 1 T p QY = 1 T N by noting that every spectral vector y in the data set can be written as a linear combination of p linearly independent vectors taken from the data set, say Yp = [yi 1 , . . . , yi p ], where the weights add to one: i.e., y = Ypβ, where 1 T p β = 1. It turns out then, the constraint</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">1 T p QY = 1 T N is equivalent to 1 T p QYp = 1 T N or else to 1 T p Q = 1 T p (Yp) -1 . Defining qm = 1 T p (Yp) -1</formula><p>, we get the equality constraint</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">1 T p Q = qm.</formula><p>Then, the problem (3) simplifies to</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">Q * = arg max Q log | det(Q)| s.t. : QY 0, 1 T p Q = qm. (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">)</formula><p>We solve the optimization problem (4) by finding the solution of the respective Kuhn-Tucker equations using a sequencial quadratic programing (SQP) methods. This methods belongs to the constrained Newton (or quasi-Newton) and guarantee superlinear convergence by accumulating second-order information regarding the Kuhn-Tucker equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref>. Each quadratic problem builds a quadratic approximation for the Lagrangean function associated to <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(4)</ref>. For this reason, we supply the gradient and the Hessian of f in each SQP iteration.</p><p>Usually, the hyperspectral data sets are huge and, thus, the above maximization is heavy from the computational point of view. To lighten the MVSA algorithm, we initialize it with the set of endmembers M ≡ [m1, . . . , mp] generated by the VCA <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref> algorithm. We selected VCA because its is the fastest among the state-of-the-art pure pixel-based methods. Since the output of VCA is a set of p vectors that are in the data set, then we can discard all vectors belonging to the convex set generated by the columns of M . If the number of endmembers is high, it may happen that the initial simplex provided by VCA contains very few pixels inside and, therefore, most are outside, violating the nonnegativity constraints and slowing down the algorithm. In such cases, we expand the initial simplex to increase the number of pixels that are in the convex hall of the identified endmembers, which speeds up the algorithm. The pseudocode for the MVSA method is shown in below. Symbols g(Q):,j and g(Q)i,: stand for, respectively, the jth column and the ith line of g(Q), the gradient of f (Q).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Algorithm: Minimum Volume Simplex Analysis (MVSA) Input</head><formula xml:id="formula_8">: p , Y , (f (Q) ≡ log | det(Q)|) Output: matrix Q 1: Q0 := vca(Y ,'Endmembers',p) 2: Q0 := expand(M ); 3: Y := discard(Y ); if y is inside the simplex 4: Inequality constraint A * Q ≥ b, A = Y T ⊗ Ip, b = 0pn 5: Equality constraint Aeq * Q = beq, Aeq = Ip ⊗ 1 T p , beq = q T m III -251 6: g(Q) := -(Q -1 ) T , where g(Q) is the gradient of f 7: [H(Q)]i,j := -[g(Q):,j * g(Q)i,;],</formula><p>where H(Q) is the Hessian matrix of f 8: Q := SQP(f, Q0, A, b, Aeq, beq, g, H)</p><p>Based on experimental evidence, we have come to the conclusion that the complexity of the MVSA algorithm is roughly O(p 3 ), provided that the initial Q is a feasible solution. Otherwise, the complexity depends on the number active constraints. This is the reason why we start the algorithm with VCA, discard the spectral vectors that are inside the inferred initial simplex, and expand it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS</head><p>-11 -  MNF-MVT unmixing algorithms applied to simulated data sets. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows a projection on a subspace of the true endmembers, the endmembers inferred by MVSA, VCA, and MNF-MVT, and the spectral vectors. The data set has size n = 10000 pixels and a number of endmembers p = 3, part a), and p = 10, part b). The data is generated according to the linear observation model <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(1)</ref>. The abundance fractions are Dirichlet distributed with parameter μi = 1, for i = 1, . . . , p. The spectral signatures of the endmembers are mineral reflectances, with 224 spectral bands, obtained from a library. To ensure that no pure pixel is present, we discarded all pixels with any abundance fractions larger than 0.8. Notice the high quality of the MVSA estimates in both secenarios: the stars representing the true endmembers are all incide the squares representing the MVSA estimate. The VCA produces the worst estimate, as it was not conceived for data sets failing the pure pixel assumption.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> shows the times in seconds and the Frobenius norm ?</p><p>M -M F of the endmember matrix estimates yielded by the MVSA and NMF-MVT algorithms. The algorithms run in a 3.4GHz Pentium 4 PC. MVSA performs much better with respect to both time and error. However, concerning the time complexity, and for the sample size n = 5000, the time MVSA takes gets larger than the NMF-MVT time for, roughly, p &gt; 15.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Robustness to outliers and noise</head><p>When there are outliers and noise in the data set, we run a final step in which we replace the hard constraint QY 0 with the soft constraint -1 T hinge(-QY )1n, where hinge(x) is an element-wise operator that, for each component, yields the negative part of x. The modified optimization problem is</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">Q * = arg max Q log | det(Q)| -λ 1 T hinge(QY )1n s.t. : 1 T p Q = qm,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where λ controls the relative weight between the soft constraint and the the log | det(Q)| term. Notice that, this soft constraint gives zero weight to nonnegative abundance fractions and negative weight to negative abundance fractions. In this way there is slack for the abundance fractions originated in outliers or noise to be negative.</p><p>To solve (5), we apply again SQP to the new objective function, but now removing the inequality constraint, i.e., Q := SQP(f sof t , Q0, Aeq, beq, g, H), where f sof t is the new objective function, Q0 is the output of steps 1 to 8 shown at the end of Section 2, and Aeq, beq, g, H are defined as before.</p><p>We applied this robust version of the MVSA algorithm to the data set described above, with n = 5000 and p = 3, but now introducing additive zero-mean Gaussian noise to the spectral v ectors such as the SNR ≡ A 2 F / w 2 F (w denotes the noise cube) was</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III -252</head><p>set to 10 dB. The errors ?</p><p>M -M F of the MVSA and NMF-MVT estimated endmember matrices were of 0.2 and 1.2, respectively. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows the results. Notice the good performance of the MVSA algorithm. This are just very preliminar results that, nevertheless, illustrates the potential of this soft constraint tool. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have introduced the minimum volume simplex analysis (MVSA) algorithm, a new method to unmix hyperspectral data, under the linear mixing model. MVSA fits a minimum volume simplex to the data set, imposing positivity and sum to one constraints on the abundance fractions. The resulting optimization problem is solved by finding the solution of the respective Kuhn-Tucker equations using a sequencial quadratic programming (SQP) method.</p><p>A shortcoming of the minimum volume simplex framework is that even a single outlier may force the simplex of minimum volume to be far away from a reasonable solution. To cope with outliers and noise, we have introduced a robust version of the MVSA algorithm. In this version, the positivity hard constraint imposed on the abundance fractions was replaced by a soft constraint of hinge loss type. This formulation seeks for a minimum volume simplex where most abundance fractions are nonnegative allowing, however, some may be negative.</p><p>The effectiveness of the new method was illustrated in a limited comparison with the state-of-the-art non-negative matrix factorization method <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>, where the MVSA method yielded very competitive results.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Unmixing results for (a) p = 3 and (b) p = 10 number of endmembers for MVSA, MNF-MVT, and VCA algorithms. Dots represent spectral vectors; all other symbols represent inferred endmembers by the unmixing algorithms. Notice que quality of MVSA estimates.This section presents results obtained by MVSA, VCA, and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Noisy scenario. As in Fig. 1 for n = 5000, p = 3, and SNR = 10 dB.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Comparison of MVSA and NMF-MVT algorithms for different number of endmembers and sample size n = 5000. The time is in seconds and A F stands for the Frobenius norm of matrix A.</figDesc><table><row><cell>p</cell><cell cols="2">MVSA M -M F time (sec.) ?</cell><cell cols="2">NMF-MVT M -M F time (sec.) ?</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0.876</cell><cell>153</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>0.04</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0.785</cell><cell>344</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>74</cell><cell>5.154</cell><cell>730</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>References</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithm taxonomy for hyperspectral unmixing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Manolakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Keshava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Algorithms for Multispectral, Hyperspectral, and Ultraspectral Imagery</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4049</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proc. SPIE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vertex component analysis: A fast algorithm to unmix hyperspectral data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nascimento</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bioucas-Dias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="898" to="910" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A quantitative and comparative analysis of endmembr extraction algorithms from hyperspectral data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Perez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Plaza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Plaza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="650" to="663" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does independent component analysis play a role in unmixing hyperspectral data?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nascimento</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bioucas-Dias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endmember extraction from highly mixed data using minimum volume constrained nonegative matrix factorization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Miao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="765" to="777" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimum-volume transforms for remotely sensed data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="542" to="552" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hyerspectral unmixing algorithm via dependent component analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nascimento</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bioucas-Dias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Internationla Geoscience and Remote sensing Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4033" to="4036" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semisupervised linear spectral unmixing using a hierarchical bayesian model for hyperspectral imagery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dobigeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-Y</forename><surname>Tourneret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-I</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2684" to="2695" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the decomposition of mars hyperspectral data by ica and bayesian positive source separation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moussaoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauksdóttir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jutten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chanussot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Douté</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Benediksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurocomputing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>accepted</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">N-FINDR: an algorithm for fast autonomous spectral endmember determination in hyperspectral data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Winter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the SPIE conference on Imaging Spectrometry V</title>
		<meeting>of the SPIE conference on Imaging Spectrometry V</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3753</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="275" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automating spectral unmixing of aviris data using convex geometry concepts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Boardman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">JPL Pub.93-26,AVIRIS Workshop</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="14" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial/spectral endmember extraction by multidimensional morphological operations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Perez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Plaza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Plaza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2025" to="2041" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new growing method for simplex-based endmember extraction algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-I</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Ouyang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2804" to="2819" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-negative least-correlated component analysis for separation of dependent sources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chong-Yung</forename><surname>Chi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Workshop on Optimization and Signal Processing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hong Kong</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>The Chinese University Hong Kong</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hyperspectral image unmixing via alternating projected subgradients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Skaf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Parente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zymnis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Asilomar Conference</title>
		<meeting>Asilomar Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new scheme for decomposition of mixed pixels based on nonnegative matrix factorization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Liming</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Xutao</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bin</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jian Qiu</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Internationla Geoscience and Remote sensing Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1759" to="1762" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hyperspectral subspace identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bioucas-Dias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nascimento</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fletcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Practical Methods of Optimization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley and Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
