<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Cooperative driving: an ant colony system for autonomous intersection management</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011-10-12">12 October 2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jia</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
							<email>jia.wu@utbm.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Systèmes et Transports</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Technologie de Belfort-Montbéliard</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Rue Thierry Mieg</addrLine>
									<postCode>90010</postCode>
									<settlement>Belfort cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Systèmes et Transports</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Technologie de Belfort-Montbéliard</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Rue Thierry Mieg</addrLine>
									<postCode>90010</postCode>
									<settlement>Belfort cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Abdeljalil</forename><surname>Abbas-Turki</surname></persName>
							<email>abdeljalil.abbas-turki@utbm.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Systèmes et Transports</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Technologie de Belfort-Montbéliard</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Rue Thierry Mieg</addrLine>
									<postCode>90010</postCode>
									<settlement>Belfort cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Systèmes et Transports</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Technologie de Belfort-Montbéliard</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Rue Thierry Mieg</addrLine>
									<postCode>90010</postCode>
									<settlement>Belfort cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Abdellah</forename><surname>El</surname></persName>
							<email>abdellah.el-moudni@utbm.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Systèmes et Transports</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Technologie de Belfort-Montbéliard</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Rue Thierry Mieg</addrLine>
									<postCode>90010</postCode>
									<settlement>Belfort cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">El</forename><surname>Moudni</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Systèmes et Transports</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Technologie de Belfort-Montbéliard</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Rue Thierry Mieg</addrLine>
									<postCode>90010</postCode>
									<settlement>Belfort cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Cooperative driving: an ant colony system for autonomous intersection management</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2011-10-12">12 October 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5189BFD0563EB2476F1A59DCAA2B92F0</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10489-011-0322-z</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T11:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Ant colony system</term>
					<term>Cooperative driving</term>
					<term>Autonomous intersection management</term>
					<term>Wireless communication</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Autonomous intersection management (AIM) is an innovative concept for directing vehicles through the intersections. AIM assumes that the vehicles negotiate the right-of-way. This assumption makes the problem of the intersection management significantly different from the usually studied ones such as the optimization of the cycle time, splits, and offsets. The main difficulty is to define a strategy that improves the traffic efficiency. Indeed, due to the fact that each vehicle is considered individually, AIM faces a combinatorial optimization problem that needs quick and efficient solutions for a real time application. This paper proposes a strategy that evacuates vehicles as soon as possible for each sequence of vehicle arrivals. The dynamic programming (DP) that gives the optimal solution is shown to be greedy. A combinatorial explosion is observed if the number of lanes rises. After evaluating the time complexity of the DP, the paper proposes an ant colony system (ACS) to solve the control problem for large number of vehicles and lanes. The complete investigation shows that the proposed ACS algorithm is robust and efficient. Experimental results obtained by the simulation of different traffic scenarios show</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Electronic supplementary material The online version of this article</head></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Over the past decade, wireless technologies with positioning systems have received a great attention <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> since they offer a tremendous potential for reinforcing the link between the vehicles (the drivers), the traffic environment, and the control system. A new active research area, cooperative driving, has appeared. Cooperative driving was first introduced in the early 1990s <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> for the lane changing and merging in platoon. Then, it has been further investigated in the fields like the freeway on ramp system <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, guiding vehicle through unsignalized intersection <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>, which uses another appellation "Autonomous Intersection Management" (AIM).</p><p>More precisely, by means of V2I (Vehicle-to-Infrastructure) and positioning technology, the traffic controller is continuously aware of the number of vehicles, their positions, and their speeds. The traffic control algorithms can be based on new data <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, even be completely changed <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> for un-signalized intersection. AIM explicitly determines the sequences of vehicles or robots for a real-time application. A sequence is a stringent order of distributing the right-of-way to vehicles or to robots. The right-of-way is sent to the robot or displayed to the driver by means of the onboard signalization. Each vehicle that approaches the intersection is managed separately and waits for receiving its right-of-way before crossing the intersection. Vehicle informs the others (vehicles or infrastructure) about its arrival time, its access time, and its exit time. Other information such as the movement, the braking, and the speed of vehicles could be collected to distribute the right-of-way. AIM requires vehicles equipped with at least a positioning system and a wireless communication system which is able to communicate with the infrastructure.</p><p>The AIM is quite different from the traditional traffic control system and presents the following important novelties:</p><p>-Unlike the traditional control systems that decide the duration of phases (the green light given to movements) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> or decide whether or not the phase is still kept for another period of time <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>, AIM allows to precisely decide which vehicle has the right-of-way and addresses the right-of-way to only admitted vehicles. -The decision is performed according to the actually observed traffic instead of predicting the volume of the traffic from the past statements of the inductive loops. -It uses cooperative driving techniques for deciding an optimized sequence. -It facilitates the deployment of priority policies between vehicles because each vehicle is considered individually.</p><p>Most researches of AIM are dedicated to the safety issues, i.e. avoid vehicle collision at intersection <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Recently, more and more researches address the traffic efficiency-the optimization of the passing sequence <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. It is noted that one of the major difficulties of the latter is the traffic control complexity since each vehicle is considered individually. Here we enumerate two typical works to the best of our knowledge. One notable work is the one presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The authors have enumerated all feasible schedules (all allowable passing sequences of vehicles). Then trajectory planning algorithms were used to choose the most efficient schedule that guides the vehicles to cross the intersection as soon as possible. The idea of this work is quite novel since it not only considers the safety of driving, but also takes into account the traffic efficiency. However, as the author pointed out that the main problem of this method is the complexity of cooperative driving planning: it exponentially increases with the number of vehicles and lanes. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, the authors have proposed a dynamic programming and a branch and bound algorithm, respectively. Both algorithms optimize the sequence without enumerating all possible solutions. However, the complexity exponentially increases with the number of lanes.</p><p>Another notable work is realized by Kurt and Peter <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>. They have introduced an intelligent agent, called intersection manager, which assigns reservations of space and time to each autonomous vehicle, operated by a driver agent. The intersection control policy is based on FCFS (First Come First Serve) policy with a low computational cost. More recently (2010), a mixed reality platform on which an autonomous vehicle can interact with multiple virtual vehicles is implemented <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, in order to show feasibility of AIM. The experience shows that AIM outperforms traffic signals and stop signs in low traffic load (≤140 vehicles/hour/lane). Nevertheless, a query is raised about this simple control policy: Is it still efficient to control traffic in heavy traffic load?</p><p>All the above researches show that the proper arrangement of passing sequence will improve the traffic efficiency at intersections. However, the solution space of sorting vehicles is very huge. This paper proposes a heuristic based on an ant colony system algorithm, for quickly obtaining efficient sequences. The algorithm is compared to AIM based on FCFS control policy and to three other recent traffic control strategies that use traffic lights. The first one is an adaptive traffic light control that uses inductive loops for evaluating the traffic volume. The two other strategies use wireless communication and positioning technologies to optimize the green light duration.</p><p>This paper is organized as follows: First, a basic configuration of AIM system is introduced. Then the system behavior is analyzed. Based on the analysis, the traffic control at intersection is formulated as a combinational optimization problem. The problem complexity is discussed. Although an algorithm of dynamic programming can find an optimal solution <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, it cannot fulfill the real-time requirement as the problem complexity grows. Therefore, we draw an analogy between the dealt problem and a traveling salesman problem (TSP), with respect to all the constraints. Then, an ant colony system algorithm that has efficiently solved TSP <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> is adopted to solve the problem more quickly with ensuring the accuracy. The main idea of this algorithm works to search an approximate solution of combinatorial optimization problems by a set of ants which cooperate through exchanging information via pheromone. Finally, the paper discusses the results of simulations before concluding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">System overview</head><p>The AIM system gets the following important ambitions:</p><p>-The accesses to the intersection are ordered (sequence) according to the requests received from the vehicles via the wireless communication. -Each vehicle individually receives its right-of-way, with respect to the sequence. -Each vehicle as well as the infrastructure instantaneously participates to the decision making process. -Regardless technological and practical limitations, such as the road capacity or the restriction of the wireless communication, the traffic management at intersections is able to consider an unbounded number of vehicles without a preprogrammed schedule.</p><p>In the following, we will discuss the architecture of the studied protocol of AIM through the negotiation architecture and the signalization strategy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Negotiation network</head><p>To the best of our knowledge, there are two possible architectures of the negotiation network. The first one is decentralized. Each vehicle directly negotiates with the other vehicles to obtain the right-of-way. The second one is centralized. The intersection manager receives the requests of vehicles and sends the right-of-way accordingly.</p><p>The decentralized prototype presented by Grünewald, Rust and Witkowski <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> has shown that collisions would occur if a vehicle had missed some messages broadcasted by other vehicles. This is due to the fact that each robot autonomously decides the right-of-way for itself according to its presence list which can be inconsistent. A centralized architecture overcomes this problem, if the decision is taken by a referee (intersection manager) that owns a common presence list. This architecture contributes to avoid some collision, even if the list is incomplete. Indeed, all missed vehicles are not able to traverse the intersection until they are included into the presence list of the intersection manager.</p><p>However, this rule raises another problem. Deadlock is possible if there are no supplemental positioning technologies (e.g., position markers) in order to make the intersection manager aware of the order of approaching vehicles. As proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, robots detect position markers (landmarks) at particular points of the infrastructure, in order to avoid deadlocks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Signalization strategy</head><p>There are at least two strategies that allow a vehicle to go through the intersection. The simpler one informs a particular vehicle that the conflict zone is free. A more sophisticated one specifies the time and the velocity of the reservation given to each vehicle. The second strategy deserves more attention. This strategy states that the vehicle loses the reservation if it determines that it will not arrive at the intersection at the time and/or the velocity specified in the reservation. In this case, the vehicle may be unable to stop in front of the conflict zone due to the physical parameters of the situation. Hence, a vehicle must estimate whether it will respect the reservation specification before a given time and position. Otherwise, collision is possible because vehicle is not as controllable as one can expect <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. This safety issue is well-known in the traffic engineering literature (see dilemma zone <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>). One solution to this problem is to consider a buffer time, as stated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Protocol of AIM</head><p>Based on the above description, we propose a basic protocol of AIM system. The protocol is a centralized architecture of discrete point positioning and signaling technology. The main objective of the first technology is to guarantee that an authenticated vehicle is currently passing over a particular point of the infrastructure. Consider a 4-lane intersection as presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, where each lane is divided into two zones by the conflict zone: the storage zone and the exit zone. Position markers are placed at the entry of each zone. Thus, there are three position markers on each lane. This configuration could confirm the arrival of a vehicle (by the position marker 1), its access to the conflict zone (by the position marker 2), and its departure (by the position marker 3).</p><p>The signaling technology uses existing DSRC (Dedicated Short Range Communications) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> to transmit and receive text-based signals. The main objective of this technology is to successfully transmit the right-of-ways. The communication between vehicles and the intersection manager is mainly divided into three stages according to the movement of vehicle: the request of the right-of-way, the delivery of the rightof-way, and the removal of the right-of-way. The signaling technology combines with the technology of discrete point positioning to authenticate vehicles and to send the appropriate data according to their positions.</p><p>Based on this protocol, we can picture the operation of the system (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). When a vehicle arrives at the intersection (it passes over the position marker 1), the intersection manager sends the map of the intersection to this vehicle and locks its right-of-way. Then it computes the best se- quence and accordingly distributes the appropriate right-ofways to the first admitted vehicles of non-conflicting movements. When the last admitted vehicle passes over the position marker 3, it proceeds to free vehicles of the conflicting movements and so on. If some vehicles arrive before the end of the sequence, the intersection manager computes a new sequence without considering vehicles that have already received the right-of-way. The objective of this rule is to avoid an emergency braking to the drivers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Problem formulation</head><p>The main concern of AIM is to define the passing sequence based on vehicles' information. Before proposing a solution to this problem, traffic pattern of the proposed system is analyzed at first. Then, the formulation of the control problem is given based on the analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Traffic pattern at an isolated intersection controlled by AIM</head><p>Since the concept of AIM is quite different from traditional traffic system which relies on the estimation of traffic flow rate, we need to focus on the discrete events observed by position markers:</p><p>1. Vehicle arrivals at the intersection; 2. Vehicle accesses to the conflict zone; 3. Vehicle departures.</p><p>Events <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> are the input data of the control problem and other events are used to ensure the safety. To decide the passing sequence, the system needs only an estimation of the instants of accesses to the conflict zone. Thus, we are interested in approximating the access times in consideration of the following three parameters:</p><p>1. τ : the lower bound of the time taken to cover the distance between the position marker 1 and 2, which is used to predict the theoretical arrival time of vehicle; 2. d: the minimum safe headway time between two successive vehicles that move on the same lane (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>(a)); 3. s: the minimum time between two successive vehicles that access to the conflict zone from conflicting movements (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(b)</ref>).</p><p>To ensure the safety in the conflict zone, right-of-ways are assigned to vehicles of non-conflicting (compatible) movements. For example, a safe interval s is entailed between two vehicles from lanes L 1 and L 3 (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). s takes into account the start-up lost time <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and the time for clear-Fig. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Two conflicting movements of a 4-lane intersection shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, following the National Electrical Manufacturers Association convention. For sake of readability, the turn-left and turn-right movements are not presented ance of the conflict zone. In the reminder, we will call s and d safe headway.</p><p>τ , d and s depend on several parameters such as pavement surface conditions, profiles of the drivers, and weather conditions. One way to accurately estimate them is to refer to empirical observations. Literature is rich in terms of values and formulas with adjustment factors for approximating these parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29]</ref>. Since the scope of this paper is not the estimation of these values, we will use the widely admitted standards <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Formulation of the control problem</head><p>Now, let us concentrate on the control of AIM. The main question is: how can the system ensure smoother traffic flow based on the observations of position markers? One answer to this question is to optimize the sequence of accesses to the conflict zone at each arrival of vehicles.</p><p>More precisely, given the presence list of vehicles by position markers 1 and theoretical arrival times at the conflict zone, the control of AIM involves a passing sequence of vehicles which minimizes the maximum exit time (the time when the last vehicle traverses the conflict zone), on respecting the safe headways.</p><p>The formulation of the control in AIM is presented in the following (Notations are defined in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>):</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Given : r (i,1) , . . . , r (i,n i ) , i ∈ [1, L] with r (i,q i ) &lt; r (i,q i +1) , q i ∈ [1, n i -1] Find min max i∈[1,L] {e (i,n i ) }</formula><p>Subjects to the constraints:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">|e (i,q i ) -e (j,q j ) | ≥ d, i = j ∧ q i = q j + 1, s, i ˆ =j, e (i,q i ) ≥ r (i,q i ) (1)</formula><p>where ˆ = denotes two conflicting movements coming from lanes L i and L j . </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(i, q i )</formula><p>The q i th arrival vehicle on the lane L i r (i,q i ) The theoretical arrival time of vehicle (i, q i ) e (i,q i ) The exit time of vehicle (i, q i ). The exit time refers to the time when a vehicle accesses to the conflict zone d Safe headway respected by vehicles on the same lane s Safe headway respected by vehicles of conflicting movements</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 2 Parameters of an example</head><p>Theoretical arrival times d s</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">L 1 r (1,1) = 0 r (1,2) = 3 r (1,3) = 8 2 6 L 2 r (2,1) = 1 r (2,2) = 5 r (2,3) = 10 L 3 r (3,1) = 4 r (3,2) = 7 L 4 r (4,1) = 6</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> An optimal vehicles passing sequence of the example given in Table <ref type="table">2</ref> The minimization of the maximum exit time is an interesting approach to reduce the vehicle delay. Indeed, as the authors prove in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, the earlier the vehicles are able to exit the network (by appropriate use of the available control measures) the less time they will have spent in the network.</p><p>To better explain the control process, consider an example where nine vehicles are present at a 4-lane intersection in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. There are three vehicles present on lanes L 1 , L 2 respectively, two on L 3 and one on L 4 . All the vehicles have not yet the right-of-way. The infrastructure provides the date at which these vehicles will be theoretically ready to cross the conflict zone, according to the observations of the position marker 1 and the parameters τ , d and s. Table <ref type="table">2</ref> summarizes all the required data to compute the best passing sequence. Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> presents an optimal sequence with the minimal exit time, i.e. 17 seconds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Complexity</head><p>One of the major obstacles to achieve AIM is the problem complexity because the control considers each vehicle individually. The following proposition gives us the number of all feasible sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposition 1 An intersection of L-lane admits exactly</head><formula xml:id="formula_4">L i=1 n i ! L i=1 (n i !) (2)</formula><p>ordered sequences of vehicles.</p><p>Proof There are L i=1 n i ! possible sequences. As on each lane, the n i vehicles are stringently ordered (vehicle-overtake is forbidden after they have crossed the position marker 1), we conclude that the number of all feasible sequences equals to <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</p><p>We observe that the complexity of problem sharply increases with the number of vehicles and lanes. Hence, it is not possible to find the optimal solution by an exhaustive search. Hence, we could make use of some precious theories in combinational optimization. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, a dynamic programming algorithm is used to successfully solve the control problem in a simple intersection with two lanes. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, a branch and bound algorithm is proposed. Both algorithms can be generalized easily for the control of any layout of intersection <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32]</ref>. To the best of our knowledge, the time complexity is not lower than (n L ), where n and L denote the total number of vehicles present at intersection and the number of lanes, respectively. However, it should be noted that even if the proposed control strategy has greatly reduced the time complexity, as the geometries of intersection become more complex, the computing time increases significantly. Hereby, the control strategy based on an exact algorithm cannot fulfill the real-time requirement of AIM. That argues for seeking help from meta-heuristics which have good reputations in solving complex problem in short time.</p><p>In the following, we use the ant colony system to solve the problem (1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Control strategy: ant colony system</head><p>Ant colony optimization (ACO) is one of the meta-heuristic optimization methods, which is inspired by the foraging behavior of ant colonies, and targets discrete optimization problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. In the framework of ACO, a set of artificial ants cooperate to find the solution of a problem by exchanging information via pheromone deposited on graph edges <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. ACO has been successfully applied to many combinatorial optimization problems, e.g., TSP <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36]</ref>, assignment problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>, scheduling problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>, and vehicle routing problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>.</p><p>TSP <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> is one of the most famous combinatorial optimization problems, where the goal is to find the shortest route that visits all the cities once and just once, given the finite number of cities and the distance between any two cities. In fact, there is an analogy between the problem (1) and the TSP. If we consider each vehicle as a city to be visited, then the required headway between each pair of vehicles determines the distance between two adjacent cities. Thus, the problem (1) can be converted to an analogous TSP, where the shortest path that visits each city once and just once corresponds to the sequence of vehicles with the minimal exit time. In this way, the ACS algorithm, one of the most successful ACO variants, is proper to solve <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Before introducing the ACS algorithm, a graphical representation of the problem (1) is needed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Graphical representation of the problem</head><p>In this subsection, we consider a 4-lane intersection (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). However, we draw the reader's attention to the fact that the proposed control strategy can be applied to all intersection layouts. An acyclic and directed graph G = (V , A, w) with n + 2 nodes is constructed as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6</ref>. V (nodes) represents all the present vehicles and two dummy nodes, A (arcs) indicates the precedence relationship between two nodes (vehicles) and w (weights) denotes the weight of arc (safe headway time).</p><p>A node (i, q i ) represents the q i th arrival vehicle of the lane L i , where 1 ≤ q i ≤ n i , i ∈ [1, L]. The two dummy nodes S (Source node) and T (Terminate node) indicate the beginning and the end of a sequence, respectively. The weight of arc (v i , v j ), are defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">w(v i , v j ) = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ d, if v i = (i, q i ) and v j = (i, q i + 1) s, if v i = (i, q i ), v j = (j, q j ) and i ˆ =j 0, otherwise<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where ˆ = denotes two conflicting movements coming from lanes L i and L j .</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6</ref> illustrates all the successors of a node (1, 2) in the graph G. A weight d is assigned to the arc from (1, 2) to (1, 3) since the vehicles (1, 2) and (1, 3) on the same lane must respect a minimal safe headway d; while the weight of arcs from (1, 2) to all the nodes on the lane L 2 equals to 0 since movements of vehicles on the lanes L 1 and L 2 are non-conflicting. For the arcs from (1, 2) to (3, 1), (3, 2), and (4, 1), a weight s is assigned to each arc because the movement of the vehicle (1, 2) conflicts with any movement of vehicles coming from L 3 and L 4 . It should be noted that for other nodes, the similar precedence relations (arcs) can be deduced as the node (1, 2). Hence, all arcs of the graph (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6</ref>) are not represented, for sake of readability.</p><p>A feasible solution of the problem ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) is a path P (S, T ) from the source node S to the terminate node T which visits all the nodes of the graph once and only once with respect to the precedence constraints defined by the arcs. In the reminder of this paper, a path refers to a feasible solution of the problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</p><p>Based on the definition of the graph G, the length of a sub-path from S to a node (i, q i ) (denoted as L (i,q i ) ) indicates the access time of the corresponding vehicle (i, q i ) in a sequence. However, L (i,q i ) ≥ r (i,q i ) , r (i,q i ) denotes the theoretical arrival time. Hence, r (i,q i ) is marked at the top of each node (i, q i ) in order to restrict the length of sub-path. With this in mind, the length of a path P (S, T ) denoted as L T is calculated by the following recurrent formula that begins from the node S and terminates at the node T :</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">L v j = max{L v i + w(v i , v j ), r v j }<label>(4)</label></formula><p>with v i the direct predecessor of v j and r v j the theoretical arrival time of the node v j , L S = 0. A path P * (S, T ) is an optimal solution of the problem, iff for all paths P (S, T ), we have L * T ≤ L T .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Solution construction</head><p>The ACS algorithm (Algorithm path, an ant also modifies the amount of pheromone on the visited arcs by applying the local updating rule. Once all ants have arrived at the node T , the amount of pheromone on arcs is modified by a global updating rule.</p><p>From the description of the above algorithm, the initialization of pheromone, the state transition rule, and the pheromone updating rule are needed to be specified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">Initialize pheromone values by heuristic</head><p>We use the method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> to set the initial pheromone τ 0 = (n • L 0 ) -1 , where n is the total number of nodes (i, q i ) and L 0 is the maximum exit time of the sequence found by a proposed heuristic.</p><p>This simple heuristic works as follows: right-of-ways are assigned to vehicles of non-conflicting movements whose headways are equal to the minimal value d. Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref> shows the sequence of the example introduced in Table <ref type="table">2</ref> by applying this heuristic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.2">State transition rule</head><p>An ant a is in the position of the node j , then it chooses the node k to move to by applying the state transition rule:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">k = ⎧ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ arg max u∈V a (j ) {τ (j, u) • η(j, u) β }, if q ≤ q 0 exploitation K, otherwise (biased exploration) (5)</formula><p>where τ (j, u) is the pheromone on the arc (j, u) and η(j, u) is the corresponding heuristic information if ant a moves from j to u, V a (j ) is the set of nodes that remain to be visited by the ant a positioned on the node j . The value of parameter β (β &gt; 0) denotes the importance of heuristic information. The parameter q 0 (0 ≤ q 0 ≤ 1) determines the relative importance of exploitation versus exploration: if q, a random number uniformly distributed in [0, 1], is smaller than q 0 , then the ant a chooses the next vehicle k with the maximal value τ (j, u) • η(j, u) β , that is called exploitation; otherwise, the next node is expressed as a random variable K, which is chosen according to the probability distribution (6):</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">p a (j, k) = τ (j,k)•η(j,k) β u∈Va (j ) τ (j,u)•η(j,u) β , if k ∈ V a (j ) 0, otherwise<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">6</ref>) gives the probability with which the ant a chooses to move to the node k.</p><p>The heuristic information η(j, k) represents the impact on the length of sub-path L k after visiting the node k, which is defined as the reciprocal of the increase of length plus 1, as shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">η(j, k) = (L k -L j + 1) -1<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where L j and L k are given in (4). The reason of adding 1 is to prevent the denominator from being 0. The state transition rule favors transitions toward nodes connected by short arcs and with large amount of pheromone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.3">Pheromone updating rule</head><p>During the process of building a solution, ants change the pheromones of the visited arcs by the local updating rule:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">τ (j, k) = (1 -ρ) • τ (j, k) + ρ • τ 0 (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">)</formula><p>where τ 0 is the initial pheromone level and ρ is a pheromone decay parameter (0 &lt; ρ &lt; 1). The smaller the value of ρ, the faster the solution converges; whereas the larger it is, the diversity of the solution increases. By local updating rule, each time an ant passes through an arc, this arc becomes slightly less desirable for other ants. In this way, ants would not search in a narrow neighborhood of the best previous path.</p><p>After one iteration, all ants have finished a path from the node S to T and a global pheromone updating rule ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) is applied. However, only the globally best ant is allowed to deposit pheromone. This intends to lead ants to the neighborhood of the best path and results in a higher convergence speed.</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">τ (j, k) = (1 -α) • τ (j, k) + α • τ (j, k) (9)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">τ (j, k) = (L gb ) -1 , if (j, k) ∈ global-best-tour 0, otherwise<label>(10)</label></formula><p>α is the pheromone decay parameter (0 &lt; α &lt; 1) and L gb is the length of the globally best path until this iteration. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Analysis of ACS parameters</head><p>From the description of the ACS algorithm, we can see that the parameters α, β, ρ, q 0 , m, C decide the quality of the solution. Next, we will conduct a series of experiments to further investigate these parameters. For each parameter, its influence on the relative percentage deviation (RPD) of the optimal solution is studied. RPD is defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">RPD = s -s * s * × 100% (<label>11</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">)</formula><p>where s is the solution obtained by ACS and s * is an optimal solution calculated by the dynamic programming algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. The following experiments are implemented in Matlab on a 2.40 Ghz Pentium IV processor based PC. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> summarizes the experimental factors used to define the test scenarios: sum of flow rates of each compatible movement λ, simulation time T , number of conflicting movements M, safe headways d and s. The total number of vehicles is up to: n = λ×T ×M. We assume that the arrivals of vehicles obey the Poisson distribution which represents a real-life traffic system with sufficient accuracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. The first three factors are divided into three levels: L (Low), M (Middle) and H (High) according to the values. The safe headway d is set to 2 seconds since it is widely recognized that the maximum traffic flow rate is lesser than 0.5 vehicles per second <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>. Another safe headway s is set in the range of <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref> seconds.</p><p>Three test cases: case L, case M, and case H, are considered in the experiments. Ten independent runs are carried out and are averaged for each case. The values of parameters are set initially to the following values according to the report of Dorigo <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>: During the investigations, one or two parameters are changed each time to study its influence or their influences on the solution.</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">α = 0.1, β = 2, ρ = 0.1, q 0 = 0.9, m= 10</formula><p>The investigation begins with the parameter q 0 , which decides the degree of exploration versus exploitation. The value is set from 0 to 0.9 with a step length of 0.1. The result is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">8</ref>. We can see that the small value of q 0 (between 0.1 and 0.3) gives better results. Therefore, q 0 is set to 0.1. This configuration favors the biased exploration, which encourages exploring the arcs with less pheromone.</p><p>Next, the parameters α and ρ are tested together. They decide the speed of pheromone decay during the local updating and the global updating. The two parameters are set from 0 to 0.9 with a step length of 0.1. The values of the rest parameters: β = 2, q 0 = 0.1, m = 10. The results are reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>.</p><p>We can see that in each case, the combination of α = 0.3, ρ = 0.1 give the minimum RPD. This configuration will increase the speed of the pheromone evaporation on the arcs out of the best path. As a consequence, the optimal solution obtained so far will be reinforced. Now let us consider the parameter β. The value of β determines the importance of heuristic information. It is set from 0 to 5 with a step length of 1. The values of tested parameters are set to the following values: α = 0.3, ρ = 0.1, q 0 = 0.1, m = 10. Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref> presents the experiment results.</p><p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>, it is better to set β as 3. Besides, for each case, in particular case H, when β is 0, the performance of ACS become extremely poor since the information of heuristic plays an important role in the algorithm.</p><p>The last two important parameters are m and C. These parameters are related to not only the quality of solution but also to the computation cost. We begin the investigation by the parameter m, which denotes the number of ants. In the experiments, m varies from 5 to 25 with a step length  ρ α 0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 0 0 0.38 0.13 0.63 0.65 0.37 0 0.12 0.12 0.75 0.1 0 0.13 0 0 0 0 0.13 0.14 0.13 0 0.2 0.25 0 0 0 0 0.14 0 0.13 0.13 0.13 0.3 0 0 0.13 0 0.26 0 0 0 0.13 0.14 0.4 0.12 0 0.14 0.14 0 0.13 0.13 0 0.27 0.27 0.5 0 0 0.26 0 0.12 0.39 0 0.13 0.51 0.12 0.6 0.13 0.27 0 0.13 0 0 0.13 0.13 0 0.13 0.7 0.13 0.13 0.12 0 0 0 0.26 0.13 0 0.13 0.8 0 0 0.26 0 0.13 0.25 0 0 0.13 0.12 0.9 0.26 0 0.13 0.25 0 0.14 0 0.13 0 0.13 (c) Case H ρ α 0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 0 1. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_17">= 0.3, ρ = 0.1, β = 3 q 0 = 0.1, C = 5.</formula><p>The results about the RPD and the computation cost (CPU time) are presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">10</ref>. Obviously, the quality of the solution enhances as the number of m increases. However, considering the computation cost, a compromise must be made. Since m = 5 gives a relative good solution (RPD &lt; 2.5%) in short calculation time (&lt;1 s), the value of 5 is suggested. As the parameter m, C determines the precision of solution and the computation cost. The value of C is taken from 5 to 50, while other parameters α, ρ, q 0 , β, m take values 0.3, 0.1, 0.1, 3, 5, respectively. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">11</ref> shows the influence of the parameter C on the quality of the solution and the computation cost. Based on these results, we can see that a value of 5 will achieve the best possible compromise.</p><p>From the above experiments, the parameters of ACS are: α = 0.3, ρ = 0.1, β = 3, q 0 = 0.1, m = 5, C = 5. The configuration of the parameters is adapted to any layout of intersection, since several intersections are considered to obtain these values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Example</head><p>Now we apply ACS algorithm to the example introduced at the end of Sect. 3.2.</p><p>At first, the pheromone is initialized:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">τ 0 = (n • L 0 ) -1 = 1 9 × 26 = 0.0043</formula><p>where L 0 is the length of a feasible path found by the proposed heuristic shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>.</p><p>Then Algorithm 1 is implemented and yields a solution in 0.17 seconds, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">12</ref>. The number at the top of each node (i, q i ) denotes the access time of the corresponding vehicle. The sequence of nodes on the shortest path corresponds to the optimal passing sequence of vehicles (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">13</ref> presents the simulation of microscopic carfollowing behavior based on the optimal passing sequence. Gipps model <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54]</ref> is used to simulate the vehicle behavior since it shows lower error values on the accuracy of a traffic-simulation system <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref>. Each curve represents vehicle's relative distance to the position marker 1 over time.</p><p>At the beginning, vehicles (1, 1) and (2, 1) receive the right-of-ways distributed by the intersection manager. Once Fig. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> An optimal solution found by ACS they have passed over the position marker 3, the intersection manager sends the right-of-ways to vehicles (3, 1), <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2)</ref>, and (4, 1) of conflicting movements. As the last vehicle (3, 2) has passed over the position marker 3, the left vehicles (1, 2), <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2)</ref>, and (2, 3) receive the right-of-ways.</p><p>We can note that the last four vehicles receive the rightof-way after 12 s rather than 15 s (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>). Since the exit time can be reduced in practical if the vehicles exit the intersection more quickly than expected. The position marker 3 will be helpful to save the time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Experiments</head><p>In this section, we will conduct a series of experiments to evaluate the robustness of the proposed algorithm. In addition, the traffic control effectiveness of AIM based on ACS will be studied.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Algorithm performance comparisons</head><p>The performance of Dynamic programming and ACS under different scenarios are investigated, i.e. level L, M and H defined in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>. Fifty test problems are generated for each level.</p><p>First, the accuracy of the algorithm ACS is measured by two criteria: the Relative Percentage Deviation (RPD) given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> and the Percentage of the Optimal Solution produced (POS). The results (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">5</ref>) show that as the scale of problem increases, although the average POS decreases, the average RPD keeps in a low value, i.e. the maximal average RPD = 2.45%.</p><p>Next, the computation times of ACS and the dynamic programming algorithm are compared (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">6</ref>). We note that ACS finds a high quality solution in a very short period of time (less than one second), even in the level H.</p><p>From above comparisons, we see that ACS consistently performs well in various scenarios on the solution quality while reducing the computational cost.   1. Adaptive control system: a traditional traffic control method which is proven efficient in the current traffic system. Here, the method presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> is used for comparison; 2. New traffic control system based on wireless communication proposed by Gradinescu <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>: the controller keeps tracking the vehicles by the wireless communication, thus the estimation of the traffic volume is more precise. The timing plan is updated in time (during each cycle). The famous Webster's formula <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref> is applied to calculate the cycle length and the green time according to the estimated demand; 3. New traffic control system proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>: the control strategy is based on the Little's formula <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>. The average delay experienced by the vehicles in the network is directly proportional to the average queue size. Hence, the controller tries to minimize the queue size by giving a green light to the approach with the maximal weighted queue length. The queue lengths are measured precisely by the advanced wireless communication and positioning technologies; 4. Autonomous intersection management proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>: This comparison aims to know whether the opti- mization of passing sequence will improve traffic efficiency in heavy traffic load. Hence, we compare our system with the AIM based on FCFS "First Come, First Served" control policy.</p><p>It is noted that although the new traffic systems 2 and 3 adopt the advanced technologies of wireless communication and of positioning systems, the traffic control is still based on traffic lights. In the following, we use the abbreviations "Adaptive", "Webster", "LQF-MWM", and "AIM (FCFS)" to represent the above systems, respectively. "AIM (ACS)" represents the AIM system based on the proposed ACS algorithm.</p><p>The performances of all the systems are evaluated by the following criteria:</p><p>1. Evacuation time: the time to evacuate all the vehicles present in one hour; 2. Throughput: the ratio between the number of vehicles passed over the position marker 2 and the number of vehicles passed over the position marker 1 during the time of simulation; 3. Mean vehicle delay: this quantity is calculated by the difference between the estimated travel time in the absence of the intersection control and the travel time in the presence of the intersection control; 4. Mean queue length: it is defined as the cumulative number of vehicles stopped before the conflict zone divided by the simulation time.</p><p>The intersection under consideration is a T-intersection of six lanes presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">14</ref>. The traffic is able to execute the left turn and right turn at this intersection. The set of conflicting movements are illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">15</ref>. The distance between the position marker 1 and 2 is 150 m and the lane width is 3.5 m. The simulation step is 1 s. The simulation runs sixty minutes and each point in the following  First, let us compare AIM (ACS) with the traditional traffic control system. The results show that AIM (ACS) outperforms the system "Adaptive". Besides, its performance is as stable as the system "Adaptive". Turning to the comparison with other new traffic control systems, AIM (ACS) also presents the best performance. We observe that "Webster" exhibits the poorest performance since its inherent limitation of the control strategy: although the green time is updated every cycle, it cannot react quickly to the traffic. For "LQF-MWM", it shows good performance at low traffic load (≤0.3 pcpspl), however as the traffic load in-   creases, its performance grows worse. That is due to the frequent change of right-of-way when each approach accumulates too many vehicles waiting for the right-of-way. The same conclusion can be drawn from "AIM (FCFS)". When the traffic load is low, i.e. ≤0.35 pcpspl, it has the compatible performance with "AIM (ACS)"; as the traffic load increases, it shows a sharp decline in its performance. The comparison with "AIM (FCFS)" proves that reasonable arrangement of vehicle passing sequence will improve the traffic efficiency.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Discussion</head><p>The simulations show that the proposed system has capacity to improve the traffic efficiency. Whereas, there are several issues that deserve further investigations:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Feasibility</head><p>A prototype based on NXT robots (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">20</ref>) has been built to study the feasibility of AIM. During the tests, we have not observed any collision. (As shown in the animation: Online Resource 1 and 2.) It is noted that the safety issue depends on the precision and the robustness of the positioning system. The prototype proves the feasibility of the proposed protocol of AIM, for at least industrial applications (e.g. robots). Moreover, the European Rail Traffic Management (ERTMS)/ETCS levels 2 and 3 control the train access to the block segments using electronic position markers (Eurobalise), as we have proposed in this paper.</p><p>We draw the reader's attention to the fact that AIM can be forthcoming because Europe (France, Germany, Switzerland, etc.) and the United States have launched clean car sharing programmes to reduce pollution in urban areas. Some programmes (e.g., PRAXITELE, Liselec, and Autolib in France, City-Car in Switzerland, IntelliShare in the USA) have planned to limit the access of certain zones of the city to green car sharing. In other words, some intersections of the urban area will be exclusively shared by fleets of vehicles that can be quickly equipped together for negotiating their access. Hence, AIM has a great potential to be applied in green car sharing zones.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Priority vehicles</head><p>Vehicles such as bus, vehicle with less pollution, can have the priority to cross intersection than common vehicles, as stated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. In this case, the intersection manager could take into account giving priority to these vehicles by assigning a weight to each vehicle. Vehicles with high priority have greater weights. The object of control turns to minimize the weighted sum of exit times of all present vehicles. The proposed algorithm can easily adapt to this new problem except that the length of the path corresponds to the weighted sum of vehicle exit time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Reaction to dangerous situations</head><p>Since generally the actual traffic is very complex, the intersection manager should be flexible to deal with emergencies. For example, how to deal with the situation where a vehicle suddenly stops in the conflict zone? The position marker 3 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) will help to reduce risks of collisions. If a vehicle stalls at the conflict zone, the position marker 3 will not inform the intersection manager of its departure. Thus, the intersection manager will not free the vehicles of the conflicting movements. Nevertheless, some supplemental surveillance equipments, such as traffic cameras, are needed to aid monitoring the traffic, as it is required for the current traffic control system (traffic lights). Hence, the proposed system just contributes to a better supervision and reduces the risk of collision.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Conclusion</head><p>This paper introduces a protocol of autonomous intersection management system to efficiently control the traffic. This new traffic control system is capable of managing the vehicles individually based on wireless communication and positioning technologies. The right-of-way is sent to the robot or displayed to the driver by means of the onboard signalization. Analysis of the new system renders the control as a combinational optimization problem. An algorithm of ant colony system is proposed to solve the control in real time. Simulations show that the proposed system performs better than the adaptive controller which is popularly used at present and even better than the innovative systems based on the new technologies. In addition, this system has the potential to be applied to any intersection with more complicated layout. In the future, we will provide more validation data not just limit on the simulation environment. Moreover, the proposed ant colony system is used to quickly improve a sequence that initially results from simple rules based on the headway time of each vehicle and on its temporal distance from the conflict zone. This encourages us to explore some interesting properties of the optimal solution for contributing to the decentralization of the sequence formation in the future.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1 Elementary configuration of the infrastructure</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 Communication between a new coming vehicle V3 and the intersection manager</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3 Safe headways</figDesc><graphic coords="4,315.09,322.23,222.23,124.86" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6 Graphical representation of the example inTable 2 (arcs from the node (1, 2) are illustrated)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8 Analysis of the parameter q 0</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 9 Fig. 10 Fig. 11</head><label>91011</label><figDesc>Fig. 9 Analysis of the parameter β</figDesc><graphic coords="10,53.31,285.70,233.26,390.42" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 13</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13 Simulation of Microscopic car-following behavior</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>5. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Traffic control effectivenessIn this part, the traffic control effectiveness (improvement in efficiency of traffic flow) of AIM based on ACS is evaluated. The simulation is implemented in a traffic simulation environment where the car-following model (Gipps model)<ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54]</ref> is used to simulate the behavior of vehicles. The inputs of the simulation (d, s and τ ) are provided by the regional project (Belfort, France) "Edude de Définition pour la Desserte en Transport Collectif et l'Intermodalité autour de la Future TGV de l'Aire Urbaine".The effectiveness of AIM based on ACS is compared with the following four traffic control systems:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 14 T</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14 T-intersection between the roads Boulevard John Fitzgerald Kennedy, Faubourg de Lyon, and Rue de Belfort at Belfort, France (map from http://maps.google.com)</figDesc><graphic coords="12,306.97,53.05,235.80,158.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 15</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Fig. 15 Layout and set of conflicting movements of T-intersection shown in Fig. 14</figDesc><graphic coords="13,53.76,334.90,232.20,170.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 16</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Fig. 16 Evacuation time (s: second)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 17</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Fig. 17Throughput</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 17Throughput</figDesc><graphic coords="13,306.36,53.06,237.24,167.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 18 Fig. 19</head><label>1819</label><figDesc>Fig. 18 Mean vehicle delay (s: second)</figDesc><graphic coords="13,306.97,260.40,235.80,155.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 20</head><label>20</label><figDesc>Fig. 20 Prototype of an elementary AIM</figDesc><graphic coords="14,51.44,53.05,236.88,176.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Definition of notation</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Notation Meaning</cell></row><row><cell>L</cell><cell>Total number of lanes</cell></row><row><cell>n</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>i Number of vehicles present on the lane L i</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Sequence of vehicles calculated by the proposed heuristic</figDesc><table><row><cell>Ant j uses a state transition rule to build a</cell></row><row><cell>solution;</cell></row><row><cell>A local pheromone updating rule is applied;</cell></row><row><cell>end for</cell></row><row><cell>A global pheromone updating rule is applied;</cell></row><row><cell>end for</cell></row><row><cell>Fig. 7</cell></row></table><note><p>1) is applied, in order to find the shortest path P * (S, T ). It works as follows: m ants are positioned on the node S at first. Each ant builds a path from S to T by the state transition rule. While constructing its Algorithm 1 ACS ALGORITHM Initialize pheromone values based on a heuristic; Deposit m ants on the node S; for i = 1, . . . , C do (C: Number of iterations) for j = 1, . . . , m do (m : Number of ants)</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Experimental design for generating test scenarios</figDesc><table><row><cell>Experimental factors</cell><cell>Values</cell><cell>Levels</cell></row><row><cell>Sum of arrival rates λ</cell><cell>U a [0, 0.15]</cell><cell>L</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>U[0.15, 0.3]</cell><cell>M</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>U[0.3, 0.5]</cell><cell>H</cell></row><row><cell>Simulation time T</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>L</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>100</cell><cell>M</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>150</cell><cell>H</cell></row><row><cell>Number of conflicting traffic movements M</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>L</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>4</cell><cell>M</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>6</cell><cell>H</cell></row><row><cell>Safe headway d</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Safe headway s</cell><cell>U[3, 10]</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>a Uniform distribution</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Analysis of parameters α and ρ</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Accuracy of ACS</figDesc><table><row><cell>Levels</cell><cell>RPD</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Average POS</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Minimum</cell><cell>Maximum</cell><cell>Average</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>L</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>3.13%</cell><cell>0.23%</cell><cell>93%</cell></row><row><cell>M</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>3.90%</cell><cell>0.56%</cell><cell>66%</cell></row><row><cell>H</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>5.19%</cell><cell>2.45%</cell><cell>8%</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Average computation time (seconds)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Levels</cell><cell>Dynamic programming</cell><cell>ACS</cell></row><row><cell>L</cell><cell>0 .1439</cell><cell>0.0832</cell></row><row><cell>M</cell><cell>1 0 .1722</cell><cell>0.3642</cell></row><row><cell>H</cell><cell>350.2716</cell><cell>0.9939</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cooperative driving of automated vehicles with inter-vehicle communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sakaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Uno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tsugawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE intelligent vehicles symposium</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE intelligent vehicles symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="516" to="521" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A merging control algorithm based on inter-vehicle communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Uno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sakaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tsugawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings 1999 IEEE/IEEJ/JSAI international conference on intelligent transportation systems</title>
		<meeting>1999 IEEE/IEEJ/JSAI international conference on intelligent transportation systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="783" to="787" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inter-vehicle communications and their applications to intelligent vehicles: an overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tsugawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE intelligent vehicle symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002. 2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="564" to="569" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Practical results of a longitudinal control concept for truck platooning with vehicle to vehicle communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Gehring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE conference on intelligent transportation system 1997</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="122" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated vehicle control developments in the PATH program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shladover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Desoer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hedrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tomizuka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Walrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mcmahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sheikholeslam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mckeown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Veh Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="130" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collision avoidance among AGVs at junctions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Raina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mittal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE intelligent vehicles symposium</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE intelligent vehicles symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000. 2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="589" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cooperative driving at blind crossings using intervehicle communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Fei-Yue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Veh Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1712" to="1724" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of an optimization methodology for adaptive traffic signal control at diamond interchanges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Elefteriadou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Transp Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="629" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive traffic lights using car-to-car communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gradinescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gorgorin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Diaconescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Cristea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Iftode</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE 65th vehicular technology conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Spring</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007. 2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="25" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel signal-scheduling algorithm with quality-of-service provisioning for an isolated intersection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wunderlich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cuibi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Elhanany</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Urbanik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Intell Transp Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="536" to="547" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Traffic intersections of the future</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dresner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The twenty-first national conference on artificial intelligence. NECTARTrack (AAAI 06)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1593" to="1596" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The vehicle platoon controller in the decentralised, autonomous intersection management of vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Neuendorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bruns</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE international conference on mechatronics 2004</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE international conference on mechatronics 2004</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="380" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Validation and simulation of a decentralized intersection collision avoidance algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Naumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rasche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tacken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tahedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE conference on intelligent transportation system 1997</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">818</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">823</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collision avoidance as a differential game: realtime approximation of optimal strategies using higher derivatives of the value function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lachner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE international conference on systems, man and cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997. 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2308" to="2313" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The SCOOT on-line traffic signal optimisatoin technique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Traffic Eng Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OPAC: a demand-responsive strategy for traffic signal control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gartner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transp Res Rec</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">906</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The PRODYN real-time traffic algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Farges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tufal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The 4th IFAC symposium on transportation systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="312" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning policy selection for autonomous intersection management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dresner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The AAMAS 2007 workshop on adaptive and learning agents</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007. ALAg 2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="39" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete intersection signal control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abbas-Turki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">El</forename><surname>Moudni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE international conference on service operations and logistics and informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007. 2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A branch and bound algorithm for new traffic signal control system of an isolated intersection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dridi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">El</forename><surname>Moudni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="999" to="1004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiagent traffic management: a reservation-based intersection control mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dresner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the third international joint conference on autonomous agents and multiagent systems</title>
		<meeting>the third international joint conference on autonomous agents and multiagent systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004. 2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="530" to="537" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bringing simulation to life: a mixed reality autonomous intersection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Quinlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tsz-Chiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Stiurca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE/RSJ international conference on intelligent robots and systems (IROS) 2010</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6083" to="6088" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ant colony system: a cooperative learning approach to the traveling salesman problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dorigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gambardella</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Evol Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using mini robots for prototyping intersection management of vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grünewald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rust</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Witkowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The 3rd international symposium on autonomous minirobots for research and edutainment (AMIRE 2005)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="292" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Traffic control systems handbook. Dunn engineering asociates and siemens intelligent transportation systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fhwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Vehicle safety communications project task 3 final report-identify intelligent vehicle safety applications enabled by DSRC. US Department of Transportation: National Highway Traffic Safety Administration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nhtsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Handbook of transportation engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kutz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Markov model for headway/spacing distribution of road traffic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Intell Transp Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="773" to="785" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supporting drivers in keeping safe speed and safe distance: the SASPENCE subproject within the European framework programme 6 integrating project PReVENT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bertolazzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Biral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Da</forename><surname>Lio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Saroldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tango</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Intell Transp Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="525" to="538" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ingénierie du trafic routier</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eléments de théorie du trafic et applications. Seconde edn. Presses de l&apos;Ecole National des Ponts et Chaussées</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Review of road traffic control strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Diakaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kotsialos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2041" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intersection traffic control by a novel scheduling model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abbas-Turki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">El</forename><surname>Moudni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE/INFORMS international conference on service operations</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="334" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ant colony optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dorigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stutzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ant colony optimization theory: a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dorigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Blum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theor Comput Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ant system: optimization by a colony of cooperating agents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dorigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Maniezzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Colorni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Syst Man Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Part B, Cybern</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Laboratorio di Calcolatori, Dipartimento di Elettronica</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dorigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Maniezzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Colorni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>91-016</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Politecnico di Milano</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Milano, Italy</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech Report</note>
	<note>Positive feedback as a search strategy</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exact and approximate nondeterministic treesearch procedures for the quadratic assignment problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Maniezzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IN-FORMS J Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ant system applied to the quadratic assignment problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Maniezzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Colorni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Knowl Data Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="769" to="778" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ants can colour graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Oper Res Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An ant colony optimization algorithm for shop scheduling problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Blum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sampels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Math Model Algorithms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing an ACO algorithm with other heuristics for the single machine scheduling problem with sequence-dependent setup times</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gagné</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gravel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Oper Res Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="895" to="906" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ant colony optimization for resource-constrained project scheduling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Merkle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Middendorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schmeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Evol Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="346" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ant colony optimization with global pheromone evaluation for scheduling a single machine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Merkle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Middendorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidance-solution based ant colony optimization for satellite control resource scheduling problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z-R</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L-J</forename><surname>Ke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10489-010-0234-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved ant system algorithm for the vehicle routing problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bullnheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hartl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Oper Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">0</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="328" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An enhanced ant colony optimization (EACO) applied to capacitated vehicle routing problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C-Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z-J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S-W</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K-C</forename><surname>Ying</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">D-Ants: savings based ants divide and conquer the vehicle routing problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reimann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Doerner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hartl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput Oper Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="563" to="591" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Charles</forename><forename type="middle">El</forename><surname>Ronald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Clifford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Traffic flow fundamentals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>May</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Road research technical paper</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Webster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
			<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Road Research Laboratory</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles of highway engineering and traffic analysis, 3rd edn</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mannering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kilareski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Washburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Hoboken</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Elevator traffic handbook: theory and practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Barney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<pubPlace>Taylor &amp; Francis, London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A behavioural car-following model for computer simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gipps</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transp Res, Part B, Methodol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multsim: a model for simulating vehicular traffic on multi-lane arterial roads</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gipps</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math Comput Simul</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative evaluation of microscopic car-following behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Panwai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Intell Transp Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="325" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A proof for the queuing formula: L = λW</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jdc</forename><surname>Little</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oper Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
