<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The &quot;Bubble&quot; Technique: Interacting with Large Virtual Environments Using Haptic Devices with Limited Workspace</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lionel</forename><surname>Dominjon</surname></persName>
							<email>ldominjon@ingenierium.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">CPNI Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Angers</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anatole</forename><surname>Lécuyer</surname></persName>
							<email>anatole.lecuyer@irisa.fr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jean-Marie</forename><surname>Burkhardt</surname></persName>
							<email>jean-marie.burkhardt@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">) EIFFEL Project</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Paris</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Guillermo</forename><surname>Andrade-Barroso</surname></persName>
							<email>guillermo.andrade@ondim.fr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Richir</surname></persName>
							<email>simon.richir@univ-angers.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">CPNI Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Angers</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">INRIA/IRISA</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>France (</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">INRIA</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The &quot;Bubble&quot; Technique: Interacting with Large Virtual Environments Using Haptic Devices with Limited Workspace</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5969F9F673F5040D24839434BB935FF9</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T10:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The "Bubble" technique is a novel interaction technique to interact with large Virtual Environments (VE) using a haptic device with a limited workspace. It is based on a hybrid position/rate control which enables both accurate interaction and coarse positioning in a large VE.</p><p>The haptic workspace is displayed visually using a semi-transparent sphere (looking like a bubble) that surrounds the manipulated cursor. When the cursor is located inside the bubble, its motion is positioncontrolled. When the cursor is outside, it is ratecontrolled. The user may also "feel" the inner surface of the bubble, since the spherical workspace is "haptically" displayed by applying an elastic forcefeedback when crossing the surface of the bubble.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction and previous work</head><p>Haptic interfaces were shown to greatly enhance interaction with Virtual Environments (VE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>. Using such interfaces enables to touch, grasp and feel physical properties of virtual objects. However, in the case of grounded interfaces such as the VIRTUOSE force feedback arm <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref>, these devices allow a haptic interaction only inside their limited physical workspace. Therefore, the user can not reach and interact with virtual objects located outside this workspace easily. Some software solutions have already been proposed as interaction techniques to address this issue. A first technique is based on the concept of clutching <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref>, which allows the user to perform movements in a series of grab-release cycles. When the user reaches an uncomfortable posture with the interface, he/she may press a 'declutch' button to freeze the virtual cursor/object in the VE. Then he/she can move the haptic device to a more comfortable position, and then release the 'clutch' button to unfreeze the virtual cursor. A second technique consists in amplifying the user's motion, i.e. defining a scaling factor between the haptic workspace and the VE <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1]</ref>. However, a high amplification of the movements may sometimes exacerbate fine control and precision tasks.</p><p>In this paper, we propose a novel interaction technique to provide a natural way to reach and touch virtual objects in a VE larger than the workspace of the haptic device.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Description of the "Bubble" technique</head><p>To overcome the mismatch between the workspace of the haptic device and the size of the VE, we got inspired by the hybrid position/rate control described in some previous tele-operation studies <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>. Position control is used around the central position of the device for fine positioning, while rate control is used at the boundaries of the device, for coarse positioning <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>. We adapted this approach, using the following adjustments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Control modes of the "Bubble" technique</head><p>A spherical bounding volume is defined around the neutral position of the haptic device (see Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). The control mode of the manipulated object (here: the ) is switched when it crosses the surface of the bounding volume. When the cursor is located inside, its motion is position-controlled (direct mapping of the user's motion onto the cursor's motion). When the cursor is outside, it is rate-controlled, and it may reach any location of the VE very quickly. Unlike previous implementations of hybrid position/rate control in tele-operation, we chose here to display the spherical bounding volume both visually and haptically in the VE. This double display ensures a consistency between the visual and haptic spaces.</p><p>The visual display of the bounding volume consists in a semi-transparent sphere, looking like a "bubble" (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). The semi-transparency of the bubble improves the perception of the bubble position relatively to its surroundings <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref>.</p><p>The haptic display of the bubble is achieved by applying an elastic radial force as the cursor crosses the surface and goes outside the bubble (see Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>). The user can thus "feel" and slide on the inner surface of the bubble. The reaction force is computed using Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>), where k is a constant stiffness, D is the distance between the endpoint of the haptic device and the centre of the bubble, R is the radius of the bubble, and r is the normalized radial vector pointing outside the bubble (in our implementation k=200 N/m and R=10 cm).</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">r R D k F ⋅ - ⋅ - = ) (<label>(1)</label></formula><p>In the rate control mode, the velocity (V ) of the cursor is computed using Equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(2)</ref>. A non-linear control law was implemented to enable small and precise motions of the cursor as well as the ability to move the cursor in a very fast way. In our implementation, K was set to 0.03 N -3 .s -1 . The haptic display (elastic force) of the bounding volume is expected to improve the rate control, by simulating the use of an elastic device <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">r R D K r F K V ⋅ - ⋅ = ⋅ ⋅ = 3 3 ) ( '<label>(2)</label></formula><p>When in rate control, the visual model of the bubble moves with the same velocity as the cursor. This preserves the relative position of the cursor relatively to the surface of the bubble, and gives the impression that the bubble is actually following the cursor.</p><p>In one implementation of the Bubble technique called BubbleCam, we propose to attach the camera used to render the VE to the centre of the bubble. This "camera metaphor" <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref> gives the impression that the objects of the VE are moving, instead of the cursor and the bubble. With the BubbleCam technique, the user may also navigate in the VE, in addition to the haptic exploration of objects. A first advantage is that the point of view is always focused on the main zone of interest (i.e. inside the bubble: the zone of haptic interaction). The camera-metaphor also enables the use of our technique when having a visual display smaller than the size of the database of the VE (e.g. when displaying a whole car at scale 1 on a Workbench). Last, attaching the point of view to the bubble can improve the co-location of the haptic and visual spaces. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Conclusion and future work</head><p>We have presented a novel interaction technique called the "Bubble" technique based on a hybrid position/rate control. This technique is useful to interact with a large VE using a haptic device with a limited workspace. The Bubble technique was presented to the Haption Company <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref> and it was much appreciated. It will be available in the next release of the VIRTUOSE API <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref> (the commercial haptic programming interface of Haption).</p><p>Future work will mainly consist in evaluating the Bubble technique, compared with other interaction techniques dedicated to the provision of force-feedback in large virtual environments.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>F</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Visual display of the bubble in the VE.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,335.16,156.84,187.08,143.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>References</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PHANToM Haptic Device Implemented in a Projection Screen Virtual Environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vance</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Joint 7th International Immersive Projection Technologies Workshop and 9th Eurographics Workshop on Virtual Environments</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<orgName type="collaboration">Haption Company</orgName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.haption.com" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Survey of Design Issues in Spatial Input</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hinckley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pausch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Goble</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kassell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Symposium on User Interface Software &amp; Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lorentz Levitation Technology: a New Approach to Fine Motion Robotics, Teleoperation, Haptic Interfaces, and Vibration Isolation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hollis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Salcudean</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Symposium for Robotics Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effectiveness Of Haptic Sensation For the Evaluation of Virtual Prototypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Volkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vance</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ASME Journal of Computing and Information Science in Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Performance in Six Degree of Freedom Input Control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Toronto</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
	<note>Bubble Cursor</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
