<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Semi-Random Backoff: Towards Resource Reservation for Channel Access in Wireless LANs</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
							<email>ryuan@tsinghua.edu.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Tsinghua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100084</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Alibaba Group</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100026</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Computer Engineering Depart-ment</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Massachusetts Amherst</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01003</postCode>
									<settlement>Amherst</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Thomson Broadband</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100088</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Western Macedonia</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>50100</postCode>
									<settlement>Kozani</settlement>
									<country key="GR">Greece</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">TNList and CFINS Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tsinghua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100084</postCode>
									<settlement>Bei-jing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Semi-Random Backoff: Towards Resource Reservation for Channel Access in Wireless LANs</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">EB032388C0445FB8AEEFEDDA3E6FBC76</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TNET.2012.2202323</idno>
					<note type="submission">received July 17, 2011; revised January 18, 2012; accepted March 20, 2012; approved by IEEE/ACM TRANSACTIONS ON NETWORKING Editor G. Bianchi. Date of publication June 13, 2012; date of current version February 12, 2013.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T06:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper proposes a semi-random backoff (SRB) method that enables resource reservation in contention-based wireless LANs. The proposed SRB is fundamentally different from traditional random backoff methods because it provides an easy migration path from random backoffs to deterministic slot assignments. The central idea of the SRB is for the wireless station to set its backoff counter to a deterministic value upon a successful packet transmission. This deterministic value will allow the station to reuse the time-slot in consecutive backoff cycles. When multiple stations with successful packet transmissions reuse their respective time-slots, the collision probability is reduced, and the channel achieves the equivalence of resource reservation. In case of a failed packet transmission, a station will revert to the standard random backoff method and probe for a new available time-slot. The proposed SRB method can be readily applied to both 802.11 DCF and 802.11e EDCA networks with minimum modification to the existing DCF/EDCA implementations. Theoretical analysis and simulation results validate the superior performance of the SRB for small-scale and heavily loaded wireless LANs. When combined with an adaptive mechanism and a persistent backoff process, SRB can also be effective for large-scale and lightly loaded wireless networks. Index Terms-802.11 wireless LAN, backoff algorithm, medium access control (MAC), resource reservation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>R ESERVATION is a well-known technique for arbitrating accesses to shared resources. In TDMA networks [2], radio resource is organized by superframes, and a central coordinator can assign one or more time-slots in each superframe as reserved resources to stations. In reservation ALOHA (R-ALOHA) [10], a time-slot can be automatically reserved Manuscript</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>is set to 7, which is the default window size for voice traffic in 802.11e EDCA.</p><p>by a station that successfully used it in the previous superframe. Since channel access in the reserved slots suffers less network collisions, reservation is considered more suitable for QoS-aware applications than pure contention-based methods.</p><p>Achieving reservation in CSMA networks is challenging. Currently, most contention-based access protocols in CSMA networks, including 802.11 DCF and 802.11e EDCA, employ fully random backoff methods to resolve network collisions. These approaches emphasize on high availabilities and are designed to be plug-and-play, and they are inherently resistant to resource reservation.</p><p>This paper borrows the ideas of reservation from TDMA and R-ALOHA and applies them in wireless CSMA networks. The built-in carrier-sensing mechanism in a CSMA network is leveraged to achieve synchronization among the wireless stations, but the fully random backoff processes of the wireless stations are changed to an opportunistically random process. This new method, named semi-random backoff (SRB), allows a station to reuse a time-slot in consecutive backoff cycles. Herein, a backoff cycle is defined as a period of time when the backoff counter decrements from the maximal number to zero. Different from a TDMA network, the duration of a time-slot in a CSMA network varies over time. It can be as short as merely several microseconds if the slot is idle (for carrier sensing), or as long as hundreds of microseconds if the slot is busy (for packet transmission). The varied length of the time-slot reduces the wasted time in idle slots while achieving reservation in CSMA networks.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> illustrates the operation of SRB by an example. Stations A and B both want to transmit data. In backoff cycle 1, the stations set their backoff counters randomly within window , . Upon collision, they randomly set their new backoff counters from doubled contention window, which allows them to successfully transmit data in backoff cycle 2. These operations are the same as those of legacy DCF/EDCA. After successful transmissions, both stations set their counters to a common deterministic value (backoff cycle 3), rather than two random values respectively in as legacy 802.11 DCF/EDCA does. Afterwards, stations A and B can lock onto slot 2 and 4, respectively, in subsequent backoff cycles (backoff cycle ), without colliding with each other again. A further collision brings the system back to legacy DCF/EDCA.</p><p>By intentionally setting the backoff counter to a deterministic value , the SRB forms a service ring of size among all the competing stations. Each station randomly probes unused time-slots in the service ring and occupies them once the probe succeeds. The SRB requires only the status information of a prior transmission and incurs no extra overhead compared to existing DCF/EDCA. The only difference between the SRB and legacy DCF/EDCA is the deterministic setting of backoff counter after successful data transmissions. This difference allows minimum modifications to the software/firmware when implementing SRB on top of existing 802.11 DCF/EDCA devices. However, the SRB yields remarkable improvement in system performance. Analysis in Section III shows that SRB significantly reduces the collision rate within several backoff cycles. For example, in a 4-node network with , SRB can reach collision-free state with an average number of 2.28 backoff cycles. Simulations in Section IV demonstrate that SRB achieves up to 35% higher throughput than legacy EDCA. This throughput gain is remarkable as it is achieved at no extra cost. In addition, the SRB is fully compatible with legacy DCF and EDCA.</p><p>The SRB can be less effective in some cases. Results in Section IV show that SRB's performance gain degrades considerably when the number of active stations exceeds the fixed service ring size . This issue is addressed in Section V with an adaptive mechanism. This mechanism adjusts to values commensurate with the number of active stations in the network. The algorithm does not require the direct acquisition of the actual number of active stations. Instead, it only needs to track the number of busy slots in each backoff cycle. Simulation study verifies that it improves the system performance considerably when the number of active stations changes, and the control algorithm converges quickly within several backoff cycles.</p><p>The SRB is also not as effective under light traffic loads due to failed slot reservation across multiple backoff cycles. This is because SRB claims a time-slot merely by continuously accessing it in each backoff cycle. If a reserved time-slot is not used in a backoff cycle (called an empty slot), it will automatically be released. To overcome this problem, we advocate a persistent backoff scheme for SRB. This solution treats the occurrence of an empty time-slot as a successful transmission and tracks a reserved time-slot by keeping on counting its backoff counter (persistent backoff) even if there are no data to send. This ensures the reservation of a time-slot for sporadic data transmissions. The effectiveness of this approach is verified by simulations in Section VI.</p><p>SRB builds on the assumption that all stations in the network decrease their backoff counters in a synchronized manner. However, in practice, this assumption can be broken by many factors, such as different interframe spaces, channel errors, clock drift, carrier-sense errors, and presence of hidden/exposed terminals. The impacts of these factors were examined via simulations in Section IV-B. Our main finding is that, though all these factors reduce its performance gain, the SRB method still outperforms legacy EDCA in every tested case. The fundamental reason is that SRB automatically reverts back to the standard random backoff method<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> in case of unsynchronized backoff and can take advantage of the deterministic features once synchronized backoff is available.</p><p>The idea to use carrier sensing for resource reservation is applicable in a variety of CSMA-based networks, such as the HCCA networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and multiradio multichannel networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. This general approach has been explored independently by different research groups in recent years. A first exploration to this approach is the enhanced backoff algorithm (EBA) proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, where each station announces its backoff counter value in the frame header that allows other stations to select different values for their backoff counters, thus collisions are avoided. Zero Collision (ZC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> eliminates the explicit backoff information announcement in EBA and obtains such information implicitly by learning. The extra cost is the online tracking of each time-slot's status. The most similar work to SRB is the learning BEB (L-BEB) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> proposed by <ref type="bibr">Barcelo et al.</ref> in the summer school of EUNICE 2008, followed by analytical studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> and enhancements <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> in 2009 and 2010. For comparison, the basic idea of SRB was first published as a poster in ACM SIGCOMM 2009 <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and as a full paper in IEEE ICNP 2009 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Both L-BEB and SRB employ deterministic backoff to resolve network collision. However, they are independent works, and their analytical models, verification approaches, as well as some other details are very different. Detailed discussions on the two separate proposals are included in Section VII.</p><p>This paper is an extended version of the ICNP work <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Our contributions are threefold.</p><p>• First, we propose a general framework to use carrier sensing for achieving resource reservation in CSMA-based networks. The approach is simple and elegant, incurs no extra cost, and requires minimal modification to existing implementations. Results show that it significantly reduces network collisions and increases system throughput. • Second, we provide an analytical model that can be used to evaluate and predict the performance of SRB in nonideal situations, such as carrier-sense errors, clock skew, etc. It obtains the collision rate, system throughput, as well as convergence speed of collision in closed form. • Third, we investigate the limitations with the basic SRB solution and propose several enhancements to improve its performance. In particular, we provide a simple yet flexible mechanism that dynamically controls the service ring size to boost the system throughput when the number of active stations in the network changes over time. Additionally, we enhance SRB with a persistent backoff scheme that enables resource reservation across multiple backoff cycles. The rest of this paper is organized as follows. Section II describes the concept of SRB and its application in 802.11 DCF/EDCA and provides some discussions on related issues. Section III presents theoretical analysis on the protocol. Section IV gives detailed simulation results on the performance.</p><p>Enhancements to SRB in a number of practical scenarios are studied in Sections V and VI. Section VII presents detailed discussions on related works, and Section VIII concludes the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PROTOCOL DESCRIPTION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Concept of SRB</head><p>For the sake of illustration, we discretize the timeline of a CSMA network based on the duration of a time-slot (the length of the time-slot can be varying) and tag each time-slot as . Define as the value of station 's backoff counter at time-slot . The proposed SRB scheme states that when station completes a data transmission at time-slot , its backoff counter is updated based on the results of the transmission as follows:</p><p>for a successful transmission for a failed transmission (1) where represents the backoff window size as defined in traditional random backoff methods, and is a newly introduced parameter in SRB with deterministic values. Usually, stations share the same during channel access. However, if it is desired, stations can also have different -values, given that certain constraints be satisfied (detailed later in Section II-C). Here, a successful transmission means a transmission that is acknowledged by the receiver via ACK, nACK, block ACK, or other appropriate signals. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref>Once the backoff counter is updated, a station proceeds its usual backoff process. When its counter reaches zero, the station transmits data, and then updates its counter. If the station finds no data to send (post-backoff), the backoff ceases; whenever new traffic comes, the station restarts its backoff process with a new random initial value for the counter. This behavior is exactly the same as the legacy 802.11 DCF/EDCA. In Section VI, we show that this behavior can be changed to further improve SRB's performance.</p><p>Equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> shows two components with SRB, a random component and a reservation component. The random component is used to randomly probe the contention window for a time-slot to avoid collision. The reservation component, which sets the backoff counter to a deterministic value , is used to reserve that time-slot for future transmissions in subsequent backoff cycles. Accordingly, a station can stay in one of two states: random state and reservation state at any time. Transition between the two states only requires a station's own transmission result in the previous backoff cycle, which is always known to the station.</p><p>The operation of SRB can be best illustrated using a service ring (with slots) as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. Stations A and B probe unused time-slots on the ring by the random component at first. Whenever successful, they reserve these unused slots by setting the backoff counter to . If each station can lock onto a different slot in the ring for channel access, resource reservation can be achieved and collisions avoided.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>, is a time-varying parameter among stations. It can be controlled by different random backoff methods. For example, the change of can follow a binary exponential increase fashion when applying SRB to DCF/EDCA, or follow other varying patterns like multiplicative increase linear decrease (MILD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> or linear increase linear decrease (LILD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Generally, SRB can be used to enhance performance for all random backoff methods in CSMA networks.</p><p>is a fixed parameter for a station used for reservation. It defines the maximal number of available slots in the service ring for reservation. It can be dependent or independent of . In this paper, it is set to when applying SRB to the 802.11 DCF/EDCA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. SRB in 802.11 Networks</head><p>We discuss how the SRB can be applied to 802.11 DCF and 802.11e EDCA networks. Since both DCF and EDCA are based on binary exponential backoff (BEB), we focus on how to adapt the concept of SRB to the BEB algorithm. For illustration, we use a prefix R (reservation) to refer the method with SRB capability, like R-BEB, R-DCF and R-EDCA.</p><p>As previously mentioned, the only difference between SRB and a traditional random backoff method is the reservation component. By adding a reservation component, BEB evolves to R-BEB. Since in BEB the average interval between successive successful transmissions is time-slots, in R-BEB we set reservation parameter to the same value, so as to keep the average delay of R-BEB in reservation state similar to the average delay in BEB.</p><p>The pseudocode of R-BEB is as follows. In the pseudocode above, only lines 3 and 4 deal with the reservation component. Since it is easy to differentiate a unicast transmission from a broadcast/multicast transmission, implementing the reservation component in R-BEB becomes a trivial task that requires minimum modification to the existing implementation of BEB.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. SRB With Different Priorities</head><p>When applying SRB to 802.11e EDCA, coexistence of different priorities needs to be addressed. Note that 802.11e EDCA uses different for traffics of different priorities, thus ( ) may take different values in such cases. A question to be raised is the following: How can collision free reservation be achieved in case of different ?</p><p>Consider an -station network with different parameters . Denote as the backoff counter of station at a certain time-slot . We claim the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 1: A sufficient condition to have collision-free reserved slots for the stations is that for where is the greatest common divisor of , i.e., . Proof: By contradiction, suppose two stations, and , suffer a collision for the first time after time-slots since slot . That is, , which implies , where . According to SRB's rules, we have which means</p><p>, where is an integer. Analogously, for a proper integer . By the congruence theory, we have which says</p><p>. Since is a factor of , this also means . However, this violates our assumption.</p><p>defines a global service ring shared among all contending stations in the network. Theorem 1 states that as long as stations select different slots from the global service ring, they can have collision-free reserved slots.</p><p>From Theorem 1, we can derive the condition to multiplex a slot in the global service ring. Consider a subset in , where , then we have the following corollary.</p><p>Corollary 2: Station can multiplex a slot in the global service ring without incurring collision if both the following two conditions are satisfied: 1) , where ; 2) for , where . Proof: By contradiction, suppose station and satisfy the two conditions in Corollary 2, and they first get collided after time-slots since slot .</p><p>This implies . Similar to the proof for Theorem 1, we can derive the values of backoff counters at time-slot as: , , where and are integers. Define . By the congruence theory, we have . Note that is a factor of , hence , which violates our second condition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Discussions</head><p>SRB builds on the underlying assumption that contending stations decrease their backoff counters concurrently upon idle slots. However, in practice, this assumption does not always hold true. The use of arbitrary interframe space (AIFS), the presence of hidden/exposed terminals, as well as some other factors can break this assumption. A number of typical cases are analyzed in the following.</p><p>1) SRB With Different IFS: For most random backoff algorithms, the same interframe space (IFS) is used for all contending stations. This ensures the synchronized change of backoff counters. However, in some cases, contending stations can use different IFS for channel access (such as the AIFS in 802.11e EDCA). As an example, consider two stations A and B with different IFS, denoted as and , and suppose . Then, station A always decreases its backoff counter faster than B. The difference will accumulate over time, and the two stations' lock to their respective time-slot will fail.</p><p>The impact of different IFSs on the performance of SRB is investigated via simulation in Section IV-B. While the performance enhancement of SRB is indeed impaired by the accumulation of IFS differences, we find the SRB can still obtain performance gain over the legacy random backoff methods (like 802.11e EDCA). This is due to the temporary reservation achieved before the timing difference reaches the threshold that can break the synchronization, as well as the reservation achieved among stations with the same IFS (we assume that some stations still share the same IFS, as with the case of EDCA).</p><p>Inherently, different IFS will make it more difficult for stations to synchronize with each other. Within the SRB framework, the way to differentiate various traffic types is to configure a different for each traffic type. Higher-priority traffic types are configured with smaller .</p><p>2) SRB in Multihop and Error-Prone Networks: Synchronized decrements of backoff counters may also be broken due to factors that are not dependent on the protocol itself, such as hidden terminals (in multihop networks), exposed terminals, carrier-sense errors, clock skew, and power-saving operations. The presence of channel errors due to signal fading or interference, common in wireless communications, can also impair the performance of SRB.</p><p>All these "unpleasant" factors reduce network efficiency since they eventually lead to failed transmissions. However, the beauty of SRB lies in the fact that it reverts back to the standard random backoff upon such "bad" conditions, and when the situation improves, it takes advantage of the reservation capability to obtain performance gain. Simulation results in Section IV-B demonstrate that SRB may have similar performance to normal DCF/EDCA in several extreme cases, but it never underperforms the normal DCF/EDCA, and in most cases it performs significantly better.</p><p>3) High-Efficiency SRB: So far, we have assumed that the reservation parameter is fixed for a station or an access category. However, in practice, the number of active stations varies over time, which may lead to low channel utilization if , or high collision probability if . Obviously, it is desirable to update adaptively to the change of to obtain higher performance. Section V discusses this enhancement in more details.</p><p>Another issue with SRB is that it is designed for heavy traffic situations. For light traffic cases, the effect of reservation is fairly limited since reserved slots are automatically released if not used for a time. To overcome this inefficiency, we propose a persistent backoff scheme to allow a station to retain its reservation even when it has no data to send. Section VI has more details on this topic.</p><p>4) Backward Compatibility: Both R-DCF and R-EDCA are fully backward compatible with the legacy DCF and EDCA. Stations running legacy DCF/EDCA can interoperate directly with stations running R-DCF/R-EDCA. The presence of legacy DCF/EDCA stations can degrade the performance of a R-DCF/R-EDCA network because the legacy stations will perform random backoff and increase the collision probabilities of the R-DCF/R-EDCA stations. Detailed simulation results are presented in Section IV-B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. PERFORMANCE ANALYSIS</head><p>Consider a wireless LAN with stations sharing the same medium. Each station sends saturated unicast data to the channel. We model the backoff process in the network by a service ring consisting of slots, labeled from 0 to (as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). A pointer moves around the ring; when it reaches a slot selected by a station, this station has an opportunity to transmit data. Define a global backoff cycle as the period when the pointer moves from slot 0 to slot in the service ring.</p><p>Suppose that in a certain global backoff cycle, there are stations in reservation state, and the remaining stations are in random state. Each station in reservation state has reserved one slot from the service ring. These reserved slots are different from each other. Each station in random state (also called a random station in our analysis), on the other hand, uniformly selects one random slot from the service ring . 3  There are various reasons causing a station to be in the random state, such as failed data transmission in previous backoff cycle, the presence of hidden terminals, carrier-sense errors, clock skew, or power-saving operations. 4 We also assume no capture effects and no channel errors in our analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Collision Probability</head><p>There are three types of slots in : empty slot, selected by no station; collision-free slot, selected by exactly one station; 3 The number of slots selected by a random station in a global backoff cycle depends on the value of . For the case and fixed, the average number of slots selected by a random station in a global backoff cycle is exactly one. 4 Note that all these factors lead to the same effect that a station's backoff counter drifts away from its expected value. To simplify the model, we assume the drift is random and independent in our analysis.</p><p>and collision slot, selected by two or more stations. A collisionfree slot corresponds to a successful data transmission, while a collision slot corresponds to a network collision. Denote the set of collision-free slots in by . We compute the probability to yield exactly collision-free time-slots in when stations are in reservation state, expressed as , shortened as . We start with a simple case where . In this case, all stations are random stations, so SRB is reduced to the standard random backoff method. We have <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> where is expressed as (see the Appendix)</p><p>Next, we consider the case . For analysis, we divide the set , and the set of random stations into two subsets.</p><p>• For , those slots that are selected by stations in reservation state are treated as reserved slots, and the remaining slots are treated as random slots. Clearly, we have reserved slots and random slots. • For , we divide it into two subsets: the reservation subset ( ) that contains reserved slots not selected by any random station, and the random subset ( ) that contains random slots selected by exactly one random station. Obviously, , where . • For the random stations, denote by those select reserved slots and by those select random slots. and . By first conditioning on variable and then on variable , can be expanded as <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref> where is the probability to have random stations out of that select reserved slots <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> and is the probability that reserved slots are selected by random stations <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> and is the probability that random stations select random slots and yields collision-free slots. Since no reservation occurs here, we use the result in (3) directly ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TABLE I AVERAGE CONVERGENCE TIME</head><p>can be obtained by combining (4)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. Thus, the collision probability<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">5</ref> in a backoff cycle, given stations in reservation state, can be written as (8)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Convergence Rate</head><p>In addition to the collision probability, another key metric that determines system performance is speed of convergence of the collision probability. Consider a synchronized network with stations. Each station owns a service ring of size . We claim the following.</p><p>Claim 3: The network always suffers collisions if . Proof: Since each collision-free station reserves exactly one time-slot, the number of collision-free stations cannot surpass the number of available slots . Therefore, when , the network always suffers collisions.</p><p>In the following analysis, we assume . Define as the number of reserved slots in backoff cycle . has possible states, . indicates a collision-free state in the network, while represents collision states (at least one station is still in random state). We claim the following.</p><p>Claim 4: For , the network reaches collision-free state in finite time with probability 1.</p><p>Proof: Clearly, is an absorbing state. , so are transient states. Thus, is an absorbing Markov chain. Claim 4 holds true according to the theorem of the absorbing Markov chain <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p><p>Denote the state space of Markov chain as , where is the set of transient states, and is the set of absorbing states (with the unique element ). The one-step transition probability matrix of this Markov chain is expressed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> where is the transition probability matrix for transient state set and , .</p><p>is exactly the probability to yield collision-free slots in a global backoff cycle given reserved slots in the service ring, thus</p><p>We have derived in (4), hence can be obtained. Let denote the number of backoff cycles elapsed before the network reaching collision-free state given initial state . We call the convergence time starting from state . According to the absorbing Markov chain theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, the average convergence time when the system begins with initial state , denoted as , is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> where , and is the fundamental matrix. Furthermore, by the transition probability matrix , we can derive the collision probability in each backoff cycle. Suppose that the system has a state at backoff cycle , and denote the collision probability at backoff cycle by , then the collision probability after global backoff cycles, , is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> where .</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>, the vector gives the probability distribution from state to a state in after global backoff cycles. In Table <ref type="table">I</ref>, we show the average convergence time when the system begins with a fully random state (no reserved slots present). We set to 4, 8, and 16 because they are the service ring sizes for different access categories when we apply SRB to EDCA. For comparison, we also present results from our simulation on ns2. Each simulation result is an average of 10 000 samples. Clearly, the theoretical results agree well with the simulation results, which validates our analytical model.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">I</ref> shows that the convergence time is quite small when the ratio is smaller than 0.8. When approaches 1, the convergence time increases sharply. This is reasonable because a higher ratio means lower probability to find an unused slot in the service ring.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> shows how the collision probability evolves with backoff cycles with (at global backoff cycle 1). Only two cases are considered, and . We see that the collision probability converges to zero, and the convergence rate is faster for a smaller ratio . We also present our simulation results on ns2 to confirm the analytical results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. SIMULATION RESULTS</head><p>This section presents detailed simulation results from the network simulator ns2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. The WLAN patch [33] is used due to its clear implementation of backoff and physical clear channel assess (CCA) mechanism. Integrating SRB into this patch only requires an insertion of merely three lines of codes. In our study, two types of EDCA are compared: the legacy EDCA and the SRB-based EDCA (R-EDCA). Our simulation considers a typical 802.11 wireless LAN environment where an AP is located at the center and mobile stations uniformly spread in a 30-m circle around the AP. The receiving range and carrier-sense range are set to 40 and 65 m, respectively. Each station in the network carries a UDP stream to the AP. The traffic is generated according to Pareto ON/OFF distribution, with both ON and OFF periods following Pareto distribution <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">6</ref> with constant packet size 1000 B. We use 802.11g OFDM (with data rate 54 Mb/s) as the physical layer, and RTS/CTS is disabled as in practical platforms. Window sizes ( and ) are set to default values as specified in 802.11e <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Unless otherwise indicated, the CCA probability is set to 99%, and no channel errors are considered. The AIFS for all traffic types is set to 2, except for simulations in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>(a) and (b) later in this section. The MAC buffer length is set to 100 frames. Other parameters are set to the default values as used in ns2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Throughput and Collision Rate</head><p>The network throughputs and collision rates of both R-EDCA and traditional EDCA are shown in shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>. Both single-traffic and mixed-traffic cases are studied. For single-traffic case, we study three types of traffic: voice (AC-VO), video (AC-VI), and best-effort data (AC-BE). For the mixed-traffic case, we study the mixing of video plus voice (AC-VI+AC-VO) and video plus data (AC-VI+AC-BE). In our studies, the number of wireless stations ( ) in the network varies from 1 to 30 (excluding AP).</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>(a) compares the achieved throughput by R-EDCA and EDCA for AC-VO, AC-VI, and AC-BE. For each traffic type, R-EDCA achieves better throughput than EDCA. The gap between them initially increases with the increase of . After reaching a threshold (the service ring size ), the gap starts to decrease and eventually converges. At these thresholds, R-EDCA exhibits 38.1% ( , 95% confidence interval), 44.8% ( , 95% confidence interval), and 34.2% ( , 95% confidence interval) higher throughput than EDCA for AC-VO, AC-VI, and AC-BE. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>(b) studies the throughput for two cases of mixed traffic, video plus voice (thus AC-VI+AC-VO), and video plus data (thus AC-VI+AC-BE).</p><p>In each case, half of the stations send traffic with high priority (voice in the first case, and video in the second case), and half send traffic with low priority. We observe a superior performance of R-EDCA over legacy EDCA when increases, which demonstrates the capability of R-EDCA to handle prioritized traffics.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>(c) and (d) shows the measured collision rate corresponding to (a) and (b). The collision rate is defined as the ratio of the number of collisions to the overall transmission attempts. Compared to legacy EDCA, R-EDCA exhibits an almost collision-free state when the number of stations is small. For a larger , the collision rate of R-EDCA rises sharply and approaches that of the legacy EDCA. The onset point for the increase is regulated by the size of global service ring. As long as stations can be accommodated by the service ring, the network can achieve extremely low collision rate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Robustness 1) Coexistence of Different AIFS:</head><p>In the mixed traffic case shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>(b), we assumed that different traffic types share the same AIFS. However, in practice, different traffics can use different AIFS for service differentiation. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>(a) and (b) investigates the system performance when different AIFS coexist in a network. In this experiment, we consider a network with an AP and six stations, with each station generating saturated traffic to the AP. Stations are evenly placed around the AP, and they can sense each other. Among the six stations, we let stations send video (VI) traffic, and the remaining stations send best-effort (BE) traffic [Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5(a)</ref>] or background (BK) traffic [Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5(b)</ref>]. We measure the network throughput when increases from 0 to 6. The AIFS for VI, BE, and BK traffic is set to 2, 3, and 7, respectively (the default setting in 802.11e). From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5(a</ref>) and (b), we see two distinct trends for R-EDCA and legacy EDCA. R-EDCA achieves higher throughput at both ends ( or ) and lower throughput in the middle, but legacy EDCA exhibits the opposite. This is because, at both ends, stations share a common AIFS, so the throughput gains more with synchronized reservation. In the middle, however, the gain is reduced due to the presence of multiple AIFS that impair the effectiveness of resource reservation.</p><p>Nevertheless, R-EDCA always has higher throughput than legacy EDCA. The gain is obtained from the resource reservation temporally achieved by the stations share the same AIFS.</p><p>2) Impact of Errors, Hidden Terminals, and Coexistence With Legacy Stations: Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5(c)-(f</ref>) studies performance of R-EDCA and legacy EDCA when several "unpleasant" factors are present. In these tests, the network settings are the same as in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>(a) and (b), except that now each station only sends VI traffic to AP. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>(c), we show how R-EDCA reacts against carrier-sense errors, where the CCA probability decreases from 100% (perfect) to 80% (imperfect). We see that the presence of carrier-sense errors impairs the performance of R-EDCA, but has limited effect on EDCA. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5(d)</ref> shows the effect of frame error rate (FER) on the throughput performance. With the error rate increasing from 0% to 30%, both R-EDCA and EDCA have degraded performance, however R-EDCA is more susceptible to FER because it relies on error-free frame transmissions to achieve resource reservation.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>(e), the impact of interference from hidden terminals is investigated. We set up neighboring small LANs around the six-station target network. Each neighboring LAN has an AP and two stations that run legacy EDCA. Each station in neighboring LANs generates 5-Mp/s UDP traffic to its AP. A neighboring LAN interferes with exactly one station of the target network. As expected, with more stations interfered by hidden terminals ( increases from 0 to 6), the performance of R-EDCA degrades accordingly.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>(f), we consider the situation where EDCA and R-EDCA stations coexist in the network. The -axis in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5(f</ref>) represents the number of legacy EDCA stations (out of six) in the network. We see that the network performance decreased when the number of legacy stations increases, reaching the minimum when all the stations are legacy stations.</p><p>The results in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5(c</ref>)-(f) confirm that R-EDCA never performs worse than legacy EDCA. In most cases, it performs better than legacy EDCA. This is due to inherent reservation nature of SRB, its automatic adaptation to network conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Delay and Fairness</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>(a) and (b) shows the delay performance in a network with six stations, each generating 4-Mb/s UDP traffic to the AP via AC-VI (thus a total workload of 24 Mb/s in the network). In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>(a), we draw the cumulative distribution function (CDF) of medium access delay for R-EDCA and EDCA, and in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>(b) we draw the CDF of end-to-end delay <ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">7</ref> for them. In both cases, R-EDCA's delay is deterministic, located at a single point, whereas legacy EDCA's delay is distributed over a period of time. For comparison, in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>(a), R-EDCA has a deterministic medium access delay value of 1.356 ms 8 ; legacy EDCA has an average access delay 1.837 ms, with standard variation 0.002033 (in seconds). R-EDCA clearly outperforms legacy EDCA.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>(c) shows the Jain fairness index <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> of R-EDCA and EDCA during a period of 0.1 s. 9 The number of active stations increases from one to 20. We can see that when is less than the service ring size 8, R-EDCA has a near-perfect fairness performance. However, when , R-EDCA's fairness performance is close to EDCA. It is easy to see this since when , each station can reserve a slot from the ring and get served exactly once in a backoff cycle, which yields a fair access among stations.</p><p>V. ADAPTIVE SRB Results in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> show that the performance of SRB is closely related to the number of active stations and the service ring size . If , many slots in the service ring will be idle, whereas if , the collision rate will be high. Both negatively impact the system performance. Thus, it is desirable to adapt the service ring size to the number of active stations in order to achieve higher performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Optimal Reservation Parameters</head><p>Definition 1: The reservation index is defined as the ratio of the number of stations in reservation state, , to the number of total active stations in the network, , i.e., . Obviously, varies over time. It is dependent on the network condition: carrier-sense errors, the presence of hidden/exposed terminals, clock drift, channel error rate, and many other factors that can cause a station's failure to lock onto a time-slot in the service ring. In the following analysis, we tentatively treat as a constant first, then we change to understand how the value of affects the system performance.</p><p>Let us revisit the analytical model in Section III. Since , we can readily express the collision probability as function of , i.e., . Then, the system throughput, denoted as , can be derived using ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) 8 This access delay can be calculated as , where and have the same meaning with terms in (13). 9 Similar results are obtained for a larger time window like 0.5 or 1 s.</p><p>where is the average time of a successful frame transmission, is the average time of a collision, is the average payload size for a data frame, and is the minimum duration of a physical time-slot (for carrier sensing only).</p><p>Intuitively, we can tune the reservation parameter to the number of active stations . However, in reality, it is not easy to obtain the exact number of active stations <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> due to limited information or computation complexity. In what follows, we consider the congestion index instead.</p><p>Definition 2: The congestion index is defined as the ratio of the number of observed busy time-slots to the total time-slots in a backoff cycle, i.e., . Suppose that a station observes busy time-slots in the last backoff cycle, and define variable as the real number of active stations in the network. According to the Bayes theorem, the probability for variable to take on a value of can be expressed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> where is the probability that out of time-slots are used by active stations for channel access. Using the inclusion-exclusion principle, we have <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> In <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> the range of variable is set to . When is large, e.g., , is often too small to produce significant effect on the ultimate results. To simplify our analysis, we assume , and the distribution of in interval is uniform. 10 We rewrite ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) as <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> Therefore, the expected throughput when we observe busy time-slots in a backoff cycle can be derived as <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref> depicts system throughput as a function of the congestion index . The system throughput rises sharply with at first. It achieves its maximum at the optimal point and fades afterwards. Theoretically, can be obtained by solving the following differentiation equation: <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> 10 One can try other types of distribution for , but our investigation using the symmetric triangle distribution (peaked at ) suggests that the derived optimal congestion index varies only slightly for different distributions.  It is difficult to derive a close-form expression for . In Table <ref type="table">II</ref>, we list the values of against different reservation ratio and packet size . Theoretically, is also a function of , but our numerical study shows that has negligible effect on . Table <ref type="table">II</ref> indicates that increases with , but slightly decreases with .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Adaptive Algorithm</head><p>To sustain a high throughput for varying , we propose a control algorithm to tune the parameter adaptively based on the observed congestion index . The idea is quite simple. When too many busy slots are found in a backoff cycle (high congestion index ), we double our service ring size , whereas when too few busy slots are found (a low congestion index ), we reduce the service ring size by half. We set two thresholds and (</p><p>) for triggering the increase/decrease of . This yields the following algorithm.   The reason to use binary exponential increase/decrease (B-EIED) instead of many other control algorithms like Additive Increase Multiplicative Decrease (AIMD) or LILD is because binary exponential operations maintain a stable common service ring. As stated in Corollary 2, the size of the common service ring is defined by the GCD of each station's parameter . However, the linear or additive operation of tends to generate a small GCD (usually 1 or 2), which reduces the effectiveness of SRB.</p><p>Choosing different parameter settings of and would produce different system performance for SRB. Larger or smaller makes the system more sensitive to the variation of congestion index , causing a frequent change of . Our simulations show that choosing and can cover most of the testing scenarios.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Simulation Validation</head><p>Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9</ref> show the simulation results of R-EDCA with adaptive algorithm, in comparison to the results of R-EDCA without adaptive algorithm and original EDCA. All simulation settings and network configurations are identical to that used in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>(a), except that only the video access category (VI) is used. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref> compares the throughput among the three methods. As expected, the use of adaptive algorithm to the R-EDCA greatly improves the system throughput. It has sustained high throughput even when the number of active stations becomes large. This is different from the case of R-EDCA without adaptive algorithm, which reduces its throughput after exceeds the fixed service ring size . Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9</ref> shows the network collision rate against the number of active stations . We see a flat curve for R-EDCA with adaptive algorithm, but a sharp rising curve at the point for R-EDCA without adaptive algorithm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Convergence Speed</head><p>With the adaptive change of , a natural question is how fast the control algorithm can track the number of active stations . We vary the number of active stations in a wireless LAN every 2 s and measure the service ring size of a station that is active throughout our measurement period. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10</ref> shows the results. With the change of active stations at time epoch 2, 4, 6, 8, the service ring size varies dramatically in a short time, which causes spikes in the figure. Typically, the control algorithm needs several backoff cycles to reach a steady state. However, when compared to the steady period, which is usually in the timescale of seconds, the transition period is relatively small (up to tens of milliseconds in most cases).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI.</head><p>FOR LIGHT TRAFFIC LOADS A limitation with the SRB is that although it is highly effective for heavy traffic configurations, it is less effective under light or moderate traffic scenarios. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11</ref> illustrates this limitation. In a six-station network, each station generates video traffic with rates varying from 0 to 7.5 Mp/s, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11</ref> shows how the collision rate changes with the total workload. We see that for heavy traffic (over 30 Mb/s), R-EDCA can effectively reduce the collision rate (see the curve of R-EDCA), but for light to moderate traffic (less than 25 Mb/s), R-EDCA has collision rate comparable to legacy EDCA.</p><p>SRB is less effective for light traffic because it releases reserved time-slots when it has no data to send in these slots, and needs to restart the reservation process when new data arrives. One way to solve this problem is to keep the reserved across multiple backoff cycles, even when the station has no data to send. To achieve this, if a station's backoff counter decreased to zero and it has no data to send, the station treats this event as a successful transmission and resets its backoff counter to the fixed value , which starts a new backoff cycle. We name this process as persistent backoff, and the corresponding improved SRB as   Compared to R-BEB (Algorithm 1), the -BEB algorithm enables a station to retain its reservation state even in the case that it has no data send in a reserved time-slot (herein an empty slot). Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11</ref> shows the collision rate for EDCA with (tagged -EDCA). We see almost no collisions for across the entire traffic load range. The two curves of SRB and converge to zero for a workload beyond 30 Mb/s. This implies that the two methods can both eliminate collisions under heavy traffic loads, but significantly outperforms SRB in case of light to moderate traffic loads.</p><p>facilitates reservation across multiple backoff cycles, thus considerably expands the effective range of SRB. Since the duration of an idle slot in CSMA networks is very small, the wasted time in idle slots is minimal compared to TDMA networks. The additional cost of is the requirement for a station to continuously synchronize the change of its backoff counter with other stations even when it has no traffic to send. However, this does not incur much extra overhead for a station since the information of channel state is readily available when the station is active. Upgrading SRB to just needs a minor change to the software or firmware implementation of the backoff module.</p><p>When combined with the adaptive control algorithm, can best serve data deliveries with QoS. For many applications with QoS requirements, such as voice or video, their traffic rate is not high enough to saturate the reserved time-slots for every backoff cycle. By using , lower traffic rate stations can perform effective reservation across multiple backoff cycles.</p><p>Theoretically, The SRB method can be further extended in many areas. As an example, the setting of the backoff counter upon failed transmissions can be optimized by intentionally choosing a value that is not likely used by other stations, similar to that of the zero collision MAC in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. Another interesting approach is the use of nonuniform probability distribution when choosing a time-slot from the service ring, and this probability distribution can be adjusted via online learning of channel status in each time-slot. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> discusses such a technique and claims that it accelerates the convergence speed of collision rate. However, each of the these extensions incurs extra cost in the increased system complexity and learning overhead.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. RELATED WORK</head><p>The simplicity and easy deployment of binary exponential backoff (BEB) contributed to the popularity of 802.11 DCF/EDCA. However, practical measurements <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and analytical studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> reveal that such random methods suffer high collision rate in the cases of increased number of stations and heavy traffic loads. To reduce the collision rate and improve BEB, a series of MAC enhancements are proposed. Among them, some aim to improve BEB by changing the varying pattern of backoff window size, such as MILD <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and LILD <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>; others explore ways to dynamically adjust the contention window size based on the observed channel conditions or network status, including idle sense <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and methods to estimate the number of contending stations <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. While the first approach still suffers a high collision rate in the case of increased number of contending stations, the second requires additional efforts to estimate the channel condition or the number of contending stations. Both approaches can only mitigate the collision problem to some extent at their own cost. In contrast, this paper proposes a SRB, which can completely remove collisions without any additional cost.</p><p>The SRB advocates an elegant combination of CSMA with TDMA and achieves this by purposeful control of the timing to access the shared medium. The original idea of SRB is inspired by R-Aloha in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, and we presented the basic idea in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and further in more details with a full-fledged analytical model and enhancements in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> as well as this paper. The SRB is such a general approach that it had received much attention from other researchers, producing independent works with similar ideas. Learning BEB (L-BEB) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, developed by Barcelo et al., is a very similar work to SRB. L-BEB uses deterministic backoff upon successful transmissions to reduce collisions in consecutive backoff cycles, which is in the same spirit as R-Aloha and SRB. The L-BEB solution was further investigated and developed in their following studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. Although these two pieces of research work proceeded independently, <ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">11</ref>they performed a number of similar explorations: 1) both examined the issue of priority, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> and [14, Section III]; 2) analytical study of performance is provided in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and [14, Section IV]; 3) convergence issues are discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> and [14, Section IV]; 4) adaptation problem for large networks is addressed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, and Section V of this paper.</p><p>However, it is worth pointing out that there are significant differences in many aspects of the two works. First, Barcelo's analytical model relies on queuing theory and probability estimation, and approximate results are presented, while our model in this paper deals with combinatorial analysis, and close-form results are obtained. Second, Barcelo's study focuses on channel efficiency, while our work in this paper emphasizes on robustness against perturbations such as carrier-sense errors, clock skew, etc. Third, the two works also differ in their ways to handle adaptation for networks size. Our work further addresses the light traffic load issue, which was not addressed in Barcelo's work. While our work provides more theoretical and consistent insights on the basic idea of combining CSMA and TDMA, we believe that the idea is best understood by detailed examination of both works.</p><p>There are also some other works related to SRB. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, the idea of R-Aloha is further developed and enhanced for voice and real-time traffic in cellular networks at the cost of increased system complexity and extra signaling overheads. Rhee et al. propose Z-MAC <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, which introduces TDMA into the CSMA-based sensor networks. Due to the multihop nature with sensor networks, Z-MAC requires substantial extra efforts such as neighbor discovery, slot assignment, and global time synchronization to resolve collision between stations. An early work that considers reducing collision by intentional control of the backoff process is the EBA <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. EBA explicitly requires a station to announce its backoff value in its frame header, so that neighboring stations can adjust their backoff values to avoid conflicts with this station. The method is further improved by zero collision (ZC) MAC, where the explicit information announcement is replaced by implicit information learning from each backoff cycle. Compared to SRB and L-BEB, ZC needs to track the status of each time-slot and assumes a fixed number of slots in a backoff cycle, but it produces a higher convergence speed. Reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> presents an insightful between these two approaches, with proposals to accelerate the convergence speed. Authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> consider establishing collision-free schedules for broadcast and multicast traffic in networks with multiple collision domains, which is complementary to this work. There are also some recent works following SRB for other network paradigms, like the polling-based networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and the multiradio multichannel networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>VIII. CONCLUSION SRB is a simple, elegant, and effective approach that achieves resource reservation in a CSMA network at no extra cost. In SRB, a station simply needs to track the results of its data transmission to properly reset the backoff counter, and sense the wireless channel to synchronize the decrement of its backoff counter with other stations, both of which are already common components for a CSMA network. In the case of imperfect carrier sense, clock skew, or the presence of hidden terminals, SRB reverts back to a random backoff scheme. SRB can be readily used to enhance current 802.11 DCF/EDCA, with minimum modification to existing implementations. It is also backward compatible with legacy DCF/EDCA. Analytical study and simulation results show that SRB performs better than or equal to the legacy 802.11 DCF/EDCA in all possible scenarios. With enhancements including the adaptive mechanism and the persistent backoff process, SRB can achieve even higher performance gain over legacy 802.11 DCF/EDCA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX PROOF OF (3)</head><p>Proof: We label each station as . Let denote the event that station selects a collision-free slot and denote the event that station selects a collision slot. Clearly <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> where is a permutation of . The inclusion-exclusion principle gives <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> where is the probability that for the selected stations (out of stations), , each is collision-free during the slot selection procedure. It is easy to derive that <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> Since are randomly selected from ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) Substituting ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) into (20) yields the result.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Resource reservation achieved by the semi-random backoff method.is set to 7, which is the default window size for voice traffic in 802.11e EDCA.</figDesc><graphic coords="1,303.00,171.12,253.02,87.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Reservation achieved by SRB on (a) discrete timeline and (b) service ring. All slots are represented as equal-length slots for illustration.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,303.00,65.10,252.00,73.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Collision probability in each global backoff cycle. The simulation results are presented with 95% confidence intervals. (a) , . (b) , .</figDesc><graphic coords="6,37.98,64.14,252.00,153.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Throughput and collision rate of R-EDCA and EDCA in both single-and mixed-traffic cases. (a) Throughput in single-traffic case. (b) Throughput in mixed-traffic case. (c) Collision rate in single-traffic case. (d) Collision rate in mixed-traffic case.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,121.02,64.14,352.98,322.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Performance of R-EDCA and EDCA in unsynchronized networks. Results are presented with 95% confidence intervals. (a) Different AIFS (VI versus BE). (b) Different AIFS (VI versus BK). (c) Carrier-sense error. (d) Channel error. (e) Hidden terminals. (f) Legacy EDCA stations.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,43.02,64.14,504.00,331.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Delay and fairness performance for R-EDCA and legacy EDCA. (a) Medium access delay. (b) End-to-end delay. (c) Jain rairness index.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,85.02,64.14,423.00,153.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Throughput versus the congestion index . Parameter settings: ms, ms, B, s, , .</figDesc><graphic coords="10,357.00,64.14,142.02,117.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Throughput versus number of stations in the network.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,88.02,63.12,153.96,130.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Network collision rate versus number of stations in the network.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,88.02,232.14,154.98,129.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Adaptive service ring size to the number of active stations .</figDesc><graphic coords="11,352.02,64.14,154.18,129.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. The pseudocode of BEB with , called -BEB, is as follows. (Terms have the same meanings as in Algorithm 1.) Algorithm 3: The -BEB Algorithm Require: This algorithm runs only when has reached 0. 1: if a successful transmission an empty slot then</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Collision rate versus offered traffic load for different methods.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,87.00,64.14,154.02,126.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Algorithm 2 runs independently on each station. It only needs to evaluate from its local information, which is readily available via counting the number of busy slots in a backoff cycle. Hence, it does not place any extra requirements on hardware.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Algorithm 2: The EIED Control Algorithm</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">1: for each new backoff cycle do</cell></row><row><cell>2:</cell><cell></cell><cell>/*Update the congestion index */</cell></row><row><cell>3:</cell><cell>if</cell><cell>then</cell></row><row><cell>4:</cell><cell></cell><cell>/*Increase service ring</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">size*/</cell></row><row><cell>5:</cell><cell>end if</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6:</cell><cell>if</cell><cell>then</cell></row><row><cell>7:</cell><cell></cell><cell>/*Decrease service</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">ring size*/</cell></row><row><cell>8:</cell><cell>end if</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">9: end for</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>The standard random backoff refers to the binary exponential backoff used in 802.11 DCF/EDCA throughout this paper.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Typically, a broadcast/multicast (B/M) transmission without any ACK cannot be recognized as a successful transmission. However, in wireless LANs, uplink B/M data is transmitted in a unicast way to the access point (AP), and only B/M data from AP to stations is transmitted with no ACK, thus we can ignore the difference between unicast and B/M traffic when we discuss SRB in wireless LANs.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_2"><p>In our analysis, as long as two or more stations pick up the same time-slot, we assume a collision occurs. However, in practice this claim may be not valid due to the capture effect. In general, the collision probability calculated in (8) should be slightly higher than practical results.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_3"><p>In ns2, the average time of ON and OFF periods are set to 50 ms, and the shape parameter is 1.5.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_4"><p>Note that the end-to-end delay is calculated as the difference from the time when a packet is inserted to the MAC at the sender to the time when a packet is delivered to the upper layer by MAC at the receiver. Thus, this delay includes the buffer delay at both ends. However, since in this experiment the traffic load offered in the network is merely moderate, the buffer delay is negligible. If the traffic saturates the network, then the buffer delay would be significant.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="11" xml:id="foot_5"><p>No cross citation exists between the two until the recent study<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, as well as this work.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the United States National Science Foundation under Grant EFRI-0735974 and Grant NetSE-1065133 and the Army Research Office under Contract W911NF-08-1-0233. Part of this work was published in the Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP), Princeton, NJ, October 13-16, 2009.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Yong He received the B.S. and Ph.D. degrees in control science and engineering from Tsinghua University, Beijing, China, in 2004 and 2009, respectively.</p><p>He is currently a Researcher with the Alibaba Group, Beijing, China. His research interests include access control for wireless networks, software defined radio, cooperative diversity, load balancing, and traffic scheduling for content delivery networks.</p><p>Jie Sun received the B.S. and M.S. degrees from Xi'an Jiaotong University, Xi'an, China, in 1999 and 2002 respectively, and the Ph.D. degree from the University of Massachusetts, Amherst, in 2010, all in electrical and computer engineering.</p><p>Her research interests cover analog equalizer design for indoor transmission of multi-gigabit-per-second data rates using millimeter waves. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Medium access control (MAC) quality of service enhancements</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE standard 802.11e: Amendment to IEEE Std</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society LAN MAN Standards Committee</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005-11">Nov. 2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">802</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic reservation TDMA protocol for wireless ATM networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-F</forename><surname>Frigon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="370" to="383" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-02">Feb. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to Probability, 2nd ed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Grinstead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Snell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Providence</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>Amer. Math. Soc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>RI</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding congestion in IEEE 802.11b wireless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Jardosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Ramachandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Almeroth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Belding-Royer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. USENIX IMC</title>
		<meeting>USENIX IMC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-10">Oct. 2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance analysis of the IEEE 802.11 distributed coordination function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bianchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="535" to="547" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-03">Mar. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MACAW: A media access protocol for wireless LAN&apos;s</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bharghavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="212" to="225" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of link-layer backoff schemes on point-to-point Markov fading links</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Soni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chockalingam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-01">Jan. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic tuning of the IEEE 802.11 protocol to achieve a theoretical throughput limit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Conti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gregori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Trans. Netw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="785" to="790" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-12">Dec. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Idle sense: An optimal access method for high throughput and fairness in rate diverse wireless LANs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heusse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guillier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Duda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-08">Aug. 2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="132" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A system for broadcast communication: Reservation-ALOHA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Crowther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rettberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Walden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ornstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Heart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 6th HICSS</title>
		<meeting>6th HICSS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973-01">Jan. 1973</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="374" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability and performance of the R-ALOHA packet broadcast system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tasaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="717" to="726" />
			<date type="published" when="1983-08">Aug. 1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A quantitative measure of fairness and discrimination for resource allocation of shared computer systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hawe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>DEC Tech. Rep. TR-301</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combating network collisions by reservation in wireless CSMA networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Barcelona, Spain</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-08">Aug. 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semi-random backoff: Towards resource reservation for channel access in 802.11e wireless LANs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE ICNP</title>
		<meeting>IEEE ICNP<address><addrLine>Princeton, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-10">Oct. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deterministic backoff: Towards efficient polling for 802.11e HCCA in wireless home networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE ICC</title>
		<meeting>IEEE ICC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards high-performance dedicated control channel in multi-radio multi-channel networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Converg. Inf. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-06">Jun. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kalman filter estimation of the number of competing terminals in an IEEE 802.11 network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bianchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Tinnirello</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="844" to="852" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive optimization of IEEE 802.11 DCF based on Bayesian estimation of the number of competing terminals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lopez-Toledo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vercauteren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Mobile Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1283" to="1283" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-09">Sep. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Packet reservation multiple access for local wireless communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Valenzuela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gayliard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ramamurthi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="885" to="890" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-08">Aug. 1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">C-PRMA: A centralized packet reservation multiple access for local wireless communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bianchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Borgonovo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fratta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Musumeci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zorzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="422" to="C436" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-05">May 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Z-MAC: A hybrid MAC for wireless sensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Rhee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Warrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Min</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SenSys</title>
		<meeting>ACM SenSys</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="101" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EBA: An enhancement of the IEEE 802.11 DCF via distributed reservation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Mobile Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="390" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-04">Apr. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Design and analysis of an asynchronous zero collision MAC protocol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Walrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:0806.3542</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Medium access control for wireless networks with peer-to-peer state exchange</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. CoRR</title>
		<meeting>CoRR</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1829" to="1836" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Decentralised learning MACs for collision-free access in WLANs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Malone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Duffy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Leith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1009.4386v1</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning-BEB: Avoiding collisions in WLAN</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barcelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bellalta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Eunice Summer School</title>
		<meeting>Eunice Summer School</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carrier sense multiple access with enhanced collision avoidance: A performance analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Barcelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bellalta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sfairopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM IWCMC</title>
		<meeting>ACM IWCMC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="733" to="738" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Traffic prioritization for carrier sense multiple access with enhanced collision avoidance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barcelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bellalta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sfairopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zuidweg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. MACOM</title>
		<meeting>MACOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic parameter adjustment in CSMA/ECA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barcelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bellalta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sfairopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. MACOM</title>
		<meeting>MACOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="24" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fairness and convergence of CSMA with enhanced collision avoidance (ECA)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barcelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lopez-Toledo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE ICC</title>
		<meeting>IEEE ICC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a collision-free WLAN: Dynamic parameter adjustment in CSMA/E2CA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barcelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bellalta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sfairopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Verma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EURASIP J. Wireless Commun. Netw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">708617</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Network Simulator-ns-2</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.isi.edu/nsnam/ns/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
