<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Rational Series over Dioids and Discrete Event Systems</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Ste</forename><surname>´phane Gaubert</surname></persName>
							<email>stephane.gaubert@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Domaine de Voluceau</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">INRIA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>BP 105</addrLine>
									<postCode>78153</postCode>
									<settlement>Le Chesnay Ce ´dex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Rational Series over Dioids and Discrete Event Systems</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">66119E2E73321A364D85185C295FA9AA</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T15:10+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>We survey the different kinds of rational series which arise in the study of Discrete Event Systems (DES) and of certain related Markov Decision Processes. The use of rational series over fields is classical, e.g. as transfer functions, generating series of finite Markov chains, skew Ore series in Difference and Differential Algebra, commutative multivariable series for linear PDE with constant coefficients, Fliess' noncommutative generating series for bilinear systems. It turns out that all these more or less familiar classes of series admit useful counterparts for DES, when the scalars belong to some dioids <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> such as the (max; +) semiring. The main interest of this series theoretical point of view consists in introducing some efficient algebraic techniques in the study of these dynamical systems. Since this paper is obviously too short for such a program, we have chosen to propose an introductive guided tour. A more detailed exposition will be found in our references and in a more complete paper to appear elsewhere.</p><p>1 Rational Series in a Single Indeterminate 1.1 Rational Series as Transfers of (max; +)-Linear Systems We consider systems of recurrent linear equations in the (max; +) algebra of the form x(n) = Ax(n 1) Bu(n); y(n) = Cx(n) ; <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> where 1 x(n) 2 R p max , u(n) 2 R max ; y ( n )2 R max . As it is well known <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>, this class of systems encompasses in particular the dater equations of SISO Timed Event Graphs (TEG). A straightforward argument shows that the least solution 2 of (1) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">y(n) = M k 2 N CA k Bu(n k) ; (2)</formula><p>1 Rmax denotes the "(max,+) semiring" (R[ f 1g; max; +). The reader is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> for the general notation about dioids. In particular, and denote the sum and the product, " denotes the zero and e the unit (in Rmax, a b = max(a; b), a b = a + b, " = 1, e = 0 ).</p><p>2 which corresponds for a TEG to the earliest behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>hence, the input-output behavior of the system is completely determined by the following</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">transfer series 3 H = M k2N CA k B X k = C ( AX) B 2 R max [[X]] ;<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where 4 M def = L k2N M k . A series is realizable if it admits a representation of the form (3) for some finite dimensional triple (A; B; C). The celebrated Kleene-Schu ¨tzenberger Theorem <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> states that realizable series coincide with rational series defined as follows.</p><p>Definition 1. Let S denote a dioid. The dioid of rational series over S in the indeterminate X is the least subset of S[[X]] containing the polynomials and stable by the operations ; and . Thus, the transfer series H = C(AX) B of a stationary finite dimensional (max; +) linear system is rational.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Generating Series of Bellman Chains</head><p>Let us consider a Markovian maximization problem with finite state S = f1; : : : ; n g , finite horizon k, final reward b and transition reward i Aij ! j. The value function for the initial position i 2 S is thus given by v (k)   i def = max i1:::ik [A ii1 + : : :</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">+ A i k 1 i k + b ( i k )] :<label>(4)</label></formula><p>This is a particular case of Bellman chain (Akian, Quadrat and Viot <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>). As it is well known and obvious from (4), the value function is given by a product of matrices in the (max; +) algebra, that is, v (k) = A k b. Now, let us consider the vector of generating series</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">V i def = M k v (k) i X k = M k (A k b) i X k 2 R max [[X]] :<label>(5)</label></formula><p>An immediate comparison with <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref> shows that the generating series of an homogeneous Bellman chain with finite state are rational.</p><p>3 Given a semiring S, S[[X]] denotes the semiring of formal series H = L k HkX k , equipped with componentwise sum and Cauchy product. S[X] denotes the subdioid of polynomials. We shall sometimes write (HjX k ) instead of Hk, in line with the scalar product notation</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(HjH 0 ) def = L k HkH 0 k .</formula><p>4 For a in a dioid D, a is to be interpreted as the least upper bound of the set fa 0 ; a 1 ; a 2 ; : : : g with respect to the natural order a b () a b = b. Here, D = ( S [[X]]) nn and the convergence of (AX) is immediate, due to the fact that AX has no constant coefficient. In the scalar case (a 2 D = R m ax[[X]]), a is well defined iff a0 = ( a j X 0 ) e . See <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> for a more precise discussion. Strong stabilization holds if the value = is allowed (whenever a; b 6 = ").</p><p>We also introduce the following central notion which already appears in the theory of nonnegative rational series <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 5 (Merge of Series).</head><p>The merge of the series s (0) ,…, s (c 1) is the series t such that 8k 2 N, 8i 2 f 0 ; : : : ; c 1 g , t i + kc = s (i) k .</p><p>For instance, the series (X 2 ) 1X(1X 2 ) = 0 1 X 0 X 2 2 X 2 0 X 3 3 X 4 : : : is the merge of the series X = 0 0 X 0 X 2 : : : and 1(1X) = 1 2 X 3 X 2 : : : Definition 6 (Ultimately Geometric Series). The series s is ultimately geometric if 9K 2 N, 9 2 S , 8 k K , s k +1 = s k .</p><p>We have the following central characterization first noted by Moller <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> for S = R max . Theorem 7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Let S be a commutative dioid satisfying the weak stabilization condition. Then, a series is rational iff it is a merge of ultimately geometric series.</p><p>As a corollary, we obtain a version of the classical periodicity theorem <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corollary 8 (Cyclicity).</head><p>Assume that S is commutative without divisors of zero and satisfies the strong stabilization condition. Let A 2 S n n be an irreducible matrix. Then, 9 2 S and k 0; c1 such that A k+c = A k .</p><p>The proof <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> consists in showing that all the merged series which appear in (AX) ij have the same asymptotic rate -independent of ij -due to the irreducibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Example 1 (Computing the Value Function of a Bellman Chain). Let us consider the</head><p>Bellman Chain (4), whose transition rewards are described on Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. For instance, the 5 For a more complete study of rational identities, see Bonnier and Krob <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>. The two labels (C) and (SC)recall that these identities are specific to commutative rational series.</p><p>6</p><p>The strong stabilization is borrowed to Dudnikov and Samborkskiȋ <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> for a comparison of these properties.</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">n e 3 2 2 1 n e e 1 e V1 = ( 1 X ) V 1 XV2e V2 = ( 2 X ) V 2 XV3</formula><p>: : :</p><p>V n= ( nX)Vn XV1 : arc n e ! 1 means that A n1 = e. We take as final reward a Dirac at node 1: b i = e if i = 1 , b i = " otherwise. Let v be the value function defined by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">4</ref>) and consider the generating series V given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">5</ref>). V can be computed by performing a Gaussian elimination 7 on the system V = AXV b displayed on Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. After some computations making an intensive use of the rational identities (C),(SC), we get eventually </p><formula xml:id="formula_6">V 1 = ( 1 X ) X n ( nX) . Taking the coefficient of V 1 at X p ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">(s t) n def = M p+q=n s p p (t q ) :</formula><p>This noncommutative product arises from the rule Xa=(a)X,8a2 S .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Skew Series and Discounted Bellman Chains</head><p>Let A 2 R nn max and let us consider the following Markovian discounted optimization problem (discounted "Bellman chain") with initial state i, final state j and horizon k:</p><p>(A [k] ) ij def = max i1;:::;ik 1 A ii1 + A i1i2 + : : :</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">+ k 1 A i k 1 j ;<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where 2]0; 1] denotes the discount rate. We have the following Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equation</p><p>(A [k+1] ) ij = max q A iq + (A [k] ) qj :</p><p>After introducing the automorphism of R max and of R nn max :</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">x 2 R max ; ( x ) def = x ; A 2 R n n max ; ( A ) ij def = (A ij ) ; we rewrite (8) as A [k+1] = A (A [k] ), hence A [k] = A (A) : : : k 1 ( A ):<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Since A [k] = ( ( AX) jX k ), the asymptotic study of the sequence of "skew powers" A [k] reduces to the evaluation of the matrix (AX) whose entries are skew rational series.</p><p>7 E.g. V2 can be eliminated by noting that V2 = ( 2 X ) V 2 XV3 is equivalent to V2 = (2X) XV3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Theorems of Representation for (max; +) Rational Skew Series</head><p>We again consider simple series which write s = ( aX p ) bX n or equivalently s = bX n (fX p ) with a; b; f 2 R max , p 1; n 0 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">Theorem 9. A skew series s 2 R max [[X; ]] is rational iff it is a sum of simple series.</formula><p>This theorem is rather surprising because rational series usually cannot be expressed with a single level of star in noncommutative structures. The proof uses the machinery of noncommutative rational identities, such as</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">(S) (a b) = a (ba )</formula><p>together with a few specific "commutative" identities, in particular 8a; b 2 R max ; p 1; ((a b)X p ) = ( aX p ) (bX p ) :</p><p>(10)</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Definition 10. The series s 2 R max [[X; ]] is ultimately skew geometric iff 9K 2 N; 2R max k K ) s k+1 = (s k ) (= + s k ) :<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Theorem 11. A series s 2 R max [[X; ]] is rational iff it is a merge of ultimately skew geometric series.</p><p>We obtain as a corollary the following remarkable periodicity theorem first proved by Braker and Resing <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> (for primitive matrices).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theorem 12 (Skew Cyclicity). For an irreducible matrix</head><formula xml:id="formula_14">A 2 R nn max , 9c 1, 8ij, 9 ij such that A [k+c] ij = ij c (A [k] ij ) for k large enough.</formula><p>Example 2 (Value Function of a Discounted Bellman Chain). Let us compute the value function v for the discounted version of the Bellman Chain described in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. Using the identity <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, it is not too difficult to obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">V 1 = ( 1 X ( X) X n ) with = L 1in 1 i (i+1</formula><p>). An application of the identity (S)</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">gives V 1 = ( 1 X ) ( X) X n , hence v (p) 1 = 1 [ p ] [ p n ] , which rewrites: v (p) 1 = max 1 p 1 ; 1 p n 1 with = max<label>1in 1</label></formula><p>( i (i + 1)) :</p><p>3 Rational Series in Several Commuting Indeterminates</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Timed Event Graphs with Unknown Resources and Holding Times</head><p>As shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>, the algebraic modelization of Timed Event Graphs uses the two</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">operators 8 : u 2 R Z max 7 ! y 2 R Z max ; y ( k ) = 1 + u ( k ) : u 2 R Z max 7 ! y 2 R Z max ; y ( k ) = u ( k 1) :</formula><p>When some task has an unknown duration 1 , we get an equation of the form y(k) = 1 + u ( k ) , which suggests to introduce a new operator 1 : 1 u(k) def = 1 + u(k). In the same vein, an unknown initial marking q 1 (say an unknown number of parts, of machines) is represented by a new operator 1 : 1 u(k) = u ( k q 1 ) . Then, the dater functions of a TEG with unknown resources and holding times satisfy the following polynomial equations 9 :  materials for part i (u i (k) = date of k-th arrival), and the output y i represents the dates of production of the same part. For instance, the expression 10 H 11 = 1 ( 1 2 ) shows that for the autonomous regime, one part of type 1 exits every t 1 + t 2 units of time (after time t 1 ).</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">x =</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Some Algebraic Results</head><p>Let S denote a (commutative) dioid. It follows from the commutative rational identities (C),(SC) that a series s 2 S [[X 1 ; : : : ; X n ]] is rational iff it can be written s = L k i=1 u i v i where u i ; v i are polynomials. However, we have a much more precise result inspired by the theory of rational subsets of N k <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>Definition 13. A simple series s writes s = aX 1 1 : : : X k k ( L r i =1 a i X i1 1 : : : X ik k ) , where the vectors ( 1;i ) 1ik ; : : : ; ( r ;i ) 1ik form a free family of N k . Theorem 14. Assume that S is totally ordered. Then, a series s 2 S [[X 1 ; : : : ; X m ]] is rational iff it is a sum of simple series.</p><p>The proof uses essentially the following kind of rational identity:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">(aX) (bY ) (cXY ) = ( aX) (bY ) (aX) (cXY ) (bY ) (cXY ) : (12)</formula><p>9 B = f";eg denotes the boolean semiring. 10 For the autonomous regime starting at time 0 (e.g. if an infinite quantity of inputs become available at time 0, see [2, §5.4.4.1]), the monomial transfer n N i k i i can be interpreted as "the event n occurs at the earliest at time </p><formula xml:id="formula_20">P i ki ti".</formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">H n = n 1 2 1 2 2 ( 1 2 ) n 2 1 2 ( 1 2 ) n 1 1 2 ( 1 2 ) n 1 n 2 2 1 2 2 ( 1 2 ) n 2</formula><p>( 1 2 )</p><p>(modulo the licit additional simplification rules s i t i = max(s;t) i</p><p>). This expression specifies the input/output behavior in function of the unknown processing times t 1 ; t 2 . In particular, the term 10 n 1 2 1 2 2 ( 1 2 ) n 2 in the expression of H n 11 means that, for the autonomous regime, the part of type 1 numbered 0 has a transfer time of nt 1 , while the part of the same type numbered 1 has a transfer time of 2(t 2 +t 1 )+( n 2) max(t 1 ; t 2 ) .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Example 5 (Heaviside Calculus for some Special Variational Inequalities). Let us search</head><p>for the least solution u; v of the system 11 : 0 @v @x @v @t ; @u @x ; @u @t ); u max(+v;f); v + u : (13)</p><p>A discretization gives with the R max notation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">u h (x; t) h u h (x h; t) h u h (x; t h) v h (x; t) f(x; t) v h (x; t) h v h (x h; t h) u h (x; t) :<label>(14)</label></formula><p>Introducing the space and time shifts Xu(x; t) def = u(x h; t) and T u ( x; t) def = u(x; t h),</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">we get u h ( h X h T)u h v h f v h h XTv h u h :<label>(15)</label></formula><p>A Gaussian elimination gives the least solution u = ( h X h T ( h XT) ) f :</p><p>The convergence of this star in R max [[X;T]] yields the compatibility condition e.</p><p>After some computation involving the rational identities (C), (SC), <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>, we obtain u = ( h X) ( h T) ( h X) ( h XT) ( h T) ( h XT) f :</p><p>We have for the second term of this sum:</p><p>( h X) ( h XT) f(x; t) = sup p;n0 [hp + hn + f(x hp hn; t hn)] = sup qn0 [h(q n) + hn + f(x hq; t hn)] :</p><p>After an analogous argument for the two other terms, we introduce the three kernels</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">k 1 (;) = + ; k 2 (;) = ( ) + + + if 1 otherwise, k 3 (;) = ( ) + + + if 1 otherwise.</formula><p>Then, letting h ! 0, we get the explicit solution u(x; t) = sup ;0</p><p>[max(k 1 ; k 2 ; k 3 )(;) + f ( x ;t )] :</p><p>11 u; v; f are maps R 2 ! R. ;; ; ; are constant. We do not address the regularity issues here.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Rational Series in Non Commuting Indeterminates</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Definition and Basic Examples</head><p>Let denote the free monoid over a finite alphabet . The series y = L w2 (yjw)w (in R max hhii) is recognizable iff there exists 2 R 1n max ; 2R n 1 max , and a morphism : ! R nn max such that (yjw) = (w). The general version of the Kleene-Schu ¨tzenberger theorem states that recognizable and rational series coincide.</p><p>Example 6 (Deterministic Cost). Let (Q; q 0 ; ) denote a finite deterministic automaton, : Q ! R max a final cost and : Q ! R max a transition cost. Let w = w k : : : w 1 2 k denote a sequence of decisions (w i denotes the i-th letter of w, read read from right to left). We consider the cost</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">(cjw) def = k X n=1</formula><p>(q n 1 ; w n ) + ( q k ) ;subject to q n = (q n 1 ; w n ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> (by convention, (cjw) = " if (q 0 ; w )is undefined). This is the discrete counterpart of the usual integral cost R T 0 (x(t); u ( t ))dt + (x(T)) for the system _ x = f(x; u).</p><p>The series L w (cjw)w is recognizable (take = Dirac at q 0 and 8a 2 ;8p; q 2 Q; (a) pq = (q;a) if (q;a) = p and " otherwise).</p><p>Example 7 (A Workshop with Different Schedules). We consider a workshop with 2 machines M 1 ; M 2 and 2 different regimes of production corresponding to the processing of 2 differents parts (a) and (b), as represented 12 by the TEGs (a) and (b) displayed on Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>. We assume that the workshop can switch from a regime to the other, according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">1 Regime (a) 2 M 2 x 1 M 1 1 M 1 1 1 x 2 x 2 2 A(a) = h 1 " " 1 2 " 1 2 " i x 3</formula><p>Regime (b) </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Asymptotic Behavior of (max; +) Automata</head><p>The asymptotic analysis of a recognizable series y consists in estimating (yjw) where w is a word of length k ! 1 . We consider the worst case performance: r worst  (yjw) = min w k ;:::;w 1 2;</p><p>(yjw)6 =" max ik;:::;i0 [ ik +(w k ) ikik 1 +: : : + ( w 1 ) i 1 i 0 + i 0 ]:</p><p>This min-max problem consists in finding a schedule minimizing the transfer time of the k-th input. We remark that for the subclass of deterministic 15 series, (yjw) does not involve maximization, so that the computation of r opt. and r worst become dual. More formally, we introduce y 0 = L (yjw)6 = 1 (yjw)w 2 R min hhii (where R min def = ( R [ f + 1g; min; +)) and we get: Proposition 16. For a deterministic series y, r opt. k = 0 (M 0 ) k 0 , where 0 ; 0 ; 0 is a R min -linear representation of y 0 , M 0 = L a2 0 (a) and all the operations are interpreted in R min .</p><p>Thus, we are reduced to characterize the series which admit deterministic representations. Under some finiteness and integrity conditions on ; ; , e.g. if 8a; i; j; (a) ij 2 Z , the series y is deterministic <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>. However, the minimal dimension of a deterministic representation can be arbitrarily larger than the dimension of ; ; . Thus 13 See <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The multiplicity of w -i.e. (yjw) -is equal to the sum of the multiplicative weights of all the paths with label w from the input to the output. E.g. (yjba) = 1 1 2 2 1 2 . 14 The mean case performance r mean k = E(yjw k ) -where w k is a random word of length kis dealt with in the first order ergodic theory of TEGs <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>.</p><p>computing r opt. from Prop. 16 can be much more complex than computing r worst from Th. 15. Some different techniques based on rational simplifications can sometimes be applied as in Ex. 9, but it is hopeless to obtain universal canonical forms since the equality of (max; +) rational series is undecidable <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. It remains an open question whether the asymptotic behavior of r opt. can be exactly evaluated for some reasonable classes of series without appealing to the above determinization procedure.</p><p>Example 9. For the automaton of Ex. 7, lim k r opt. k =k = min(max i ( i ); max i ( i )). When 2 1 , 2 1 , this follows for instance from the easily obtained expression y = ( 2 a 2 b )( 2 a 2 b) .</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. A Simple Bellman Chain with its Generating Equations</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. (a): A Single Machine Producing 2 Types of Parts. (b): A Cascade of n Machines.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3.A Workshop with Two Production Regimes and its Equivalent (max; +) Automaton an open loop schedule described by a word w 2 f a; bg . E.g. the word baa means that the two machines first follow two tasks with times and precedence constraints determined by the TEG (a) and after that one task described by the TEG (b). The behavior of the workshop under the schedule w = w k : : : w 1 is determined by the system of non stationary (max; +) linear equationsx w (0) = B; x w (n) = A ( w n ) x w ( n 1); y w ( n ) = Cx w (n) ; 1nk ; (17)12The interpretation of regime (b) is the following. A part is processed by M2 during 2 time units. Then it is sent to M1 (processing time of 1). For simplicity, we have neglected the transportation times. A dual interpretation can be provided for regime (a). The initial condition B = [ e;e; "] T require M1 and M2 to begin to work at time e = 0 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>wk;:::;w12 max ik;:::;i0 [ ik +(w k ) ikik 1 +: : : + ( w 1 ) i 1 i 0 + i 0 ]:Theorem 15<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. Let y be the series given by the linear representation ; ; .Let M = L a2 (a). Then r worst k = M k .This is a superposition principle which states that the worst case behavior is obtained by mere superposition of the TEGs with transition matrices (a); a2 .Example 8. For the automaton of Ex. 7, the asymptotic behavior is determined by the eigenvalue of M = A(a) A(b), i.e. lim k (r worst k ) 1 k = lim k r worst k =k = = max i=1;2 max( i ; i ) .We next turn to the dual optimal case measure of performance 14 : r opt.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>1.3 Representation Theorems for Rational Series over Commutative Dioids Definition 2 (Simple Series). A</head><label></label><figDesc>series s 2 S [[X]] is simple if it writes s = aX k (bX p ) with a; b 2 S , k 2 N , p 2 N n f 0 g .</figDesc><table><row><cell>Theorem 3. Let S be a commutative dioid. A series s 2 S [[X]] is rational iff it is a sum</cell></row><row><cell>of simple series.</cell></row><row><cell>The proof consists in reducing an arbitrary rational expression to a sum of simple series via the following classical rational identities 5</cell></row><row><cell>(C) (a b) = a b (SC) (ab ) = e aa b n 1; (P(n)) a = ( e a : : : a n 1 )(a n ) :</cell></row><row><cell>Definition 4 (Weak and Strong Stabilization). The dioid S satisfies the weak stabi-lization condition 6 if</cell></row><row><cell>8a; b; ; 2 S ;9 c; 2 S ; 9 K 2 N ; 8 k K; a k b k = c k : (6)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>we obtain the value function with initial state 1 and</figDesc><table><row><cell>horizon p</cell><cell>v (p) 1 = max(p; n(p n)) :</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2 Skew Rational Series</cell></row></table><note><p>Let be an endomorphism of the semiring S. The semiring of skew series over S, denoted by S[[X; ]] is by definition the set of formal sums s = L n2N s n X n equipped with the usual componentwise sum and the skew product:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Ax Bu; y=Cx; A2(B[ i ; i ]) nn ; B2( B [ i ; i ]) np ; C2( B [ i ; i ]) rn (with essentially as many i as unknown holding times and as many i as unknown markings). The transfer H = CA Bis a rational series of B[[ i ; i ]]. Transfer of a Machine with Two Part Types). Consider a single machine producing 2 different parts with processing times t 1 ; t 2 . Under a cyclic scheduling, we obtain the TEG shown on Fig. 2,(a). The input u i represents the arrivals of row</figDesc><table><row><cell>Example 3 (t 1 u 1 u 2 t 2 t 1 t 2</cell><cell>y 2 H = y 1</cell><cell>1 1 2 1 2 2</cell><cell>( 1 2 )</cell><cell>u 2 u 1</cell><cell>t 2</cell><cell>M 1 t 1 t 2 t 1</cell><cell>t 2</cell><cell>M 2 t 1</cell><cell>t 2</cell><cell>Mn t 2 t 1 t 1</cell><cell>y 1 y 2</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Example 4 (Transfer of a Flowshop with n Identical Machines). Let us consider a cascade of n identical machines of type shown on Fig.2,(b). The transfer matrix of the flowshop is equal to H n . An easy induction gives</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Akian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Quadrat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Viot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Bellman processes. This conference</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Baccelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Olsder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Quadrat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Synchronization and Linearity</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Berstel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Reutenauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Rational Series and their Languages</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Algorithms and Applications in Timed Discrete Event Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Braker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-12">Dec 1993</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Delft University of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dioids and Discrete Event Systems. This conference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endomorphisms of semimodules over semirings with an idempotent operation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dudnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Samborskiȋ</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. in USSR</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Izvestija</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Automata, Languages and Machines, volume A</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Eilenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<publisher>Acad. Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rational sets in commutative monoids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Eilenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Schu ¨tzenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Algebra</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The ´orie des syste `mes line ´aires dans les dioı ¨des. The `se</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gaubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-07">July 1992</date>
			<publisher>E ´cole des Mines de Paris</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance evaluation of timed automata</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gaubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Report</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1922-05">1922. May 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>INRIA</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Timed automata and discrete event systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gaubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ECC93</title>
		<meeting>the ECC93<address><addrLine>Groningen</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-07">July 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On rational series in one variable over certain dioids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gaubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Report</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2162</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994-01">Jan. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>INRIA</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On semigroups of matrices in the (max; +) algebra</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gaubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">INRIA</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-01">Jan. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Research Report 2172</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complete systems of B-rational identities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Krob</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theor. Comp. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The equality problem for rational series with multiplicities in the tropical semiring is undecidable</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Krob</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research report</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universite ´de Paris 7, LITP</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A complete system of identities for one letter rational expressions with multiplicities in the tropical semiring</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Krob</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bonnier-Rigny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>93.07</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">LITP</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universite de Paris 7</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Research Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Stochastic linear systems in the (max; +) algebra. This conference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mairesse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Maslov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Samborskiȋ</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Idempotent analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>RI</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The ´orie alge ´brique des Syste `mes a `E ´ve ´nements Discrets. The `se</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>E ´cole des Mines de Paris</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The nondeterministic complexity of a finite automaton</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>M. Lothaire</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Mots. Hermes</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
