<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">LOGIC AND TIME&apos;</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012-12-28">28 Dec 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<addrLine>29 December</addrLine>
									<postCode>1977</postCode>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>D.C</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">LOGIC AND TIME&apos;</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2012-12-28">28 Dec 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">29A3B0C2E818329C6077A585D3C8F15B</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received April 17, 1978.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T03:45+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>been the case that'. We can then define a future operator F = G for 'it will (at least once) be the case that' and a past operator P = -H-for 'it has (at least once) been the case that'. E.g. if p stands for 'Socrates is running', Ep represents something like 'Socrates will (sooner or later) be running', and Pp something like 'Socrates has (on at least one occasion) been running'. Now it turns out that even in this simple, purely propositional tense logic, which inferences are to be recognized as valid (always and in all cases leading from truths to truths) depends on one's cosmology: E.g. the inference from Gp to Fp can only be counted as valid if we suppose time has no last moment. Many philosophers have held that some properties of time can be determined a priori, while others can only be settled empirically. (A subtle variant is the view of Kant, important for logic through its influence on Brouwer. Kantians distinguish synthetic a priori features of time, such as its linearity, which are, as it were, built into the human mode of perception, from other questions, including those of time's infinite extent and division, on which pure reason cannot speculate without falling into antinomies.) Some philosophical logicians have gone so far as to urge that tense logic ought to be especially or exclusively concerned with enumerating those arguments in tensed language whose validity can be certified a priori, without recourse to facts or hypotheses from science or philosophy. (See e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.) Prior <ref type="bibr">[19,</ref> Chapter IV] firmly rejected this suggestion: 'Logical purity ... is a will-o'-the-wisp. The logician must be like a lawyer ... in the sense that he is there to provide the metaphysician, perhaps even the physicist, the tense-logic he wants, provided that it be consistent. <ref type="bibr">'</ref> Tense logicians, following Prior's recommendation, have busied themselves tracing out the consequences of a myriad assumptions about time. Now serious cosmological theories of time are theories of the eternal, immutable structure of the B-series: The 'now' has no place in cosmology. Such theories would be most appropriately expressed in a tenseless language. Indeed we find ancient metaphysical theories expressed in metaphor, and modern scientific theories in differential equations. E.g. the ever-popular doctrine of Eternal Return (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>) likens Time to a snake swallowing its own tail, while the current scientific theory is expressed in Einstein's field equations. Confusion often results if one attempts to discuss in a tensed language, e.g. English, what can only accurately be spoken of tenselessly, or vice versa. McTaggart's 'proof' <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> of the unreality of time is a particularly awful example. Tense logic, however, in enumerating which arguments in tensed language are valid on which cosmological assumptions, manages to convey in the tensed vernacular (a large part of) the content of theories originally expressed in a tenseless mathematical or poetic medium. ?1. Linear time. Careful speakers may avoid the Nixonism 'this point in time', but who does not speak of 'long' periods of time and 'distant' epochs? We can scarcely believe there are people who do not use spatial metaphors in talking about time. (But there are; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>.) The oldest metaphor is that of the time-line. Semantics. Aframe is a pair ? = (X, R) consisting of a nonempty set and a binary relation on it. A valuation in X is a map V: {pi: i = 0, 1, 2, ... .} -power set (X). We extend V to a map, by abuse of language also called V, defined on all formulas, as follows: </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">V( -a) = X -VWcr, V(a t O = V<label>(</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Given a theory T. we define for maximal T-consistent sets: rppJ4-Va(GaeFr-aZsi).</head><p>A T-chronicle on a frame X = (X, R) is a function x assigning each x e X a maxi- mal T-consistent set in such a way that for all x, y e X: xRy - (x)pX(y).</p><p>x is prophetic (historic) if whenever some Fa (resp. Pa) belongs to some there is a y with xRy (resp. yRx) and a c x(y); x is perfect if both historic and pro- w PROOF OF THEOREM 1.2. The Rabin structure consists of the set Seq of finite sequences of natural numbers equipped with the 'initial segment' relation and the functions s -+ s * n ( = s with n at end), for n = 0, 1, 2, .... Monadic second order logic allows quantification not only over elements of the universe of discourse, but also over arbitrary subsets, though not over (polyadic) relations. M. 0. Rabin <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> has shown: The monadic second order theory of the Rabin structure is effectively decidable. Since a copy of the rationals in their usual order C = (Q, &lt;) can be coded up in the Rabin structure, the monadic second order theory of C is also decidable.</p><p>By a Ldwenheim-Skolem argument, any formula satisfiable in a linear order is satisfiable in a countable one, i.e. in a suborder of D. To every formula ca of tense logic we associate a formula ca* of the monadic second order language of linear orders. If ca contains variables po, ..., pI, a* will contain as free variables the first order variable u and the second order variables U, AO, ..., An: CLAIM. For any a and any valuation V in a dense linear order X = (X, R), if V(cx) # 0 and V(a*) -X, then V can be extended to a valuation V' on the completion of X with V'(a) # 0.</p><p>PROOF OF CLAIM. Let a, V, X satisfy the antecedent of the claim. Let x be the prefect chronicle on X, x(x) = {a: x e V(a)}. Extend x to a chronicle x' on the completion X' of X by setting X'(xy,z) = some r satisfying the consequent of (*) above. Let V' be the valuation of X', V'(pi) = {x E X': pi E x'(x)}. Using the fact that V(a*) = X, one can check inductively that for subformulas of a, V'(13) n x = V(1). Hence V'(a) # 0.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D</head><p>From the claim it readily follows that the indicated axioms are complete for Dedekind-continuous linear orders. Close examination of the proof shows that a formula satisfiable in any Dedekind-complete linear order without endpoints (e.g the Tychonoff plank or a Souslin line) is satisfiable in the reals S.</p><p>An order X = (X, R) is homogeneous if for every x, y E X there is an orderautomorphism of X carrying x to y. X is metrizable if there exists an operation + on X making it into an ordered Abelian group. Let L1, L2, L3, L4 be respectively the classes of (1) dense linear orders without endpoints, (2) discrete linear orders without endpoints, (3) homogeneous linear orders, (4) metrizable linear orders.</p><p>Plainly L4 c L3 c L1 U L2.</p><p>CLAIM. t9(L1) n t9(L2) = t9(L3) = t9(L4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PROOF OF CLAIM. If a is satisfiable in a linear order in L1, it is satisfiable in a countable such order, i.e. in an isomorph of the rationals C. But C E L4. If a is satisfiable in a member of L2, it must be consistent with the axioms (Al) -(A4), (A6), (A)8. A close examination of the completeness proof for discrete orders</head><p>shows that a formula consistent with these axioms is satisfiable in the order ? = (X, R), where X = {(q, n); q rational &amp; n an integer} ordered lexicographically, ie. (q, n)R(q', n') iff q &lt; q' or (q = q' and n &lt; n'). (The principle (*) above is useful in verifying this; we are suppressing many details here.) But this X is in L4. From these observations the claim is immediate. D From the claim it readily follows that the indicated axioms are complete for homogeneous, or equivalently for metrizable, orders. D</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PROOFS OF DECIDABILITY. Rabin's Theorem applies directly in all cases except</head><p>Dedekind-continuous and homogeneous (metrizable) orders. But these exceptional cases reduce to the other cases by the claims used in proving completeness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D No effort has been made to ascribe each particular result to its original author; references to original papers can be found e.g. in [16]. R. A. Bull's work on discrete and Dedekind-continuous orders [3] requires special mention since these cases are by far the most difficult.</head><p>(Let us remark that if we assume time is metrizable, we may wish to introduce explicitly variables x, y, z, ... for elements of the time-group, and symbols +, 0, &lt; for the group addition, identity, and order. We can then introduce opera- While the Kripke-Lemmon and Rabin-Gabbay methods apply to a wide range of natural assumptions about time, pathological cases do exist, e.g. an a with t9(,p(a)) # iz(a). Recently S. K. Thomason has perfected a general method for constructing pathologies: Consider a second order language with a denumerable infinity of nary predicates for each n. Thomason produces a single formula Z of tense logic (indeed, of future tense logic: z involves only G and not H) and an effective assignment of a formula (pO of (future) tense logic to each formula qp of our second order language with no free variables. He then shows that for any set 0 of such second order formulas, 0 has s standard model if and only if {z-} U {($: qP e 0} is simultaneously satisfiable in some frame. Thus the notorious bad behavior of second order logic infects tense logic, too. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> for details.</p><p>Though pathological examples generally have no intuitive interpretation, no connection with anyone's idea of the nature of time, Thomason has found one example which does. Let us form a theory T by adding to the axioms for, say, endless linear time, the axiom:</p><p>(A12) GFp --FGp. Then ,1(T) = 0, though no contradiction can be derived from T, and Teven has a reasonable interpretation: Its axioms are true in a universe in which the Second Law of Thermodynamics holds, if we restrict the variables pi to range only over statements about macroscopic events. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> for this example, and for information on completeness proofs via Boolean-algebraic semantics and decision procedures via 'finite model property' results, which we have neglected here in favor of Kripke-Lemmon relational semantics and Rabin-Gabbay decision procedures.</p><p>More variants: Logic and grammar. Proposals have been made for modifying the syntax of tense logic to bring it into closer connection with the actual workings of the tense-system of English verbs. Naturally one does not wish to imitate every feature of the sometimes chaotic surface idiom of English; rather one would like tense logic to reflect underlying deep structures which we can expect to be more regular, more nearly universal (common to many languages), more transparently related to semantic interpretation. As new work in linguistics is assimilated by logicians, more 'realistic' tense logics will doubtless be constructed.</p><p>H. Kamp has suggested (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>) introducing connectives S, U to represent 'since' and 'until' as in:</p><p>Ever since the roof caved in, it's been wet in the house. Until we get the roof fixed, it will be damp in the house. Formally, we consider valuations in structures (X, R, x*) consisting of a frame with designated element, and set: V(Ja) = X if x* E V(ca), 0 otherwise. Long ago Reichenbach <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> proposed evaluating tensed statements at a pair of instants ('time of utterance' and 'time of reference') as a way of bringing out the difference between the present perfect ('Socrates has run') and the preterite ('Socrates ran'). In <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> this idea is revived in connection with the distinction alleged to exist between: He said they would do it. He said they will do it.</p><p>Where the latter, unlike the former, is held to imply that the time of their doing it should be later than now and not just later than the time of his saying 'they'll do it'. A related proposal is to evaluate formulas over time-intervals, in order to reflect distinctions of aspect, as between the progressive 'Socrates was talking' and the ordinary 'Socrates spoke'.</p><p>Prior repeatedly urged ([19 Chapter, VIII], and throughout <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>) that tense logic should make allowance for statements which are neither true nor false. Specifically he held that a statement involving a proper name, e.g. 'Socrates is standing', cannot be 'statable' at times before the origin of the name's bearer, e.g. in Solon's day. In 3-valued tense logic one must distinguish 'will always be (statable and) true' from 'will never be (statable and) false'. Kripke-Lemmon and Rabin-Gabbay method apply to this variant of 'classical' tense logic, and to the other variants mentioned above.</p><p>Considerable work is now being done on systems of tense logic inspired by English grammar (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>), though there are critics who claim none of the systems developed so far is adequate from a linguistic point of view (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>). (Incidentally, the other papers in the volume containing <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> present a good sample of some current directions in tense logic.) ?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Indeterminism. Determinists affirm, and indeterminists deny, that the past already inevitably determines, by natural law and cause-and-effect, everything that is ever going to happen. Common forms of indeterminism are adherence to traditional doctrines of Free Will and belief that subatomic events occur unpredictably (except statistically) and at random. The concern of Aristotle and mediaeval writers with the logic of indeterminism is well known. (See [20, paper 3], for the latter.) Lewis Carroll, C. S. Peirce, J. Lukasiewicz among modern logicians opposed determinism. Prior's fullest account of indeterminist tense logic is in [19, Chapter</head><p>VII]; see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> for commentary. Among the sects of indeterminists distinguished by Prior, our concern here will be mainly with the group variously called 'Ockhamist', 'Rylean', 'Actualist'.</p><p>Indeterministis recognize one past but many equipossible futures: Time is a 'garden of forking paths' <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Ockhamists hold that in case p deals with future contingencies, 'Ep', 'it will be that p', has a truth-value true or false, though we cannot know but can only guess what that value is, until we see which of the many possible futures actually comes about. Ockhamists recognize a sense of 'necessary' as 'necessary given the past (and present)' or 'now unpreventable' on which the past is necessary (along with the present) but the future, in some of its apsects, is not. The truth-value of statements of form 'It necessarily will be that p', unlike plain 'will' statements, is independent of which possible future is the one that is eventually going to come to pass. All this leads to a system of Ockhamist indeterminist tense logic as outlined below. (See [19, Chapter VII], or <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> for more on the connection between intuition and formalism.) A tree is a frame X = (X, R) which is irreflexive, transitive, and such that the predecessors of any element are linearly ordered. For x e X, an x-branch is a maximal chain (linearly ordered subset) in {y: xRy}. For an x-branch B and y E B the restriction By is the y-branch {z e B: yRz}, while for yRx, the extension BY is the y-branch B U {x} U {z: yRz &amp; zRx}. B c X is a branch if it is an x-branch for some x; this x is then uniquely determined and may be denoted XB. Let 53(X) denote the set of all branches.</p><p>We picture time as a tree. If x represents the present, its predecessors represent the past, and the x-branches our possible futures. The truth-value of a future tense statement depends on which x-branch we think of as representing the course of events which is actually going to turn out to happen. <ref type="figure">, --, G, H,</ref> and<ref type="figure">C</ref> cx is satisfiable if V(ca) # 0 for some V, and valid if ac is not satisfiable. Given these definitions, the pure tense logic of Ockhamism (set of validities not involving the symbol [1) is iz(To), the logic of linear time as in ? 1 above. The pure modal logic (validities without G, H) is the Lewis system S5. The interest comes in the mixed formulas: e.g. PL~p --LIPp is valid, while FL~p --ELFp is not, as the reader will see who works through the definitions. Other examples are given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Syntax for Ockhamist logic takes -</head><p>Ockhamism, which we have just formalized, is not the only variety of indeterminism. The school called 'Peircean' or 'Antactualist' insists that 'it will be that p' can only mean 'it definitely will be that p', i.e. the Peircean 'will' is what we have symbolized by 'LIF' above. Peirceans regard the Ockhamist's 'it simply will be that It is notorious that certain logicians have thought that the tertium non datur must be given up on account of indeterminism. (This was the inspiration for the Lukasiewicz 3-and 4-valued logics; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.) And indeed if, like the Ockhamists and unlike the Peirceans, one takes 'it simply will be that p in the actual course of events' as meaningful, and if, like the Peirceans and unlike the Ockhamists, one insists that every meaningful statement must have a truth-value now which is independent of which possible future may in the end be actualized, then the only reasonable thing to say is that 'Fp' is true when every possible future contains a moment of p's truth, false when none does, and some third, middle, neuter truth-value otherwise. This kind of trivalent approach has been formalized by R. H. Thomason <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. We will not enter into details here, but note that though he abandons the metalogical principle of bivalence, Thomason does not give up the object-language principle p V -p. Indeed Thomason accepts all Ockhamist validities, and one must introduce a special symbol T of 'it is true that' to bring out the difference between his approach and Ockhamism. Thus the Ockhamist approach in some sense 'includes' the Peircean and Trivalent approaches; so let us turn to its formal study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>p (in whatever future happens to get actualized)', which we have symbolized by 'F', as unintelligible. Peirceans thus resemble intuitionists who in mathematics insist 'not p' must mean 'provably not p', who regard the classical 'it simply doesn't happen to be the case that p' as unintelligible (or at least not a mathematical assertion). Peirceans regard as meaningful only those formulas of the</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Axiomatizability. It is an open question whether Ockhamist logic is finitely axiomatizable (on the basis of the four rules cited above). It is recursively axiomatizable.</head><p>To see this, call a tree X = (X, R) metrically synchronizable if there exists an ordered Abelian group @3 = (G, +, &lt;) and a map j: X --G such that:</p><p>Vx, y E X (xRy -]j(x) &lt; j(y)), VB c X(B a max chain --j maps B onto G). We first note that every tree X = (X, R) can be extended to a metrically synchronizable one. Indeed, extend the partial order R to a linear order R' on X (possible by Zorn's Lemma), and extend the linear order X' = (X, R') to a metrizable one X+ = (X+, R+) (possible since for any infinite cardinal x the order on a ,-saturated ordered Abelian group is ,-saturated). One can readily (by 'pulling back') obtain a metrically synchronizable V = (X*, R*) and an embedding] making the following diagram commute, where i is the identity on X and h, k inclusions: One can readily verify that aP will be valid in a tree X if and only if a is valid in all subtrees of X. Now for metrically synchronizable trees, one can construct an explicitly metric tense logic, as in the last paragraph of ? 1, for which a reasonable set of axioms can be provided, whose completeness can be established by a Henkin argument.</p><p>Combining the observations of the last three paragraphs, one readily sees that the set of Ockhamist validities is recursively enumerable (RE); hence by a Craig argument it is recursively axiomatizable, as asserted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Decidability. It is open whether Ockhamist logic is decidable, though we have some partial results.</head><p>There exists a countable, saturated tree, and it is codable in the Rabin structure, so that sets of formulas of Ockhamist logic which are valid in countable trees is decidable. Unfortunately there exist formulas (and even Peircean formulas) which are valid in countable models but not in all models. Here is one such (see <ref type="bibr">[</ref> By a bundle on a tree X we mean a subset (S of 53(X) containing at least one xbranch for each x and closed under restriction and extension. Pseudo-satisfaction with respect to a bundle (S is defined like ordinary satisfaction (see above), but with (S in place of Q(32). a is strongly valid if its negation is not even psuedo-satisfiable. A Lowenheim-Skolem argument shows that any pseudo-satisfiable formula is pseudo-satisfiable in a countable tree and with respect to a countable bundle on that tree. This fact makes it possible to apply Rabin's Theorem to conclude that the set of strongly valid formulas is decidable. Unfortunately, there exist valid formulas which are not strongly valid. E.g. (see [4, Example B]): FDGoFrjp -+ &lt;GFp.</p><p>We show by a lengthy argument in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> that any Peircean formula which is pseudosatisfiable is satisfiable simpliciter; hence the set of valid Peircean formulas is decidable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H. Kamp (unpublished) has recently discovered a finite axiomatization of the set of formulas which are strongly valid on the assumption that time is dense. It is strange that density should be required for the proof of completeness for these axioms; but it is, and the finite axiomatizability of the class of strong validities (without topological assumptions about time) remains at this writing an open question.</head><p>It is clear from this short account (and we have not touched on every topic; e.g. there is interesting unpublished work of R. Jeffrey on indeterminism and tenseless but dated statements) that much work remains to be done in indeterminist tense logic. ?4. Relativity. Among the common sense (mis)conceptions upset by Einstein are some so basic as to seem almost 'analytic', built into the English language (if not the Hopi; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>). Not merely the truth of things always taken for granted, but even the meaning of ordinary ways of speaking is called into question. What can 'will' mean when what is future from one point of view can be past from an-other? The logic of tensed discourse must, it seems, be revised in the light of modern physics.</p><p>To begin with the special theory, for present purposes the Minkowski frame 9) will consist of the set M of quadruples of real numbers, equipped with the partial order: (x0, Yo, Zop to) AM (xl, Y1, Z1, tO) (x1 -xo)2 + (Yiyo)2 + (z1 -zO)2 &lt; (t1to)2 &amp; to &lt; t1.</p><p>Let V be frame consisting of the set W of point-events of spacetime and the causal earlier-later relation &lt; w, which holds between two positions u, v in W if a signal (material or electromagnetic) could be sentfrom u to v. The special theory of relativity tells us that V -_W.</p><p>Relativity teaches us to treat time and space evenhandedly. Thus relativistic tense logic must take its variables pi as ranging over statements, e.g. 'it is raining', whose truth-value can vary with place, as well as time, of utterance. Let us give 'will' a causal interpretation, so Fp is true at a position u E W if and only if there is some position v with u &lt; w v and p true at v. Then causal special relativistic tense logic turns out to be simply the set of all a valid in the frame W.</p><p>One readily verifies that the axioms (A1)-(A3) of ?1 hold for this logic. Prior [19, Appendix B5], argues that (All) is also valid, i.e. the Minkowski frame is convergent. And indeed if V(x4 + y4 + z2) + ti &lt; t for i = 0, 1, then indeed (xi, yi, zi, ti) &lt; M (0, 0, 0, t). Physically, in the special theory, any two forward light cones eventually overlap. Now axioms (A1)-(A3), (Al 1) are complete for transitive, convergent frames; it would be premature, however, to claim them complete for special relativity. Indeed, they take no account of the denseness and continuity of Minkowski space; moreover it is by no means clear that any formula satisfiable in some such frame is satisfiable even in a subframe of 91. The complete axiomatization of causal special relativistic logic remains an open problem. For a recent advance, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>The causal interpretation of 'will' is not the only one possible in special relativity. On the special theory, each suitably moving (inertial) observer has a (global) frame of reference in which any two positions u, v are labelled either 'u earlier than v' or 'a, v simultaneous' or 'u later than v'. Moreover, u is causally, or absolutely, earlier than v if and only if it is earlier than v from every inertial oserver's point of view. Thus the causal reading of 'Fp is true at u' amounts to: It should be noted that individual members of E can be quite pathological. Gddel's famous 'rotating universe' <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, is a solution to the field equations in which every position in spacetime is causally accessible from every other: You can get from one to the other 'by a round-trip on a rocket ship'. The tense logic of this particular relativistic model is simply the trivial logic of circular time discussed at the beginning of ?2 above. The real world seems to be quite different from Godel's universe. The endless expansion of the universe, the growth of entropy, the dissipation of starlight, the asymmetric pattern of decay of K-mesons, seem to establish a fundamental distinction between two directions in time, making the causal earlierlater relation asymmetric.</p><p>Causal time is not the only time in our universe. The Cosmological Principle asserts that the largest-scale features of the universe are uniform in all directions. Because of this isotropy, there is at any position in spacetime a preferred frame of reference, in which the recession of the most distant galaxies due to the expansion of the universe proceeds at the same pace in all directions. This is called the comoving frame, since it moves along with the 'mean motion of matter'. Moreover these frames, taken at different spacetime positions, fit together coherently, to give us a linear time, called cosmic time, of objective physical significance. However the physical facts about the universe which make it possible to introduce this notion of time do not follow from general relativity theory per se. Indeed, in G6del's model no such time can be defined.</p><p>Einstein leaves us with (at least) two kinds of time: causal time and cosmic time. Godel, however, shows that the facts (i) that the former does not degenerate and trivialize, and (ii) that the latter can be introduced at all, are not guaranteed by the general theory of relativity itself, though they do follow from other observed regularities: Cosmological Principle, Second Law of Thermodynamics, &amp; c. Now many might characterize these latter physical generalizations as more 'fact-like' than 'law-like', mere 'particular facts about the distribution of matter and motion' in the universe. <ref type="bibr">Godel</ref>  Syntax. We consider a quantification theory with predicates but no constants or operation symbols. We fix a designated singularly predicate E for 'exists' or 'is now (still, already) extant'. We take -, -+, V, G, H as primitive.</p><p>Semantics. We consider structures of form (X, R, U, I) where (X, R) is a frame, U a nonempty set, and I a function assigning to each n-ary predicate A and each x E X a subset Ax of Un; and where U = UXUxEx. Given a structure W of this sort, we define what it means for a formula qo(v1, ..., v") to be satisfied in W at x E X when the variables displayed are taken to stand for elements a,, ..., ane U, as follows: This formalism can be criticized on several grounds (and has been, though no effort will be made here to trace each criticism to its sources). It is too generous, some say, in that it allows that an individual a might exist at one time x (i.e. a E Ex), cease to exist by a later time y, and be 'resurrected' as it were at a still later time z; whereas, it is often held, some sort of continuity is essential to identity over time (survival through changes).</p><p>Our formalism is too generous (for some tastes) in another way, for it allows nonexistents to have properties and to stand in relations with each other and with existents (e.g. we may have a E Ax though a ? Ex). Now in ordinary language we do say that Kafka is famous, though he is no longer alive (and was not very famous during his lifetime), and we do say Queen Elizabeth stands in the relation 'descendant of' to William the Conqueror, though he is no longer with us. On the other hand, it would be odd to say either that Bertrand Russell is bald, or that he is not bald, and it would be even odder to ask what truth-value 'Russell is bald' had in Queen Anne's day. To the extent that our formalism supposes all such 'truth-value gaps' are filled in, it departs from common usage.</p><p>The formalism is also generous enough to permit some coding operations by which we can adapt a method used by Kripke for intuitionistic logic (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>) to show that the monadic tensed predicate calculus is undecidable; this remains true even if we restrict ourselves to linear time. Indeed, if we assume time is ordered like the reals, then Scott (unpublished) has shown that the set of validities of monadic tensed predicate calculus is not even arithmetical.</p><p>On the other hand, our formalism is too stingy in that it permits no comparisons between different stages of the same entity. E.g. 'I am fatter than I once was' cannot be symbolized.</p><p>The formalism is too stingy in another way. It provides no means for expressing collective statements to the effect that all members of some class, which class is specified by means of some condition its members currently satisfy, at some earlier (or later) time simulatenously satisfied (will satisfy) some other condition. Consider: Each of the current rulers of X has been (at some point in his career) a homeless exile. Once all the current rulers of X were simultaneously in exile.</p><p>The former might by symbolized by something like Vx(Rx -* P(Hx)), but the latter cannot be represented in our symbolism at all. K. Fine (unpublished) shows Craig's Interpolation Theorem fails for quantified tense logic as we have formalized it, and still fails if we restrict the formalism in various ways (by requiring (X, R) to be a linear order, by requiring that Ex = U for all x, &amp; c). Without entering into details, we remark that the stinginess of the formalism just complained of is at the root of Fine's proof.</p><p>Adjustments in the formalism of one sort or another might satisfy some critics, but there is no way to satisfy them all at once, and the disappointing metatheorems </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>We introduce a formal system to show what arguments are valid, what logical laws hold, if time is linear. Syntax. We use variables po, Pl, P2, ... and primitive connectives G, G, and H, treating &amp;, v, *-+, F, and P as abbreviations. We let a, j, ... range over (well- formed) formulas, defined as usual. All axiomatic systems we consider will have all truth-functional tautologies as axioms, and all will have the same three rules of inference: Substitution, Modus Ponens, and Temporal Generalization. This last allows us to infer Ga and Ha from a. For T a theory (= set of formulas) we write T F-a to indicate that a follows by these three rules when in addition to the tautologies the formulas in T are taken as axioms. z(T) = fa: T F-a}. A set r of formulas is T-consistent if for no conjunction r of members of r is r E C(T). By a Lindenbaum argument, any T-consistent set can be extended to a maximal T-consistent set. Henceforth in any context where a fixed T is in question, r, z, el ... will range over maximal T-consistent sets.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>a) U V(:), V(Ga) = {x e X: Vy e X(xRy y e V(a)}, V(Ha) = {x e X: Vy e X(yRx y e V(a)}. a is satisfiable in X if V(a) + 0 for some valuation V, and valid in X, in symbols X a= ,t if V(a) = X for all valuations V. If K is a class of frames, set @9(K) = {a: 1X e K X I= a}. If T is a theory, set ,(T) = {X: Va e TX l= a}. each pair (b) is the mirror image of (a), the result of switching G and H. (In place of (A4) we could use: (PFp V FPp) -+ (Pp Vp VFp); see [19, Appendix B6].) Let Lo be the class of all linear orders, so t9(LO) represents the logic of linear time. 1.1. THEOREM (FINITE AXIOMATIZABILITY). t9(LO) = 7(TO). 1.2. THEOREM (DECIDABILITY). t9(LO) is effectively decidable. PROOF OF THEOREM 1.1. A straightforward induction on proofs shows Z(TO) c t9(Lo). A method due to S. A. Kripke and E. J. Lemmon establishes the opposite inclusion.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>phetic. A chronicle x gives rise to a valuation V(pi) = {x: pi e x(x)}. If x is perfect, inductively we see that for any a, V(a) = {x: a e x(x)}.Applying this to T To, to prove Theorem 1.1 it will suffice to construct, given any ca with -a c z(To), a perfect chronicle x on a linear order X with ca E x(x) for some x. The construction requires some lemmas, which are easily obtained once one has derived a few consequences (e.g (Gp &amp; Fq) -+ F(p &amp; q)) from To:(pi)rFpz*-+ va(HaEeJ i -c EF-) va(aE e r -+ pa E z) +-+ vc(cx i -+ Fa e r); the required X and x, we start with a one-point X0 = (txo}, RO) and the TO-chronicle Xo(xo) = some r with ca E r. Having a finite linear order ?4 = (X", R.) and TO-chronicle Xn, given any Fj3 (or Pa) in x(x) for any x e X",, (p2) gives us a zi with %n(x)pJ (resp. Jlpv,(x)) and j3 E zi. (p3) and (p4) allow us to form another order 3En1+ and chronicle Xn1+ extending an, Xnn by inserting a point y somewhere before (resp. after) x, and setting xn+?(y) = z. By a suitable diagonalization, we can get the X, x we need in countably many steps.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>say about the topology of the time-line? Direct observation tells us nothing of time's fine structure, since there is a lower threshold, the duration of the 'specious present', below which the passage of time is not noticeable. Current theory (mathemtical formulations of physics) seems to assume a correspondence of instants of time with real numbers, and hence a time which is continuous in the sense of Dedekind. But actually one could work as well with the hyperreals of A. Robinson's nonstandard analysis, which though densely ordered are not Dedekind-continuous. And already the hypothesis of a discrete time (and space) has been invoked in some attempts to explain the failure to detect free quarks! The question of time's local structure is as old as Zeno, but still unsettled. Tense logicians have surveyed all the alternatives.Their results are tabulated below. For each class L of linear orders listed on the left below, @9(L) is decidable; moreover the axioms listed on the right, when added to To, give a theory T complete for L, i.e. A9(L) = 7r(used in Theorem 1.1 can be modified to produce a linear order X with endpoints, or without endpoints, or dense, or discrete, as required. For details, see the survey<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.Before turning to Dedekind-continuity and homogeneity, let us note that for any T -To, any linear order X = (X, R), any T-chronicle x on X we have: To verify this it is enough to show {Pa: 3y e Y a e x(y)} U {Fa: 3z e Za e x(z)} is T-consistent. But every finite subset holds in some Z(y), y e Y.) Now for any a, let a* be the conduction of all formulas resulting from (A9)(a) or (b) by substituting for the variable p a subformula of a. A gap in a dense linear order X = (X, R) is a pair Y, Z satisfying the antecedent of (*) above. The completion of X is the Dedekind-continuous order ' = (X', R') obtained by adding to X an element xy,z between Y and Z for every gap Y, Z.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>tors 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>and gP joining group elements with formulas, e.g. 59:(x + y) (p &amp; q) meaning 'it will be the case x + y time-units hence that p &amp; q'. Plain Fp will then be definable as 3x &gt; 0 $Fxp and similarly for P. This metric tense logic, as it is called, has been extensively investigated. (See [19, Chapter VI].) It is not hard to write down axioms whose completeness can be proved by a Henkin-style argument; but decidability is lost.) ?2. Variants: Nonlinear time. The oldest alternative to the picture of time as a line is the picture of time as a circle. This leads to a trivial tense logic, with Gp +-+ Hp, Gp -) p. Ways to detrivialize circular time, including the interesting 'East-West' logic of C. L. Hamblin, can be found in [19, ?4.1]. For each class L of frames listed on the left below, @9(L) is decidable, and the axioms on the right give a theory T complete for L. (X, R) is forward convergent if: Vw e XVx, y e X(wRx &amp; wRy -) 3z e X(xRz &amp; yRz)) and backward convergence is similarly defined. Prior, [19, ?1.4], says 'some theologians and some Marxists' view time as (transitive and) forward convergent, but nonlinear. Other temporal interpretations of the classes of frames listed above will appear below. PROOFS OF COMPLETENESS. Standard Kripke-Lemmon methods apply. PROOFS OF DECIDABILITY. D. M. Gabbay [10] has shown how to use Rabin's theorem in nonlinear time. Let Y be the set of elements of Seq of form (a0, bo, a,, b1, ..., an, bn) with each ai either 0 or 1 (but bi unrestricted). Let S be the following relation on Y, S+ its transitivization: sSt n-+ 3n(s = t * 1 * n V t = s * 0 * n). The frames S = (Y, S), A+ = (Y, S+) are definable in the Rabin structure. A close examination of the completeness proofs shows that any formula consistent with (Al), (A2) (resp. with (A1)-(A3)) is satisfiable in D) (resp A+). From this observation decidability for arbitrary (resp. transitive) frames follows. Convergence requires more work. Taking the 'forward' case, for any a, let a* be the conjunction of all formulas that result from A 1I (a) by substituting for the variable p a Boolean combination of subformulas of a in full conjunctive normal form. (We insist on a normal form simply so that there will be only finitely many formulas to consider.) CLAIM. For any a and any valuation V in A, if V(a) # 0 and V(a*) = Y, then there is a valuation V' on a forward convergent frame J'f with V'(a) ? 0. PROOF OF CLAIM. Define a new relation S' on Y by: sS't 1,+ V1(j subformula of a &amp; s e V(G13) --t e V(13)). Using the fact that V(a*) = Y, one can check that A' = (Y, S') is a forward convergent frame. Let V' be the valuation in A' assigning each pi the same subset of Y as V did. One can check that for every subformula of a, V'(13) = V(13). In particular V'(a) # 0. L From the claim the completeness of the indicated axioms for convergence follows readily. Gabbay has formulated this method of proof very generally. C]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Formally, we</head><label></label><figDesc>set, in the definition of satisfaction: V(aSj3) = {x: 3y(yRx &amp; y E V(a) &amp; Vz(yRz &amp; zRx --z E V(13))) and treat U dually. Thus Gp amounts to , ( pU(p Vp)). It can be shown that for any elementary class (EC) of linear orders, there is an a in S, U-logic with A9(L) -iC(To U {al}).It has been suggested (see [19, ?4.3]) to introduce in discrete linear time operators T, Y for 'it is just about to be the case that' ('it will at the very next moment be the case that') and 'it has just been the case that' ('was at the very last moment'). (The letters T, Y suggest 'tomorrow' and 'yesterday'.)It has been suggested (e.g. in<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>) to introduce an operator J for 'now' as in: She said they'd be here by now.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>] (for 'necessary (given the past and present)') as primitive, with &amp;, v, 4-, F, P, ando (for -L1 ~-) defined. In constructing formal systems we take as rules besides the three usual ones for tense logic (Sub, MP, Temp Gen), Gddel's Neccessitation Rule (to infer [. Note choice of a B e 53(X) amounts to chosing XB to represent the present and B to represent the future that will become actual. V is extended to all formulas as follows: ) = {B e 53(X): VB e 30() (XB' = XB --B' e V(a))}.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Ockhamist logic sketched above which, when written in primitive notation, have every G preceded by a C] or L1 ~-; these we may call Peircean formulas. See [19, Chapter VII], or [4] for background.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>h</head><label></label><figDesc>If a is a formula of Ockhamist logic, and p a variable not in a, we inductively define the relativization 13P top of a subformula fi of a as follows:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>4, Example D], for details): -[ c Fp &amp; DF-p &amp; DG(p --Hp) &amp; DG(p --ocGq &amp; ocGq)].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>3</head><label></label><figDesc>point-event v(p true at v &amp; V inertial observer O(u earlier v for D)).Suppose we try instead what might be called an 'intersubjective' rather than 'objective', causal, reading: V inertial observer ?] point-event v(p true v &amp; u earlier v for D).This should give rise to a wholly different scheme of tense logic; but details have not been worked out yet.The general theory of relativity does not present us with any one mathematical model of V = (W. &lt;w). Rather, Einstein's field equations determine a whole class E of frames some of which are better models than others. (Adding boundary conditions to the equations narrows down the class of solutions.) By causal general relativistic tense logic we mean what in the notation of ? 1 would be called A9(E),the set of a valid in all frames consistent with the field equations. To those familiar with the general theory, it is plain that (Al)-(A3) still hold. Prior (loc. cit.) argues that (Al 1) is lost. On the general theory two light cones 'may so twist away from one another that ... they never intersect'. Cocchiarella<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, calls (Al)-(A3) postulates for 'relativistic causal time', though they could hardly be claimed to be complete.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>interprets his own work as showing no ultimate, metaphysical reality can be claimed for time: Thus he arrives, by more cogent arguments, at the same conclusion as McTaggart. Our account has grossly oversimplified the physics and philosophy of relativistic time. We refer the reader to [7] (esp. Introduction, and Chapters 1 and 7) and to [24] (esp. Chapters IV and V). One issue we have overlooked is the alleged incompatibility between the relativistic viewpoint and indeterminism. (For this see [21].) ?5. Quantification. A number of topics in propositional tense logic have not been discussed, e.g. Diodorean modal logics [19, Chapter II] and the search for general completeness theorems (e.g. a broad syntactically-characterized class of xx for which 9(p(at))7= r(Cta)), but let us now say a few words about quantification theory. We sketch one formalism here.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>W k-x A(vj1, ..., vir)[ai, ..., a.] (ai1, ., ai) e Ax, A an r-ary predicate. W k=,, .-(v1, ..., v.)[al, ..., an] not 2( x ( (v1, ..., V.)[al, ..., an], and handled similarly 2f l G(p(v1, ...I vn)aj, ..., an] Vy(xRy -W k= p(v1, ..., v.)([al, ...</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(undecidability of monadic predicate calculus and failure of interpolation) survive many minor adjustments. Philosophical problems of time and existence relevant to projects for constructing a quantified tense logic are surveyed by Prior in [19, Chapter VIII]; special difficulties of quantified indeterminist logic are treated in [4, ?2]. Quantification theory remains the least developed part of tense logic.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This content downloaded on Fri, 28 Dec 2012 06:47:06 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Association for Symbolic Logic Stable URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/2273296 . Accessed: 28/12/2012 06:47 Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at . http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp .</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Borges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The garden offorking paths</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yates</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Labyrinths</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">(</forename><surname>Yates</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Irby</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>New Directions</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The theologians</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Irby</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Labyrinth</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">(</forename><surname>Yates</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Irby</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>New Directions</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An algebraic study of tense logic with linear time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bull</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOURNAL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The unrealfuture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theoria</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decidability for branching time</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Studia Logica</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tense and modal logic, doctoral dissertation, U. C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cocchiarella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
			<pubPlace>L. A.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The physics of time asymmetry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C W</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berkeley and Los Angeles</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dummett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Elements of intuitionism</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model theory for tense logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gabbay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Mathematical Logic</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decidability results in non-classical logics</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Mathematical Logic</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tense systems with split truth table</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Logique et Annalyse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An example of a new type of cosmological solution of Einstein&apos;s field equation of gravitation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Godel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Modern Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="447" to="450" />
			<date type="published" when="1949">1949</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A remark about the relationship between relativity theory and idealistic philosophy</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schilpp</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Harper</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="555" to="562" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diodorean modality in Minkowski spacetime</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Goldblatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Studia Logica</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On determinism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lukasiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>L. Borkowski</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
			<pubPlace>North-Holland, Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Selected works</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mcarthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Tense logic, Reidel</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The unreality of time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M E</forename><surname>Mctaggart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mind</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">187</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="474" />
			<date type="published" when="1908">1908</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Prior</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Time and modality</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Past, present and future</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Papers on time and tense</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time and physical geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Putnam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Philosophy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">0</forename><surname>Rabin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Decidability of second order theories and automata on infinite trees</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Mathematical Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="35" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Transactions of the</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Elements of symbolic logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Reichenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1947">1947</date>
			<publisher>McMillan</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sklar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Space</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Spacetime</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berkeley and Los Angeles</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Thomason</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Indeterminist time and truth-value gaps</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="264" to="280" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semantic analysis of tense logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Thomason</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOURNAL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reduction of tense logic to modal logic</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theoria</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reduction of second order logic to modal logic</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Zeitschrift far Mathematische Logik und Grundlagen der Mathematik</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tense logic as a system of logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F A K</forename><surname>Van Benthem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Tubingen Conference on Formal Semantics</title>
		<meeting>the Tubingen Conference on Formal Semantics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977-12">December 1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tense logic and standard logic</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Logique et Analyse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Whorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I T</forename><surname>Language</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Press</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">8540</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge; PRINCETON UNIVERSITY PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
