<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear Control of Mechanical Systems With an Unactuated Cyclic Variable</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grizzle</surname></persName>
							<email>grizzle@umich.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Control Systems Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48109-2122</postCode>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR CNRS 6597</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">IRCCyN</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Ecole Centrale de Nantes</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>44321</postCode>
									<settlement>Nantes cedex 03</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Senior Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Claude</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moog</surname></persName>
							<email>claude.moog@irccyn.ec-nantes.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Control Systems Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48109-2122</postCode>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christine</forename><surname>Chevallereau</surname></persName>
							<email>christine.chevallereau@irccyn.ec-nantes.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Control Systems Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48109-2122</postCode>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear Control of Mechanical Systems With an Unactuated Cyclic Variable</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1FCD9C82C30A4FB35635235C1E27775D</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TAC.2005.847057</idno>
					<note type="submission">received November 12, 2003; revised September 1, 2004 and December 18, 2004.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T10:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Asymptotic stability</term>
					<term>feedforward systems</term>
					<term>mechanical systems</term>
					<term>nonlinear control</term>
					<term>robots</term>
					<term>underactuation</term>
					<term>zero dynamics</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Numerous robotic tasks associated with underactuation have been studied in the literature. For a large number of these in the plane, the mechanical models have a cyclic variable, the cyclic variable is unactuated, and all shape variables are independently actuated. This paper formulates and solves two control problems for this class of models. If the generalized momentum conjugate to the cyclic variable is not conserved, conditions are found for the existence of a set of outputs that yields a system with a one-dimensional exponentially stable zero dynamics-i.e., an exponentially minimum-phase system-along with a dynamic extension that renders the system locally input-output decouplable. If the generalized momentum conjugate to the cyclic variable is conserved, a reduced system is constructed and conditions are found for the existence of a set of outputs that yields an empty zero dynamics, along with a dynamic extension that renders the system feedback linearizable. A common element in these two feedback problems is the construction of a scalar function of the configuration variables that has relative degree three with respect to one of the input components. The function arises by partially integrating the conjugate momentum. The results are illustrated on two balancing tasks and on a ballistic flip motion.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>battement) without falling over (i.e., with internally bounded states).</p><p>Motions that include a ballistic phase are also often viewed as dexterous. Examples include dismounting from a high bar or platform diving. In these cases, the underactuation is manifest in the lack of contact with any surface. The ballistic phase is normally of short duration since reestablishing contact with a surface (e.g., ground, mat, water,</p><p>) is an objective of the maneuver. A typical control problem would be to execute a predefined motion, with emphasis on achieving a final state that is compatible with an elegant landing on a mat (no rebounding or slipping), or re-entry into the water (no splash). Similar things can be said for back flips, tumbling, and somersaults.</p><p>The objective of this paper is to contribute to the control of mechanical systems that are capable of executing such dexterous maneuvers in the plane. The literature on underactuated (a.k.a., super-articulated <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>) systems and nonholonomic systems is vast. A few representative control works include the study of accessibility in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>, stabilization of equilibria through passivity techniques in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> and energy shaping in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, stabilization and tracking via backstepping in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>, the use of virtual constraints to achieve stabilization of orbits in <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>, and path planning in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Representative works in the robotics area are cited in Section II. One of the novelties of the present paper is to recognize that balancing on a pivot while executing a motion and planning a back flip share a common mathematical problem: Designing a set of outputs that results in a minimal zero dynamics: Exponentially minimum phase and one dimensional in the first case, and empty, in the second. In part, this is of course related to the maximal feedback linearization problem, which has been solved completely when static state feedback is considered <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, while only partial results are known when dynamic state feedback is allowed, c.f. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> and references therein. The additional requirement being achieved here is that the "nonfeedback linearizable part" of the system is exponentially stable, and no general results are available on this aspect.</p><p>Section II identifies a special class of mechanical systems with one degree of underactuation that underlies the study of dexterous maneuvers in the plane as discussed previously. The key feature is that the systems possess a cyclic variable and this variable is unactuated <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. Section III formulates and solves two related control problems. If the generalized momentum conjugate to the cyclic variable is not conserved, conditions are found for the existence of a set of outputs that yields an exponentially minimum phase system with a one-dimensional zero dynamics, along with a dynamic extension that renders the system locally input-output decouplable. When these two properties are met, it is well known that asymptotic tracking of an open Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Planar tree structure attached to an inertial frame via a freely acting pivot. All joints are actuated except the attachment at the pivot. A coordinate convention is indicated. Though not shown, prismatic joints and springs can also be included. set of output trajectories is possible, with all internal states remaining bounded <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. If the generalized momentum conjugate to the cyclic variable is conserved, a reduced system is constructed and conditions are found for the existence of a set of outputs that yields an empty zero dynamics, along with a dynamic extension that renders the system input-output decouplable. When these two properties are met, is well known that local dynamic state feedback linearization is possible <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. In both of these feedback problems, the principal contribution is the construction of a scalar function of the configuration variables that has relative degree three with respect to one of the input components <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. The theoretical results are illustrated on three simple examples in Section IV. This paper is wrapped up with some additional discussion of the results in Section V and concluding remarks in Section VI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. MOTIVATING CLASSES OF SYSTEMS</head><p>This section uses two classes of systems to set the stage for the mathematical and control developments that follow. The first class consists of planar rigid bodies connected in a tree structure-no closed kinematic chains-with the base attached to an inertial reference frame via a pivot, that is, an unactuated revolute joint. It is supposed that each link has nonzero mass, and that each connection of two links is independently actuated so that the system has one degree of underactuation ( degrees of freedom with independent actuators). It is further supposed that all joints are frictionless, but this assumption is really only important at the pivot. Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows an example of such a system. Though not indicated in the figure, massless springs may be attached between links and between links and the inertial reference frame; prismatic joints between links are also allowed. This class of systems clearly includes the Acrobot <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>, the brachiating robots of <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>, the gymnast robots of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref> when pivoting on a high Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Planar tree stucture in ballistic motion. All joints are actuated. A coordinate convention is indicated. Though not shown, prismatic joints can be included as can springs that act between links but not between a link and the inertial frame. bar, and the stance phase models of Raibert's one-legged hopper <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, as well as RABBIT <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. The control objectives will be to stabilize the system about an equilibrium point or to track a set of reference trajectories with internal stability. The second class of systems consists of planar rigid bodies, once again connected in a tree structure, but this time, it is assumed that the mechanism is undergoing ballistic motion. As before, it is supposed that that each link has nonzero mass and each connection of two links is independently actuated. In addition, it is assumed that there are no springs between any link and an inertial reference frame. Such a system has three degrees of underactuation: degrees of freedom and independent actuators. Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows an example of such a system. This class of systems clearly includes the gymnast robot of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> when dismounting from the high bar, the planar diver of <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, the flip gait of the robot in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, the ballistic phase of the four-link planar robot in <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>, and the ballistic phase of running in planar biped robots <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> and Raibert's hopper <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. The control objective will be to maximally linearize the system so as to facilitate the construction of a trajectory that transfers the state of the system from one point to another in finite time.</p><p>Consider the -link system shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>, along with the indicated coordinates,</p><p>, where, for convenience, the reference frame has been attached at the pivot point. The kinetic energy is quadratic, , with positive definite. Since the kinetic energy is independent of the orientation of the reference frame, is independent of ; that is . The coordinate is said to be cyclic <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> (a.k.a., external in <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>) whereas are called shape variables. The form of the potential energy depends on whether the system is evolving under the action of gravity (for example, in a vertical plane versus a horizontal plane) and whether or not springs have been attached at the joints. Electromagnetic and electrostatic forces are excluded, and hence, the potential energy depends only on the configuration variables. Mechanical systems where the kinetic energy is quadratic in the velocities and the potential energy depends only on the configuration variables are said to be simple.</p><p>Denote the Lagrangian by , and assume that the system is actuated such that where . Consider next the -link system shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, along with the indicated coordinates,</p><p>, where are the Cartesian coordinates of the center of mass. Suppose further that there are no springs between a link and an inertial reference frame. Then, the equations of motion decompose as <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref> where in a vertical plane is the gravitational constant and if the system is evolving on a horizontal plane without friction, then . As in the first class of systems considered, is also a cyclic variable of because the kinetic energy is independent of the chosen orientation of the inertial reference frame.</p><p>The important point is that the dynamics of the body coordinates, , and the Cartesian coordinates of the center of mass, , are decoupled. Since the center of mass coordinates are unactuated, the control of the system (3) can be reduced to the control of a system having one degree of underactuation as in (2) by eliminating the trivial dynamics , . In this sense, the two systems in Figs. <ref type="figure">1</ref> and<ref type="figure">2</ref> are very similar: They give rise to control problems for systems with DOF, actuators, and the cyclic coordinate is unactuated. One way in which the systems are often different is that angular momentum about the center of mass of (3) is always conserved, whereas (2) may or may not have a conserved quantity depending on the potential energy. For example, consider a system as in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> in a horizontal plane without friction; suppose furthermore there are no springs between any link and the inertial reference frame. Then, the angular momentum about the pivot point is a conserved quantity, and thus this feature-conservation of angular momentum-is possible in (2) as well. Conservation of angular momentum gives rise to a nonholonomic constraint <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and changes fundamentally the nature of the control problem.</p><p>In summary, the models of the simple mechanical systems represented by Figs. <ref type="figure">1</ref> and<ref type="figure">2</ref> present the common feature of an unactuated, cyclic variable. System (2) has one degree of underactuation whereas even though system (3) has three degrees of underactuation, in the proper coordinates, the control problem decouples into the control of a system of the form (2) plus keeping track of the evolution of the center of mass variables. These observations are used in the next section to motivate the class of models analyzed. As a final remark, it is worth noting that <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> has shown quite clearly that even for systems with two degrees of freedom, if the cyclic coordinate and the unactuated coordinate do not coincide-such as in the inverted pendulum on a cart-then the system possesses quite different properties from a control point of view.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. CONTROL OF SIMPLE MECHANICAL SYSTEMS WITH AN UNACTUATED CYCLIC VARIABLE</head><p>Consider the classes of mechanical systems motivated in Section II. Roughly speaking, the goal is to determine a set of outputs that gives rise to a zero dynamics of "smallest possible" dimension, and if this dimension is nonzero, also to assure that the zero dynamics is stable <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. More precisely, in the case of a system where the generalized momentum conjugate to the cyclic variable is not conserved, a set of outputs will be found that leads to local dynamic input-output decouplability and a one-dimensional exponentially stable zero dynamics, and for systems where the conjugate momentum is conserved, a set of flat outputs <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> will be determined; that is, a set of outputs will be found that leads to the construction of a regular dynamic feedback and a local change of coordinates in which the system is linear.</p><p>Before proceeding, it is worth noting that if outputs are chosen to correspond to the actuated variables, that is, , for , then each component has relative degree two and the associated decoupling matrix is invertible (one says the system has vector relative degree (2, ,2) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>). Such a choice leads to a two-dimensional zero dynamics, which, moreover, can be shown to be once again a Lagrangian system <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref> and, thus, can never have an asymptotically stable equilibrium. One way to get around this problem is to construct a set of outputs such that the associated zero dynamics has dimension one and, hence, is not Lagrangian. For special cases, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> shows how to construct an output component that has relative degree three with respect to one of the input components. This idea is developed in much more generality here.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Partial Integration of a One-Form</head><p>This subsection presents a key result that will lead to the construction of outputs for the system (2) so that the associated zero dynamics has dimension one and, hence, may admit an asymptotically stable equilibrium point. As will be seen in the next subsection, the abstract one-form considered here naturally arises from consideration of momentum. The result formalizes and extends previous work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>.</p><p>The following lemma can be viewed as a special case of the Pfaff-Darboux Theorem, whose role in control systems theory was first highlighted in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. As a point of notation, given a collection of smooth real-valued functions defined on some open set , denotes the corresponding codistribution as defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>; that is, the span is computed point-wise over . Lemma 1: Consider a smooth -dimensional manifold . Let be a smooth one-form on and suppose there is a set of coordinates defined in an open neighborhood of a point in which has the form (4) Then, for any , there exists a smooth function such that at each point of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> Moreover, in the coordinates , one such function is (6) Proof: Because is smooth, the functions are smooth on . The integral in ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) is well-defined at each point in because the integrand is smooth and the integral is evaluated over a closed and bounded interval. Since it follows immediately that, at each point in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> Remark 1: The -tuple is a valid set of coordinates on . Indeed Said another way, the map that takes to is a diffeomorphism. Note that if is all of , then the result of Lemma 1 is global.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Model Class and a Normal Form</head><p>Consider a simple 1  DOF Lagrangian system with independent actuators, where the unactuated variable is a cyclic coordinate of the kinetic energy. Specifically, let the configuration space be , an open connected subset of , with local coordinates denoted by , and take canonical coordinates on . Let the kinetic energy be given by , where is positive definite and 1 Recall that simple means that the kinetic energy is quadratic in the velocities and the potential energy depends only on the configuration variables. smooth everywhere on , and satisfies (i.e., is cyclic). Let the potential energy, , depend only on the configuration variables and be smooth. Denote the Lagrangian by and assume that the system is actuated according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. The model can then be written as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. Subsequent analysis and feedback design are more easily accomplished if the system is first transformed into the normal form <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> . . . <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> where , , are the entries in the first row of . The definition of and the required (regular) static state feedback transformation are given in the Appendix. Note that everywhere is positive definite, is never zero. Note also that does not depend on because is cyclic. Denote the generalized momentum conjugate to <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> by . Because the kinetic energy is quadratic and the potential energy depends only on the configuration variables, it follows that <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> From the assumption on the actuation and the assumption that is cyclic <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> For later use, note that <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> implies that the relative degree of is at least three.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> Using ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) to express the normal form in terms of the state variables , instead of , shows that ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) is (globally) static state feedback equivalent to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> which was introduced in <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> and will be called the modified normal form. Since only a change of state variables has been made, the feedback required to go from (2) to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> is the same as that used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>.</p><p>Associate to the one-form and the normalized one-form Applying Lemma 1 for , define the function <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> Direct computation then leads to <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> where Note that since does not depend on , it must be differentiated at least twice more before appears; in other words, has at least relative degree three with respect to .</p><p>This concludes the preliminary analysis required for subsequent feedback design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Systems Where the Generalized Momentum Conjugate to the Cyclic Variable is not Conserved</head><p>It is first assumed that , the generalized momentum conjugate to , is not constant along solutions of the model (1); that is <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> It is also assumed that there exists a static equilibrium point corresponding to some constant value of the control, and that when defining via <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>, is taken as so that vanishes 3 at the equilibrium point. In this case, conditions will be identified under which the set of outputs . . . <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> a constant, yields an exponentially minimum phase system. More precisely, conditions will be given such that the zero dynamics is well defined in a neighborhood of the given equilibrium point, has dimension one, and is exponentially 3 Alternatively, let q be arbitrary, for example, zero, and define y = K(p 0 p ) + , where p is the value at the equilibrium point, q . stable for all , and moreover, the system is dynamically input-output decouplable (equivalently, invertible).</p><p>Before proceeding with the analysis, the intuition behind this choice of outputs is discussed. As stated earlier, a more standard choice of outputs would be , for , where each component has relative degree two. Such a choice leads to a two-dimensional zero dynamics, which can be shown to be once again a Lagrangian system <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>, and thus can never have an asymptotically stable equilibrium. By seeking an output component with a relative degree higher than two, the dimension of the zero dynamics can be reduced, opening up the possibility of either having no zero dynamics at all, or, of creating one that is scalar and asymptotically stable. For the class of systems being studied, no output function of relative degree four has been found (see Section V-B for more discussion on this point). The most obvious relative degree three function available is the conjugate momentum , which is a linear combination of the velocity components. If the first component of the outputs were modified to , the resulting zero dynamics manifold would include a one-dimensional submanifold of equilibria associated with and, thus, asymptotic stability of the zero dynamics would be impossible. Inspired by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, by associating to a one-form and then partially integrating it, a function was determined that depends only on the configuration variables and has at least relative degree three with respect to one of the input components (after a static feedback was used to put the system in normal form). Hence, any function of and has at least relative degree three with respect to that input component. Moreover, by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>, if , for , then is proportional to through the strictly positive quantity . Thus the choice , , and , for , should lead to the exponentially stable zero dynamics . The main result is now stated. Theorem 1: Consider the simple mechanical system (2) with DOF, independent actuators and the unactuated coordinate is cyclic. Associate to the system the outputs defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>, with , and define (16) Then, in a neighborhood of any equilibrium point at which is nonzero, the system is i) exponentially minimum phase; ii) dynamically, input-output decouplable. Moreover, once the system is transformed into the normal form of ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>), or into the modified normal form of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, then the dynamic extension . . . <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> renders it statically input-output decouplable.</p><p>Proof: The zero dynamics is invariant under regular static state feedback and dynamic extensions <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Hence, assume the system has already been transformed into the normal form <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> and then apply the dynamic extension <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. It follows that , for . It remains to differentiate the first output component. Equation ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) yields <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> The arguments will now be dropped so that the formulas remain compact and readable. Differentiating <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> again yields <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> Due to the dynamic extension <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, have at least relative degree three and has at least relative degree two, thus the inputs do not appear in . Differentiating once more and keeping track only of the terms where the inputs appear yield <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> where is given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>. Therefore, the decoupling matrix is <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> and is invertible at a given point if, and only if, is nonzero at that point. In a neighborhood of an equilibrium point , is nonzero if, and only if <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> Wherever the decoupling matrix is invertible, the zero dynamics is locally well defined and the set of differentials, , is independent <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and, hence, has dimension . System <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> with the dynamic extension (17) has dimension , and thus the zero dynamics has dimension one. To determine the zero dynamics, it is enough to find a function whose differential is independent of . In the Appendix, it is shown that is an appropriate choice. On the zero dynamics manifold (that is, when ), , , and , . Thus, from <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> [see also (78) in the Appendix], in a neighborhood of an equilibrium point where , the zero dynamics is <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> Since is positive, the zero dynamics is exponentially stable for all . Remark 2: Note that an integrator has not been added on . This is because is designed to have relative degree three with respect to , while it only has relative degree two with respect to . With the dynamic extension, has relative degree three with respect to .</p><p>Remark 3: From <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, exponential minimum phase plus local static input-output decouplability after a dynamic extension implies the existence of a feedback that induces local asymptotic tracking of output trajectories with internally bounded states. See the three-link robot in Section IV-C-2 for an example.</p><p>Remark 4: If in ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>) is selected with , then the dynamic extension becomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> and the decoupling matrix is invertible in a neighborhood of an equilibrium point if, and only if <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> Choosing different values of may be useful for avoiding singularities.</p><p>Remark 5: The results of the Theorem 1 are inherently local for two reasons. First of all, the decoupling matrix typically has singularities away from the equilibrium point (see the examples in Section IV). Second, even if the decoupling matrix were globally invertible and if the zero dynamics were globally exponentially stable, global asymptotic stabilizability of an equilibrium does not necessarily follow; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr">Ch. 9]</ref>. A global feedforward representation of the system is discussed in Section V-A; see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Systems Where the Generalized Momentum Conjugate to the Cyclic Variable is Conserved</head><p>It is now assumed that , the generalized momentum conjugate to , is constant along solutions of the model; that is <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> which is equivalent to . In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, can be treated as a constant, yielding the reduced-order model <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> Let be given and define as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>. In this case, conditions will be given such that <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> with outputs . . . <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref> is locally, dynamically, feedback linearizable. Note that ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>) is a simplification of (15) arising from . Theorem 2: Consider a simple mechanical system (2) with DOF, independent actuators, and the unactuated coordinate is cyclic. Suppose that the generalized momentum conjugate to the cyclic coordinate is conserved along the motions of the system so that the reduced system ( <ref type="formula">27</ref>) can be defined. Associate to <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> the outputs defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref> and define <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref> Then, in a neighborhood of any point at which is nonzero, the following hold.</p><p>i) System ( <ref type="formula">27</ref>) is dynamically feedback equivalent to a controllable linear system. ii) System ( <ref type="formula">27</ref>) is the strongly accessible part of (2), and can be viewed as a representation of the uncontrollable part. iii) System ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) is dynamically feedback equivalent to a linear system with a one-dimensional uncontrollable part. iv) System <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> with outputs ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>) is dynamically inputoutput decouplable and has no zero dynamics. Moreover, the dynamic extension ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) renders ( <ref type="formula">27</ref>) statically feedback linearizable.</p><p>Proof: As in the proof of Theorem 1, apply to (27) the dynamic extension <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. Once again, , for and it remains to differentiate the first output component. From ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>, by taking and , it follows that <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref> (31) <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref> Thus, the decoupling matrix is <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> and is invertible in a neighborhood of a given point if and only if is nonzero at that point. In a neighborhood of a point where the decoupling matrix is invertible, the sum of the relative degrees of the outputs is , which equals the sum of the dimensions of ( <ref type="formula">27</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. It follows that <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> with outputs <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref> has no zero dynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, and thus any regular static feedback that locally input-output linearizes ( <ref type="formula">27</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, also renders the closed-loop system locally input-to-state linear in the coordinates ; the associated Brunovsky canonical form is , . Corollary 1: The same results hold for (3) with the exception that the uncontrollable part has dimension five <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> where is a constant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. EXAMPLES</head><p>This section will illustrate the theoretical results of Section III on systems of the type depicted in Figs. <ref type="figure">1</ref> and<ref type="figure">2</ref>. The systems are chosen to be simple enough that the calculations are straightforward and sufficiently complex to illustrate a range of possible applications of the main theorems. The first example treats a robot with two rigid links connected via an actuated revolute joint and attached at one end to a pivot; that is, the Acrobot. A novel feature is that the robot is placed on a frictionless horizontal plane to remove gravity. If nothing else were done, the angular momentum about the attachment point would be conserved, so stabilization about an equilibrium would not be possible. A spring is therefore added between the world frame and the first link, and a stabilizing controller is then designed through the use of Theorem 1. The second example treats a robot consisting of three serial links connected by independently actuated revolute joints, attached to a pivot, and constrained to evolve in a vertical plane. For this system, the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> are not applicable for designing a stabilizing controller. Theorem 1 is applied to design a controller that achieves stabilization about an equilibrium point and asymptotic tracking of trajectories. The last problem studied focuses on ballistic motion in a vertical plane, which is a key part of a model of running. The model assumes a robot with two rigid links connected via an actuated revolute joint. The angular momentum about the center of mass is conserved, creating a nonholonomic constraint. Corollary 1 is applied to feedback linearize the accessible part of the system. The linear representation of the dynamics is shown to be advantageous for path planning. The singularities that prevent the system from being globally linearized are explicitly noted and how to plan a path through such a singularity is illustrated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Computing the Outputs</head><p>The key to applying the results of Section III is the explicit computation of the function in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> used to define the outputs. For all of the examples treated here, plus a wide range of other examples, the computation of this function is handled by the following lemma. The proof by direct symbolic integration is not given.</p><p>Lemma 2: Consider a simple mechanical system of the form (2), with DOF and mass inertia matrix . Suppose that and can be expressed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> where , and that . Then, for and , ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>) can be evaluated explicitly as <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref> Remark 6: Write so that and Hence, everywhere that , it follows that and . Therefore, is a positive real number everywhere that . The minimum value of over is equal to , which is, therefore, also positive everywhere that . The corresponds to the principal value. If , then ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>) can be evaluated explicitly as . Remark 7: If and either or , then</p><p>. In this case, the results simplify to the results obtained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>.</p><p>Remark 8: For a general point of interest , (12) can be evaluated as which is just in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref> minus the same function evaluated at .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Planar Two-Link Structure Attached to a Pivot</head><p>This example treats the planar two-link robot depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. The purpose of the example is to emphasize the role of the potential energy in determining whether generalized Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. Two-link robot attached to a pivot and constrained to move in a horizontal plane. The joint q is actuated, while q is passive; a linear spring with stiffness K is attached with rest position q = 0. From left to right, the links have length L and L and the masses are m and m . momentum is conserved, and to demonstrate in the simplest possible setting the computations needed to apply Theorem 1 in order to achieve asymptotic stabilization of an equilibrium. The robot consists of two point masses connected by two rigid, massless links, with the links joined by an actuated revolute joint (the use of a distributed mass model would not change any of the following analysis). The connection to the pivot is unactuated and frictionless.</p><p>The configuration variables are chosen as and , where is the angle of the first link referenced to a world frame attached to the pivot point and is the relative angle between links one and two. A linear spring of stiffness is introduced between the first link and the world frame, with rest position . The plane of movement is assumed to be horizontal, and thus the acceleration due to gravity is . The case where the gravity is non zero can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>1) Mathematical Representation: The dynamic model is easily obtained with the method of Lagrange and verifies that is a cyclic variable. The complete dynamic model is not given; instead, the system is immediately written in the modified normal form <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> as <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(39)</ref> In <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref>, note that , given by ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>), is the usual angular momentum of the robot about the attachment point. Since the robot is constrained to a horizontal plane, if the spring constant were zero, then angular momentum would be conserved and asymptotic stabilization to an equilibrium point would be impossible.</p><p>2) Control Law Design: The control law design consists of the preliminary feedback needed to place the system in the (modified) normal form (as explained in the Appendix), the definition of an output, and a second static state feedback used to linearize and stabilize the resulting input-output map. For the two-link robot, the output is selected as <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref> where is to be chosen <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(41)</ref> and is the value of at the equilibrium of interest, .</p><p>For single-input systems, the dynamic extension ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) is trivial:</p><p>. Since it only amounts to relabeling the input, it is dropped. Direct calculation confirms that has relative degree three <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(42)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(43)</ref> Suppose that . Let real scalars , and be chosen such that is exponentially stable. Then, (43) leads to the locally input-output linearizing and exponentially stabilizing control law <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> (44)</p><p>The actual torque applied to the actuated joint is computed from (75) of the Appendix.</p><p>3) Simulation: For the simulations, the robot is assumed constrained to a horizontal plane , the spring attaching the first link to the reference frame is assumed linear with </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>stiffness</head><p>, and the model parameters are selected as , , , and . The equilibrium point was chosen as , , which corresponds to , and satisfies . The scalars were arbitrarily chosen to place the eigenvalues of the error equation at 1.3. The free parameter in the output was arbitrarily set to . Since , the zero dynamics has a slightly slower speed of convergence than the output error equation.</p><p>The state feedback controller <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref> was simulated for the initial condition , , , . Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">4</ref> shows the evolution of the commanded output and its derivatives along with the evolution of the configuration variables of the robot. The output rapidly converges to zero and the configuration variables converge to the desired equilibrium point. An animation of the motion is available at <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Planar Three-Link Serial Structure Attached to a Pivot</head><p>This example treats the planar three-link robot depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref>. The robot consists of three point masses connected by three rigid, massless links, with the links joined by an actuated revolute joint. The connection to the pivot is unactuated and frictionless. The links are labeled through starting from the pivot and the masses are similarly labeled through . The parameter values given in Table <ref type="table">I</ref> were selected to approximate the biped robot RABBIT with the legs held together <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The configuration variables are chosen as through , where is the angle of the first link referenced to a world frame attached to the pivot point, is the relative angle between links one and two, and is the relative angle between links two and three. No springs are used. The plane of movement is assumed to be vertical and, thus, the acceleration due to gravity is . The example further illustrates the application of Theorem 1 through the use of an output component that has relative degree three with respect to only one of the input components and the use of a nontrivial dynamic extension in the design of the feedback controller. Both local asymptotic tracking and exponential stabilization to an equilibrium point are demonstrated. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TABLE I MASS AND LENGTH PARAMETERS FOR THREE-LINK MECHANISM</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) Mathematical Representation:</head><p>The complete dynamic model is easily obtained using the method of Lagrange and yields immediately the modified normal form <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> as <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref> with , as given in Lemma 2, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>. Note that is the angular momentum of the robot about the attachment point and is computed from the previous data via <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</p><p>2) Control Law Design: The goal is to demonstrate local exponential stability and asymptotic tracking about an equilibrium point. An equilibrium point was found from , , and , resulting in ; see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5(a)</ref>. The control law design consists of the preliminary feedback needed to place the system in the (modified) normal form (as explained in the Appendix), the selection of two outputs, the dynamic extension that renders the system statically decouplable (and, hence, statically input-output linearizable), and a second static state feedback used to linearize and stabilize the inputoutput map. For the three-link robot, the outputs have been selected as <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref> where is to be chosen, and the function is determined this time via Remark 8. The dynamic extension is <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(48)</ref> which consists of adding a single integrator on . Introduce a state vector , and express the composition of ( <ref type="formula">45</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref>, and ( <ref type="formula">48</ref>) as <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref> Direct calculation confirms that has (vector) relative degree three <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> with respect to . Indeed, using Lie derivative notation, the output derivatives are <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref> where corresponds to the decoupling matrix in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>. Evaluating the right-hand side of ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) at the equilibrium point gives 2.35, and thus the decoupling matrix is invertible in a neighborhood of this point. It follows that a feedback law that provides asymptotic tracking is <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> (51) for any constant matrices that render the error equation exponentially stable:</p><p>, for . For the simulation, the matrices were arbitrarily chosen to be diagonal and to place all of the eigenvalues of the error equation at 1. The free parameter in the output was arbitrarily chosen as . Since , the zero dynamics is about one-third as fast as the output error equation. Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>. Demonstration of asymptotic tracking and stabilization for the three-link mechanism. For the first 40 s, the motion consists of an initial transient, followed by tracking of sinusoidal trajectories that correspond to knee bends. At 40 s, the reference trajectory is abruptly set to zero, thereby commanding the system to an equilibrium point.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) Simulation Results:</head><p>The simulation demonstrates asymptotic tracking and exponential stabilization. The initial condition was taken as (1.1,1.42, 1.80,0,0,0), and is depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5(b)</ref>. For the first 40 s, the robot is commanded to track sinusoidal references that cause it to execute a form of calisthenics, namely, deep knee bends; at 40 s, the references are abruptly set to constant values corresponding to the equilibrium point in order to demonstrate convergence to a constant set point. The asymptotic convergence of the outputs to the commanded references is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>, along with the evolution of the configuration variables and the applied joint torques. An animation of the motion is available at <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Planar Two-Link Structure in Ballistic Motion</head><p>This examples illustrates how the locally linearizing coordinates of Theorem 2 can be used to advantage in planning a flip gait in a planar two link structure undergoing ballistic motion. The boundary constraints chosen in the flip gait are motivated by bipedal running <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. The singularities in the decoupling matrix will be explicitly computed and related to configuration changes of the mechanism.</p><p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">7</ref>, the mechanism consists of three point masses joined by two massless bars in an actuated, revolute joint. The four configuration variables are selected as , , , and , where relates the orientation of the mechanism to a world frame and is the relative angle between the two links. The mechanism's position with respect to a world frame is represented by the Cartesian coordinates of its center of mass. The point masses are given by , , ; the bar connecting to has length and that connecting to has length . </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) Mathematical Representation:</head><p>The complete dynamic model is easily obtained using the method of Lagrange and yields immediately the modified normal form (11) <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref> with control and <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(53)</ref> The strongly accessible portion of the model has dimension three, and involves , , . Due to ballistic motion, there is a five-dimensional uncontrollable subsystem that is completely decoupled from the actuated portion of the model, and this is given by , , , , . How these two parts interact in a path planning problem is explained next.</p><p>2) Interaction Through Boundary Conditions: The flight phases of a gymnastic robot, such as a tumbler or a bipedal runner, are typically short-term motions that alternate with single support phases. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">4</ref> The creation of an overall satisfactory motion is closely tied to achieving correct boundary conditions at the interfaces of the flight and single support phases. The state of the robot at the end of a flight phase determines the initial conditions for the single support phase, and consequently the state of the robot at the end of a flight phase is typically more important than the exact trajectory followed during the flight phase.</p><p>At the beginning and end of a flight phase, the robot is in contact with a surface, assumed here to be identified with the horizontal component of the world frame. Assume furthermore that the robot is in single support, with the contact point being either the mass or . In single support, there are two holonomic constraints that tie the position and velocity of the center of mass to those of the angular coordinates; in other words, there is a loss of two degrees of freedom. Conservation of angular momentum through yields an additional (nonholonomic) constraint on the angular velocities. In particular, the desired final joint velocities must be chosen to satisfy this constraint.</p><p>The duration of the flight phase is determined from , with the initial conditions coming from the initial positions and velocities of the angular coordinates at lift-off, and the end condition of the height of the center mass coming from the desired final configuration of the angular coordinates at touchdown. Once the flight time is known, determining whether or not there exists a solution of the reduced model <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(54)</ref> that is compatible with a given set of initial and final conditions is a difficult problem: Once a trajectory for is chosen, must be numerically integrated, and if does not have the desired value, then must be altered. Such an iterative procedure is poorly adapted to online computations. Theorem 2 will be applied to simplify this task. It should be noted that the value of the momentum is unknown before the start of the flight phase, and thus it is not even possible to determine the reduced model ( <ref type="formula">54</ref>) before the initial condition of the robot is known at lift-off.</p><p>3) Determining a Ballistic Motion Trajectory in Linearizing Coordinates: Local, input-output linearizing coordinates for the reduced model <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(54)</ref> are constructed from and its first two derivatives. Define by <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(41)</ref>. Direct computation leads to (55) <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(56)</ref> To determine the linearizing control, one more derivative is needed <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(57)</ref> (58)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wherever</head><p>, a linearizing feedback can be constructed such that (59) For arbitrary initial and final conditions of the linear model (59), it is trivial to define a feasible trajectory. Indeed, it suffices to define a three-times continuously differentiable function passing from given initial values to given final values. One could even use a polynomial of order five or greater.</p><p>Since the change of coordinates going from ( <ref type="formula">54</ref>) to (59) is local, not every solution of (59) can be mapped back onto a solution of <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(54)</ref>. From (55), , the "global" orientation of the robot, can only be changed through modification of the inertia parameter, , because the angular momentum is constant. The inertia term can only be changed through variation of the internal angle . Since is bounded, so is . These kinds of constraints, which must be applied point-wise in time on the trajectories of (59), are made explicit by computing the inverse of the coordinate change.</p><p>4) Constraints Point-Wise in Time Associated With the Linearizing Coordinates: The calculation of , , and in terms of , , and yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(60)<label>(61) (62)</label></formula><p>The first equation only admits a solution for , and then has two solutions: One for and another for . These two domains for the cosine define two "configuration classes" of the robot, with the extreme points of the domains corresponding to the links being completely folded or unfolded. At the extreme points of the domains, attains an extremum and consequently, is zero. At an extreme point of , cannot be determined from (62), which takes the form . Since vanishes at an extreme point, ( <ref type="formula">57</ref>) is used with to obtain (63) with the sign of being determined by continuity (with torque control, there cannot be discontinuities in the velocity). The robot will then pass through the singularity, and change configuration classes.</p><p>Consequently, when generating a motion, two cases can present themselves, according to whether the motion stays always in the same configuration class or not. If the initial and final configuration are in the same configuration class, then a trajectory can be generated by imposing . Both open-loop and feedback controls are equally easily computed starting from the linear model. If the initial and final configurations are in different configuration classes, a trajectory can be computed that passes through a singularity at a single time instance, , where</p><p>vanishes. An open-loop control can be determined as before. On the other hand, a feedback implementation is not possible based on inverting in (58). However, since the flight phase is typically of short duration and the input is calculated as a function of the initial conditions, an open-loop control is probably sufficient.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5) Simulation Without Passing Through a Singularity:</head><p>The model parameters were selected as , , , , and . For this simulation, the mass of the robot is supposed initially in contact with the ground, with configuration defined by , , and angular velocities , . The objective is to transfer the robot at the end of a flight phase so that when the mass of the robot touches the ground, its configuration is , with angular velocity proportional to and . The initial and final configurations are depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">8</ref>; they belong to the same configuration class. From the initial conditions of the robot and the desired final the flight time is computed as . Conservation of angular momentum implies that . The initial and final values of and its first two derivatives were computed from ( <ref type="formula">41</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(55)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(56)</ref>. A fifth-order polynomial of was defined that satisfied these boundary conditions. The resulting trajectories of , , are depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">9</ref>; the point-wise in time constraints associated with (60)-(62) are met. The input torque for the system was computed using <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(57)</ref> and (75) of the Appendix. The resulting trajectories in terms of and are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">10</ref> and the evolution of the robot in the vertical plane is presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">8</ref>. An animation of the motion is available at <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</p><p>6) Simulation With Passage Through a Singularity: For this simulation, the mass of the robot is supposed initially in contact with the ground, with configuration defined by , and angular velocities , . The objective is to transfer the robot at the end of a flight phase so that when the mass of the robot touches the ground, its configuration is , with angular velocity proportional to , . The initial and final configurations are depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">11</ref>; they do not belong to the same configuration class. From the initial conditions of the robot and the desired  final configuration, the flight time is computed as . Conservation of angular momentum implies that . The initial and final values of and its first two derivatives were computed as before. So that the robot changes configuration class, at , the trajectory was forced to pass through a singularity corresponding to , that is, and . A seventh-order polynomial in was defined that satisfied the six boundary conditions, plus , . The resulting trajectories of , , are depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">12</ref>. The corresponding trajectories in terms of and are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">13</ref> and the evolution of the robot in the plane is presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">11</ref>. An animation of the motion is available at <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. ADDITIONAL TECHNICAL POINTS</head><p>This section provides additional discussion on a few points that would have broken the flow of the main developments.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. A Cascade Structure</head><p>The feedback designs of Section III-C that have been illustrated on the two-link and three-link models have singularities where the decoupling matrix looses rank. Results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> show that (within the category of analytic systems and compensators) achieving an invertible decoupling matrix via dynamic compensation is a necessary condition for the existence of a compensator that achieves asymptotic tracking of an open set of reference trajectories. Hence, while it is not necessary that the particular decoupling matrix constructed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> be invertible, at least some other decoupling matrix would have to be invertible for asymptotic tracking to be possible on a larger set.</p><p>If one is only trying to accomplish stabilization on a large set and not asymptotic tracking, it is then interesting to consider feedback designs that avoid the requirement of an invertible decoupling matrix. One way that this may be approached for the systems studied in Section III-C is the following. First, use <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> to rewrite <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> in the coordinates as</p><p>, (64) takes the form of a feedforward nonlinear system (66) for which various feedback stabilization methods have been developed <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref>. Backstepping suggests considering and as virtual controls <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, leading to the simpler (block-)feedforward system (67) For a two-link system, and are empty, leading to the two dimensional system , the global asymptotic sta-bilization 5 of which has been studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. The problem of asymptotically stabilizing (67) on large sets is open for systems with three or more links.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Checking Feedback Linearizability</head><p>This section offers a few observations on the generic nonfeedback linearizability of the model class studied here when generalized conjugate momentum is not conserved. The reason to check this property is that if the systems were feedback linearizable, then it would be possible to achieve an empty zero dynamics instead of a zero dynamics with dimension one. Recall that for single-input systems, it is known that a system is dynamically feedback linearizable if, and only if, it is statically feedback linearizable. For multiple-input systems, dynamic feedback does enlarge the class of linearizable systems, but necessary and sufficient conditions for dynamic feedback linearizability are not known. If one restricts the outputs used to achieve dynamic feedback linearizability (often called flat outputs) to being only functions of the configuration variables, however, then for mechanical systems with one degree of underactuation, necessary and sufficient conditions for dynamic feedback linearization are known <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>; in particular, for the class of systems being studied in this paper, the conclusion is that there do not generally exist flat outputs depending only on the configuration variables.</p><p>Consider first a two-DOF system written in the form of (64), and suppose that . Such a system has a single input and, thus, necessary and sufficient conditions for feedback linearizability can be checked. Applying the method of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> , in which case is a linearizing (or flat) output. These conditions are not generally satisfied for the class of systems being studied; in particular, applying them to the two link example of Section IV-B proves that it is not feedback linearizable.</p><p>Consider next a system with three-DOF written either in the form <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> or (64). Applying once again the method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, the system is statically feedback linearizable only if (68) moreover, the same obstruction persists if an integrator is added on so the dynamic extension used in this paper does not render the system static feedback linearizable. The obstruction (68) is present in the three-link example of Section IV-C.</p><p>We know of only two mechanical systems that meet the conditions of this paper and are feedback linearizable: The inertia wheel pendulum <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref> and the RTAC or TORA (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> and the references therein). Both systems satisfy the condition 5 The Lyapunov function used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> was not shown to be proper or radially unbounded. For the Acrobot, a periodicity property of G can be used to fill this lacuna when the dynamic model is extended in the obvious way to I R .</p><p>, and thus is a linearizing output. The method of this paper also finds the locally linearizing coordinates. This is shown only for the inertia wheel pendulum.</p><p>In the coordinates of Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>, the modified normal form of the inertia wheel pendulum is (69) where (70) and the parameters are as defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>. Since and are constant, ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) is trivially integrated about the equilibrium point to obtain</p><p>Defining the output as and using ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">20</ref>), the model (69) in the coordinates becomes (72)</p><p>At the upright equilibrium, and, hence, (72) is linear in the coordinates after the application of a static state feedback.</p><p>Remark 9: More generally, the underlying reason for the static feedback linearizability of the inertia wheel pendulum can be tied to be the following result, which applies to DOF mechanisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. Consider again the one-form associated with the generalized conjugate momentum (9) and suppose that is closed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Let</head><p>. Then, a simple computation shows that: a) has at least relative degree four; b) the outputs , , have decoupling matrix (21) with ; c) when the decoupling matrix is invertible, these outputs have vector relative degree (4, 2, , 2) and, thus, the system is static feedback linearizable; and d) the coordinate transformation required to linearize the system is canonical and given by , , where . For the inertia wheel pendulum, is closed because the first row of the inertia matrix is constant; moreover, the relative degree four function is proportional to . In the case of the RTAC, the first row of the inertia matrix is not constant in the appropriate coordinates, but is still closed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSION</head><p>Motivated by a large number of dexterous robots that have been introduced in the literature over the past fifteen years, this paper has analyzed simple planar mechanical systems with an unactuated cyclic variable and an independent actuator for each shape variable. This class of models is naturally associated with balancing tasks and includes -link extensions of the Acrobot, the stance phase of Raibert's hopper and many other robots. Typical control objectives include stabilizing an equilibrium and asymptotically tracking a predefined motion. Through a simple decomposition procedure, models with an unactuated cyclic variable and an independent actuator for each shape variable also arise for certain systems executing a ballistic motion, such as diving, dismounting from a high bar, and tumbling. For these systems, since momentum is conserved, since the initial conditions are usually determined by the end of a single support phase, and since the ballistic phase is usually of short duration, asymptotically tracking a predefined motion is not a reasonable objective. Instead, the main problem is to determine if a of initial and final conditions is compatible, and if so, to generate online a trajectory that joins them.</p><p>The paper presented two novel control results. When the generalized momentum conjugate to the cyclic variable was not conserved, conditions were found for the existence of a set of outputs that yielded a one-dimensional, exponentially stable zero dynamics, along with a dynamic extension that rendered the system locally input-output decouplable. By existing results, a controller that achieves asymptotic stabilization and tracking is then easily constructed. When the generalized momentum conjugate to the cyclic variable was conserved, a reduced system was constructed and conditions were found for the existence of a set of outputs that yielded an empty zero dynamics, along with a dynamic extension that rendered the system locally input-output decouplable. By existing results, a local coordinate transformation and dynamic feedback controller that linearize the input-to-state map are then easily constructed. The solutions to these two control problems had a common underlying element: The computation of a function of the configuration variables that had relative degree three with respect to one of the input components. It was interesting that this function arose by partially integrating a physical quantity, the conjugate momentum.</p><p>The theoretical results were illustrated on three simple examples. Stabilization of an equilibrium was demonstrated on a variant of the Acrobot without the influence of gravity. The purpose of the example was to emphasize the role of the potential energy in determining whether generalized momentum is conserved, and to demonstrate the computations needed to apply the results of the paper in the simplest possible setting. Asymptotic stabilization about an equilibrium and asymptotic tracking were both illustrated on a serial, three-link, mechanism attached to a pivot and constrained to evolve in a vertical plane. This example provided a nontrivial illustration of the results for a system with multiple inputs. The last example illustrated how locally linearizing coordinates can simplify the path planning problem for a ballistic flip motion of a two-link mechanism. The singularities in the decoupling matrix were explicitly computed and related to configuration changes of the mechanism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Normal Form</head><p>The normal form is taken from <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>. Let and partition the generalized coordinates into actuated and unactuated parts per , . This induces a decomposition of the model ( <ref type="formula">2</ref> The static state feedback taking (2) into ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>) is (75)</p><p>The feedback is regular because and .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parameterization of the Zero Dynamics</head><p>From the choice of outputs <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>, , ; . Hence, to determine the zero dynamics, it is enough to find a function whose differential is independent of , modulo</p><p>This is most easily done if the model is expressed in the coordinates . Then, condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> for the invertibility of the decoupling matrix at an equilibrium becomes <ref type="bibr">(77)</ref> where, in the new coordinates, is the equilibrium point and the potential energy is Model <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> with the dynamic extension (17) can be rewritten as (78)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Computing</head><p>and evaluating their differentials at the equilibrium point and modulo (76), results in (79) and, hence, modulo (76). Next, computing and evaluating its differential at the equilibrium point and modulo (76) and yields (80) and, thus, modulo (76), proving that can be used to parameterize the zero dynamics in a neighborhood of an equilibrium point.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Stabilization to an equilibrium. The figure shows the convergence of the commanded output, its first two derivatives, and the configuration variables.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Three-link mechanism, connected at a pivot, consisting of point masses and massless bars. The links have length L through L starting at the pivot; the masses are m through m . (a) Equilibrium pose with the center of gravity centered over the pivot. (b) Initial condition used in the simulation, with the equilibrium position superimposed in the background.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Two-link robot undergoing ballistic motion in a vertical plane. Only the joint q is actuated. From left to right, the links have length L and L and the masses are m , m , and m .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Motion of the robot passes from left to right without passing through a singularity. The initial configuration (1 010 left) and final configuration (1 010 right) belong to the same configuration class. The center of gravity follows a parabolic trajectory.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Based on the initial and final conditions of the flight phase, a trajectory for p and its derivatives is derived. The plot shows that _ p satisfies the constraint (=(a 0 a )) _ p (t) (=(a + a )).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig.10. Computed open-loop control transfers the robot from its initial state to the desired final state ( ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Motion of the robot passes from left to right, with a singular position occurring when the two links are aligned. The initial configuration (1 010 left) and final configuration (1 0 10 right) belong to different configuration classes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Based on the initial and final conditions of the flight phase, a trajectory for p and its derivatives is derived. The plot shows that _ p hits the constraint =(a + a ) in the middle of the flight phase, which allows the change in the configuration class to occur.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig.<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref>. Computed open-loop control transfers the robot from its initial state to the desired final state ( ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="2,305.16,65.38,246.00,257.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>If friction were allowed at the unactuated joint, then the relative degree would in general be only one.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_1"><p>That is, one end of the mechanism is in contact with a rigid surface, and the contact point is neither slipping nor rebounding; in other words the contact point is acting as a pivot.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Recommended by Associate Editor Z. P. Jiang. The work of C. Moog and C. Chevallereau was supported in part by the CNRS through the program ROBEA. The work of J. W. Grizzle was supported by the National Science Foundation under Grant ECS-0322395.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable control of a simulated one-legged running robot with hip and leg compliance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ahmadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buehler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Autom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-02">Feb. 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking fast inverted trajectories of the underactuated Acrobot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Berkemeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fearing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Autom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="740" to="750" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-08">Aug. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controlled lagrangians and the stabilization of mechanical systems I: The first matching theorem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Leonard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Marsden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2253" to="2270" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-12">Dec. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinematic controllability for decoupled trajectory planning in underactuated mechanical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bullo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lynch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Autom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="402" to="412" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-08">Aug. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable trajectory tracking for biped robots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cambrini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chevallereau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stojic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 39th IEEE Conf. Decision and Control</title>
		<meeting>39th IEEE Conf. Decision and Control<address><addrLine>Sydney, Australia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-12">Dec. 2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4815" to="4820" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Periodic stabilization of a 1-DOF hopping robot on nonlinear compliant surface</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Canudas-De-Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Roussel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goswani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IFAC Symp. Robot Control</title>
		<meeting>IFAC Symp. Robot Control<address><addrLine>Nantes, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-09">Sep. 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="410" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RABBIT: A testbed for advanced control theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chevallereau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Abba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Aoustin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Plestan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Westervelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Canduas-De Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grizzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Control Syst. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-10">Oct. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal reference trajectories for walking and running of a biped robot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chevallereau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Aoustin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Robotica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="569" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-09">Sep. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking of a joint path for the walking of an underactuated biped</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chevallereau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Djoudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Robotica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design and actuation optimization of a 4 axes biped robot for walking and running</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chevallereau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sardain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robotics and Automation</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robotics and Automation<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-04">Apr. 2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3365" to="3370" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear Control Systems: An Algebraic Setting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Conte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Perdon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Control and Information Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">242</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999-03">Mar. 1999</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flatness and defect of nonlinear systems: Introductory theory and examples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fliess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lvine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rouchon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1327" to="1361" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Lie-Bcklund approach to equivalence and flatness of nonlinear systems</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="922" to="937" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-05">May 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new approach to the control of the planar one-legged hopper</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Francois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Samson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1150" to="1166" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motion control of a brachiation robot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fukuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Saito</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Robot. Auton. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-07">Jul. 1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flip gait synthesis of a biped based on Poincare map</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Geng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 2nd Int. Workshop Robot Motion and Control</title>
		<meeting>2nd Int. Workshop Robot Motion and Control<address><addrLine>Bukowy Dworek, Poland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-10">Oct. 2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="243" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path planning for nonholonmic systems with drift</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Godhavn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Balluchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Crawford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Amer. Control Conf., Albuguerque</title>
		<meeting>Amer. Control Conf., Albuguerque<address><addrLine>NM</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-06">Jun. 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="532" to="536" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Classical Mechanics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Reading, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Publications on robotics and control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grizzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.eecs.umich.edu/~grizzle/papers/robotics.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-08">2004. Aug</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Necessary conditions for asymptotic tracking in nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grizzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Di Benedetto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lamnabhi-Lagarrigue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1782" to="1794" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-09">Sep. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Involutive subdistributions and canonical forms for distributions and control systems,&quot; in Theory and Applications of Nonlinear Control Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hermes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>C. I. Byrnes and A. Lindquist</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>North-Holland</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="135" />
			<pubPlace>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Isidori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Nonlinear Control Systems: An Introduction</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global output-feedback tracking for a benchmark nonlinear system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kanellakopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1027" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-05">May 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking control of mobile robots: A case study in backstepping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nijmeijer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1393" to="1399" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A recursive technique for tracking control of nonholonomic systems in chained form</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="279" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-02">Feb. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of a simplified hopping robot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Koditschek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buehler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="605" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New results on control of multibody systems which conserve angular momentum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kolmanovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mcclamroch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Coppola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Dyna. Control Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="447" to="462" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear and Adaptive Control Design. Adaptive and Learning Systems for Signal Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kristic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kanellakopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kokotovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications and Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the linearization via a restricted class of dynamic feedback</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Jeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1385" to="1391" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-07">Jul. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Invariance control for a class of cascade nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mareczek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Spong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1636" to="1640" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-04">Apr. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the largest feedback linearizable subsystem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Marino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control of a motion of an Acrobot approaching a horizontal bar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Miyazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sampei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Koga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Robot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="480" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A control of underactuated hopping gait systems: Acrobot example</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Miyazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sampei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Koga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Conf. Decision and Control</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conf. Decision and Control<address><addrLine>Sydney, Australia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-12">Dec. 2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4797" to="4803" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preliminary studies of a second generation brachiation robot controller</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nakanishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fukuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Koditschek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robotics and Automation</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robotics and Automation<address><addrLine>Albuquerque, NM</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-04">Apr. 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2050" to="2056" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A brachiating robot controller</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Autom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-04">Apr. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control of underactuated mechanical systems with two degrees of freedom and symmetry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Olfati-Saber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Amer. Control Conf</title>
		<meeting>Amer. Control Conf<address><addrLine>Chicago, IL</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-06">Jun. 2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4092" to="4096" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear control of underactuated mechanical systems with applications to robotics and aerospace vehicles</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">California Inst. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-02">Feb. 2001</date>
			<pubPlace>Pasadena, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Normal forms for underactuated mechanical systems with symmetry</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-02">Feb. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control of giant swing motion of a two-link horizontal bar gymnast robot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Imadu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Robot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="465" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stabilization of underactuated mechanical systems via interconnection and damping assignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ortega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Spong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gomez-Estern</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1218" to="1233" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-08">Aug. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable walking of a 7-DOF biped robot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Plestan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grizzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Westervelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Abba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Autom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="653" to="668" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-08">Aug. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Legged Robots That Balance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Raibert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Configuration flatness of lagrangian systems underactuated by one control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rathinam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Control Optim</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">376</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="164" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics and control of a class of underactuated mechanical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reyhanoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Der Schaft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mcclamroch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kolmanovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1663" to="1671" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-09">Sep. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flatness, motion planning and trailer systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rouchon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fliess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 32nd IEEE Conf. Decision and Control</title>
		<meeting>32nd IEEE Conf. Decision and Control</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-12">Dec. 1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2700" to="2705" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Swing and locomotion control for a two-link brachiation robot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Saito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fukuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Arai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Control Syst. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-02">Feb. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control strategies for mechanical systems with various constraints-Control of nonholonomic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sampei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kiyota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ishikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Conf. Systems, Man, Cybern. C</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conf. Systems, Man, Cybern. C<address><addrLine>Tokyo, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="165" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trading the stability of finite zeros for global stabilization of nonlinear cascade systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sepulchre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Arcak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Teel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-03">Mar. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sepulchre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jankovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kokotovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Constructive Nonlinear Control. Communications and Control Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London, U.K.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control problems in super-articulated mechanical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Seto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baillieul</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2442" to="2453" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-12">Dec. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Virtual constraints: A constructive tool for orbital stabilization of underactuated nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shiriaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Canudas-De-Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-09">Sep. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The swing up control problem for the Acrobot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Spong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Control Syst. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-02">Feb. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy based control of a class of underactuated mechanical systems</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IFAC World Congr</title>
		<meeting>IFAC World Congr<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="435" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear control of the inertia wheel pendulum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Spong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Corke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lozano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1845" to="1851" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A nonlinear small gain theorem for the analysis of control systems with saturation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Teel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1256" to="1270" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-09">Sep. 1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hybrid zero dynamics of planar biped walkers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Westervelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grizzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Koditschek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-01">Jan. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stabilization of Acrobot in upright position on a horizontal bar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yamakita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yonemura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Michitsuji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robotics and Automation</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robotics and Automation<address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-05">May 2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3093" to="3098" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Since September 1987, he has been with The University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, where he is a Professor of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science. His research interests have often focused on theoretical aspects of nonlinear systems and control, including geometric methods for continuousand discrete-time systems, and observer design in discrete-time. He has been a consultant in the automotive industry since 1986, where he jointly holds fourteen patents dealing with emissions reduction through improved controller design. His current interest in bipedal locomotion grew out of a sabbatical in Strasbourg</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grizzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Axelby Award from the IEEE Control Systems Society; and with J. Sun (Univ. of Michigan) and J. Cook (Ford), the 2003 IEEE Control Systems Society Technology Award. He has served as an Associate Editor for the TRANSACTIONS ON AUTOMATIC CONTROL AND SYSTEMS and Systems and Control Letters</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Plestan (Ecole Centrale, Nantes, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Vehicular Technology Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983. 1992. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Abba (Univ. of Metz, France) and F. Publications Chairman for the 1989 Conference on Decision and Control, on the Control Systems Society&apos;s Board of Governors in 1997-1999, and is currently an Associate Editor for Automatica and a Member of several awards committees</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Framce, in 1980 and 1987, respectively. Since 1983, he has been with the CNRS, and currently holds the position of</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claude</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Since 1989, she has been with the CNRS in the Institut de Recherche en Communications et Cybernetique de Nantes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Conte</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Perdon</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Nantes, France; Nantes, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">January 2004. 1988</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Nantes, Nantes</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>1985, and received the Ph.D. degree in control and robotics from Ecole Nationale Suprieure de Mcanique. Her research interests include modeling and control of robots, especially control of robot manipulators and legged robots</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
