<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Global Finite-Time Stabilization by Output Feedback for Planar Systems Without Observable Linearization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Chunjiang</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
							<email>chun-jiang.qian@utsa.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Uni-versity of Texas at San Antonio</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Antonio</addrLine>
									<postCode>78249</postCode>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ji</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Uni-versity of Texas at San Antonio</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>San Antonio</addrLine>
									<postCode>78249</postCode>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Global Finite-Time Stabilization by Output Feedback for Planar Systems Without Observable Linearization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BE0842AB6E14F7617D5234351CECD190</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TAC.2005.849253</idno>
					<note type="submission">received February 27, 2004; revised October 18, 2004. Recom-</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T13:53+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Finite-time stabilization</term>
					<term>nonlinear systems</term>
					<term>output feedback</term>
					<term>unobservable linearization</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This note considers the problem of global finite-time stabilization by output feedback for a class of planar systems without controllable/observable linearization. A sufficient condition for the solvability of the problem is established. By developing a nonsmooth observer and modifying the adding a power integrator technique, we show that an output feedback controller can be explicitly constructed to globally stabilize the systems in finite time. As a direct application of the main result, global output feedback finite-time stabilization is achieved for the double linear integrator systems perturbed by some nonlinear functions which are not necessarily homogeneous.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>The problem of global stabilization by output feedback for a class of planar systems without controllable/observable linearization is an interesting and challenging problem in the nonlinear control field. The difficulty of the problem mainly stems from the lack of new observer for linearly unobservable systems to which the traditional Luenberger observer is inapplicable due to the unobservable linearization <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>In attempting to solve the problem, several preliminary results have been achieved. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, a novel reduced-order observer was proposed to estimate the unmeasurable states. Combining this new observer with the smooth state feedback controller constructed by the adding a power integrator tool, a smooth output feedback controller was explicitly constructed to render the planar system globally asymptotically stable under a high-order growth condition. However, this smooth result does not permit the presence of uncontrollable and unstable linearization, due to the violation of the well-known necessary condition for the existence of a smooth controller (i.e., the linearized system has no uncontrollable modes whose eigenvalues are on the right-half plane <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>). Later, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> removed this limitation by developing a nonsmooth design method. As a matter of fact, to overcome the intrinsic obstacle caused by the uncontrollable unstable linearization, nonsmooth adding a power integrator <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> was used to construct the controller.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the convergence of the closed-loop systems is asymptotic with infinite settling time. The issue of how to use output feedback to stabilize the planar system without observable linearization in finite time is still an open problem. The finite-time stabilization is of interest because systems with finite-time convergence demonstrate some nice features such as faster convergence and robustness to uncertainties <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. However, the problem of finite-time stabilization by time-invariant controller is quite challenging even in the state feedback case. This problem has been studied by <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, and seminal results have been achieved. Compared with the state feedback case, there are fewer results dealing with output feedback finite-time stabilization. An interesting result was given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, where the finite-time stabilization of the double integrator systems was achieved by coupling a finite-time convergent observer with a finite-time control law. When the double integrator system is perturbed by a nonhomogeneous function, local finite-time stabilization was achieved by homogeneous output feedback.</p><p>In this note, we focus on the global finite-time stabilization by output feedback for a wider class of planar systems which are not necessarily linearly controllable/observable. The systems under consideration include the double integrator system as a special case and indeed cover a more general class of planar systems. We establish a sufficient condition under which the output feedback finite-time stabilization of the systems is achievable. The output feedback controller is comprised of a finite-time stabilizer, which is designed in the spirit of adding a power integrator <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, and a new observer with nonsmooth structure that distinguishes it from those observers used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. To overcome the difficulties in the stability analysis caused by the nonsmoothness of the observer, a more rigorous design process has to be used to select an appropriate gain that guarantees the finite-time convergence of the observer. One notable feature of our design scheme is that it is not based on the commonly used separation principle. On the contrary, the observer itself will not converge unless a controller is implemented.</p><p>The note is organized as follows. In Section II, we formulate the control objective of the note and give a sufficient condition for the existence of finite-time stabilizers using output feedback. The main result is contained in Section III, where a design algorithm is presented for the explicit construction of a reduced-order nonlinear observer as well as a nonsmooth state feedback control law. Examples are also included in the section to demonstrate the significance of our output feedback stabilization results. In Section IV, we discuss a special case when the planar system is a generalized double integrator system. A global result is achieved for a class of planar systems with nonhomogeneous nonlinearities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PROBLEM STATEMENT AND PRELIMINARIES</head><p>Throughout this note, we consider the following nonlinear system:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">_ x 1 = x p 2 + 1 (x 1 ) _ x 2 = u + 2 (x 1 ; x 2 ) y = x 1 (2.1)</formula><p>where i(1), i = 1; 2, are C 0 functions with i(0) = 0, i = 1; 2 and p 1 is an odd integer. The objective of the note is to find a continuous output feedback controller of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">_ z = (z; y); z2 IR u = u(z; y) (2.2)</formula><p>such that the closed-loop system (2.1)-(2.2) is globally stable, moreover, all the trajectories will converge to the origin in finite time <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p><p>To be more precise, we adopt the following definitions and the Lyapunov-like Theorem <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> for the finite-time stabilization. Consider _ y(t) = f (y(t))</p><p>(2.3)</p><p>where f : I R n ! IR n is continuous and f (0) = 0. Definition 2.1 (Finite-Time Stability): The zero solution of (2.3) is finite-time convergent if there are an open neighborhood U of the origin and a function T : U n f0g ! (0; 1), such that 8 x 0 2 U , every solution x(t; 0; x 0 ) of system (2.3) with x 0 as the initial condition is defined and x(t; 0; x0) 2 U n f0g for t 2 [0; T (x0)), and lim t!T (x ) x(t; 0; x 0 ) = 0. The zero solution of (2.3) is finite-time stable if it is Lyapunov stable and finite-time convergent. When U = IR n , then the zero solution is said to be globally finite-time stable. Theorem 2.2: Suppose there exist a C 1 positive-definite and proper function V : I R n ! IR and real numbers k &gt; 0 and 2 (0; 1), such that _ V + kV is negative semi-definite, where _ V (x) = (@V (x)=@x)f (x). Then, the origin is a globally finite-time stable equilibrium of (2.3).</p><p>To solve the problem of finite-time stabilization via output feedback for (2.1), we assume the following condition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assumption 2.3:</head><p>There is a ratio of odd integers h 2 (0; 1), such that for all x 1 ; x 2 2 IR j 1 (x 1 )j jx 1 j p=(p+10h) 1 (x 1 )</p><p>(2.4) j 2 (x 1 ; x 2 )j (jx 1 j h=(p+10h) + jx 2 j h ) 2 (x 1 )</p><p>(2.5)</p><p>where 1 (x 1 ) 0 and 2 (x 1 ) 0 are smooth functions.</p><p>Remark 2.4: It should be noted that for any C 1 function 1(x1) with 1 (0) = 0, growth condition (2.4) is automatically satisfied. As a matter of fact, by the C 1 property of the function j 1 (x 1 )j jx 1 j' 1 (x 1 ) jx 1 j p=(p+10h</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">) 1 + x 2 1 ' 1 (x 1 )</formula><p>where ' 1 (x 1 ) is a smooth function. Similarly, if 2 (1) is only a C 1 function of x1, condition (2.5) also holds automatically.</p><p>In the remainder of the section, we introduce three lemmas which will serve as bases for the development of an output feedback finitetime controller for (2.1). The first two lemmas are the key tools for adding a power integrator and their proofs can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p><p>Lemma 2.5: Let q 1 be an odd integer or a ratio of odd integers.</p><p>Then, the following inequality holds: ja 0 bj q 2 q01 ja q 0 b q j 8a 2 IR; b 2 IR: The next lemma plays a key role in constructing the observer for the planar systems.</p><p>Lemma 2.7: Let the real number r 2 (0; 1) be a ratio of odd inte- gers. Then, the following inequality holds for any real numbers 0 &lt; l &lt; 1 and t t r + (1 0 t) r + l 2 t 1+r (2 r 0 1)l 10r :</p><p>(2.6) Proof: When jtj 1, by the fact that the numerator of 1 + r is even, we have t r + (1 0 t) r + l 2 t 1+r t r + (1 0 t) r :</p><p>Calculating the minimum of t r + (1 0 t) r on the compact set ftj jtj 1g yields t r + (1 0 t) r + l 2 t 1+r</p><p>(2 r 0 1) l 10r (2 r 0 1); jtj 1: (2.7)</p><p>In the case when jtj &gt; 1, using Young's Inequality, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">t r + (1 0 t) r + l 2 t 1+r = [t r + (1 0 t) r ] (1+r)=2 2=(1+r) + [l 2 t 1+r ] (10r)=2 2=(10r) (t r + (1 0 t) r )t 10r (1+r)=2 l 10r : (2.8) Let f(t) = (t r + (1 0 t) r )t 10r : The time derivative of f(t) is f 0 (t) = 1 + 1 t 0 1 r 0 r t 1 t 0 1 r01 ; jtj &gt; 1:</formula><p>By using the following inequality (x r 0 1 &lt; r(x 0 1) for x &gt; 0, 0 &lt; r &lt; 1, [7, p. 40])</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">1 0 1 t 10r 0 1 &lt; 0(1 0 r) 1 t ; jtj &gt; 1 it can be shown that f 0 (t) = 1 + 1 t 0 1 r01 1 t 0 1 0 r t &lt; 1 0 1 t 0 1 r01 1 0 1 t 10r = 0 jtj &gt; 1:</formula><p>This, in turn, implies that f(t) is decreasing on (01; 01) and (1; 1). Consequently, f(t) minff (01); lim t!+1 f(t)g = minf2 r 0 1; rg: Applying the inequality 2 r 0 1 &lt; r(2 0 1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> yields f(t) 2 r 0 1. Therefore, when jtj &gt; 1, (2.8) can be estimated as t r + (1 0 t) r + l 2 t 1+r (2 r 0 1) (1+r)=2 l 10r (2 r 0 1)l 10r :</p><p>This, together with (2.7), implies that for any t, t r +(10t) r +l 2 t 1+r (2 r 0 1)l 10r .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. GLOBAL FINITE-TIME STABILIZATION BY C 0 OUTPUT FEEDBACK</head><p>In this section, we develop a constructive design method for an output feedback controller, which stabilizes (2.1) in finite time. The fundamental design tools are a modified version of the adding a power integrator technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and a nonsmooth one-dimensional nonlinear observer that is inspired by but substantially different from the one used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Due to the implementation of this nonsmooth observer, a rigorous design process has to be used to select an appropriate gain that guarantees the finite-time convergence of the closed-loop system.</p><p>The following theorem is the main result of the note. Theorem 3.1: Under Assumption 2.3, there is a continuous output feedback controller of the form shown in</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">_ z=0 @L(x ) @x [z + L(x 1 )] p=(p+10h) + 1 (x 1 ) u=u x 1 ; (z + L(x 1 )) 1=(p+10h) ; for a C 1 L(x 1 )</formula><p>(3.1) such that the closed-loop system (2.1)-(3.1) is globally finite-time stable.</p><p>Proof: The construction of output feedback finite-time stabilizer is accomplished by three steps. First, by modifying the adding a power integrator technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, a finite-time stabilizer is explicitly constructed using state feedback. Then, we reconstruct the one-dimensional observer proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> in such a way that the estimate of the unmeasurable state, with suitable gain and controller, will converge to the real value in finite time. Finally, we replace the unmeasurable state with the estimate recovered from the observer. An appropriate selection of the observer gain function will render the closed-loop system globally finite-time stable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Design of Finite-Time State Feedback Stabilizer</head><formula xml:id="formula_6">Let V1(x1) = (1=2)x 2 1 . Hence, by Assumption 2.3 _ V 1 x 1 x p 2 + x 1+p=(p+10h) 1 1 (x 1 ):</formula><p>Clearly, the C 0 virtual controller x 3p Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, we then construct the Lyapunov function</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">V 2 (x 1 ; x 2 ) = V 1 (x 1 ) + x x s p+10h 0 x 3(p+10h) 2 201=(p+10h)</formula><p>ds which can be proved to be C 1 , positive definite and proper by using similar proofs in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Moreover, it can be shown that @ @x 1 where N(x1) c1 @x 3(p+10h) 2 =@x1 is a smooth function.</p><p>Next, we estimate the terms in (3.2). First, by Lemmas 2.5 and 2.6, we have jx1 kx p 2 0 x 3p 2 j jx1j2 10p=(p+10h) j2j p=(p+10h) 1 6</p><p>x 1+p=(p+10h) 1 + 0 1+p=(p+10h) 2 for a constant 0 &gt; 0:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">(3.3)</formula><p>By the Young Inequality (Lemma 2.6), there is a smooth function</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">1 (x 1 ) 0 such that 2(x1)j2j 20(1=1+p0h) jx1j (h=1+p0h) 1 6 x 1+p=(p+10h) 1 + 1(x1) 1+p=(p+10h) 2 : (3.4)</formula><p>Note that by Lemma 2.5 , it is easy to see that jx 2 j jx 2 0 x 3 2 + jx 3 2 j 2 101=(p+10h) j2j 1=(p+10h)  + jx 1 j 1=(p+10h) 1=p (x 1 ):</p><p>Using this inequality and Lemma 2.6 , one has j 2 j 201=(p+10h) 2 (x 1 )jx 2 j h N 1 (x 1 )j 2 j 20(1=1+p0h) 2 j 2 j h=(p+10h) + jx 1 j h=(p+10h) 1</p><p>x 1+p=(p+10h) </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Nonlinear Observer Design</head><p>Motivated by the reduced-order observer in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, we now construct a one-dimensional nonsmooth compensator _ z = 0 @L(x 1 ) @x 1 ([z + L(x 1 )] p=(p+10h) + 1 (x 1 ))</p><p>(3.10)</p><p>where the nonlinear gain function L(x 1 ) with @L(x 1 )=@x 1 &gt; 1 will be determined later. Let + @L(x 1 ) @x 1 ([z + L(x 1 )] p=(p+10h) + 1 (x 1 )) 0 @L(x 1 ) @x 1 Next, we use Lemma 2.7 to estimate the last term in <ref type="bibr">(3.11)</ref>. When jej jx 2 j p0h juj + jx 2 j p0h j 2 (x 1 ; x 2 )j (p + 1 0 h) jej(juj p=h + jx 2 j p + jx 1 j p=(p+10h) ) 2 (x 1 )</p><p>for a smooth function 2(x1). Note that jx 2 j p (jx 2 0 x 3 2 j + jx 3 2 j) p (j2j p=(p+10h) + jx1j p=(p+10h) ) 2 2 (x 1 ) for a smooth function a1(x1) 0.</p><p>On the other hand, it can be shown using a similar argument to (3.14) that + e 1+p=(p+10h) a 1 (x 1 ) 0 (2 r 0 1) 2 k 10(3=4)(10h)=(1+p0h) e 1+p=(1+p0h) :</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">k 01=2 x 1+2p0h 2 k 01=2 c 2 (jx 2 0 x 3 2 j + jx 3 2 j) 1+2p0h c3k 01=2 1+p=(p+10h) 2 + k 01=2 b(x 1 )x 1+p=</formula><p>(3.17) C. Determination of the Observer Gain L(x 1 )</p><p>Since the state x 2 is not measurable, the state feedback controller x 2</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">1 + 2 2 (1+p=(p+10h))=2 + (e 2 ) (1+p=(p+10h))=2 c V (1+p=(p+10h))=2 2 + V (1+p=(p+10h)=2 3 c (V2 + V3) (1+p=(p+10h))=2</formula><p>for a positive constant c &gt; 0. With this in mind, it can be deduced from is globally finite-time stable. Moreover, for a given initial condition x0 the settling time T can be estimated as T V (x 0 ) 10 =(( c=4)(1 0 )).</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">(3.23) that _ V 2 + _ V 3 + c 4 (V 2 + V 3 ) (1+p=(p+10h))=2 0:</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 3.2:</head><p>The output feedback control scheme proposed in this note differs from the one in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> in two aspects: 1) Although it is inevitable that both state feedback controllers are nonsmooth due to the intrinsic obstacle caused by uncontrollable unstable linearization, the structure of the controller (3.18) is very different from the asymptotic state feedback stabilizer in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>; and 2) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the observer is still smooth although state feedback controller is nonsmooth. It is known that C 1 system has unique solution which conversely implies impossibility of finite-time convergence <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Therefore, to guarantee the finite-time convergence of the error dynamic, we introduce and implement a novel one-dimensional observer (3.10) that has a nonsmooth structure.</p><p>Remark 3.3: As pointed in the preceding remark, the observer has to be nonsmooth to guarantee the finite-time convergence of the observer. However, the nonsmoothness of the observer will make the stability analysis of the design process very difficult. To overcome the difficulty, a new tool, namely Lemma 2.7, is introduced to help us rigorously select a gain that guarantees the finite-time convergence of the observer.</p><p>In what follows, we show that Theorem 3.1 can be used to design an output feedback controller globally stabilizing the following system with uncontrollable unstable linearization in finite time. Due to the presence of the uncontrollable unstable linearization, the stabilization of (3.24) is very challenging. The state feedback stabilization has been solved using homogeneous controller (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>).</p><p>If we assume y = x1, the problem of output feedback stabilization of (3.24) is more difficult because of the unobservable linearization of the system. Recently, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> a nonsmooth output feedback controller was explicitly constructed to globally stabilize the system. However, the controller in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> is only an asymptotic stabilizer instead of a finite-time one. With the help of Theorem 3.1, now we are able to stabilize the system in finite-time using output feedback since 1(x1) = x1</p><p>satisfies Assumption 2.3 as illustrated in Remark 2.4.</p><p>The next example illustrates that our design method is applicable to nonhomogeneous system.</p><p>Example 3.5: Consider the following planar system: _ x 1 = x 3 2 + x 1 e x ; _ x 2 = u + ln 1 + x 2 2 ; y= x 1 : (3.25)</p><p>Apparently, (3.25) is not a homogeneous system. However, it is easy to verify that Assumption 2.3 is satisfied. Specifically, by mean-value theorem (with z = x 7=9</p><p>2 )</p><p>2 (x 1 ; x 2 ) = ln(1 + z 18=7 ) 18 denominator. This requirement can be removed by replacing function s a with sign(s)jsj a for any real number a &gt; 0. For instance, the new observer for any real number 0 &lt; h &lt; 1 will be _ z = 0 @L(x1) @x1 sign(z + L(x 1 ))jz + L(x 1 )j p=(p+10h) + 1 (x 1 ) :</p><p>Using this new function in the controller and observer, similar finitetime stabilization result can be achieved under Assumption 2.3 for any real number h 2 (0; 1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. SPECIAL CASE-FEEDBACK LINEARIZABLE SYSTEMS IN THE PLANE</head><p>When p = 1, the planar system (2.1) reduces to the following feed- interesting consequence which leads to a global solution to the problem of output feedback finite-time stabilization of (4.1). Corollary 4.1: Under Assumption 2.3 with p = 1, there is a continuous output feedback controller of the form shown in (4.2) at the bottom of the previous page, rendering (4.1) globally finite-time stable.</p><p>Proof: Apparently, (4.1) is a special case of (2.1) when p = 1 and, therefore, Corollary 4.1 is a direct consequence of Theorem 3.1.</p><p>This result is an extension of the previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> where an output feedback finite-time stabilizer was explicitly constructed for the double integrator system (i.e., i(1) = 0). Reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> also showed that local output feedback finite-time stabilization of (4.1) was achievable. As an extension, Corollary 4.1 provides a sufficient condition under which the nonlinear planar system (4.1) can be globally stabilized in finite time by output feedback. Moreover, the design method in this note is quite different from the homogeneous design in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and can be used to deal with nonhomogeneous systems.</p><p>In what follows, we use an example to illustrate that Corollary 4.1 can be used to deal with nonhomogeneous nonlinear systems.</p><p>Example 4.2: Consider the following uncertain planar system: V. CONCLUSION This note has addressed the problem of global finite-time stabilization via output feedback for a class of planar nonlinear systems. A sufficient condition has been established for the solvability of the problem. Moreover, a nonsmooth design methodology is presented for the explicit constructions of a reduced-order observer and a state feedback controller, which render the closed-loop systems globally finite-time stable. It is worthwhile pointing out that the design scheme proposed in this note, namely feedback domination, is quite different from the homogeneous methods used in most of the existing results.</p><p>As a special case, a global result on the output feedback finite-time stabilization of the double integrator perturbed by nonlinear functions is also presented in this note. Due to the use of the feedback domination design, we are able to achieve global result for a wider class of planar systems, which is not necessarily homogeneous.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Lemma 2 . 6 :</head><label>26</label><figDesc>Suppose n and m are two positive real numbers, and a 0, b 0 and 0 are continuous functions. Then, for any constant c &gt; 0 a n b m c 1 a n+m + m n + m n c(n + m) n=m b n+m (n+m)=m :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>2 =</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>c 1 = (2 0 1=(p + 1 0 h))2 101=(p+10h) and @ x 1 ) (p+10h)=p :With these in mind, it is not difficult to show that 2 j 20p=(p+10h) 2 jx 1 j h=(p+10h) + jx 2 j h 2 (x 1 )+ N(x1)j2j jx2j p + 1(x1)jx1j p=(p+10h) (3.2)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>1 + 2 ( 2 ( 3 . 5 ) 6 N 2 :</head><label>1223562</label><figDesc>x1) 1+p=(p+10h) for smooth functions N1(x1) 0 and 2(x1) 0. Similarly N(x1)j2kx2j p N2(x1)j2j 2 j2j p=(p+10h) + jx1j p=(p+10hN2(x1) 0 and 3(x1) 0. Finally, the last term in (3.2) can be estimated using Lemma 2.1(x1) + 2(x1) + 3(x1) + 4 (x 1 )) 1+p=(1+p0h)Now, it is clear that the continuous controller u</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>z + L(x 1 )) p=(p+10h) : Choose the Lyapunov function V 3 (e) = (e 2 =2). The time derivative of V3 is _ V3(e) = e(p + 1 0 h)x p0h 2 (u + 2(x1; x2)) 0ek(x 1 ) x p 2 + e 0 x 1+p0h 2 p=(p+10h) (3.11) where ((@L(x1))=@x1) := k(x1) &gt; 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>e 6 =</head><label>6</label><figDesc>0, substituting t = x 1+p0h 2 =e , r = p=(1 + p 0 h) and l = k 03=4 into (2.6) yields k 10(3=4)((10h)=(1+p0h)) e 1+p=(1+p0h) : (3.12)In addition, when e = 0, (3.12) holds automatically. Applying (32.3 and Lemma 2.6, it is easy to obtain e(p + 1 0 h)x p0h 2 (u + 2 (x 1 ; x 2 ))</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>2 2 (x 1 ) C 1 2 (x 1 )</head><label>211</label><figDesc>x 1 ) 0 is a smooth function. Thus e(p + 1 0 h)x p0h 2 (u + 2(x1; x2)) jej juj p=h + j2j p=(p+10h) + jx1j p=(p+10h) Applying Lemma 2.6 to the previous inequality yields e(p + 1 0 h)x p0h 2 (u + 2 (x 1 ; x 2 )) jekuj p=h + e 1+p=(p+10h) a1(x1)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>function b(x 1 ) and nonnegative constants c 2 , c 3 . Substituting (3.15)-(3.16) into (3.13) yields _ V 3 (e) jekuj p=h + x 1+p=(p+10h)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>( 3 . 8 )</head><label>38</label><figDesc>is not directly implementable. To get an implementable controller, we replace x2 in the controller (3.8) by (z + L(x1)) h=(p+10h) : x 1 ) (p+10h=p) h=(p+10h) (x 1 ) = 0 ( 2 0 e) h=(p+10h) (x 1 ): (3.18) Note that under this controller (3.18), jekuj p=h in (3.17) can be es- timated as follows: jekuj p=h cjej(j2j p=(p+10h) + jej p=(p+10h) ) p=h (x1) a 2 (x 1 )e 1+p=(1+p0h) hand, under the new controller (3.18), inequality (3.9) is no longer true. Instead, we have _ V 2 j u=u(x ;x ) 0x 1+p=(p+10hObviously, the choice of k(x1) such that k(x1) &gt; maxf4b(x1); 4c3; 1g and (2 r 0 1)k 10(3=4)(10h=1+p0h) a1(x1) + a2(x1) + a3(x1)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Therefore, by Theorem 2 . 2 (</head><label>22</label><figDesc>let V = V2 + V3 and = (1 + p=(p + 1 0 h))=2, the closed-loop system (2.1)-(3.10)-(3.18)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Example 3 . 4 :</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Consider the well-known benchmark system [10] _ x1 = x 3 2 + x1 _ x2 = u: (3.24)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>x 1 )j = jx 1 e x j jx 1 j 27=29 1 (x 1 )1(x1) = 1 + x 2 1 e x :Therefore, by Theorem 3.1, (3.25) is globally stabilizable in finite time by output feedback. Remark 3.6: For the sake of simplicity of the proof, we assume that h in Assumption 2.3 is a rational number with odd numerator and odd</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>is comprised of a double integrator perturbed by a lower triangular nonlinear vector field. In this case, Theorem 3.1 has the following _ z=0 @L(x ) @x [z + L(x1)] 1=(20h) + 1(x1) u=u x 1 ; (z + L(x 1 ))1=(20h) ;for a C 1 function L(x 1 )(4.2)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>3 )</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Due to the presence sin(u) in 2 (x 2 ; u), (4.3) is not homogeneous. On the other hand, it is easy to verify that Assumption 2.3 holds since 1(x1) = 0, 2(x1) = 1, and h = (7=9). By Corollary 4.1, (4.3) is globally finite-time stabilizable by output feedback. In fact, the output feedback controller can be constructed as follows: enough constant c &gt; 0.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors would like to thank the anonymous reviewers for many useful suggestions.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>mended by Associate Editor W. Kang. This work was supported in part by the National Science Foundation under Grant ECS-0239105.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Solving a Dynamic Resource Allocation Problem Through Continuous Optimization</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yingdong Lu</head><p>Abstract-A class of dynamic resource allocation problems with infinite planning horizon are studied. We observe special structures in the dynamic programming formulation of the problem, which enable us to convert it to continuous optimization problems that can be more easily solved. Structural properties of the problems are discussed, and explicit solutions are given for some special cases.</p><p>Index Terms-Dynamic programs, knapsack problems, optimization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Suppose that we have a fixed number of units W of certain resource available for demands that arrive at time epochs t = 1; 2; . . .. The composition of each demand arrival can be described by a random pair (P; Q), which represents the price and quantity. Random variable (P; Q) follows joint probability distribution f j (p), where j refers to the demand size qj and p the price. Also let Fj and F c j denote the cdf and ccdf of the price given that the demand size is q j . Manuscript received June 2, 2003; revised <ref type="bibr">July 11, 2004</ref>  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time stability of homogeneous systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bhat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Amer. Control Conf</title>
		<meeting>Amer. Control Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2513" to="2514" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuous finite-time stabilization of the translational and rotational double integrators</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="678" to="682" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-05">May 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time stability of continuous autonomous systems</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Control Optim</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="751" to="766" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic stability and feedback stabilization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brockett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Differential Geometric Control Theory</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brockett</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Millman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sussmann</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Birkäuser</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="191" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic stabilization of a class of smooth two dimensional systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dayawansa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Knowles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Control Optim</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1321" to="1349" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time controllers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Haimo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Control Optim</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="760" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Littlewood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pólya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<publisher>Cambidge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, U.K.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time stabilization and stabilizability of a class of controllable systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On an output feedback finite-time stabilization problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-02">Feb. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homogeneous stabilizing feedback laws</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kawski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Control Theory Adv. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="497" to="516" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A continuous feedback approach to global strong stabilization of nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1061" to="1079" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-07">Jul. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-Lipschitz continuous stabilizers for nonlinear systems with uncontrollable unstable linearizatiIon</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smooth output feedback stabilization of planar systems without controllable/observable linearization</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2068" to="2073" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-12">Dec. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonsmooth output feedback stabilization of a class of genuinely nonlinear systems in the plane</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1824" to="1829" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-10">Oct. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isochrone families for second order systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="1963-01">Jan. 1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On exponential observers for nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="325" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
