<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">On ordinal sums of triangular norms on bounded lattices ଁ</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2006-02-17">17 February 2006</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Susanne</forename><surname>Saminger</surname></persName>
							<email>susanne.saminger@jku.at.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Knowledge-Based Mathematical Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johannes Kepler University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>A-4040</postCode>
									<settlement>Linz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">On ordinal sums of triangular norms on bounded lattices ଁ</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2006-02-17">17 February 2006</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">811666F51E9C1E8528615364565EC869</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.fss.2005.12.021</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 4 August 2005; received in revised form 21 December 2005; accepted 23 December 2005 ଁ The support of COST Action 274 TARSKI and the framework CEEPUS SK-42 is gratefully acknowledged.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T15:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Triangular norm</term>
					<term>Ordinal sum</term>
					<term>Horizontal sum</term>
					<term>Bounded lattice</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Ordinal sums have been introduced in many different contexts, e.g., for posets, semigroups, t-norms, copulas, aggregation operators, or quite recently for hoops. In this contribution, we focus on ordinal sums of t-norms acting on some bounded lattice which is not necessarily a chain or an ordinal sum of posets. Necessary and sufficient conditions are provided for an ordinal sum operation yielding again a t-norm on some bounded lattice whereas the operation is determined by an arbitrary selection of subintervals as carriers for arbitrary summand t-norms. By such also the structure of the underlying bounded lattice is investigated. Further, it is shown that up to trivial cases there are no ordinal sum t-norms on product lattices in general.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Triangular norms were originally studied in the framework of probabilistic metric spaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> aiming at an extension of the triangle inequality and following some ideas of Menger <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. Later on, they turned out to be interpretations of the conjunction in many-valued logics <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>, in particular in fuzzy logics, where the unit interval serves as set of truth values.</p><p>Since triangular norms are special compact semigroups, the concept of ordinal sums in the sense of Clifford <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> provided a method to construct new triangular norms from given ones, but also led to the remarkable representation of continuous triangular norms as ordinal sums of isomorphic images of the product and the Łukasiewicz t-norm <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref>. For more results on triangular norms and ordinal sums see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> the unit interval was replaced by some more general structure, i.e., a bounded lattice, stimulating some investigations in topology <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37]</ref> and logic <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>. Therefore, it was quite natural to study triangular norms on bounded lattices <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref>, including special cases such as discrete chains <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> or the lattice L * = {(x, y) ∈ [0, 1] 2 | x + y 1} <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> for which also ordinal sum operations have been provided. It is worth mentioning that ordinal sum operations have also been introduced in the frameworks of, e.g., copulas <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, aggregation operators <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> or general algebraic structures such as hoops <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>. As such several types of ordinal sums are known in the literature and since many of these profit from or are based on a close relationship between the ordinal sum operation and the structure of the underlying lattice, it seemed quite natural to investigate this relationship in more detail, especially for t-norms on bounded lattices by also taking into account the concept of ordinal sums of posets (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>).</p><p>Therefore, we will focus our considerations on ordinal sum t-norms on bounded lattices which are defined through their restrictions to subintervals of the lattice and the lattice-infimum as such reflecting a kind of plug-in strategy for building new operations. On the other hand we investigate which types of lattices are appropriate candidates for allowing an arbitrary selection of the subintervals as well as an arbitrary selection of the corresponding t-norms but guaranteeing that the ordinal sum operation yields again a t-norm on the lattice. Therefore, we will concentrate in this contribution on ordinal sum t-norms built from summand t-norms only, although other summand operations could also be taken into account (compare also, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30]</ref>).</p><p>Note that due to the results of Clifford <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>, we know that an ordinal sum of semigroups (as introduced in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>) whose carriers are (bounded) lattices is again a semigroup with a carrier equal to the ordinal sum (in the sense of Birkhoff <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>) of the summand lattices. However, conversely, a straightforward application of Clifford's ordinal sum theorem to subsets of some fixed lattice L requires L to be an ordinal sum of its sublattices. But, and as we will show later, there exist ordinal sum t-norms on bounded lattices which are not an ordinal sum of some of their sublattices, i.e., ordinal sum t-norms on bounded lattices need not be ordinal sums in the sense of <ref type="bibr">Clifford.</ref> We investigate the problem by the following steps. The next section is dedicated to an overview on relevant concepts of ordinal sums, namely, ordinal sums in the sense of Birkhoff, in the sense of Clifford, as well as ordinal sums of t-norms on the unit interval. Section 3 briefly deals with t-norms on bounded lattices and introduces ordinal sum t-norms. In Section 4 we investigate such t-norms with one summand only first on some fixed subinterval then on an arbitrary subinterval revealing necessary and sufficient conditions concerning the underlying lattice. We close this section with a discussion about ordinal sum t-norms on product lattices. Subsequently, we generalize the results to ordinal sum t-norms with arbitrarily many summands in Section 5 and close this contribution by a short summary and further perspectives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">On some types of ordinal sums</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Ordinal sums in the sense of Birkhoff</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, Birkhoff provides a definition for building the ordinal sum X ⊕ Y of two disjoint posets X, Y . Due to the associativity of this construction we immediately extend this concept to families of pairwise disjoint posets for some linearly ordered index set (I, I ), I = ∅. Note that ordinal sums of disjoint posets in the sense of Birkhoff are also referred to as linear sums of posets <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Definition 2.1. Consider a linearly ordered index set (I, I ), I = ∅ and a family of pairwise disjoint posets (X i , i ) i∈I . The ordinal sum i∈I X i is defined as the set i∈I X i equipped with the following order</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">x y :⇔ (∃i ∈ I : x, y ∈ X i ∧ x i y) ∨ (∃i, j ∈ I : x ∈ X i ∧ y ∈ X j ∧ i ≺ I j).</formula><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">)<label>1</label></formula><p>If necessary, we will refer to such ordinal sums as ordinal sums in the sense of Birkhoff explicitly.</p><p>Since the order relation for elements from different summand carriers is inherited from the linearly ordered index set, ordinal sums formally minimize the number of incomparable elements of a poset with carrier i∈I X i which extends the posets (X i , i ). As such ordinal sums of posets are in general not symmetric, i.e., X ⊕ Y = Y ⊕ X.</p><p>Note that based on the linear order of the index set (I, I ) and the order on i∈I X i defined by (1) the condition of pairwise disjointness can be even relaxed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 2.2. Consider some linearly ordered index set (I, I ) and a family of posets</head><formula xml:id="formula_2">(X i , i ) i∈I . If for all i, j ∈ I with X i ∩ X j = A = ∅ it holds that (A, i ) = (A, j ), X i = (X i \ A) ⊕ A, X j = A ⊕ (X j \ A)</formula><p>, and for each k ∈ I either k I i ≺ I j or i ≺ I j I k, then there exists some index set K and a family of pairwise disjoint posets (X k , k ) k∈K such that • for each k ∈ K there exists some i ∈ I with X k ⊆ X i and • the ordinal sum k∈K X k is isomorphic to the poset ( i∈I X i , ) where is defined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</p><p>Note that the strategy just described focusses on the union of the carriers and an order compatible with the order of the underlying posets. Another possible way for introducing ordinal sums of non pairwise disjoint sets is to replace each X i by (i, X i ) and thus creating isomorphic but pairwise disjoint sets for which the ordinal sum construction in the sense of Birkhoff can be applied. We will follow our approach since it does not lead to multiple copies of elements common in several posets. Especially, for two intervals which overlap in at most one point we introduce the following concept of ordinal sums of intervals.</p><p>In case that (X, X ) has a smallest and a largest element, a X resp. b X , we denote X by [a X , b X ] = {x ∈ X | a X X x X b X } and use notions of other types of intervals accordingly. </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">x y :⇔ (∃i ∈ I : x, y ∈ [a i , b i ] ∧ x i y) ∨ (∃i, j ∈ I : x i b i ∧ a j j y ∧ i ≺ j).</formula><p>If necessary, we refer to this kind of ordinal sum as ordinal sum of intervals.</p><p>So far, we have discussed ordinal sums of posets focussing on the preservation or the construction of an order relation on the union of sets. We now turn to ordinal sums of semigroups and therefore shifting the focus from orders to operations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Ordinal sums in the sense of Clifford</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>, ordinal sums have been introduced in the context of abstract semigroups aiming at a construction of a new semigroup from a given family of semigroups. The basic idea is to extend an ordinally ordered system of non-overlapping semi-groups into a single semigroup whose carrier equals the union of the original carriers. Definition 2.4 <ref type="bibr">(Clifford [5]</ref>). Let (I, ), I = ∅ be a linearly ordered index set, (X i ) i∈I a family of pairwise disjoint sets, and (G i ) i∈I with G i = (X i , * i ) a family of semigroups. Put X = i∈I X i and define the binary operation * on X by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">x * y = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ x * i y if (x, y) ∈ X i × X i , x if (x, y) ∈ X i × X j and i ≺ j, y if (x, y) ∈ X i × X j and i j.</formula><p>Then we say that (X, * ) is the ordinal sum of all (X i , * i ) i∈I . If necessary, we refer to this type of ordinal sum as ordinal sum in the sense of Clifford.</p><p>Proposition 2.5 <ref type="bibr">(Clifford [5]</ref>). With all the assumptions of the previous definition the ordinal sum (X, * ) is also a semigroup, i.e., * is an associative operation on X.</p><p>Note that ordinality in the sense of Clifford refers to the linear order of the index set I involved. The elements of some X i , i ∈ I , need not fulfill any special order relation. On the other hand, taking into account that equality is an order relation on any set we immediately can state the following corollary.</p><p>Corollary 2.6. Any ordinal sum in the sense of Clifford can be expressed as an associative operation on an ordinal sum of a family of sets in the sense of Birkhoff.</p><p>The semigroup operation * on X is linked to the order structure of the index set and therefore also to the order of the deduced ordinal sum in the sense of <ref type="bibr">Birkhoff.</ref> Similar as in the case of ordinal sums of Birkhoff the condition of disjointness can be and has been relaxed in the case of ordinal sums in the sense of Clifford.</p><p>Proposition 2.7 <ref type="bibr">(Clifford [5]</ref>). Let (I, ), I = ∅ be a linearly ordered set, (X i ) i∈I a family of sets, and (G i ) i∈I with G i = (X i , * i ) a family of semigroups.</p><p>Assume that for all i, j ∈ I with i ≺ j the sets X i and X j are either disjoint or that X i ∩ X j = {x ij }, where x ij is both the unit element of G i and the annihilator of G j , and where for each k ∈ I with i ≺ k ≺ j we have X k = {x ij }. Put X = i∈I X i and define the binary operation * on X by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">x * y = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ x * i y if (x, y) ∈ X i × X i , x if (x, y) ∈ X i × X j and i ≺ j, y if (x, y) ∈ X i × X j and i j.</formula><p>Then (X, * ) is a semigroup.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Ordinal sums of t-norms on the unit interval</head><p>We now concentrate on a special class of semigroups with carrier [0, 1], namely t-norms which are commutative semigroups, non-decreasing in each coordinate and having 1 as neutral element. </p><formula xml:id="formula_6">= ( a i , b i , T i ) i∈I : [0, 1] 2 → [0, 1] is given by T (x, y) = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ a i + (b i -a i )T i x -a i b i -a i , y -a i b i -a i if (x, y) ∈ [a i , b i ] 2 , min(x, y) otherwise.</formula><p>If necessary, we refer to this type of ordinal sums as ordinal sums of t-norms.</p><p>Note that some differences to previous definitions can be stressed:</p><p>• The carrier of the ordinal sum is the unit interval [0, 1] which in general need not equal the union of all [a i , b i ], i ∈ I of the family of intervals involved. • The members of the family of t-norms (T i ) i∈I are not acting on the subdomains [a i , b i ], but on [0, 1].</p><p>According to the fact that all [a i , b i ] ⊆ [0, 1] and all a i as well as b i are ordered by the natural order on R an index set J , J = ∅ and a family of intervals [a j , b j ] can be found such that [0, 1] = j ∈J [a j , b j ] (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>). On each [a j , b j ] associative operations * j can be defined either as isomorphic, in fact linear, transformations of the corresponding t-norms or by the minimum such that in this case the ordinal sum of t-norms is just an ordinal sum in the sense of Clifford. Note that such an ordinal sum of t-norms yields again a t-norm. Moreover, any continuous triangular norm on the unit interval is an ordinal sum of t-norms in the sense above where each summand t-norm is isomorphic either to the product or the Łukasiewicz t-norm <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Triangular norms on bounded lattices</head><p>Extensions of triangular norms on lattices in the framework of fuzzy sets and fuzzy logic (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>) always require the top resp. bottom element of L to play the role of a neutral element resp. of an annihilator. Therefore, we concentrate on bounded lattices L only with top and bottom elements, denoted by 1 and 0, respectively, in the sequel. Definition 3.1. Consider some bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 1, 0) and denote by L the corresponding lattice order. A binary operation T : L 2 → L is called a triangular norm (t-norm) on L if the following conditions are fulfilled for all x, y, z ∈ L:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">(i) T (x, y) = T (y, x), (commutativity) (ii) T (x, z) L T (y, z) whenever x L y, (monotonicity) (iii) T (x, 1) = x, (neutral element) (iv) T (</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>x, T (y, z)) = T (T (x, y), z).</head><p>(associativity)</p><p>Note that the structure of the lattice L heavily influences which and how many t-norms on L can be defined. However, for each lattice L there exist at least two t-norms, i.e., the minimum T L M (x, y) = x ∧ y and the drastic product</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">T L D (x, y) = x ∧ y if 1 ∈ {x, y}, 0 otherwise,</formula><p>which are always the greatest and smallest possible t-norms on that lattice L. Observe that up to the trivial cases when |L| 2, we always have T L D = T L M . In case that |L| = 2, there is a unique t-norm on L which is, in fact, the standard boolean conjunction. Finally, if |L| = 1, there is only one binary operation on L.</p><p>Classical t-norms are then just t-norms on the lattice ([0, 1], ∧, ∨, 1, 0). The intervals [a i , b i ], i ∈ I , used as carriers for the ordinal sum of t-norms are subintervals with bottom element a i and top element b i . The isomorphic transformations of t-norms are t-norms on these subintervals in the sense of the definition above.</p><p>We turn to ordinal sums of t-norms on an arbitrary lattice L. Since each of its summands is described by a sublattice L i of L and a t-norm T i acting on that sublattice, the sublattice has to possess a largest element acting as the neutral element of the t-norm involved and a smallest element acting as its annihilator. Moreover, monotonicity of the final operation should be provided such that appropriate candidates for such sublattices are intervals [a, b] = {x ∈ L | a L x L b} with a L b (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>). Therefore, we define ordinal sums of t-norms on lattices in the following way. Definition 3.2. Consider some lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) and some linearly ordered index set I . Further, let (]a i , b i [) i∈I be a family of pairwise disjoint subintervals of L and (T [a i ,b i ] ) i∈I a family of t-norms on the corresponding intervals</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">([a i , b i ]) i∈I . Then the ordinal sum T = ( a i , b i , T [a i ,b i ] ) i∈I : L 2 → L is given by T (x, y) = T [a i ,b i ] (x, y) if x, y ∈ [a i , b i ] , x ∧ y otherwise.<label>(2)</label></formula><p>In the sequel we concentrate on conditions such that an operation T : L 2 → L defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">2</ref>) is a t-norm on the lattice L.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Ordinal sums with one summand only</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Ordinal sums with one summand only on some fixed subinterval</head><p>Consider some bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 1, 0) and fix some subinterval [a, b] = {x ∈ L | a L x L b}, with L the lattice order. Further assume a t-norm T [a,b] </p><formula xml:id="formula_10">on [a, b]. Then T : L 2 → L defined by T (x, y) = T [a,b] (x, y) if x, y ∈ [a, b] , x ∧ y otherwise. (<label>3</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">)</formula><p>is an ordinal sum ( a, b, T [a,b] ) of T [a,b] on L with one summand only. By this the following questions arise quite naturally:</p><p>• For which lattices L is T defined by Eq. (3) a t-norm for arbitrary t-norms T [a,b] on [a, b]?</p><p>• If T defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm for arbitrary t-norms T [a,b] on <ref type="bibr">[a, b]</ref>, what do we know about the structure of the underlying lattice L? • Do we end up with the same answers to the previous two questions?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1.">From lattices to t-norms</head><p>The following lemma provides a partial answer to the first question.  Commutativity holds due to the commutativity of ∧ and T [a,b] . It is also straightforward to show that 1 is the neutral element of T . The preservation of associativity is a direct consequence of Clifford's theorem on ordinal sums of semigroups (see also Proposition 2.7).</p><p>Finally, monotonicity is preserved due to the monotonicity of T </p><formula xml:id="formula_12">T (x, z) = T [a,b] (x, z) L T [a i ,b i ] M (x, z) L z = y ∧ z = T (y, z). Secondly, if x &lt; L a and y, z ∈ [a, b] then T (x, z) = x ∧ z = x L a L T [a,b] (y, z) = T (y, z).</formula><p>Therefore, T defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm independently of the choice of T [a,b] </p><formula xml:id="formula_13">on [a, b].</formula><p>The previous proposition only provides a sufficient and not a necessary condition for T being a t-norm, as the following example shows.  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) and is, moreover, a t-norm although L is not an ordinal sum of intervals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2.">From t-norms to the structure of the lattice</head><p>Before turning to necessary and sufficient conditions for T defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) being a t-norm we prove some basic lemmata revealing insight into the structure of the underlying lattice. Note that throughout this section we consider some bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) and a fixed subinterval [a, b] of L. Lemma 4.3. Assume that T defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm for arbitrary T [a,b] </p><formula xml:id="formula_14">on [a, b] and choose x ∈ L arbitrarily. If there exists some u ∈ [a, b[ such that x L u then x ∈ [0, a] or x ∈ [a, b], i.e., x is comparable to a.</formula><p>Proof. Assume that T defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm for arbitrary T [a,b]  </p><formula xml:id="formula_15">a ∧ x = T (a, x) = T (T [a,b] (u, u), x) = T (T (u, u), x) = T (u, T (u, x)) = T (u, u ∧ x) = T (u, x) = x,</formula><p>being equivalent to x L a and contradicting the assumption of incomparability of x to a.</p><p>Note that the previous lemma is equivalent to the following corollary focusing on the incomparability to a. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D</head><p>and is therefore associative the following equation is fulfilled</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">u = T [a,b] (b, u) = T (b, x ∧ u) = T (b, T (x, u)) = T (T (b, x), u) = T (b ∧ x, u) = T [a,b] (b ∧ x, u) = a contradicting that u ∈ ]a, b] and showing that x has to be incomparable to all u ∈ ]a, b] in case that it is incomparable to b.</formula><p>Note that the previous lemma also implies that if x is incomparable to b and there exists some u ∈ [a, b] to which x can be compared, it follows necessarily that u = a.</p><p>Lemma 4.1 shows that if the underlying lattice can be described as an ordinal sum of intervals, any ordinal sum with summands according to these intervals is again a t-norm.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.3.">Necessary and sufficient conditions</head><p>The following theorem provides necessary and sufficient conditions for an ordinal sum being a t-norm and providing insight into the structure of the underlying lattice. (i) The ordinal sum T : L 2 → L defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm for arbitrary T [a,b] </p><formula xml:id="formula_17">on [a, b]. (ii) For all x ∈ L it holds that (a) if x is incomparable to a, then it is incomparable to all u ∈ [a, b[, (b) if x is incomparable to b, then it is incomparable to all u ∈ ]a, b].</formula><p>Proof. Consider a bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) and a subinterval [a, b] of L. The necessity follows directly from Lemma 4.5 and Corollary 4.4.</p><p>For proving the sufficiency, the claim is trivially fulfilled if [a, b] = {a, b}, since then T = T L M . Therefore, we assume that ]a, b[ = ∅, i.e., there exists some u ∈ L such that a &lt; L u &lt; L b.</p><p>Commutativity holds due to the commutativity of ∧ and T [a,b] . It is also straightforward to show that 1 is the neutral element of T .</p><p>Monotonicity: Monotonicity is preserved due to the monotonicity of T [a,b] on [a, b] and the monotonicity of ∧ on the lattice L in all cases but one, namely if x / ∈ [a, b] and y ∈ [a, b] with x L y. We have to show that T (x, z) L T (y, z) is fulfilled for all z ∈ [a, b] and x, y as described just before.</p><p>If x &lt; a and y, z ∈ [a, b] it holds that</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">T (x, z) = x ∧ z L a ∧ z = a L T [a,b] (y, z) = T (y, z).</formula><p>In case that x is incomparable to a and therefore to all </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>T (T (x, y), z) = T (x, y) ∧ z = T (x, y) = T (x, y ∧ z) = T (x, T (y, z)).</head><p>Similarly, if x L z or y L z, z is comparable to all [a, b] and z L a such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">T (T (x, y), z) = T (x, y) ∧ z = z = x ∧ z = T (x, y ∧ z) = T (x, T (y, z)).</formula><p>In case that z is incomparable to x and y it holds that u ∧ z = a ∧ z for all u ∈ [a, b[.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>T (T (x, y), z) = T (x, y)</head><formula xml:id="formula_20">∧ z = a ∧ z = x ∧ a ∧ z = T (x, y ∧ z) = T (</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>x, T (y, z)).</head><p>The remaining cases can be shown analogously such that associativity is proven.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Ordinal sums with one summand on arbitrary subintervals</head><p>The previous results deal with t-norms on some fixed subinterval. How does L look like if T defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm not only for arbitrary t-norms T [a,b] but also for arbitrary subintervals [a, b]?</p><p>Recall that a bounded poset (X, , 0, 1) is called a horizontal sum of the bounded posets ((X i , i , 0, 1)) i∈I if X = i∈I X i with X i ∩ X j = {0, 1} whenever i = j , and x y if and only if there is an i ∈ I such that {x, y} ⊆ X i and x i y (compare, e.g., horizontal sums of effect algebras <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>). Theorem 4.9. Let (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) be a bounded lattice. Then the following are equivalent:</p><p>(i) for any [a, b] ⊆ L and any t-norm T [a,b] the ordinal sum operation T on L given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm on L, (ii) for all x, y ∈ L: {x ∧ y, x ∨ y} ⊆ {0, 1, x, y}, (iii) L is a horizontal sum of chains.</p><p>Proof. The equivalence of (ii) and (iii) is obvious.</p><p>(i)⇒(ii): Assume that T defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm for an arbitrary subinterval [a, b] and an arbitrary t-norm T [a,b]  The theorem shows under which condition a kind of plug-in strategy for building t-norms can be applied. Provided that the lattice is describable as a disjoint union of chains with some common bottom and top element we can choose any subinterval of the lattice and plug-in arbitrary t-norm on that subinterval such that the final operation is still a t-norm on the original lattice.</p><p>Example 4.10. Consider the lattice L = {0, a, b, c, 1} as displayed in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">3</ref> then the following cases can be distinguished:</p><p>• For any interval <ref type="bibr">[u, v]</ref> which consists of at most of two elements T [u,v] is clearly T [u,v]   M and as such T = T L M trivially a t-norm.</p><p>• For any [u, v] ⊇ {a, b} and for any t-norm T [u,v]  </p><formula xml:id="formula_21">M also T = T [0,1] M . For T [a,1] = T [a,1] D we get T (T (c, c), b) = T (a, b) = 0 = b = T (c, b) = T (c, T (c, b)),</formula><p>and therefore associativity is violated.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_22">T (0,0) (0,1) (1,0) (1,1) (0,0) (0,0) (0,0) (0,0) (0,0) (0,1) (0,0) (0,0) (0,1) (1,0) (0,0) (0,0) (1,0) (1,1) (0,0) (0,1) (1,0) (1,1)</formula><p>with ∈ {(0, 0), (0, 1)} Example 4.11. Consider the poset</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">L = {(-1, -1), (1, 1), (-x, 1 -x), (x, x -1) | x ∈ ]0, 1[}</formula><p>equipped with the product order on R 2 . It is a lattice with top element (1, 1) and bottom element (-1, -1). Moreover, it is a suitable candidate for defining ordinal sum t-norms ( a, b, T [a,b] ) for arbitrary subintervals [a, b] and arbitrary t-norms T [a,b] on [a, b], since removing the top and the bottom element leads to two disjoint chains of incomparable elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Ordinal sums on special bounded lattices</head><p>Motivated by the last example we may ask whether there are ordinal sum t-norms on product lattices with the order on the product lattice being defined coordinate-wisely. Taking into account Theorem 4.9 we know that subintervals of the product lattice and t-norms on it can be chosen arbitrarily if and only if the product lattice without top and bottom element is a disjoint union of chains. In fact, these are just product lattices which are either isomorphic to a chain, i.e., all factor lattices are singletons up to one which forms a chain, or they are isomorphic to the product lattice {0, 1} × {0, 1}, i.e., all factors are singletons up to two containing exactly two elements.</p><p>In the first case any t-norm on the quite trivial product lattice acts as a corresponding t-norm on the chain. In the second case, there exists no subinterval of the product lattice containing more than two elements besides the product lattice itself. Therefore there exist only four different t-norms on {0, 1} × {0, 1} which are displayed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Note that the values of T ((0, 1), (0, 1)) and T ((1, 0), (1, 0)) can be chosen independently of each other. Due to the incomparability of the involved elements monotonicity is not violated.</p><p>We have seen by the previous remark that ordinal sum t-norms consisting of a summand with an arbitrary subinterval as well as an arbitrary t-norm on the subinterval are possible just for very trivial product lattices. Therefore, is it possible to build an ordinal sum t-norm on a more complex product lattice taking into account not arbitrary but some special subinterval? Proposition 4.12. Consider some lattices (L i , ∧ i , ∨ i , 0 i , 1 i ), i ∈ {1, . . . , n}, n ∈ N, n 2 with |L i | &gt; 1 for all i and the corresponding product lattice L = n i=1 L i . The order on the product lattice is defined coordinate-wisely, i.e., (a</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">1 , . . . , a n ) L (b 1 , . . . , b n ) if and only if a i L i b i for all i ∈ {1, . . . , n}. An interval [a, b] = n i=1 [a i , b i</formula><p>] and an arbitrary t-norm T [a,b] on that interval lead to an ordinal sum t-norm T on L as defined by Eq. (3) if and only if either</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">[a, b] = L or ]a, b[ = ∅.</formula><p>Proof. Assume lattices (L i , ∧ i , ∨ i , 0 i , 1 i ) as given above and the corresponding product lattice L as well as some interval</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">[a, b] = n i=1 [a i , b i ]. If [a, b] = L or ]a, b[ = ∅</formula><p>, the ordinal sum T : L 2 → L defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is clearly a t-norm for arbitrary T [a,b]   <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm for arbitrary T [a,b] . Due to the structure of [a, b] there necessarily exists some k ∈ {1, . . . , n} such that [a k , b k ] = L k and some u = (u 1 , . . . , u n ) ∈ ]a, b[ and that there exist further some l, m ∈ {1, . . . , n} not necessarily different from each other or from k such that the following conditions are fulfilled:</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">• 0 k &lt; L k a k or b k &lt; L k 1 k due to the fact that [a k , b k ] = L k , • a l &lt; L l u l and u m &lt; L m b m because of u being an interior element of [a, b].</formula><p>We assume first that 0 k &lt; L k a k and recall that a, u, b and some arbitrary x ∈ L are given by b = (b 1 , . . . , b k , . . . , b l , . . . , b m , . . . , b n ), u = (u 1 , . . . , u k , . . . , u l , . . . , u m , . . . , u n ), a = (a 1 , . . . , a k , . . . , a l , . . . , a m , . . . , a n ), x = (x 1 , . . . , x k , . . . , x l , . . . , x m , . . . , x n ),</p><p>We distinguish different cases for k, l and m and show that for all possibilities we find two elements of L contradicting the incomparability conditions of Theorem 4.8. </p><formula xml:id="formula_28">k = l: Choose x ∈ L such that x k = 0 k , x l = u l and x i = a i for all i ∈ {1, . . . , n} \ {k, l}. Since 0 k &lt; L k a k L k u k , as well as x l = u l &gt; L l a l and u i L i a i = x i , x is incomparable to a but fulfills x L u with u ∈ ]a,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">k &lt; L k a k &lt; L k u k &lt; L k b k L k 1 k form a sub-chain of L k .</formula><p>Since the number n of lattices involved in the product lattice is at least two, n 2, we know that there exists some further j ∈ {1, . . . , n} such that [a j , b j ] ⊆ L j with |L j | &gt; 1.</p><p>Assume that a j = b j , i.e., a j &lt; L j b j . We choose x, y ∈ L by x = (a 1 , . . . a k-1 , 0 k , a k+1 , . . . , a j -1 , b j , a j +1 , . . . , a n ), y = (a 1 , . . . a k-1 , a k , a k+1 , . . . , a j -1 , b j , a j +1 , . . . , a n ), then again y ∈ ]a, b[, x L y but x being incomparable to a leading to a contradiction to Theorem 4.8.</p><p>If a j = b j then either 0 j &lt; L j a j or b j &lt; L j 1 j . In the first case, we build x, y ∈ L by x = (a 1 , . . . a k-1 , u k , a k+1 , . . . , a j -1 , 0 j , a j +1 , . . . , a n ), y = (a 1 , . . . a k-1 , u k , a k+1 , . . . , a j -1 , u j , a j +1 , . . . , a n ), then y ∈ ]a, b[, x L y but x being incomparable to a. In the second case, choose x, y ∈ L by x = (a 1 , . . . a k-1 , u k , a k+1 , . . . , a j -1 , 1 j , a j +1 , . . . , a n ), y = (a 1 , . . . a k-1 , u k , a k+1 , . . . , a j -1 , b j , a j +1 , . . . , a n ), then y ∈ ]a, b[, x L y but x being incomparable to b such that both cases contradict Theorem 4.8.</p><p>In case that b k &lt; L k 1 k , elements x, y ∈ L contradicting the incomparability conditions of Theorem 4.8 can be constructed in an analogous way.</p><p>Note that the previous proposition just provides insight why the method of building ordinal sum t-norms is, up to some trivial cases, not appropriate for creating t-norms on product lattices. However, there exist several other ways for defining t-norms on such lattices, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref>. Remark 4.13. Similar arguments hold for the case of t-norms on the lattice (L * , ∧, ∨,</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">0 L * , 1 L * ) with L * = {(x 1 , x 2 ) | (x 1 , x 2 ) ∈ [0, 1] 2 ∧ x 1 + x 2 1}</formula><p>, the join and the meet operation defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">(x 1 , x 2 ) ∧ (y 1 , y 2 ) = (min(x 1 , y 1 ), max(x 2 , y 2 )), (x 1 , x 2 ) ∨ (y 1 , y 2 ) = (max(x 1 , y 1 ), min(x 2 , y 2 ))</formula><p>for arbitrary (x 1 , x 2 ), (y 1 , y 2 ) ∈ L * , and bottom and top element given by 0 L * = (0, 1) resp. 1 L * = (1, 0).</p><p>As one can see immediately the removal of the bottom and top element from the lattice does not lead to a disjoint union of chains expressing that no ordinal sum t-norm in the sense of Definition 3.2 can be built on L * . Moreover, if some subinterval is fixed, elements contradicting the incomparability condition of Theorem 4.8 can in general be found similar as before in the case of product lattices. Surely there exist other strategies for defining t-norms on L * being inspired by a kind of plug-in strategy, i.e., by using transformations and projections of t-norms on L * as been carried out in, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Ordinal sums with more summands</head><p>Theorems 4.8 and 4.9 deal with ordinal sums with one summand either based on some arbitrary or fixed subinterval. We now extend these results to ordinal sums with more summands (see Definition 3.2) and end up again with a close relationship between the structure of the underlying lattice and the operation defined on that lattice. Proof. Consider some bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) and some linearly ordered index set (I, ), I = ∅. If T defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">2</ref>) is a t-norm for arbitrary summands, then for sure also for only one arbitrary summand leading to L being a horizontal sum of chains due to Theorem 4.9.</p><p>On the other hand, suppose that L is a horizontal sum of chains. We want to show that T : L 2 → L defined by Furthermore, the neutral element of T is obviously 1, leaving associativity and monotonicity to be proven.</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">T (x, y) = T [a i ,b i ] if x, y ∈ [a i , b i ] , x ∧ y otherwise,</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Monotonicity:</head><p>We have to show that whenever x L y holds then T (x, z) L T (y, z) for all z ∈ L. Consider some x, y ∈ L and assume that x L y. If x = 0 or y = 1 the inequality is trivially fulfilled for arbitrary z ∈ L.</p><p>Therefore, suppose that x, y ∈ L \ {0, 1}. Since L \ {0, 1} is a disjoint union of chains and x L y by assumption, x and y have to belong to one of theses chains, i.e., x, y ∈ C * for some chain C * ⊆ L \ {0, 1}.</p><p>For all z ∈ L \ C * the above inequality is trivially fulfilled since T (x, z) = 0 = T (y, z) due to the incomparability of x and z, resp. y and z.</p><p>If z ∈ C * ∪ {0, 1} monotonicity can be proven analogously to Lemma 4.1 by describing C * ∪ {0, 1} as an ordinal sum of intervals in the following way: Choose</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">a = {a i | i ∈ I, a i ∈ C * } and b = {b i | i ∈ I, b i ∈ C * }. Then C * ∪ {0, 1} = [0, a] ⊕ [a, b] ⊕ [b, 1</formula><p>] is an ordinal sum of intervals and T acts as an ordinal sum t-norm with one summand on that domain.</p><p>Associativity: We have to prove that T (x, T (y, z)) = T (T (x, y), z) is fulfilled for arbitrary x, y, z ∈ L. If one of the arguments is equal to 0 or 1 the equality is trivially fulfilled, such that we assume x, y, z ∈ L \ {0, 1} arbitrarily. In case that all three arguments belong to the same chain C * associativity can be shown again analogously to Lemma 4.1 by describing C * as an ordinal sum of intervals as mentioned before. In case that at least one of the arguments is from some other sub-chain associativity is trivially fulfilled since T (x, T (y, z)) = 0 = T (T (x, y), z).</p><p>In case that L is a chain, the previous propositions show immediately that the subintervals and the t-norms on them can be chosen arbitrarily up to the fact that the subintervals have to have pairwise disjoint interiors. In any case T defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">2</ref>) is surely a t-norm on L. The previous proposition emphasizes again the special role of the so-called horizontal sum in case that the family of subintervals can be chosen arbitrarily.</p><p>In case that the family of subintervals is fixed we get the following necessary and sufficient conditions, being in fact a direct generalization of Theorem 4.8. Proposition 5.2. Consider some bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1), some linearly ordered index set (I, ≤), I = ∅ and a family of pairwise disjoint subintervals (]a i , b i [) i∈I of L. Then the following are equivalent:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">(i) The ordinal sum T : L 2 → L defined by Eq. (2) is a t-norm for arbitrary T [a i ,b i ] on [a i , b i ].</formula><p>(ii) For all x ∈ L and for all i ∈ I it holds that (a) if x is incomparable to a i , then it is incomparable to all u ∈ [a i , b i [, (b) if x is incomparable to b i , then it is incomparable to all u ∈ ]a i , b i ].</p><p>Proof. Fix some bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) and a family of pairwise disjoint subintervals (]a i , b i [) i∈I of L w.r.t. some linearly ordered index set I . The necessity of the proposition is a direct result of Theorem 4.8 since by assumption that T is a t-norm for arbitrary T [a i ,b i ] on [a i , b i ] we can choose T [a i 0 ,b i 0 ] arbitrarily for some i 0 ∈ I and for all other i = i 0 we define T [a i ,b i ] = T [a,b]   M fulfilling the necessary conditions of Theorem 4.8. For proving the sufficiency assume that T is defined by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">2</ref>) and all x ∈ L fulfill the incomparability conditions for all i ∈ I . Commutativity again holds due to the commutativity of ∧ and all T [a i ,b i ] , i ∈ I as well as 1 is clearly the neutral element of T . Monotonicity is fulfilled in most cases due to the monotonicity of ∧. The remaining cases can be proven analogously to the proof of Theorem 4.8. Similarly, regarding associativity, note that T (T (x, y), z) = T (x, T (y, z)) = x ∧ y ∧ z is fulfilled up to the case where at least two elements involved are from the same subinterval [a i , b i ], which in turn can be proven analogously to the proof of Theorem 4.8.</p><p>Remark 5.3. Remember that in case of ordinal sum t-norms on the unit interval with summands based on some fixed family of subintervals ([a i , b i ]) i∈I , the unit interval could be described as an ordinal sum of some family ([a j , b j ]) j ∈J being a covering of ([a i , b i ]) i∈I .</p><p>In the case of ordinal sum t-norms on some lattice L w.r.t. some fixed family of subintervals ([a i , b i ]) i∈I there exists a family of chains (C j ) j ∈J , pairwise disjoint up to their boundaries, not necessarily forming a covering of ([a i , b i ]) i∈I , such that all [a i , b i ] and L itself can be constructed by applying either the ordinal sum or the horizontal sum construction principle to these chains resp. such built intervals consecutively. We would like to illustrate this by the following examples. As such we denote by C 1 ∪h C 2 the horizontal sum built as the disjoint union of C 1 and C 2 with identifying their bottom and top elements. Note that for any t-norm T [0, c] on [0, c], T defined by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>) is a t-norm on L.</p><p>• Similarly {0, 1} 2 is equivalent to {(0, 0), (0, 1), (1, 1)} ∪h {(0, 0), (1, 0), (1, 1)}.</p><p>Note that building new ordinal or horizontal sum of the previous lattices and keeping the corresponding t-norms on the sublattices leads again to a t-norm on the such constructed lattice.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion</head><p>We have investigated the ordinal sum construction principle for building t-norms on bounded lattices. We have shown that the structure of the underlying lattice has quite an influence on how such ordinal sum t-norms can be determined. It turned out that lattices built as ordinal and horizontal sums of chains are the most important and appropriate ones. Further that there exist no t-norms on product lattices constructed through the proposed ordinal sum construction principle except for some trivial cases regarding the t-norms or the lattices involved. Note that we have focused on subintervals of the bounded lattice as the carriers of the summand t-norms. Further investigations of sublattices, not necessarily being a subinterval, as summand carriers are discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Definition 2 . 3 .</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Consider a linearly ordered index set (I, ), I = ∅ and a family of intervals ([a i , b i ]) i∈I such that for all i, j ∈ I with i ≺ j either [a i , b i ] and [a j , b j ] are disjoint or b i = a j . The ordinal sum i∈I [a i , b i ] is the set i∈I [a i , b i ] equipped with the order defined by</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Definition 2 . 8 .</head><label>28</label><figDesc>Let (]a i , b i [) i∈I be a family of pairwise disjoint open subintervals of [0, 1] and let (T i ) i∈I be a family of t-norms. Then the ordinal sum T</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Lemma 4 . 1 .</head><label>41</label><figDesc>Consider some lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 1, 0) and a subinterval [a, b] of L. If L is an ordinal sum of intervals such that L = [0, a] ⊕ [a, b] ⊕ [b, 1], then T : L 2 → L defined by Eq. (3) is a t-norm for arbitrary t-norm T [a,b] on [a, b].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. T-norms on some special lattice (Example 4.2).</figDesc><graphic coords="6,201.34,67.67,145.08,72.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>[a,b] on [a, b] and of ∧ on the lattice L in all cases but two, i.e., if z ∈ [a, b] and either x ∈ [a, b] or y ∈ [a, b] with x L y. First assume that x ∈ [a, b] and y / ∈ [a, b]. Since y L x it follows that y &gt; L b, then</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Example 4 . 2 .</head><label>42</label><figDesc>Consider the bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) with L = {0, x, a, u, 1} as shown in Fig.1, further the subinterval [a, b] = [a, 1] = {a, u, 1} and the operation T as defined by Fig.1. It can be easily checked that T is defined by Eq. (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>on [a, b] and let x ∈ L and u ∈ [a, b[ such that x L u, i.e., x ∧ u = x. If u = a the proposition is trivially fulfilled, therefore we demand that u ∈ ]a, b[. Assume that x is incomparable to a. By such x is not contained in [a, b], i.e., x / ∈ [a, b]. Due to the associativity of T and the fact that T is also a t-norm for T [a,b] = T [a,b] D the following equality must hold</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Corollary 4 . 4 .Lemma 4 . 5 .</head><label>4445</label><figDesc>Assume that T defined by Eq. (3) is a t-norm for arbitrary T[a,b] on [a, b] and let x ∈ L arbitrarily. If x is incomparable to a, then x is also incomparable to all u ∈ [a, b[. We now turn to the incomparability with the top element b of the subinterval. Assume that T defined by Eq. (3) is a t-norm for arbitrary T[a,b] on [a, b]. If some x ∈ L is incomparable to b then x is incomparable to all u ∈ ]a, b].Proof. Consider some lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) and a subinterval[a, b]. Assume that T defined by Eq. (3) is a t-norm for arbitrary T[a,b] on [a, b]. Let x ∈ L be incomparable to b and therefore x / ∈ [a, b]. Suppose that there exists some u ∈ ]a, b] to which x can be compared. If x L u, also x L u L b contradicting the incomparability to b. Therefore, let x L u from which we can conclude that b L b ∧ x L b ∧ a = a, i.e., b ∧ x ∈ [a, b], even b ∧ x ∈ [a, b[ since b ∧ x = b would lead to a contradiction to the incomparability of b andx. Since T is a t-norm also for T[a,b] = T[a.b]   </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Corollary 4 . 6 .Remark 4 . 7 .</head><label>4647</label><figDesc>Corollary 4.4 and Lemma 4.5 already indicate that from the fact that T defined by Eq. (3) is a t-norm for some fixed subinterval [a, b] of L we can draw some conclusions about the structure of the underlying lattice L. The following corollary states under which conditions the lattice L even fulfills L = [0, a] ⊕ [a, b] ⊕ [b, 1]. It is an immediate consequence of the previous lemmata resp. a consequence of Theorem 4.8 proven later. Consider some lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) and a subinterval [a, b]. Assume that T defined by Eq. (3) is a t-norm for arbitrary T [a,b] on [a, b]. If for all x ∈ L there exist some u ∈ ]a, b[ such that x can be compared with u, then L = [0, a] ⊕ [a, b] ⊕ [b, 1]. Example 4.2 shows that there exist ordinal sum t-norms on lattices L which are not ordinal sums of intervals, i.e., L = [0, a] ⊕ [a, b] ⊕ [b, 1]. Note that those x ∈ L \ [0, a] ⊕ [a, b] ⊕ [b, 1] are incomparable to all u ∈ ]a, b[. They are further at most comparable to either a or b, but not to both at the same time (see also Fig. 2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Lattice cases.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,199.85,588.51,141.60,75.82" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Theorem 4 . 8 .</head><label>48</label><figDesc>Consider some bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) and a subinterval [a, b] of L. Then the following are equivalent:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>v ∈ [a, b[ it follows necessarily that y = b. Moreover, it holds for all z ∈ [a, b] that T (x, z) = x ∧ z L z = T [a,b] (b, z) = T (y, z). Further if x &lt; a or x incomparable to a, y ∈ [a, b], but z / ∈ [a, b] T (x, z) L T (y, z) due to the monotonicity of ∧. Associativity: Associativity holds trivially if all arguments are either from [a, b] or from L \ [a, b]. For the remaining possibilities we distinguish the following two cases: Case 1: Suppose that exactly one argument involved is from [a, b]. We assume x ∈ [a, b] and y, z / ∈ [a, b]. If y ∧ z ∈ [a, b[, necessarily y ∧ z = a. Then we can conclude that T (x, T (y, z)) = T (x, y ∧ z) = T (x, a) = a = x ∧ a = x ∧ y ∧ z = T (T (x, y), z). All other cases can be shown analogously or are fulfilled due to the associativity of ∧. Case 2: Suppose that exactly two elements involved are from the subinterval [a, b]. We choose x, y ∈ [a, b] and z / ∈ [a, b]. It can be easily verified that in case that either x or y are equal to one of the boundaries of [a, b] associativity of T is fulfilled due to the associativity and monotonicity of ∧. Therefore, we assume that x, y ∈ ]a, b[. In case that x L z or y L z, z is comparable to all [a, b] and fulfills necessarily z L b. Moreover,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>on [a, b]. Consider some x, y ∈ L being incomparable and further fulfilling x ∨ y = z = 1. Applying Corollary 4.4 to [x, 1] we get a contradiction since y is incomparable to x but comparable to z ∈ [x, 1[ due to y L x ∨ y = z. Similarly, Lemma 4.5 leads to a contradiction if x ∧ y = z = 0 for some incomparable x, y, ∈ L. In case that x, y ∈ L are comparable we clearly get {x ∧ y, x ∨ y} = {x, y}. (ii)⇒(i): Up to the trivial case where a = 0 and b = 1, i.e., [a, b] = L, we get in all other cases that [a, b] is a proper subchain of L. If some x ∈ L is incomparable to a then necessarily a = 0 and x belongs to another subchain L i of L such that L i ∩ [a, b[ = ∅. Therefore, x is also incomparable to all u ∈ [a, b[. Analogously, we can argue about some x being incomparable to b such that condition (ii) of Theorem 4.8 is fulfilled for each subinterval [a, b] of L and thus showing that T is a t-norm on L.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>on [u, v], T is a t-norm on L. • The only subintervals leading to contradictory results are [a, 1] and [b, 1]. We illustrate this for the subinterval [a, 1].There are only two t-norms on [a, 1]. For T[a,1] = T[a,1]   </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Lattice discussed in Example 4.10.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,241.35,579.59,59.16,85.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>on [a, b]. Note once again that in the latter case the only t-norm on [a, b] is T [a,b] M and as such T = T L M . In order to show the necessity assume that [a, b] fulfills [a, b] = L and ]a, b[ = ∅ and that T : L 2 → L defined by Eq. (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>b[ leading to a contradiction to Theorem 4.8. k = l = m: We select two elements x and y from L in the following way: x = (a 1 , . . . a k-1 , 0 k , a k+1 , . . . , a m-1 , b m , a m+1 , . . . , a n ), y = (a 1 , . . . a k-1 , a k , a k+1 , . . . , a m-1 , b m , a m+1 , . . . , a n ) then y ∈ ]a, b[ since a k &lt; L k b k and a m L m u m &lt; L m b m = y m . Furthermore, x L y although x is incomparable to a because of a m &lt; L m x m and x k = 0 k &lt; L k a k and as such contradicting again Theorem 4.8. k = l = m: Note that in this case 0</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Proposition 5 . 1 .</head><label>51</label><figDesc>Consider some bounded lattice (L, ∧, ∨, 0, 1) and some linearly ordered index set (I, ), I = ∅. Then the following are equivalent:(i)The ordinal sum T as defined by Eq. (2) is a t-norm for arbitrary families of pairwise disjoint subintervals (]a i , b i [) i∈I and for arbitrary t-norms T [a i ,b i ] on the corresponding [a i , b i ]. (ii) L is a horizontal sum of chains.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>is a t-norm for an arbitrary family ([a i , b i ]) i∈I and arbitrary t-norms T [a i ,b i ] on [a i , b i ]. Note that the family of subintervals is such that all members are pairwise disjoint regarding their interiors, i.e., up to boundary elements. Commutativity of T is preserved because of the commutativity of ∧ in L and T [a i ,b i ] on [a i , b i ].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>The lattice L discussed in Example 4.2, see also Fig. 1 is describable by C 1 = {0, a, u, 1} and C 2 = {0, x, 1} through L = C 1 ∪h C 2 . • Lattice L discussed in Example 4.10, see also Fig. 3 is equal to ({0, a, c} ∪h {0, b, c}) ⊕ {c, 1}.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Triangular norms on {0, 1} × {0, 1}</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On some logical connectives for fuzzy sets theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Alsina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Trillas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Valverde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Anal. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Lattice Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Birkhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
			<publisher>American Mathematical Society</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Providence, RI</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the structure of hoops</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Blok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M A</forename><surname>Ferreirim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Algebra Universalis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="257" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Free algebras in varieties of BL-algebras generated by a chain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Busaniche</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Algebra Universalis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Naturally totally ordered commutative semigroups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Clifford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. J. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="631" to="646" />
			<date type="published" when="1954">1954</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sur l&apos;équation fonctionelle de l&apos;associativité</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Climescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bull. École Polytechn. Iassy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1946">1946</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Davey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Priestley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Introduction to Lattices and Order</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>second ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Triangular norms on product lattices, Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Baets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mesiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="75" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ordinal sums of aggregation operators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Baets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mesiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Technologies for Constructing Intelligent Systems</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bouchon-Meunier</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gutiérrez-Ríos</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Magdalena</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Yager</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Physica-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="148" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Order norms on bounded partially ordered sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>De Cooman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kerre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Fuzzy Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="310" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Deschrijver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kerre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Logical, Algebraic, Analytic, and Probabilistic Aspects of Triangular Norms</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mesiar</forename><surname>Klement</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="259" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Triangular norms and related operators in L * -fuzzy set theory</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monoidal t-norm based logic: towards a logic for left-continuous t-norms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Esteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Godo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="288" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Goguen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Anal. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The fuzzy Tychonoff theorem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Goguen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Anal. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="734" to="742" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concept representation in natural and artificial languages: axioms, extensions and applications for fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Goguen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Internat. J. Man-Machine Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="561" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Treatise on Many-Valued Logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gottwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Studies in Logic and Computation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Baldock</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Research Studies Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Triangular norm-based mathematical fuzzy logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gottwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hájek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Logical, Algebraic, Analytic, and Probabilistic Aspects of Triangular Norms</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mesiar</forename><surname>Klement</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="299" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Chapter 10</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hájek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Metamathematics of Fuzzy Logic</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linearly ordered semigroups: Historic origins and A.H. Clifford&apos;s influence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">London Mathematical Society Lecture Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">231</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistische Topologien</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Höhle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Manuscripta Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="245" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Höhle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Commutative</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Non-Classical Logics and Their Applications to Fuzzy Subsets. A Handbook of the Mathematical Foundations of Fuzzy Set Theory</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Klement</forename><surname>Höhle</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="106" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>residuated -monoids</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Höhle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Non-Classical Logics and Their Applications to Fuzzy Subsets. A Handbook of the Mathematical Foundations of Fuzzy Set Theory</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Klement</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Normality in fuzzy topological spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Anal. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="364" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on the ordinal sum theorem and its consequence for the construction of triangular norms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jenei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the direct decomposability of t-norms over direct product lattices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jenei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Baets</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="699" to="707" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">∨-Distributive and infinitely ∨-distributive t-norms on complete lattices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Karaçal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Khadjiev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Über gewisse Halbverbände und kommutative Semigruppen II</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Klein-Barmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Z</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="715" to="734" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Logical, Algebraic, Analytic, and Probabilistic Aspects of Triangular Norms</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Klement</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mesiar</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Klement</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mesiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pap</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Triangular Norms, Trends in Logic</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Triangular norms as ordinal sums of semigroups in the sense of A</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Klement</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mesiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pap</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clifford Semigroup Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation of associative functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Publ. Math. Debrecen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Triangular norms on discrete settings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mayor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Torrens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Logical, Algebraic, Analytic, and Probabilistic Aspects of Triangular Norms</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Klement</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mesiar</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="230" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical metrics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Menger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="535" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="1942">1942</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the structure of semi-groups on a compact manifold with boundary</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mostert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shields</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Math., II. Ser</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Introduction to Copulas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Nelsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pastings of MV-effect algebras</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Riečanová</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Internat. J. Theoret. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1875" to="1883" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Hausdorff separation axiom for fuzzy topological spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rodabaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Topology Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On an extension of triangular norms on bounded lattices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Saminger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Klement</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mesiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Submitted for publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Espaces métriques aléatoires</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schweizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sklar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C.R. Acad. Sci. Paris Sér. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">247</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2092" to="2094" />
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical metric spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schweizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sklar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pacific J. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Associative functions and statistical triangle inequalities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schweizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sklar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Publ. Math. Debrecen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Probabilistic Metric Spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schweizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sklar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<pubPlace>North-Holland, New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Triangular norms on partially ordered sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
