<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gradualness, uncertainty and bipolarity: Making sense of fuzzy sets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2010-11-19">19 November 2010</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Didier</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
							<email>dubois@irit.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">IRIT</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Université de Toulouse</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>118 Route de Narbonne</addrLine>
									<postCode>31062, Cedex 09</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Henri</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
							<email>prade@irit.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">IRIT</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Université de Toulouse</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>118 Route de Narbonne</addrLine>
									<postCode>31062, Cedex 09</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gradualness, uncertainty and bipolarity: Making sense of fuzzy sets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2010-11-19">19 November 2010</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C122D7F721ECE8E41FF36D0AB56A5F37</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.fss.2010.11.007</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T09:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Higher-order fuzzy sets</term>
					<term>Fuzzy numbers</term>
					<term>Possibility theory</term>
					<term>Truth-functionality</term>
					<term>Uncertainty</term>
					<term>Bipolarity</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper discusses basic notions underlying fuzzy sets, especially gradualness, uncertainty, vagueness and bipolarity, in order to clarify the significance of using fuzzy sets in practice. Starting with the idea that a fuzzy set may represent either a precise gradual composite entity or an epistemic construction refereeing to an ill-known object, it is shown that each view suggests a different use of fuzzy sets. Then, it is argued that the usual phrase fuzzy number is ambiguous as it induces some confusion between gradual extensions of real numbers and gradual extensions of interval calculations. The distinction between degrees of truth that are compositional and degrees of belief that cannot be so is recalled. The truth-functional calculi of various extensions of fuzzy sets, motivated by the desire to handle ill-known membership grades, are shown to be of limited significance for handling this kind of uncertainty. Finally, the idea of a separate handling of membership and non-membership grades put forward by Atanassov is cast in the setting of reasoning about bipolar information. This intuition is different from the representation of ill-known membership functions and leads to combination rules differing from the ones proposed for handling uncertainty about membership grades.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Fuzzy set theory and its extensions seem to come to grips with three basic concepts that noticeably differ from each other but may appear conjointly in various circumstances:</p><p>(1) Gradualness: The idea that many categories in natural language are a matter of degree, including truth. The extension of a gradual predicate is a fuzzy set, a set where the transition between membership and non-membership is, in the words of its inventor, "gradual rather than abrupt''. This is Zadeh's original intuition <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. (2) Epistemic uncertainty: The idea of partial or incomplete information. In its most primitive form, it is often described by means of a set of possible values of some quantity of interest, one of which is the right one. This view leads to possibility theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and possible worlds semantics (for instance <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>).</p><p>(3) Bipolarity: The idea that information can be described by distinguishing between positive and negative sides, possibly handled separately, as it seems to be the case in the human brain <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p><p>It is clear that the three notions interact closely with one another: truth may appear to be a bipolar notion as it goes along with falsity. A fuzzy set may account for epistemic uncertainty since it extends the notion of a set. Epistemic uncertainty is gradual since belief is often a matter of degree.</p><p>As a result, the epistemological situation of fuzzy set theory and its extensions (interval-valued or type 2 fuzzy sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and variants, Atanassov <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> so-called "intuitionistic'' fuzzy sets, more recently soft sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, etc.) is often unclear and leads to some confusion in the literature:</p><p>• Controversies on the nature of vagueness between those who consider it is basically a matter of uncertainty of meaning <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, and those who incriminate the clash between the gradualness of categories and their Boolean-like use in natural language as the main source of vagueness (let alone the limited perception of shades by the human mind) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. • The existence of several views of membership functions: expressing similarity to prototypes, incomplete gradual information, or utility functions in preference modelling <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. • The temptation of interpreting any gradual notion as a membership function, even it does not refer to a set (for instance the ambiguous notion of fuzzy number, viewed either as a generalised real number or a generalised interval). • The confusion between gradual truth and gradual uncertainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, which turns out to be a variant of the former whereby sets (of truth-values, especially singletons) are confused with elements. • The confusion between membership functions and probability distributions <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p><p>• The confusion between a separate handling of positive and negative information with uncertainty about truth-degrees <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>.</p><p>The aim of this discussion paper is to clarify some of these issues, by disentangling the three notions of gradualness, epistemic uncertainty and bipolarity, laying bare the precise role of fuzzy sets in connection with such notions, thus suggesting proper uses of membership functions, and existing extensions thereof, such as interval-valued fuzzy sets, type 2 fuzzy sets and so-called "intuitionistic'' fuzzy sets. First, we try to clarify the two roles of fuzzy sets in the representation of information, distinguishing between the case when fuzzy sets represent objective entities from when they represent incomplete information (thus highlighting an opposition between ontic and epistemic representations, respectively). It includes a discussion on the ambiguous notion of fuzzy number, viewed either as a generalised number or a generalised interval. Then, we discuss the distinction between truth-values and information states, recalling that uncertainty cannot go along with truth-functionality. This view is applied to various kinds of generalised fuzzy sets. Lastly, the notion of bipolarity is introduced and again discussed in connection with fuzzy sets with two membership functions. A key-difference is made between cases when they represent more information than usual fuzzy sets and cases when they represent less information. Insight is gained into the meaning of some notions in the fuzzy set literature, distinguishing between spurious and genuine extensions of classical notions. Some topics are deliberately not discussed in details, like the relevance of fuzzy sets for modelling vagueness and the connection between similarity and fuzzy sets, but they are pointed out in Section 6. They would deserve a more extensive development.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Conjunctive vs. disjunctive sets</head><p>A set S defined in extension is often denoted by listing its elements, say, in the finite case {s 1 , s 2 , . . . , s n }. This representation, when it must be used in applications, is ambiguous. In some cases, a set represents a collection of (sometimes physical) items that has objective existence as a lumped entity. It is then a conjunction of its elements. An element inside such a set C is a component of a precisely described, composite entity. For instance, a region in a digital image is a conjunction of adjacent pixels.</p><p>In other cases, sets are epistemic constructions and represent incomplete information about the world. In this case, a set is used as a disjunction of possible items or of values of some underlying quantity, one of which is the right one. For instance I may only have a rough idea of the age x of the president of some country, and provide an interval <ref type="bibr">[a, b]</ref> as containing the right value of x. Such an interval is the disjunction of mutually exclusive elements. It is clear that the interval itself is subjective (it is my knowledge), has no intrinsic existence, even if it refers to a real fact. Another example is the set of models of a propositional knowledge base: only one of them reflects the real situation. Moreover it is likely to change by acquiring more information.</p><p>Sets representing collections of elements forming composite objects will be called conjunctive; sets representing incomplete information states will be called disjunctive. A conjunctive set is the precise representation of an objective entity (philosophically it is a de re notion), while a disjunctive set only represents incomplete information (it is de dicto). We also shall speak of ontic sets vs. epistemic sets, in analogy with ontic and epistemic actions in cognitive robotics <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. An element inside a disjunctive set D is a possible candidate for being the real value or state of the world, while elements outside D are considered impossible. A disjunctive set D represents the epistemic state of an agent, hence does not exist per se. Its characteristic function can be interpreted as a possibility distribution. This distinction between conjunctive and disjunctive sets was made by Zadeh himself <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> distinguishing between set-valued attributes (like the set of sisters of some person) from ill-known single-valued attributes (like the unknown single sister of some person). This issue has been extensively discussed by Yager <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and Dubois and Prade <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> for the study of incomplete conjunctive information (whose representation requires a disjunctive set of conjunctive sets).</p><p>Reasoning about disjunctive epistemic information modelled by a set D of possible worlds can be done in terms of epistemic modalities of plausibility and certainty, which are special cases of modal possibility and necessity. Namely an event A is considered</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">• possible (= plausible) if it is consistent with D (A ∩ D ∅), which can be denoted D♦A; • necessary (= certain), if its negation A c is inconsistent with D (hence it is entailed by D: D ⊆ A), which can be denoted DçA.</formula><p>And clearly, the duality between possibility and necessity is valid: DçA is equivalent to D¬♦A c , denoting by A c the complement of A. Interestingly, note the presence of bipolarity in this representation, under a form where the negative aspect is not just the complement of the positive one, as DçA and DçA c are inconsistent with each other but do not exhaust the possible epistemic attitudes about A. There is a third case, whereby D(¬çA) ∧ (¬çA c ) expresses ignorance about the occurrence of A. Note that this is an unorthodox view of modal logic semantics, where the satisfiability relation is extended from interpretations to epistemic states; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> for more details on this logic. Note that conjunctions and disjunctions do not merge conjunctive and disjunctive sets in the same way. If C 1 and C 2 are two conjunctive sets, their conjunction will be often interpreted as a set union C 1 ∪ C 2 (e.g. pointing out "the forest and the lake'' in an image designates a region made of the union of both). In contrast, if two reliable sources supply consistent pieces of information of the form x ∈ D 1 and x ∈ D 2 , their conjunction lead to the conclusion x ∈ D 1 ∩ D 2 , a set intersection. On the contrary the disjunction of D 1 and D 2 , natural if one of the sources is wrong, corresponds to a set union. The disjunction of two conjunctive sets C 1 and C 2 may correspond to hesitation between them, and produces the higher-order disjunctive set {C 1 , C 2 }.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Ontic vs. epistemic fuzzy sets</head><p>As a mathematical notion, a fuzzy set F is unambiguously defined through a membership function F from a set S to a (generally complete) lattice L. The mathematical object representing the fuzzy set is the membership function. Now, looking at the literature, it is clear that there are two ways of using a fuzzy set, which parallel the two way sets are used.</p><p>• The fuzzy set is used as representing some precise gradual entity consisting of a collection of items. A typical example is a region in a grey image. Due to the presence of levels of grey, the boundary of a meaningful area in the image (e.g. forest zone) is gradual. In many cases, it does not represent uncertainty about a precise boundary (just the fact that the density of trees is slowly decreasing in peripheral zones). Sometimes, the gradualness is linked to the use of a fuzzy predicate (e.g. the picture of a "populated area''). There is no uncertainty as soon as there is an agreement on the choice of the membership function (of "populated''). The same view of fuzzy sets is adopted for the gradual representation of clusters in data analysis, or linguistic partitions in fuzzy control or fuzzy random variables in the style of Puri and Ralescu <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, ranging on a set of (membership) functions. Similarly, the rating profile of a decision according to several criteria sharing a common value scale is of the same conjunctive nature. Such fuzzy sets are conjunctive and can be called ontic fuzzy sets. • In contrast a fuzzy set may model incomplete information, namely be disjunctive. In that case, as pointed out by Zadeh <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, a membership function (with values on a totally ordered set) is then interpreted as a possibility distribution, denoted over S. Now, S represents a universe of discourse, a frame of discernment, a set of possible worlds. This kind of fuzzy set is basically a subjective notion as it is attached to an agent whose epistemic state is described by distribution . Gradual notions of certainty and plausibility, that extend the modal notions mentioned earlier in this text, can be derived from possibility distributions. The degree of possibility of an event A is <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> (A) = max s∈A (s), and its degree of necessity is</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">N (A) = min s / ∈A ( (s)) = ( (A c )),</formula><p>where is the order-reversing map on L <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. It yields a theory of epistemic uncertainty devoted to the handling of incomplete information, variants of which have been proposed in the literature by Shackle (the theory of potential surprise, ( (A)) being a degree of surprise if A occurs <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>) and Spohn (ordinal conditional functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>).</p><p>A possibility distribution cannot be handled as if it were the mathematical model of an objective entity, contrary to the case of a conjunctive fuzzy set. There is always a precise ill-known (hence partially unattainable) entity that the possibility distribution is supposed to refer to, while there is no such underlying point-valued entity with a conjunctive fuzzy set. A region in a grey image, a fuzzy cluster are representations of real things. A possibility distribution is a higher-order construct.</p><p>Interestingly, a similar opposition exists in probability theory whereby a frequentist probability model P represents a physical random phenomenon and accounts for variability of (precise) observations. On the contrary, a subjective probability represents the epistemic state of an agent, assuming degrees of belief can be equated to exchangeable betting rates (a subjective probability does not exist, as De Finetti <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> claims, nor does a possibility distribution, may we add). However it is difficult to consistently account for incomplete information using a single subjective probability. To do so requires the theory of imprecise probability proposed by Walley <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. In this theory epistemic states are represented by credal sets, i.e. convex sets of probabilities P. In the robust-Bayesian view, credal sets represent incomplete information about a standard frequentist probability model. Interestingly, a [0, 1]-valued possibility distribution can encode a special kind of credal set, defined by P( ) = {P, ∀A measurable P(A) ≤ (A)} <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</p><p>Remark. Sets are also used to represent constraints, hence fuzzy sets represent elastic constraints. This is how Zadeh <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> understood possibility distributions induced by natural language sentences. And his fuzzy relational calculus for handling elastic restrictions <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> is pioneering soft constraint propagation <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>. Are sets representing constraints disjunctive or conjunctive? It all depends on the point of view. Quantities restricted by constraints are often controllable, while ill-known quantities described by epistemic sets are not. Degrees of satisfaction of such constraints represent extents to which values are allowed, not extents to which they are plausible. Yet the principles of soft constraint propagation in the fuzzy setting are in agreement with the principles of approximate reasoning and possibility theory. Epistemic states, like soft constraints, are combined via the minimum rule and then projected using a maximum operation. Necessity degrees attached to constraints represent degrees of priority. Hence, everything looks as if a soft constraint can be viewed as an epistemic fuzzy set and conversely.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Consequences on the applications of fuzzy sets</head><p>At this stage the reader must be convinced that an ontic fuzzy set is conjunctive and an epistemic fuzzy set is disjunctive. This distinction has consequences on the significance of mathematical notions defined in fuzzy set theory, for instance, the notion of scalar distance between fuzzy sets, fuzzy random variables, fuzzy systems and fuzzy optimisation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">On the use of scalar distances between fuzzy sets</head><p>Let F(S) be the set of fuzzy sets of S. A distance between two fuzzy sets F and G is a mapping d : F(S)×F(S) → R + such that d(F, G) = 0 if and only if F = G, plus other properties such as symmetry and triangle inequality. Such distances have been instrumental in fuzzy analysis, and the study of fuzzy random variables, where spaces of fuzzy sets (of R n ) must be equipped with a metric structure ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, for instance). It is clear that a scalar distance makes sense between conjunctive fuzzy sets: d(F, G) = 0 means that the two ontic entities modelled by F and G coincide. However, if F and G model epistemic states, d(F, G) = 0 does not mean that the (precise) ontic entities, say f and g, referred to by F and G are the same. As knowledge about such ontic entities is incomplete, our knowledge of the distance between f and g is incomplete too. What is known about this distance ( f, g) can be evaluated by applying the extension principle to and obtaining the disjunctive fuzzy set of possible values of the scalar (F, G).</p><p>It does not mean that a scalar distance d(F, G) between epistemic fuzzy sets F and G is useless. It is then an epistemic distance that may be instrumental in knowledge revision processes, in order to formalise the idea of minimal change <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>.</p><p>This distinction is important in data analysis applications such as regression and interpolation. For instance, the fuzzy least-squares method of Diamond <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> relies on a scalar distance between fuzzy intervals and thus makes sense for regression with fuzzy data considered as actual entities. If fuzzy data is understood as incomplete observations, it is not clear what a scalar-distance-based fuzzy least-square regression method tells us on the uncertainty pervading regression lines that could have been found, had the observations been precise. In many cases (adapting De Finetti <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>), fuzzy data do not exist (but as representing knowledge about ill-known data). Likewise, fuzzy interpolation is often interpreted as finding membership functions that achieve a trade-off between the shape of other membership functions (a task for which a scalar distance d(F, G) is appropriate), not as the study of the impact of the incompleteness of knowledge about known points of a function on the result of some standard (e.g. linear) interpolation process. For each problem, it is important to figure out whether a scalar distance between fuzzy sets is the right tool or not.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Several views of fuzzy random variables</head><p>In the theory of fuzzy random variables, a scalar distance between fuzzy sets is instrumental when defining variance <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. A fuzzy random variable is then viewed as a random conjunctive fuzzy set, i.e. a classical random variable ranging in a set of functions, and the scalar variance reflects the variability of membership functions. It makes sense if for instance, membership functions are models of linguistic terms and some "linguistic variability'' must be evaluated. This is the line initiated by Puri and Ralescu <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, in agreement with random set theory where sets are construed as lumped entities <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. However, Dempster <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> theory of upper and lower probabilities (the basis of Shafer's theory of evidence <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>) is a theory of epistemic (disjunctive) random sets that represent ill-known standard random variables. Along this line of thought is the approach to fuzzy random variables proposed by Kwakernaak <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> as well as Kruse and Meyer <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. They view a fuzzy random variable as a (disjunctive) fuzzy set of classical random variables (those induced by selection functions compatible with the random fuzzy set). Kruse and Meyer clearly define variance of a fuzzy random variable as a fuzzy set of positive reals induced by applying the extension principle to the variance formula. It represents what is known about the variance of the underlying ill-known random variable. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> for an extensive comparison of these views.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Equations with fuzzy coefficients</head><p>A great number of papers have been devoted to the study of fuzzy linear equations, the simplest form of which is Ax = B where A and B are fuzzy sets of real values (a good reference is <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>). Even though the mathematical problem makes sense, it is almost never made clear what such kinds of equations are good for. Most of the time the rationale for such equations is the lack of knowledge about coefficients. If this is to be taken for granted, A and B are disjunctive fuzzy sets that describe knowledge about the real coefficients a and b. Typically, the equation ax = b may express some physical constraint that must be respected. However in such a situation, the meaning of the fuzzy equation Ax = B is quite different: it requires that the knowledge about ax should be the same as the knowledge about b. This equality between pieces of knowledge cannot be taken for granted. On the one hand, it is not implied by the equality ax = b (the latter only enforces that Ax ∩ B ∅). On the other hand, requesting the equality of membership functions, Ax = B does not imply ax = b on the actual values a and b either. It may be that b is known while A is ill-known, in which case the equation Ax = {b} has no solution. As a consequence, the equation Ax = B is very hard to make sense of at the practical level, if the fuzzy sets A and B are understood as disjunctive.</p><p>If the value of x is known to satisfy equation ax = b where our knowledge of coefficients a and b is represented by epistemic sets A and B, then what is known about x is that it belongs to the disjunctive set {x : ax = b, a ∈ A, b ∈ B}, corresponding to the solution of the equation Ax ∩ B ∅. This topic deserves a full-fledged investigation. The study of fuzzy equations should benefit from results in interval analysis and constraint propagation. Moreover, in the multidimensional case, the system of interval equations AX = B where now A is an interval matrix and B a vector of intervals has little chance to have a set-valued solution in the form of a Cartesian product of intervals (a kind of solution some papers claim to compute in the fuzzy interval case).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Does a fuzzy system handle uncertainty?</head><p>Many fuzzy rule-based systems in systems engineering do not account for incomplete knowledge and are basically precise approximate representations of systems. For instance, Takagi-Sugeno fuzzy systems exploit precise interpolation schemes derived from fuzzy rule-based representations. In fact, a fuzzy model is seldom viewed as a disjunctive fuzzy set of precise models. It is viewed as a precise model constructed by means of fuzzy set-based techniques. Yet, it makes sense to construct fuzzy models that would represent incomplete information about a real process. Such models would produce fuzzy-set-valued outputs even when inputs are precise. The properties of such fuzzy models should be studied in connection with the underlying unknown precise model which stands for a possible realisation of the imprecise model. In other words a possible-world approach would be the right way of studying properties of such fuzzy models. A fuzzy model would possibly satisfy a property to a degree if and only if at least one precise model satisfying this property is compatible with the fuzzy one to such a degree. Similarly, a fuzzy model would certainly satisfy a property to a degree if and only if no precise model compatible with the fuzzy one to degree at least ( ) violates this property. Fuzzy differential equations could be a tool for handling such an epistemic view of fuzzy systems. However, many papers again consider fuzzy coefficients in fuzzy differential equations as objective substitute to precise coefficients, again assuming equality between a fuzzy set representing a fuzzy derivative and another fuzzy set. In contrast, the disjunctive interpretation of fuzzy sets should favour an extension of differential inclusions, expressing that the standard derivative of some function be restricted by some possibility distribution expressing incomplete knowledge (see, e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> for an early paper along this line).</p><p>This disjunctive view of fuzzy sets is valid for other areas as well: a fuzzy database can be understood as a disjunctive fuzzy set of databases. Querying such a database comes down, at the theoretical level, to querying all its possible instances <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. A response is possibly (resp. certainly) relevant to a query if it is relevant for one (resp. all) instance(s) of the fuzzy database. A fuzzy optimisation problem (with ill-known data) can be understood as a disjunctive fuzzy set of standard optimisation problems with precise data. A possibly feasible solution is feasible for at least one precise version of the problem; a certainly feasible solution is feasible whatever the actual value of the ill-known data is. It comes close to robust optimisation issues <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Fuzzy sets as sets of gradual elements</head><p>Fuzzy rule-based systems model precise functions because, when submitted to a precise input, the fuzzy set-valued output obtained by some fuzzy logic inference device applied to the fuzzy rules is systematically defuzzified. However the usual meaning of defuzzify is questionable: defuzzifying a fuzzy set of numbers yields a precise number. Yet, one might expect that stripping a fuzzy set of its gradualness yields a crisp set, since fuzziness refers to non-Booleanity. So defuzzification, as usually construed, mixes up two ideas: making a fuzzy entity crisp, and selecting a value inside a set, an instance of the confusion between uncertainty and gradualness.</p><p>As recently discussed by Dubois and Prade <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>, this type of confusion can be clarified if a notion of fuzzy element is introduced, that plays the same role for a fuzzy set as an element for a set. Viewing the nested set of -cuts induced by a fuzzy set as a one-to-many mapping (as proposed in 1975 by Negoita and Ralescu <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>), it is natural to define a gradual element as a selection function of this multimapping. Namely for any fuzzy set F, consider the one-to-many mapping</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">∈ L \ {0} → F ∈ 2 S . A gradual element of F [44] is any selection function f : → f ( ) ∈ F , ∀ &gt; 0.</formula><p>A gradual (or fuzzy) element is a kind of parameterised element of set S. It is clear that a fuzzy set can be viewed as a crisp set of fuzzy elements, and as a gradual element of the power set 2 S . Soft sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> are a generalisation of this view, doing away with the nestedness of -cuts (they are called gradual sets in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>). Such a one-to-many mapping, proposed as new in the theory of soft sets, was introduced in the 1960s as part of the definition of a random set <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. A gradual element is fuzzy but it does not account for epistemic uncertainty (it is precise at any level). Note that f is not a membership function as it is a function from a complete lattice (deprived of its bottom element) to a set, and not conversely.</p><p>This notion of gradual element has direct impact on the debate on the nature of the so-called fuzzy numbers. There are two basic traditions:</p><p>(1) The first kind of fuzzy real numbers often takes the form of a decreasing mapping from the reals to the unit interval or a suitable lattice, as proposed by Hutton <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>, or a probability distribution function <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>; variants of such a fuzzy reals were also studied by Rodabaugh <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> and Höhle <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref> and others in topology (the so-called "fuzzy real line'').</p><p>(2) The second kind of fuzzy numbers is viewed as fuzzy sets of numbers whose cuts are intervals: a better name is fuzzy interval (regardless of whether its core is reduced to a point or not). These were proposed by Zadeh <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> in 1975 and soon after studied by Mizumoto and Tanaka <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>, Nahmias <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>, Dubois and Prade <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>.</p><p>It is clear that fuzzy numbers of the second kind are generalised intervals, not just generalised real numbers. In particular, the arithmetic operations between such fuzzy numbers, defined via the extension principle, are an extension of interval arithmetics. Addition does not define a group on fuzzy intervals, for instance. Yet there are some authors who tried to equip fuzzy intervals with a group structure. This kind of attempt suggests a confusion between uncertainty and gradualness.</p><p>Likewise, the intuition behind fuzzy real numbers of the first kind is somewhat ambiguous. They are said to generalise real numbers (and Höhle <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref> has suggested they can be viewed as gradual Dedekind cuts). Yet they are defined as special mappings from the reals to a lattice (hence as membership functions of fuzzy sets). Addition and product of such fuzzy real numbers are defined by means of the extension principle. However, they do not make up a group under addition (nor does the positive fuzzy real line form a group for product). Actually, neither subtraction nor division are ever studied on the fuzzy real line.</p><p>Given the specific monotonic requirement bearing on fuzzy real numbers of the first kind, their membership function is (generally) invertible: -<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> exists. It is a gradual element of the real line. More generally, a gradual number <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> can be defined as a mapping r : L \ {0} → R we call assignment function. Then -1 is a special kind of gradual number, a monotonically decreasing one (as is monotonically decreasing). Viewed as special kinds of gradual numbers, reals r ∈ R are viewed as r such that r ( ) = r, ∀ &gt; 0.</p><p>Adding two fuzzy real numbers of the first kind 1 and 2 using the extension principle yields a fuzzy real number</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">1+2 such that -1 1+2 = -1 1 + -1 2 (pointwisely).</formula><p>It is compatible with the addition of gradual numbers, defined by the pointwise addition r1+2 = r1 + r2 . Now gradual numbers on the real line form a group structure, and the subtraction is simply defined as r1-2 = r1 -r2 (pointwisely). This is the crux of the ambiguity concerning the fuzzy real line. Consider the embedding of real numbers r in the fuzzy L-reals. It corresponds to characteristic functions of intervals (-∞, r ]. There is a bijection between such intervals and the real line. Moreover, the interval addition (-∞,</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">r 1 ] + (-∞, r 2 ] = (-∞, r 1 + r 2 ]</formula><p>is totally coherent with the corresponding real line addition (and gradual number addition). However, it looks difficult to equip the fuzzy real line of Hutton <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> and followers with a group structure (making it a genuine fuzzy real line) without interpreting the whole class of L-reals as gradual numbers. Indeed:</p><p>• Defining the subtraction in the fuzzy real line by the extension principle we get nowhere since viewing reals as sets of the form (-∞, r ], we get (-∞, r 1 ] -(-∞, r 2 ] = R and we do not retrieve subtraction on the real line; • defining it by the subtraction of gradual numbers ( -1 1 --1 2 pointwisely), we no longer get a monotonic function. So it seems that, in the fuzzy real line as studied by fuzzy topologists, the distinction between (fuzzy) sets and (fuzzy) elements is kind of unclear.</p><p>Yet, there are many natural examples of gradual numbers in fuzzy set theory (see Dubois and Prade <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>). Basically any set-function assigning a number to a set should generalise to fuzzy sets by assigning a number to each cut, in the form of a gradual number. For instance:</p><p>• The fuzzy cardinality of a fuzzy set F, especially an ontic one, is a gradual integer: |F|( ) = |F( )|; its assignment function is decreasing, hence it is a fuzzy integer à la Hutton, if the range of |F| is made of consecutive integers. Note that it is a decreasing function. As a consequence, it has oftentimes been seen as a fuzzy set of integers expressing uncertainty about cardinality . 1 This is again a confusion between gradualness and uncertainty: since the cardinality of a set is not a set, there is no reason for the cardinality of a fuzzy set to be a fuzzy set. • The fuzzy probability of a fuzzy event. This is a gradual number in the unit interval. It is a variant of the previous item. In particular, it is not a fuzzy-interval-valued probability, that is, not a generalised imprecise probability. • The fuzzy extension of the Hausdorff distance between sets: It is a gradual number dH (F, G)( ) = d H (F , G ). As it is not monotonic with it can no longer be confused with a membership function, and it does not belong to the fuzzy real line of the first kind either.</p><p>• A fuzzy interval can now be viewed as a classical interval of gradual numbers <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>. The mid point of fuzzy interval is thus a gradual number obtained by taking the midpoint of each cut.</p><p>Revisiting defuzzification, we can now make a difference between stripping a fuzzy interval Ĩ of its fuzziness and stripping it from its uncertainty. The first operation consists of integrating (Aumann-style) the cut multiple-valued mapping Ĩ over [0,1] [54] and it yields an average interval. The second operation consists in choosing a gradual number inside Ĩ . We may as well extract a gradual number from Ĩ and compute its Riemann integral to get a single number. Both operations commute if we apply the same selection operation in each cut as in the average interval <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Truth degrees, uncertainty, vagueness, and ill-known sets</head><p>The confusion between gradualness and uncertainty pervading fuzzy set theory is actually a variant of a confusion pervading some parts of the literature in logic between gradual truth values and belief degrees or information states <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref>. A very elementary form of this confusion can be observed in propositional logic already for plain truth-values. It has been argued elsewhere that in propositional logic, propositions are Boolean but (as recalled in Section 2) there are three epistemic attitudes in front of a proposition <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>. An agent is not forced either to believe (or know) p or to believe ¬ p, (s)he can be agnostic about p when information is lacking. There has been a recurrent temptation to interpret the latter epistemic state as a third truth-value, say U (for unknown) to be added to the Boolean truth-set 2 = {0, 1}. For instance, Lukasiewicz and Kleene three-valued logics, partial logic, among others seem to rely on this kind of intuition. Lukasiewicz <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref> suggests that U means possible, while Kleene <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref> interprets it as either the impossibility to compute the actual truth-value of some propositions (e.g. the results of procedure calls which might not terminate), or as unknown. Partial logic <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref> considers incomplete interpretations of the language.</p><p>In such multiple-valued logic settings, once the extended truth set obtained, connectives are then defined in a truthfunctional way. As a consequence, some (and sometimes all) tautologies of propositional calculus are lost, e.g. the laws of contradiction and the excluded middle in Kleene logic. Yet, the set 2 is the range of the propositional variables, so that the only possible value of function p ∧ ¬p is 0. This paradox is due to a confusion between truth-values and epistemic attitudes. The value U in fact corresponds to a "truth-value gap'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref> and is not a third truth-value.</p><p>One may define knowing that or believing p as the capability to semantically infer p from a set of propositions held as true (a belief base) <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>. Then inferring p entails the truth of p, but the converse is false: p may be true without the agent believing or knowing it. In fact, when p is entailed by a belief base, it means that only the truth value 1 is possible. So it makes sense to equate full belief in p with the singleton {1}; similarly full disbelief corresponds to the singleton {0}. The lack of belief in p and its negation leaves all truth values possible, and thus corresponds to the set 2 itself. So epistemic attitudes in propositional logic are in one-to-one correspondence with non-empty subsets of truth-values. Augmenting 2 with the truth-value U to account for ignorance comes down to confusing elements and subsets of a set (especially elements and singletons). A number of constructions claim to account for uncertainty or graded uncertainty but are not amenable to a truth-functional calculus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.">Ill-known sets</head><p>Introducing uncertainty in crisp set theory means attaching to elements s ∈ S one of the three non-empty subsets of 2. It is tempting to consider ill-known sets as genuine three-valued sets (denoted by Â) whose characteristic function ranges on L = 2 2 -∅ (it looks like a kind of fuzzy set) with the following conventions: Â(s) = {1} if s belongs for sure to the set;</p><p>(1) = {0} if s for sure does not belong to the set;</p><p>(2) = {0, 1} if it is unknown whether s belongs or not to the set.</p><p>Ill-known sets can also be encoded as a pair of nested sets (A * , A * ), with A * ⊆ A * , where A * \ A * collects the elements with unknown membership. It is possible to extend the standard set-theoretic operations to such three-valued sets noticing that L is the set of intervals on 2 (so that Â is an interval-valued set) and using the canonical extension of Boolean connectives by means of interval computation. It is easy to check that what is obtained is Kleene three-valued logic <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref> (encoding {0} as 0, {1} as 1 and {0, 1} as 1/2, and using the standard connectives min for conjunction, max for disjunction, and 1 -• for complement). Such kind of sets have been studied by Yao (interval-sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref>) and Pedrycz (Shadowed sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref>). However, the fuzzy set Â is not an object in itself, it is a representation of the incomplete knowledge of an agent about a set Ȧ, of which all is known is that A * ⊂ Ȧ ⊂ A * . It should be clear that the resulting algebraic structure does not address (but in a very approximate way) the issue of reasoning about the ill-known set Ȧ <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref>. For instance, the complement of Â is Âc obtained by switching {0} and {1} in the above definition, i.e. yields the pair (( A * ) c , (A * ) c ). Hence Â ∩ Âc corresponds to the pair ( A * ∩ (A * ) c , A * ∩ (A * ) c ), where A * ∩ (A * ) c = ∅ while A * ∩ (A * ) c ∅, generally. But despite the fact that Ȧ is ill-known, it always hold that Ȧ ∩ Ȧc = ∅, and this information is lost by the Kleene setting, considering subsets of truth-values as truth-values and acting compositionally. Uncertainty never goes along with compositionality <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>. Kleene's three-valued logic is more naturally truth-functional either when viewed as a simplified variant of fuzzy logic, where the third truth-value means half-true. The loss of classical tautologies then looks more acceptable. Another situation is when literals are handled as independent entities and no epistemic stance is taken on syntactic entities of the form ¬ p ∨ p when the truth-value of p cannot be obtained. Then, the tautological nature of ¬ p ∨ p cannot be detected by the computing device.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">Vagueness</head><p>This non-truth-functional view of ill-known sets where all tautologies of classical logic are preserved is used by Kit Fine <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref> applying Van Fraassen's supervaluation approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref> to vagueness. In this approach, the singleton {1} is dubbed "super-true'', i.e. true in all crisp precisiations of Â (e.g. Â ∪ Âc would be super-true). A vague concept is then viewed as one whose extension has truth-value gaps. A similar view of vague concepts is the one by Williamson <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref>. However for the latter, there exists a crisp extension Ȧ for any vague concept, but it is ill-known (contrary to Fine who does not presuppose such a crisp extension exists). A vague proposition is said to be clearly true by Williamson when applied to a situation s for which Â(s) = {1}. Note that fuzzy sets do not really aim at capturing vagueness in this sense (as Zadeh <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> himself emphasises). Vagueness refers to uncertainty of meaning, while fuzzy sets after Zadeh deals with gradualness of some natural language words, and of sets in general (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, for a detailed discussion).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3.">Fuzzy sets induced by random sets</head><p>Much related to ill-known sets is the random set view of membership functions, originally proposed by Orlov <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref> and studied at length by Goodman <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68]</ref> and Nguyen <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[69]</ref> among others. It is a randomised view of ill-known sets, whereby each precisiation of Â has a probability m(A) to be the actual one (quite in line with <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref>) and the mapping m : 2 S → [0, 1] is a probability distribution over the power set 2 S , i.e. A⊆S m(A) = 1, and m(∅) = 0. The gradual membership function of the fuzzy set Â induced by m is the one-point coverage function of the random set, i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">Â(s) = s∈A m(A).</formula><p>In this particular setting, the membership grade Â(s) can be interpreted as the probability that s belongs to the actual set Ȧ (hence there is no intrinsic gradualness modelled by this approach, contrary to Zadeh's intuition). It holds that Âc (s) = 1 -Â(s), but it is clear that the laws of excluded middle and contradiction hold (for instance Â∪ Âc (s)</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">= s∈A∪A c m(A) = 1), since if A is a realisation of Â, A c</formula><p>is the corresponding realisation of Âc ), and the fuzzy set connectives cannot be used unless some specific assumptions hold. A similar view is exploited by Lawry <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref> for his label semantics of vagueness in classification and learning tasks, considering random sets of labels that can be attached to a situation s by individuals uttering vague statements in a crisp way (declaring that, for instance, Jon is tall).</p><p>Note that the fuzzy integer measuring the cardinality of a fuzzy set representing an ill-known crisp set can be used to describe uncertainty about the cardinality of the underlying crisp entity. It is well-known that the expected cardinality of the random set defined by m is such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">s∈A m(A) • |A| = s∈S Â(s) = 1 0 | Â( )| d = k i=1 | Â( i )|( i -i-1 ), where the range Â(S) = { k = 1 &gt; • • • &gt; 0 = 0}.</formula><p>In this view, the weight ii-1 is clearly the probability that the random set m has cardinality | Â( i )|.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.4.">Gradual rough sets and similarity relations</head><p>A typical example of ill-known set is a rough set <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref>. Here, uncertainty takes the form of a partition of the universe S of objects, say S 1 , ... , S k . All that is known about any object in S is which subset of the partition it belongs to. So each subset A of S is only known in terms of its upper and lower approximations, a pair ( A * , A * ) such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">A * = {S i , S i ∩ A ∅} and A * = {S i , S i ⊆ A}.</formula><p>It is clear that truth-functionality generally fails again as</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">( A ∩ B) * ⊂ A * ∩ B * and A * ∪ B * ⊂ (A ∪ B) * .</formula><p>Rough sets can be extended by replacing an equivalence relation by a fuzzy similarity relation <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>, thus introducing degrees of possibility and necessity that an element belongs to a given crisp set, due to the fuzzy granulation of the referential.</p><p>There is an extensive literature on fuzzy rough sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[73]</ref> that seems to be unrelated to another view of fuzziness that also relies on similarity relations and induces a form of granulation of the referential, originally due to Höhle <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74]</ref> and taken up by Klawonn <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">[75]</ref>. The latter approach has roots in category theory and Heyting algebra, whereby a valued notion of equality is introduced in the form of a similarity relation. A referential set S is supposed to be equipped with a similarity-relation E that is symmetric, reflexive and transitive with respect to a triangular norm. Similarity classes [s] with membership functions [s] = E(x, •) induce a family of fuzzy sets covering the referential, and that are viewed as fuzzy points. The notion of extensional fuzzy set with respect to a similarity relation seems to generalise the notion of exact set in rough set theory, that is formed by the union of equivalence classes. The so-called extensional hull of a fuzzy set, viewed as the smallest extensional fuzzy set containing it seems to be akin with the upper approximation of this fuzzy set in the sense of the fuzzy points. In particular the extensional hull h(A) of a set A is of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">h(A) (s) = sup t∈S E(s, t)</formula><p>that does coincide with the upper fuzzy approximation of set A in the sense of fuzzy rough sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>. So this literature deals with the approximate description of sets by means of fuzzy points in the sense of a fuzzy equality relation. This extensional hull is also the definition of a fuzzy set as viewed by Ruspini <ref type="bibr" target="#b75">[76]</ref>, and the literature on similarity-based reasoning <ref type="bibr" target="#b76">[77]</ref>. This kind of fuzzy approximation of sets again leads to a non-truth-functional calculus. The connections and difference of point of view between fuzzy rough sets and similarity-based reasoning after Ruspini, have already been emphasised <ref type="bibr" target="#b77">[78]</ref>. In fact, rough sets and granulation insists on the idea that elements of the referential cannot be distinguished, while similarity, often then termed fuzzy equality, viewed as the negative of a distance, insists on making a difference between elements however close they can be. In other words, fuzzy equalities satisfy separability (x y implies E(x, y) &lt; 1), while indistinguishability relations, generalising equivalence relations do not satisfy it. More generally, the connection between fuzzy granulation, similarity semantics, fuzzy points in the style of Höhle and Klawonn, and rough sets would deserve a detailed study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Uncertainty and fuzzy sets of higher order</head><p>The same situation as for ill-known sets can be observed when considering higher-order fuzzy sets, whose motivation is often to capture uncertainty about the membership grades. The most elementary form of this kind is the intervalvalued fuzzy set (IVFS). Such IVFSs are often motivated by the idea that they define ill-known fuzzy sets. The IVFS calculus has become popular in the fuzzy engineering community of the USA because of many recent publications by Mendel and his colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b78">[79]</ref>. If intervals of membership grades are interpreted as partial ignorance about precise degrees, the truth-functional calculus of IVFSs suffers from the same ambiguity as Kleene logic applied to ill-known sets, of which it is a many-valued extension.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.">Interval-valued fuzzy sets and their variants</head><p>Following Zadeh <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, an interval-valued fuzzy set is defined by an interval-valued membership function, that is, a mapping I F from the universe U to the set of closed intervals in [0, 1]. Let I F (s) = [ F * (s), F * (s)]. The union, intersection and complementation of IVFSs are obtained by canonically extending fuzzy set-theoretic operations to interval-valued operands in the sense of interval arithmetic. As such operations are monotonic, this step is mathematically obvious. For instance, the most elementary fuzzy set operations are extended as follows, for conjunction F ∩ G, disjunction F ∪ G and negation F c , respectively:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">I F∩G (s) = [min( F * (s), G * (s)), min( F * (s), G * (s))], I F∪G (s) = [max( F * (s), G * (s)), max( F * (s), G * (s))], I F c (s) = [1 -F * (s), 1 -F * (s)].</formula><p>IVFSs are then viewed as a special case of L-fuzzy sets in the sense of Goguen <ref type="bibr" target="#b79">[80]</ref>, where</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">L = {(a, b), a ≤ b ∈ [0, 1]}.</formula><p>As a mathematical object, it is not of great generality (and is redundant in lattice-valued mathematics as argued by Gutierrez-Garcia and Rodabaugh <ref type="bibr" target="#b80">[81]</ref>). An IVFS is also a special case of type 2 fuzzy set (also introduced by Zadeh <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, and studied by Mendel and followers). In the case of type 2 fuzzy sets, the membership grades are themselves described as fuzzy subsets of the truth-set. Of course, all connectives of fuzzy set theory extend likewise to interval-valued fuzzy sets and their clones (like vague sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b81">[82]</ref>) and to type 2 fuzzy sets (using the extension principle). IVFSs can be studied as specific abstract algebraic structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b82">[83]</ref>, and a multiple-valued logic was recently proposed for them, called the triangle logic <ref type="bibr" target="#b83">[84]</ref>. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">[85]</ref> for a careful study of interval-arithmetics connectives for type 2 fuzzy sets; their results apply to the special case of IVFSs.</p><p>Independently, Atanassov <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> introduced the idea of defining a fuzzy set by ascribing a membership function + and a non-membership function -separately, assuming that an element cannot have degrees of membership and non-membership that sum up to more than 1. This idea seems to be a gradual extension of a proposal originally made by Narin'yani <ref type="bibr" target="#b85">[86]</ref>. Such a pair was given the misleading name of "Intuitionistic Fuzzy Sets'' (see the discussion in <ref type="bibr" target="#b86">[87]</ref>). In the following we adopt the terminology of Cattaneo and Ciucci <ref type="bibr" target="#b87">[88]</ref>, speaking of orthopairs of fuzzy sets to designate the pair ( + , -), interpreting the inequality + (s) + -(s) ≤ 1 as a kind of orthogonality condition. The idea of independent assignments of membership and non-membership degrees corresponds to a natural intuition (explored in the next section) that differs from the one of IVFSs, but the calculus of Atanassov orthopairs turns out to be mathematically equivalent to the one of IVFSs (e.g. Deschrijver and Kerre <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>). In fact, many papers using Atanassov notions and terminology refer to an ill-known membership function approximated by the orthopair ( + , -) in the sense that + ≤ ≤ 1 --. In this section we stick to the older, more transparent IVFS terminology and framework.</p><p>Paradoxes of IVFSs are less blatant than those due to a truth-functional handling of ill-known sets (when a Kleene third truth-value is used to refer to incomplete knowledge) because in the latter case, the lack of excluded-middle law on Boolean propositions is a striking anomalous feature. In the case of fuzzy logic, laws of classical logic are violated anyway. However, the fact that interval-valued fuzzy sets have a weaker structure than the fuzzy set algebra they extend should act as a warning. Indeed, since fuzzy sets equipped with fixed connectives have a given well-defined structure, this structure should be valid whether the membership grades are known or not. Extending the contradiction law example from ill-known sets to ill-known fuzzy sets F, the property min( F (s), 1 -F (s)) ≤ 0.5 should hold whether F (s) is known or not. This is a weak form of the contradiction law. However, applying the truth-tables of interval-valued fuzzy sets to the case when I F (s) = [0, 1] (total ignorance) leads to min(I F (s), 1 -I F (s)) = [0, 1], which means a considerable loss of information. More generally, if the degree of membership F (s) is only known to belong to some subinterval [a, b] of the unit interval, the truth-functional calculus yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">F∩F c (s) = min( F (s), 1 -F (s)) ∈ [min(a, 1 -b), min(b, 1 -a)] = I F∩F c (s).</formula><p>Clearly, I F∩F c (s) is sometimes not included in [0, 1  2 ], while min( F (s), 1 -F (s)) always is. In fact, treating fuzzy sets with ill-known membership functions by means of a truth-functional calculus of IVFSs is similar to the paradoxical treatment of ill-known sets by means of Kleene's three-valued logics.</p><p>The basic point is that the calculus of IVFSs is a multiple-valued logic where the truth set [0, 1] is turned into the set of intervals on [0, 1], i.e. intervals are seen as conjunctive sets representing genuine (ontic) truth-values. This approach does not finely address the issue of ill-known membership grades, where the latter are nevertheless supposed to be precise, even if out of reach. Choosing intervals for truth-values is a matter of adopting a new representation convention, while reasoning about ill-known membership grades does not mean changing the truth set. When reasoning about ill-known membership grades, the truth set remains [0, 1] and truth-values obey the laws of some multiple-valued calculus on [0, 1]. Then, intervals model epistemic states about truth-values, they are epistemic subsets of truth-values, just like non-empty subsets of 2 are in the case of ill-known sets.</p><p>The fact that one cannot apply the truth-functional connectives to interval and type 2 fuzzy sets with the ambition to handle uncertain membership grades is similar to the situation of imprecise probability theory with respect to standard probability theory: the former is no longer additive, that is, you cannot assume that interval-valued probabilities of events [P * (A), P * (A)] (let alone fuzzy interval-valued probabilities, see de Cooman <ref type="bibr" target="#b88">[89]</ref>, and the appended discussion papers) obey an axiom such as [P * (A ∪ B), P * (A ∪ B)] = [P * (A), P * (A)] + [P * (B), P * (B)] if A ∩ B = ∅. Indeed, upper and lower probabilities, being computed as greatest lower bounds and least upper bounds over a probability family are respectively super-additive and sub-additive, in general <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.">A scenario that generates interval-valued and type 2 fuzzy sets</head><p>The only explanation often given for having interval-valued or fuzzy set-valued membership grades is that membership values are difficult to obtain but there is seldom a protocol provided to generate these intervals of fuzzy membership values. Yet, such a setting was suggested by Bellman and Zadeh a long time ago, and it has been cast in the framework of fuzzy databases some 25 years ago. Suppose S is a set of objects described by an attribute f : S → V , where V is some measurement scale. Let F : U → [0, 1] V represent an imprecise observation of the attribute f, i.e. for each s ∈ S, F(s) is a possibility distribution over V that represents our imprecise knowledge about f(s): For an arbitrary pair s ∈ U , v ∈ V , the possibility degree that v coincides with the true attribute value f(s</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">) is F(s)(v) ∈ [0, 1].</formula><p>In particular we assume that ∃v ∈ V, F(s)(v) = 1 (one value is possible). Dubois and Prade <ref type="bibr" target="#b89">[90]</ref> considered the problem of describing the set f -1 (A) ⊆ S of objects that satisfy a crisp property A, when f is only known via F. Because of incomplete information, the subset f -1 (A) is an ill-known set bracketed by a pair of fuzzy sets F * (A) and F * (A) defined by:</p><p>• F * (A) (s) = sup v∈A F(s) (v): all objects that are more or less possibly in f -1 (A).</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">• F * (A) (s) = inf v / ∈A 1 -F(s) (v):</formula><p>all objects that more or less surely belong to f -1 (A).</p><p>The pair ( F * (A), F * (A)) is such that Support( F * (A)) ⊆ f -1 (A) ⊆ core( F * (A)) and was called a twofold fuzzy set. This kind of interval-valued fuzzy set is special: interval membership grades are of the form [a, 1] or [0, b], and the bounds are not membership grades but degrees of uncertainty that an object satisfies property A or not. Moreover it is clear that you cannot apply interval arithmetics to fuzzy set connectives to compute F * (A ∪ B) and F * (A ∩ B).</p><p>If we replace the property A by a fuzzy property Ã, and the information on attribute values by a crisp disjunctive set-valued mapping F, then we have the case where membership grades of s to f -1 ( Ã) are gradual but ill known: they belong to the disjunctive set { Ã( f (s)) : f (s) ∈ F(s)}. Then we can again define a pair of fuzzy sets F * ( Ã) and F * ( Ã) enclosing the ill-known one as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">• F * ( Ã) (s) = sup{ Ã( f (s)) : f (s) ∈ F(s)}; • F * (A) (s) = inf{ Ã( f (s)) : f (s) ∈ F(s)}.</formula><p>Likewise, you cannot apply interval arithmetics to fuzzy set connectives to compute F * ( Ã ∪ B) and F * ( Ã ∩ B). In the general case where both the knowledge about f is fuzzy and the property Ã is fuzzy, the use of Bellman and Zadeh's fuzzy truth-values <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">[91]</ref> enables us to obtain a type 2 fuzzy set f -1 ( Ã) of objects more or less satisfying property Ã as follows: the membership grade of s to f -1 ( Ã) is known via a disjunctive fuzzy set of possible membership values ˜ F-1 ( Ã) (s) = Ã( F(s)) = (s) for short, computed by applying the extension principle to the function Ã. Namely:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">(s) ( ) = sup{ F(s) (v)|v : Ã(v) = } if -1 Ã ( ) ∅, 0 o t h e r w i s e . (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">)</formula><p>This general case subsumes the two former ones. In particular, if Ã is actually a crisp set A, then (s) is a possibility distribution on the binary set {0,1}, and F * (A) (s) = (s) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>, F * (A) (s) = 1-(s) (0). It has been noticed for a long time that fuzzy truth-values ideally viewed as fuzzy intervals on the unit interval cannot be applied to crisp statements of the form x ∈ A that do not have intermediary truth-values <ref type="bibr" target="#b91">[92]</ref>. On the other hand, if F is crisp, then (s) is a crisp subset of the unit interval upper bounded by F * ( Ã) (s) and lower bounded by F * ( Ã) (s). The general approach thus inherits from these special cases the lack of truth-functionality: we cannot blindly apply the type 2 fuzzy set connectives to fuzzy truth-values (s), because these fuzzy set-valued membership grades are epistemic constructs: they are disjunctive fuzzy subsets of truth-values describing an incomplete information state. In that respect, the meaning of "fuzzy truth-values'' proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b92">[93]</ref> is sometimes misunderstood, as they cannot be at the same time genuine truth-values and ill-known ones. Such fuzzy truth-values are fuzzy sets of the unit interval understood as a representation of what is known of the truth-value of a gradual statement x is Ã when all is known about x is that x is F <ref type="bibr" target="#b90">[91]</ref>. It is then clear that is a possibility distribution over the set of truth-degrees, and not a truth-value of its own (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b93">[94]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.">Reasoning with ill-known gradual truth-values</head><p>A logic that reasons about ill-known membership grades cannot be truth-functional. It should handle weighted formulas where the weight is an interval representing our knowledge about the truth-value of the formula, similar to Pavelka's logic <ref type="bibr" target="#b94">[95]</ref>, Lehmke's weighted fuzzy logic <ref type="bibr" target="#b95">[96]</ref>. It should add the algebraic properties of the underlying logic as constraints to be respected by the formal derivations. Interval-weighted formulas are also signed formulas in many-valued logic. Reasoning about ill-known membership grades is then a matter of constraint propagation, especially interval analysis. Simple interval arithmetics on connectives is not good enough to compute accurate results. Automated reasoning methods based on signed formulae in multiple-valued logics follow this line and handle inference problems by means of optimisation techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">[97]</ref>.</p><p>The generic reasoning problem in epistemic interval-valued fuzzy logic is of the following form: Given a set of weighted many-valued propositional formulas </p><formula xml:id="formula_20">{ p i , [a i , b i ]), i = 1, ... ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">i ) ∈ [a i , b i ], i = 1, ... , n.</formula><p>This problem cannot be solved by a truth-functional interval-valued fuzzy logic. A simpler instance of this problem is the one of finding the membership function of a complex combination of IVFSs. It comes down to finding the tightest interval containing the truth-value of a many-valued formula, given intervals containing the truth-values of its atoms. For instance, finding the membership function of F ∩ F c when the knowledge about F is described by an IVFS comes down to solving for each element of the universe of discourse the following problem: maximise (resp. minimise)</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">f (x) = min(x, 1 -x) under the constraint x ∈ [a, b].</formula><p>Since the function f is not monotonic, the solution is obviously not (always) the interval [min(a, 1b), min(b, 1a)] suggested by IVFS connectives, it is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">f (x) ∈ [a, b] if b ≤ 0.5, f (x) ∈ [min(a, 1 -b), 0.5] if a ≤ 0.5 ≤ b, f (x) ∈ [1 -b, 1 -a] if a ≥ 0.5.</formula><p>Only the first and the third case match the IVFS connectives solution.</p><p>In Lukasiewicz logic, using the bounded sum and linear product connectives, inferring in the interval-valued setting comes down to solving linear programming problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b96">[97]</ref>. Especially the condition F ∩ F c = ∅ is always trivially valid using linear product, even if F is only known as an IVFS, since max(0, x + (1x) -1) = 0.</p><p>In fact this kind of reasoning can be handled at the syntactic level by reifying degrees of truth. For instance, in Łukasiewicz logic, one may express that t( p i ) ∈ [a i , b i ] by introducing truth-constants, and asserting the truth of the formula a i → p i ∧ p i → b i , where ∧ is interpreted as the minimum, and → by Łukasiewicz (in fact, any residuated) implication. Indeed, the truth-value of this expression is 1 as soon as t( p i ) ≥ a i and t( p i )</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">≤ b i . Proving that { p i , [a i , b i ]), i = 1, ... , n} implies that (p, [a, b]), comes down to proving a → p ∧ p → b from {a i → p i ∧ p i → b i , i = 1, .</formula><p>.. , n} in (for instance) Łukasiewicz logic. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b97">[98]</ref>, Hájek also considers this kind of reasoning with interval-valued fuzzy logic in the format of a fuzzy version of the modal logic S5.</p><p>In logical approaches to incompleteness and contradiction, the goal of preserving tautologies of the underlying logic (classical or multiple-valued) should supersede the goal of maintaining a truth-functional setting. Considering subsets or fuzzy subsets of a truth-set as genuine truth-values leads to new many-valued logics that do not address the issue of uncertain reasoning on the underlying original logic. Such "power-set logics'', under the ontic view, are special cases of lattice-valued logics that need another motivation than reasoning under uncertainty. Our critique encompasses as well the truth-functional calculus of type 2 fuzzy sets (mathematically studied for its own sake by <ref type="bibr" target="#b84">[85]</ref>), since it again considers epistemic fuzzy sets of truth-values as truth-values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Bipolar frameworks</head><p>At this point, it is instrumental to introduce the issue of bipolarity in fuzzy set theory. Bipolarity refers to the propensity of the human mind to reason and make decisions on the basis of positive and negative affects. It expresses the fact that beyond ranking pieces of information or acts in terms of plausibility, utility and so on, the human mind also relies on absolute landmarks with positive and negative flavour, plus a third landmark expressing neutrality or indifference, corresponding to the boundary between positive and negative zones. For instance people make choices by checking the good sides and the bad sides of alternatives separately. Then they choose according to whether the good or the bad sides are stronger. Results in cognitive psychology have pointed out the importance of bipolar reasoning in human cognitive activities <ref type="bibr" target="#b98">[99,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b99">100]</ref>. It even seems that positive and negative affects are not processed in the same area of the brain.</p><p>A bipolar scale (L , &gt;) is a totally ordered set with a prescribed interior element 0 called neutral, separating the positive evaluations &gt; 0 from the negative ones &lt; 0. Mathematically, if the scale is equipped with a binary operation (an aggregation operator), 0 is an idempotent element for , possibly acting as an identity. When the scale is bounded, the bottom (fully negative) is denoted ⊥ and the top (fully positive) .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Examples.</head><p>• The most obvious quantitative bipolar scale is the (completed) real line equipped with the standard addition, where 0 is the neutral level. Isomorphic to it is the unit interval equipped with an associative uninorm like x y/(x y</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">+ (1 -x)(1 -y)).</formula><p>Then the neutral point is 0.5, 0 plays the same role as -∞ and 1 as +∞ in the real line. Also the interval [-1, 1] is often used as a bipolar scale. • The simplest qualitative bipolar scale contains three elements: {-, 0, +}.</p><p>In bipolar scales, the negative side of the scale is the inverse mirror of the positive one. An object is evaluated on such a bipolar scale as being either positive or negative or neutral. It cannot be positive and negative at the same time. This is called a univariate bipolar framework.</p><p>Another type of bipolar framework uses two distinct totally ordered scales L + and L -for separately evaluating the positive and the negative information. This is the bivariate unipolar framework. Here each scale is unipolar in the sense that the neutral level is at one end of the scale. In a positive scale the bottom element is neutral. In a negative scale the top element is neutral. A bipolar scale can be viewed as the union of a positive and a negative scale L + ∪ L -extending the ordering relations on each scale so ∀ + ∈ L + , -∈ L -, + &gt; -. The symmetrisation of finite unipolar scales is incompatible with associative operations <ref type="bibr" target="#b100">[101]</ref>: only infinite bipolar scales seem to support such operations! Three forms of bipolarity can be found at work in the literature, we call types I, II, III for simplicity <ref type="bibr" target="#b101">[102]</ref>:</p><p>• Type I: Symmetric univariate bipolarity: It relies on the use of bipolar scales. The two truth-values true and false of classical logic offer a basic view of bipolarity. However, the neutral value only appears in three-valued logics. Probability theory exhibits a type I bipolarity as the probability of an event is clearly living on a bipolar scale [0, 1] whose top means totally sure and bottom impossible (not to be confused with true and false). The neutral value is 0.5 and refers to the total uncertainty about whether an event or its contrary occurs (not to be confused with half-true).</p><p>In decision theory, Cumulative Prospect Theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b102">[103]</ref> uses the real line as a bipolar scale. It is numerical, additive, and bipolar. It measures the importance of positive affects and negative affects separately, by two monotonic set functions + , -and finally computes a net predisposition N = + --. • Type II: Symmetric bivariate bipolarity: It works with a unipolar scale L where ⊥ = 0 is neutral. Here, an item is judged according to two independent evaluations:</p><p>• one in favor of the item, say + ∈ L • one in disfavor of the item, say -∈ L.</p><p>This is typical of formal argumentation frameworks <ref type="bibr" target="#b103">[104]</ref>. Positive and negative strengths are computed similarly on the basis of the same data and can be conflicting. If L is equipped with an order-reversing map , a constraint + ≤ ( -) may limit the allowed conflict between positive and negative information: it prevents the pair of ratings ( + , -) from expressing the idea of being fully in favour of an option and fully against it. An example of such an evaluation framework with limited conflict stems an imprecise rating on a univariate bipolar scale L in the form of an interval [ * , * ]. It is clear that lower bounds of ratings on L live on a positive unipolar scale (L + = L) and upper bounds of ratings on L live on a negative unipolar scale (L -= L , interpreting ∈ L as neutral in L -). Note that in this case, scales L + and L -are one level higher than L, in the sense that there is an actual value ∈ L and the bounds * , * represent knowledge about . It is a case where type II bipolarity represents uncertainty about type I bipolarity (as seems to be one motivation in Atanassov construction). Equivalently we can use two scales of the same nature, letting + = * and -= ( * ), where is the order-reversing map in L. This is the situation when translating IVFSs into Atanassov orthopairs of fuzzy sets. This situation is typical of uncertainty theories <ref type="bibr" target="#b104">[105]</ref> leaving room for incomplete information where each event A is evaluated by an interval [C(A), Pl(A)], C(A) and Pl(A) reflecting their certainty and plausibility respectively. Then, + = C(A), and -= C(A c ) = 1 -Pl(A). A good example of certainty/plausibility pairs displaying this kind of bipolarity are belief and plausibility functions of Shafer <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. In the case of possibility/necessity measures, the two scales are tightly related by the constraint stating that positive necessity degree N (A) &gt; 0 implies a maximal possibility degree (A) = 1. So in this case the bivariate setting is degenerated and the pair (C(A), (A)) can be mapped in a one-to-one way to a symmetric type I bipolar scale (by considering the set-function (N (A) + (A))/2, suggested by the authors a long time ago <ref type="bibr">[20, p. 125]</ref>, and exploited at length by Liu <ref type="bibr" target="#b105">[106]</ref>).</p><p>• Type III: Asymmetric bipolarity: In this form of bipolarity, the negative part of the information is not of the same nature as the positive part, while in type II bipolarity only the polarities are opposite. Especially, in the case of merging in the Type III setting, negative and positive pieces of information will not be aggregated using the same principles. The positive side is not a mirror image of the negative side either. Nevertheless, positive and negative information cannot be completely unrelated. They must obey minimal consistency requirements. In uncertainty modelling or knowledge representation, heterogeneous bipolarity corresponds to the pair (knowledge, data). Knowledge is negative information in the sense that it expresses constraints on how the world behaves, by ruling out impossible or unlikely relations: laws of physics, common sense background knowledge expressed by rules (i.e. claims like "birds fly'') are instances of negative knowledge. On the contrary, data represent positive information because it represents examples, actual observations on the world or cases.</p><p>A not yet observed event is not judged impossible; observing it is a positive token of support. Accumulating negative information leads to ruling out more possible states of the world (the more constraints, the less possible worlds). Accumulating positive information enlarges the set of possibilities as being guaranteed by empirical observation. It is supposed that both kinds of information, even if independent, are coherent with each other, in the sense that observations should lie within the possibilities left by the background knowledge. In decision making, heterogeneous bipolarity concerns the opposition between constraints (possibly flexible ones) that state which solutions to a problem are unfeasible, and goals or criteria, that state which solutions are preferred. This kind of bipolarity is extensively discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b106">[107]</ref> within the framework of possibility theory.</p><p>The difference between positive and negative information in type III bipolarity is reflected by the different types of inference processes at work in rule-based reasoning (propagating constraints about the current situation) and case-based reasoning (by extrapolating similarities between past situations and the current one). In classical logic, this distinction between positive and negative knowledge can be reflected by the distinction between conjunctive and disjunctive normal forms: A formula in conjunctive normal form can be viewed as a conjunction of clauses (hence rules in the sense of material implication) that naturally represent constraints; a formula in disjunctive normal form can be viewed as a disjunction of products (hence data-tuples in the sense of databases). Note that the latter is how Mamdani <ref type="bibr" target="#b107">[108]</ref> proposed to model fuzzy rule-based systems, then viewed as repositories of imprecise data or cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b108">[109]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">Bipolar fuzzy sets: more vs. less information than fuzzy sets</head><p>Applying the notion of bipolarity to the fuzzy set framework, it is clear that the membership scale [0, 1] of a fuzzy set is a univariate bipolar scale. The cross-over point 0.5 is neutral, in the sense that in case a final Boolean membership decision is to be made, it is indifferent to consider an element with membership grade 0.5 as a member of the set or not. One may argue that symmetric bivariate bipolarity has been introduced in fuzzy set theory by Atanassov <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. However, the isomorphism between Atanassov calculus and IVFS calculus has created some confusion on the difference between using orthopairs of fuzzy sets and IVFSs. An important issue when considering pairs of membership functions is whether it represents more or less information than a single one. This question somewhat interferes with the conjunctive or disjunctive interpretations of sets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.1.">Losing information: Atanassov pairs as interval-valued fuzzy sets</head><p>This univariate bipolar view of membership functions is adequate when the membership function is an object of investigation in itself, like the boundary of some image region, the preference pattern of some decision-maker, or the representation of a linguistic term. In particular, this membership function is a very rich and complete information. But sometimes (as for linguistic terms), the precise membership function of a conjunctive fuzzy set may be out of reach, and fuzzy sets with disjunctive interval-valued membership grades appear as a good way of accounting for such (semantic) uncertainty. The interval-valued framework can be expressed in symmetric bivariate bipolar terms considering a lower membership function + F for F and a lower membership function - F for its complement ( F ) = 1 -F , expressing positive and negative information about F, respectively. An orthopair ( + F , - F ) in the sense of Cattaneo and Ciucci is obtained (since + (s) ≤ ( -(s)) must be respected. Set-theoretic operations proposed by Atanassov directly derive from operations on interval-valued fuzzy sets, letting + F = F * and - F = ( F * ):</p><p>• Conjunction: The pair (min( F + , G + ), max( F -, G -)) represents information about the membership function min( F , G ). • Disjunction: The pair (max( F + , G + ), min( F -, G -)) represents information about the membership function max( F , G ). • Complement: The pair ( - F , + F ) represents information about the membership function ( F ). Three remarks are then crucial for a proper understanding of this symmetric bivariate bipolar framework:</p><p>(1) An orthopair ( + F , - F ) represents less information than a membership function. (2) Precisely known fuzzy sets thus correspond to orthopairs ( F , 1 -F ). But note that mathematically speaking, other kinds of embedding of fuzzy sets into orthopairs can be envisaged. (3) The truth-functional calculus of orthopairs again fails to optimally handle the incomplete information pervading membership functions.</p><p>At this point, it is interesting to point out the natural semantics of Atanassov orthopairs in terms of voting <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Namely, F + (s) may represent the proportion of voters in a population N that consider that s is F. Likewise, F -(s) may represent the proportion of voters in the same population that consider that s is not F. And 1 -F + (s) -F -(s) corresponds to abstention rate. It is clear that, the use of truth-functional connectives is again debatable. For instance, if orthopairs ( + F , - F ) and ( + G , - G ) are available, the voting result one can expect concerning F ∪ G remains imprecisely known. Namely, using Frechet bounds:</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">+ F∪G (s) ∈ [max( F + (s), G + (s)), F + (s) + G + (s)], - F∪G (s) ∈ [max(0, F -(s) + G -(s) -1), min( F -(s), G -(s))].</formula><p>Adopting truth-functional connectives needs assumptions on how people that vote for (or against) F vote for (or against) G.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.2.">Gaining information: bipolar possibility theory</head><p>In the case of a disjunctive fuzzy set, the situation is quite different: since the membership function is interpreted as a possibility distribution , the membership scale [0,1] is understood as a negative unipolar scale, where an element with membership 0 is considered impossible while the value 1 is clearly neutral: there is complete ignorance about elements with possibility 1 as to their being the right one. In this case, the membership function represents incomplete information about another ill-known object, and can also be viewed</p><p>• either as the class of possibility distributions P( ) = { ≤ } more specific than , corresponding to epistemic states reachable from by the arrival of new information <ref type="bibr" target="#b109">[110]</ref>. • or as the class of probability measures P( ) = {P, P(A) ≤ (A), A measurable}, dominated by the possibility measure induced by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b110">111]</ref>.</p><p>In such a framework, considering imprecise possibility distributions, even if conceivable, does not always sound a very promising perspective, as a possibility distribution is already expressing incomplete information. In particular, intervals [N (A), (A)] evaluating events are of the form However, a bipolar view of possibility theory has been proposed, whereby a second distribution : S → L can be introduced such that ≤ , that supplements the information given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b111">[112,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b106">107]</ref>. In bipolar terms, a possibility distribution clearly expresses negative information: ( ) is the membership function of the fuzzy set of more or less impossible elements. On the contrary, reflects empirical support stemming from collected data: (s) = 0 only indicates the lack of evidence for s. For instance, is the set of models of a possibilistic logic base, describing constraints the actual state should obey. The possibility expressed by is only potential, while the introduction of a second distribution ≤ may account for actual possibility: it is sufficient that (s) = 1 for s to be actually possible; elements such that (s) &gt; 0 have guaranteed possibility and can be viewed as a sufficiency distribution. The inequality ≤ models coherence between the two kinds of information. The degree of guaranteed possibility of an event A is computed as (A) = min s∈A (s). It evaluates the extent to which all realisations of A are actually possible. Set-function is anti-monotonic with respect to inclusion and min-decomposable for the union operation.</p><p>This kind of bipolarity is clearly of the third type (asymmetric bivariate) as information determining is of a different nature than the information determining . While the pair of set-functions (N , ) reflects the duality between "possible'' and "necessary'', the pair (N , ) rather expresses the duality between necessity and sufficiency.</p><p>Clearly, the use of the interval-like pair of distributions ,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> corresponds to adding information to (the latter being understood as 0, ), instead of making it more uncertain, since the lower distribution comes down to adding positive evidence to existing negative possibilistic information. This point is where there is total divergence between orthopairs ( + F , - F ) representing ill-known fuzzy sets and orthopairs ( , ( )) representing bipolar possibilistic information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.3.">Bipolar handling of disjunctive sets of possibilistic epistemic states</head><p>Under a purely possibilistic framework, one may consider that the pair , models the (disjunctive) set P( , ) = { , ≤ ≤ } of epistemic states . P( , ) may account for a meta-epistemic state, in the sense that it may represent what an agent knows about the actual knowledge of another entity <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. Under this view, represents what the agent knows at least, while is what the entity knows at most, as perceived by the former agent.</p><p>The pair , represents more precise information than a single potential possibility distribution (identified as P(0, ) = { , ≤ }). , corresponds to the orthopair ( , ( )). The proper embedding of membership functions into the set of orthopairs is → (0, ( )) (corresponding to the absence of positive information), that is, different from the one in Atanassov theory.</p><p>According to the possibilistic semantics, the conjunction of two pairs of distributions ( 1 , 1 ) and ( 1 , 1 ) corresponds to a more informative situation expressed by the intersection of meta-epistemic states</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">P( 1 , 1 ) ∩ P( 2 , 2 ) = { : max( 1 , 2 ) ≤ ≤ min( 1 , 2 )}.</formula><p>It corresponds, in the language of orthopairs, to the following intersection connective, strikingly different from the one in Atanassov framework:</p><p>( 1 , ( 1 )) ∩ ( 2 , ( 2 )) = (max( 1 , 2 ), max( ( 1 ), ( 2 ))).</p><p>It clearly reduces the range of potentially but not yet actually possible epistemic states. Note that this time, the proposed connective on orthopairs exactly reflects the expected semantics, since P( 1 , 1 ) ∩ P( 2 , 2 )) = P(( 1 , ( 1 )) ∩ ( 2 , ( 2 ))).</p><p>In the case of disjunction, one may suggest using P(min( 1 , 2 ), max( 1 , 2 ))), which corresponds to</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">( 1 , ( 1 )) ∪ ( 2 , ( 2 )) = (min( 1 , 2 ), min( ( 1 ), ( 2 )))</formula><p>in terms of orthopairs, but it clearly imperfectly reflects the union P( 1 , 1 ) ∪ P( 2 , 2 )) that is generally included in the former. The meaning of a negation connective in this context is unclear. One might interpret it as changing each epistemic state in P( , ) into its fuzzy set negation thus yielding ( , ( )) = ( ( ), ), i.e. Atanassov negation, which encodes the idea of "believing the opposite'' to what is expressed by , .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.4.">Clouds</head><p>Another understanding of nested pairs of [0, 1]-valued distributions , is in terms of probability families. This is the notion of cloud proposed by Neumaier <ref type="bibr" target="#b112">[113]</ref>. Recently, clouds have been cast in the possibility theory setting <ref type="bibr" target="#b113">[114]</ref>. A cloud , then encodes the probability family P( , ) = P(1 -) ∩ P( ). Again, , is clearly more informative than alone: clouds enable tighter probability bounds on events to be derived than with a single possibility distribution, i.e.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>max(N (A), (A c )) ≤ P(A) ≤ min( (A), 1 -(A))</head><p>where and N are possibility and necessity measures based on , and is a guaranteed possibility measure based on .</p><p>In this view, bipolarity is symmetric again, as and 1-can be indifferently exchanged. Namely, 1-is interpreted as another standard (potential) possibility distribution, which is not the case with the previous semantics in terms of meta-epistemic states. In particular (A c ) (resp. 1 -(A)) is just the degree of necessity (resp. possibility) of event A computed from possibility distribution 1 -. Moreover, clouds , clearly contain the same information as clouds 1 -, 1 -, so that negation does not mean much in this framework. Moreover the case when = is called "thin cloud'' and it represent the maximally informative case, corresponding to the Atanassov style embedding of fuzzy sets in his orthopairs. The same conjunction and disjunction of orthopairs as in Section 9.3 are sanctioned by the cloud approach, but conjunction only partially captures the probabilistic semantics this time: indeed, for instance P(min( 1 , 2 )) ⊂ P( 1 ) ∩ P( 2 ), generally.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.5.">Bipolar preference</head><p>Finally another interpretive framework for IVFSs and Atanassov orthopairs is in preference modelling. Consider S as a set of criteria, and (s) the rating of some alternative with respect to criterion s. This rating belongs to a bipolar scale [0, 1] where 0.5 represents indifference, 1 excellence, and 0 total failure to satisfy the criterion. In that case, IVFSs clearly capture the idea of imprecise rating, as the idea of infinite precision does not sound realistic in this kind of context. This form of uncertainty has sometimes been described in terms of Atanassov orthopairs in multicriteria decision processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b114">[115]</ref>. Then, the Atanassov terminology in this case is uselessly misleading as it is just another encoding of interval-valued computations. It only makes uncertainty processing more opaque than the IVFS setting.</p><p>However a purely bipolar view of decision evaluation is at odds with this kind of interpretation. First, even when is precise, the use of a bipolar evaluation scale may lead to a bipolar handling of the decision process, distinguishing between negative arguments against an alternative (those elements s with (s) &lt; 0.5) and positive arguments in favour of this alternative (those elements s with (s) &gt; 0.5), and handling the two sides separately in further information aggregation procedures (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b115">[116]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b116">[117]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b117">[118]</ref> in the numerical setting, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b118">[119]</ref> in the qualitative setting).</p><p>A quite different approach consists in considering two points of view on evaluating alternatives, by listing, on the one hand, constraints that such alternatives should satisfy, and, on the other hand, a set of goals (or desires) that should preferably be attained. In this view, S is a set of alternatives, (s) is the extent to which alternative s is feasible (according to all constraints), and (s) to what extent it is preferred (according to all goals). The inequality (s) ≤ (s) mirrors the fact that it is more demanding to be preferred than to be feasible. Under this view, the IVFS [ , ] does not express any kind of uncertainty, and 1 -(s) is the extent to which an alternative s should be rejected as unfeasible. It leads to combination operations that differ from those inspired by the IVFS setting but agree with the possibilistic bipolar setting: it is clear that an alternative satisfies two constraints 1 and 2 if and only if it satisfies at least the constraint min( 1 , 2 ) (feasibility is decreased), and that the satisfaction increases as more goals are attained so that the degree of satisfaction induced by 1 and 2 is at least max( 1 (s), 2 (s)). This asymmetric bipolar view, developed in more details in <ref type="bibr" target="#b119">[120]</ref> does not match Atanassov calculus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.">Conclusion</head><p>This paper is a plea for significance when using fuzzy sets as a modelling tool. As such, a fuzzy set is an abstract mathematical entity and its proper use in practice needs a proper interpretive framework. Noticeably, sets, whether fuzzy or not, should be differently handled when they represent objective entities and when they model incomplete knowledge about an ill-known precise entity. In particular, fuzzy sets viewed as possibility distributions, should be handled in some kind of possible worlds semantics, as they represent mutually exclusive elements. However, the role of fuzziness is not always to capture uncertainty, just to make Boolean notions gradual, for instance uncertainty, in the case of possibility theory. The distinction between ontic and epistemic interpretations of sets (that are viewed as a conjunction or a disjunction of elements) is important when applying the mathematics of standard fuzzy sets to real problems, and it becomes crucial to keep it in mind when studying higher-order fuzzy sets where membership grades are themselves intervals or fuzzy sets of membership values. In particular, insofar as higher-order fuzzy sets are supposed to represent uncertainty about lower-order fuzzy sets, straightforward interval arithmetic extensions of fuzzy set algebras achieve a poor approximation of the process of reasoning under such uncertainty, a process that cannot rely on a compositional calculus.</p><p>Atanassov's "intuitionistic'' fuzzy sets are shown to be somewhat misleading for several reasons. It has been repeatedly said that the intuitionistic nature of this construction is dubious, because the Atanassov system is isomorphic to algebras of IVFSs. Interpreting Atanassov orthopairs just in terms of ill-known membership functions thus makes orthopairs of membership functions just another encoding of interval-valued fuzzy sets. The most natural interpretation of Atanassov system is in terms of bipolarity, whereby membership and non-membership functions correspond to independent and consistent pieces of positive and negative information or preference. While the epistemic understanding of interval-valued fuzzy sets can be captured by type II (symmetric) bipolarity, there is another view whereby pairs of membership and non-membership functions as considered more informative than single membership functions, contrary to the IVFS-based uncertain fuzzy set view. However, the corresponding extensions of fuzzy set-theoretic operations to orthopairs of membership functions are then generally at odds from the IVFS-like connectives that Atanassov proposed.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>[a, 1] or [0, b], and are thus already very imprecise. For instance, if a quantity x is only known to lie between a and b &gt; a, considering these bounds as ill-known (for instance a ∈ [a -, a + ], b ∈ [b -, b + ]) sounds like an overly precise representation involving two levels of knowledge: as [a, b] is an epistemic interval, the pair ([a -, a + ], [b -, b + ]) then represent meta-epistemic knowledge that can be useful if one has to reason about partial ignorance concerning x, i.e. propagating uncertainty about epistemic state [a, b], not if we have to propagate the uncertainty pervading the value of x. In the latter case one may adopt [a -, b + ] as a conservative representation of our knowledge about x.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>n}, find the most narrow interval [a, b] such that (p, [a, b]) can be deduced. It corresponds to the following optimisation problem: maximise (resp. minimise) t(p) under the constraints t( p</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>We too followed this path in papers from the 1980s.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>We denote bipolar fuzzy sets in this way, not to confuse them with orthopairs.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information and Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy sets as a basis for a theory of possibility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On databases with incomplete information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lipski</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between attitudes and evaluative space: a critical review, with emphasis on the separability of positive and negative substrates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Cacioppo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Berntson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The concept of a linguistic variable and its application to approximate reasoning, Part I</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Atanassov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Intuitionistic Fuzzy Sets</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Physica-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Soft set theory-first results</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Molodtsov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Mathematics with Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vagueness</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Routledge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>London</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An information-based discussion of vagueness: six scenarios leading to vagueness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Esteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Godo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Categorization in Cognitive Science</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lefebvre</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="891" to="909" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Chapter 40</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The three semantics of fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The paradoxical success of fuzzy logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Elkan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Expert</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy entropy and conditioning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kosko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the relationship between some extensions of fuzzy set theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Deschrijver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kerre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Action representation and partially observable planning using epistemic logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Herzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Marquis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI-03)</title>
		<meeting>the International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI-03)<address><addrLine>Acapulco; San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1067" to="1072" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PRUF -a meaning representation language for natural languages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Man-Machine Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="460" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Set-based representations of conjunctive and disjunctive knowledge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Yager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Incomplete conjunctive information</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="797" to="810" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple modal logic for reasoning about revealed beliefs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sossai</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chemello</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5590</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="805" to="816" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ECSQARU</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy random variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Puri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ralescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="422" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Possibility Theory</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York (NY)</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Plenum Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shackle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Decision, Order and Time in Human Affairs</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>second ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general non-probabilistic theory of inductive reasoning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Spohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of UAI&apos;90</title>
		<meeting>UAI&apos;90</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier Science</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="322" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Finetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Theory of Probability</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Walley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Statistical Reasoning with Imprecise Probabilities</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When upper probabilities are possibility measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Possibility theory in constraint satisfaction problems: handling priority, preference and uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fargier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semiring-based constraint solving and optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R S</forename><surname>Bistarelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Montanari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metric spaces of fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Diamond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kloeden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0165-0114</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On a new class of distances between fuzzy numbers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S C</forename><surname>Bertoluzza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Corral</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathware and Soft Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation and application of fuzzy numbers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Heilpern</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0165-0114</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Belief change rules in ordinal and numerical uncertainty theories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Belief Change</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publisher</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="392" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy least squares</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Diamond</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0020-0255</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the variance of fuzzy random variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Körner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0165-0114</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Random Sets and Integral Geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Matheron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J.Wiley &amp; Sons</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Upper and lower probabilities induced by a multivalued mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dempster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Mathematical Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Shafer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">A Mathematical Theory of Evidence</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy random variables-I. Definitions and theorems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kwakernaak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Statistics with Vague Data, D</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>Reidel Publishing Company</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Higher order models for fuzzy random variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Couso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sánchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Equations with fuzzy numbers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Biacino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lettieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Approach to modelling and simulation of uncertain dynamical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hüllermeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Uncertainty, Fuzziness and Knowledge-Based Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">About yes/no queries against possibilistic databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bosc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Pivert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Intelligent Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="691" to="721" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete Optimization with Interval Data: Minmax Regret and Fuzzy Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kasperski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Studies in Fuzziness and Soft Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">228</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gradual elements in a fuzzy set</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soft Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applications of Fuzzy Sets to Systems Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Negoita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ralescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Birkhauser Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Basel</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Normality in fuzzy topological spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fuzzy Real Numbers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy addition in the L-fuzzy real line</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rodabaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Set and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy real numbers as Dededkind cuts with respect to a multiple-valued logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Höhle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Set and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The four operations of arithmetic on fuzzy numbers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mizumoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Systems Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nahmias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Operations on fuzzy numbers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Systems Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="626" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gradual numbers and their application to fuzzy interval analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fortin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fargier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="388" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Set defuzzification and Choquet integral</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ogura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ralescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Uncertainty, Fuzziness and Knowledge-Based Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On ignorance and contradiction considered as truth-values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Logic Journal of the IGPL</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Possibility theory, probability theory and multiple-valued logics: a clarification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Mathematics and Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Philosophical remarks on many-valued systems of propositional logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Łukasiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Selected Works</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Borkowski</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>North-Holland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1930">1930. 1970</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="481" to="495" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kleene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Introduction to Metamathematics, Van Nostrand</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1952">1952</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Partial logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Blamey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Philosophical Logic</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gabbay</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Guentner</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="353" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>second ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Singular terms, truth-value gaps, and free logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Van Fraassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Philosophy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="481" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interval-set algebra for qualitative knowledge representation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ICCI</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Abou-Rabia</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Koczkodaj</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="370" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shadowed sets: representing and processing fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pedrycz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Part B</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From possibilistic information to Kleene&apos;s strong multi-valued logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Cooman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fuzzy Sets, Logics and Reasoning about Knowledge</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="323" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Vagueness, truth and logic</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="300" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Singular terms, truth-value gaps, and free logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Fraassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Philosophy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="481" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Vagueness</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Routledge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>London</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fuzzy and random sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Orlov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Prikladno Mnogomiernii Statisticheskii Analyz, Nauka, Moscow</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="280" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Russian</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some new results concerning random sets and fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On modeling of linguistic information using random sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling and Reasoning with Vague Concepts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lawry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Studies in Computational Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Rough Sets-Theoretical Aspects of Reasoning about Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Pawlak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rough fuzzy sets and fuzzy rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of General Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparative study of fuzzy rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Radzikowska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kerre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Many-valued equalities, singletons and fuzzy partitions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Höhle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soft Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Klawonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fuzzy points, fuzzy relations and fuzzy functions</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Novak</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Perfilieva</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Physica-Verlag GmbH</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="453" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Discovering the World with Fuzzy Logic</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the semantics of fuzzy logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ruspini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Approximate Reasoning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Logical approaches to fuzzy similarity-based reasoning: an overview, Preferences and Similarities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Godo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CISM Courses and Lectures</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">504</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similarity versus preference in fuzzy set-based logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Modelling Incomplete Information: Rough Set Analysis, Studies in Fuzziness and Soft Computing</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Orlowska</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Physica Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="461" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advances in type-2 fuzzy sets and systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">177</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">L-fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Goguen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Order-theoretic, topological, categorical redundancies of interval-valued sets, grey sets, vague sets, intervalvalued &quot;intuitionistic&apos;&apos; sets, &quot;intuitionistic&apos;&apos; fuzzy sets and topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J G</forename><surname>García</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rodabaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vague sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B W L</forename><surname>Gau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man and Cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="610" to="614" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advances and challenges in interval-valued fuzzy logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cornelis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Deschrijver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kerre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="622" to="627" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Triangle algebras: a formal logic approach to interval-valued residuated lattices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Gasse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cornelis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Deschrijver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kerre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1042" to="1060" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b84">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The algebra of fuzzy truth values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="347" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b85">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sub-definite set-New data type for knowledge representation, Memo 4-232, Computing Center</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Narin'yani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Russian</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Novosibirsk, Russia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>with an English summary</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b86">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Terminological difficulties in fuzzy set theory-the case of</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gottwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hájek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kacprzyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intuitionistic Fuzzy Sets&apos;&apos;, Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="491" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b87">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic intuitionistic principles in fuzzy set theories and its extensions (A terminological debate on Atanassov IFS)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cattaneo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ciucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3198" to="3219" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b88">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A behavioural model for vague probability assessments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>De Cooman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b89">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some issues in knowledge representation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Twofold fuzzy sets and rough sets</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b90">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local and fuzzy logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bellman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fuzzy Sets, Fuzzy Logic, and Fuzzy Systems: Selected Papers by Lotfi A. Zadeh</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>River Edge, NJ, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>World Scientific Publishing Co., Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="335" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b91">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A computational approach to approximate and plausible reasoning with applications to expert systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="747" to="748" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b92">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy logic and approximate reasoning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Synthese</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b93">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy-set based logics-an history-oriented presentation of their main developments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Esteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Godo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.elsevier.com/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Handbook of The History of Logic</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gabbay</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Woods</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="449" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Many-valued and Nonmonotonic Turn in Logic</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b94">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Metamathematics of Fuzzy Logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hájek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b95">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Degrees of truth and degrees of validity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lehmke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Discovering the World with Fuzzy Logic</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Physica Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="237" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b96">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proof theory of many-valued logic-linear optimization-logic design: connections and interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hähnle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soft Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b97">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On vagueness, truth-values and fuzzy logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hájek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Studia Logica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="382" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b98">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Measurement of Meaning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Osgood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Suci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tannenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
			<publisher>University of Illinois Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b99">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond bipolar conceptualizations and measures: the case of attitudes and evaluative space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Cacioppo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Berntson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personality and Social Psychology Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b100">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Moebius transform on symmetric ordered structures and its application to capacities on finite sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grabisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Discrete Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b101">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An introduction to bipolar representations of information and preference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Intelligent Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="866" to="877" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b102">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advances in prospect theory: cumulative representation of uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Risk and Uncertainty</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="323" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b103">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using arguments for making and explaining decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Amgoud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">173</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b104">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.wiley.com/Chapter" />
		<title level="m">Formal representations of uncertainty</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bouyssou</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pirlot</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="156" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Decision-making-Concepts and Methods</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b105">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uncertainty theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Studies in Fuzziness and Soft Computing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>second ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b106">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An overview of the asymmetric bipolar representation of positive and negative information in possibility theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1355" to="1366" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b107">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of fuzzy logic to approximate reasoning using linguistic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mamdani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1182" to="1191" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b108">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy set-based methods in instance-based reasoning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hüllermeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="322" to="332" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b109">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Handbook on Defeasible Reasoning and Uncertainty Management Systems</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Smets</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publisher</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="226" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Quantified Representation of Uncertainty and Imprecision</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b110">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supremum preserving upper probabilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>De Cooman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Aeyels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b111">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge-driven versus data-driven logics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hajek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Logic, Language, and Information</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b112">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clouds, fuzzy sets and probability intervals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Neumaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reliable Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b113">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unifying practical uncertainty representations: II. Clouds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Destercke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chojnacki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Approximate Reasoning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="677" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b114">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-criteria decision-making methods based on intuitionistic fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G.-J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b115">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bipolar and bivariate models in multicriteria decision analysis: descriptive and constructive approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grabisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pirlot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Intelligent Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="930" to="969" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b116">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A graded quadrivalent logic for preference modelling: Loyola-like approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fortemps</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Slowinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Optimization and Decision Making</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b117">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bipolar preference modeling and aggregation in decision support</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Öztürk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tsoukiàs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Intelligent Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="970" to="984" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b118">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the qualitative comparison of decisions having positive and negative features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fargier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-F</forename><surname>Bonnefon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="417" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b119">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bipolar possibility theory in preference modeling: representation, fusion and optimal solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Benferhat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kaci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
