<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">SE-AKA: A secure and efficient group authentication and key agreement protocol for LTE networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chengzhe</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Integrated Services Networks</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xidian University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Waterloo</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Waterloo</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hui</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<email>lihui@mail.xidian.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Integrated Services Networks</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xidian University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rongxing</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
							<email>rxlu@ntu.edu.sg</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Communication Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Electrical and Electronics Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanyang Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sherman</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
							<email>xshen@bbcr.uwaterloo.ca</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Waterloo</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Waterloo</settlement>
									<region>Ontario</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">SE-AKA: A secure and efficient group authentication and key agreement protocol for LTE networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">78D3F66C1A638751B04A10D43886C1A4</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.comnet.2013.08.003</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 27 January 2013 Received in revised form 31 July 2013 Accepted 6 August 2013</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T10:53+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Authentication and key agreement (AKA) Privacy Group communication Long Term Evolution (LTE) 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>To support Evolved Packet System (EPS) in the Long Term Evolution (LTE) networks, the 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) has proposed an authentication and key agreement (AKA) protocol, named EPS-AKA, which has become an emerging standard for fourth-generation (4G) wireless communications. However, due to the requirement of backward compatibility, EPS-AKA inevitably inherits some defects of its predecessor UMTS-AKA protocol that cannot resist several frequent attacks, i.e., redirection attack, man-in-the-middle attack, and DoS attack. Meanwhile, there are additional security issues associated with the EPS-AKA protocol, i.e., the lack of privacy-preservation and key forward/backward secrecy (KFS/KBS). In addition, there are new challenges with the emergence of groupbased communication scenarios in authentication. In this paper, we propose a secure and efficient AKA protocol, called SE-AKA, which can fit in with all of the group authentication scenarios in the LTE networks. Specifically, SE-AKA uses Elliptic Curve Diffie-Hellman (ECDH) to realize KFS/KBS, and it also adopts an asymmetric key cryptosystem to protect users' privacy. For group authentication, it simplifies the whole authentication procedure by computing a group temporary key (GTK). Compared with other authentication protocols, SE-AKA cannot only provide strong security including privacy-preservation and KFS/KBS, but also provide a group authentication mechanism which can effectively authenticate group devices. Extensive security analysis and formal verification by using proverif have shown that the proposed SE-AKA is secure against various malicious attacks. In addition, elaborate performance evaluations in terms of communication, computational and storage overhead also demonstrates that SE-AKA is more efficient than those existing protocols.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>With the development of mobile communication systems, numerous authentication and key agreement (AKA) protocols have been proposed. To improve the security weaknesses in Global System for Mobile Communications (GSM) <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>, UMTS-AKA, which is based on GSM's successor Universal Mobile Telecommunications System (UMTS), was proposed at the network level <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[2]</ref> for authenticating 3G mobile subscribers. UMTS-AKA can negotiate security keys between a subscriber and the serving network and then achieve mutual authentication between the two parties. UMTS-AKA can also successfully defeat most of the vulnerabilities found in GSM systems and ensure a more secure telecommunication environment. Nevertheless, it is still vulnerable to some sophisticated attacks, such as redirection and man-in-the-middle attacks. Recently, a novel authentication protocol dedicated for Evolved Packet System (EPS) has been proposed in the Long Term Evolution (LTE) project <ref type="bibr">[3]</ref> by the 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP), known as EPS-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[4]</ref>, which is based on its predecessor UMTS-AKA protocol. Backward compatibility of EPS-AKA is an important factor for its wide acceptance, but it may also hinder progress and limit the design freedom. On one hand, EPS-AKA inevitably inherits some defects of UMTS-AKA and cannot resist known typical attacks found in UMTS-AKA, i.e., redirection attack that is discussed by <ref type="bibr">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">24]</ref>, man-inthe-middle attack which is studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">30]</ref>, and DoS attack that is given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">30]</ref>; on the other hand, there are some additional security issues associated with the EPS-AKA protocol that cannot be neglected, i.e., the lack of privacy-preservation and key forward/backward secrecy (KFS/KBS). Although most of the existing studies of mobile communication protocols have focused on confidentiality and authentication requirements, yet privacy-preservation <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[9]</ref>, another important issue in mobile communication networks, has not been well addressed. Recently, Arapinis et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[10]</ref> highlight the privacy problems of the 3G network, they exposed two novel threats to the user privacy in 3G telephony systems, i.e., IMSI paging attack and AKA protocol linkability attack, which make it possible to trace and identify mobile telephony subscribers. At the same time, they propose amendments to these privacy issues. Moreover, EPS-AKA still uses a symmetric key K shared between the user equipment and the home subscriber server to perform authentication and key agreement. All subkeys are generated using K. Therefore, disclosure of K is equal to the disclosure of whole procedure of EPS-AKA, i.e., EPS-AKA does not provide KFS/KBS. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref>With the emergence of group-based communication scenarios, there are a large number of user terminals with the same properties in a network, e.g., machine-type communication (MTC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[13]</ref>. These kinds of devices can form a group when they are in the same region, belong to the same applications, etc. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[17]</ref>. If a large number of devices in a group need to access the network successively over a short period of time, available authentication methods will suffer from high network access latency until completing authentication procedures of all devices in the same group, especially when these devices roam in a visited domain which is far from their home domain. The reason is that every device must perform a full AKA authentication procedure with home authentication server, so authentication signaling in the network will increase. Meanwhile, the overload of home authentication server will increase due to frequently generating authentication vectors. To the best of our knowledge, most of existing authentication schemes on 3G/LTE networks do not have group authentication mechanism and are not suitable for the authentication of group-based communications, and few authentication protocols for group communications have been proposed. Ngo et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[18]</ref> develop an individual and group authentication model for wireless network services, which uses dynamic key cryptography and group key management to provide authentication for individual and group of users and services; Aboudagga et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[19]</ref> present an associated authentication protocol for mobile groups and individual nodes over heterogeneous domains. However, they are designed for specific scenarios and lack of universality. Recently, Fun et al. propose a novel group-based handover authentication scheme with privacy preservation for mobile WiMAX networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[20]</ref>. This scheme improves performance of group-based handover authentication in mobile WiMAX networks. However, it has not discussed the existing attacks, meanwhile, it is designed for WiMAX networks and may not be suitable for LTE networks. Cao et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[21]</ref> propose a group-based authentication and key agreement for MTC in LTE networks, which can effectively authenticate a group of devices at the same time. However, their scheme is totally based on asymmetric cryptography by adopting bilinear pairing technique, which is costly in computation and may not be suitable for resource-constrained mobile device in LTE networks.</p><p>Considering security, effectiveness and universality simultaneously, we propose a secure and efficient authentication and key agreement protocol, called SE-AKA, for LTE networks in this paper. The main contributions of this paper are as follows.</p><p>First, SE-AKA meets the security requirements defined in EPS-AKA and can resist the existing attacks including redirection, man-in-the-middle and denial-of-service attacks, etc. Besides, motivated by the research done by Arapinis et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[10]</ref>, we adopt an asymmetric key cryptosystem to enhance user's privacy-preservation in LTE networks. In addition, SE-AKA can guarantee KFS/KBS through combining Elliptic Curve Diffie-Hellman (ECDH). Furthermore, we use automatical analyzing tool ProVerif <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[22]</ref> to verify the security of SE-AKA to show its security strength. Second, the group authentication mechanism is designed which can efficiently authenticate devices in a group compared with the traditional protocols. The results of analysis show that the transmission overhead of the whole authentication is considerably reduced. The computational overhead of home subscriber server and the storage overhead in the serving network can also be decreased. Third, SE-AKA is proposed based on LTE network infrastructure which can fit in with all of the scenarios for performing group-based authentication in the LTE networks.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows: In Section 2, we discuss the related works. In Section 3, we review the EPS-AKA protocol, introduce our network architecture, and recall Elliptic Curve Diffie-Hellman <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[32]</ref> as the preliminaries. Then, we present our SE-AKA protocol in Section 4, followed by its security analysis and performance evaluations in Section 5 and Section 6, respectively. Finally, We conclude this paper with remarks about future work in Section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Related work</head><p>There have been many research works on authentication and key agreement protocols in 3G/LTE networks. In 2003, Harn and Hsin <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[23]</ref> used the concept of hash chain and message authentication code (MAC) to design an ER-AKA protocol, which is expected to enhance the security of the original UMTS-AKA protocol. However, the protocol has greatly increased space and communication overhead in the hash chain's storage and transmission.</p><p>In 2005, Zhang and Fang <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[24]</ref> pointed out that 3GPP AKA has some security weaknesses. The first weakness is that it is vulnerable to a variant of false base station attack, which allows an adversary to redirect user traffic from one network to another. The second weakness is that it allows an adversary to use the authentication vectors (AVs) corrupted from one network to impersonate the other networks. The third weakness is that the use of synchronization between a mobile station (MS) and its home network (HN) incurs resynchronization. To overcome these weaknesses, Zhang and Fang propose an improved authentication and key agreement protocol called AP-AKA. In AP-AKA, it allows the entities to have the flexibility of selecting execution flows dependent on the MSs in the foreign networks (FNs) and the HN. Lee et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[25]</ref> extend AP-AKA to make it more efficient. They found that the AP-AKA for 3GPP has three drawbacks as follows: <ref type="bibr">(1)</ref> The FN must turn back to the HN for a request of another set of AVs when the MS stays in the FN for a long time and exhausts its set of AV for authentication. Additional, bandwidth consumption therefore is introduced between the FN and HN; (2) Each MS in the particular FN has n copies of AV. If there are m MSs in the FN, the FN must store m n authentication vectors. This is extra space overhead; and (3) When the n copies AVs are all consumed, FN must go back to HN to get another n copies AVs to authenticate MS. In this way, the authentication of an MS cannot be completed without the help by the HN of the MS, for each communication when the n copies are all used.</p><p>In 2005, X-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[26]</ref>, a symmetric key-based authentication protocol, is proposed to prune off the transmission of AVs in UMTS-AKA and improve its bandwidth consumption. However, it does not resist redirection and man-inthe-middle attacks. Al-Saraireh and Yousef <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[27]</ref> design a symmetric key-based authentication protocol for UMTS networks. Al-Saraireh and Yousef's protocol mainly focuses on reducing the bandwidth required for transmitting AVs. Hence, the AVs are generated by MSs instead of by serving networks. Al-Saraireh and Yousef's protocol eliminates the cost of delivering AVs during authentication. The protocol, however, does not resolve the security issues in defeating redirection and man-in-the-middle attacks.</p><p>In 2010, Ou et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[28]</ref> propose Cocktail-AKA to overcome the congenital defects of UMTS-AKA. Cocktail-AKA uses two varieties of AVs (called MAV and PAV) to produce several effective AVs. In the protocol, each service network produces its own AVs (MAVs) in advance. These MAVs are produced only once but can be reused later. While authenticating the MS, the HLR/AuC calculates a private authentication vector (PAV) for MS. The PAV is transferred to the SGSN. Then, the SGSN uses the PAV and MAV to generate several effective AVs for subsequent authentications. Unfortunately, Cocktail-AKA is vulnerable to denial-of-service (DoS) attacks <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[29]</ref>.</p><p>In 2011, Huang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[30]</ref> introduce a secure AKA (S-AKA) protocol which can resist the typical attacks and they also give the formal proof of the S-AKA protocol to guarantee its robustness. However, similar to other existing protocols, the protocol is not suitable for group-based communications due to lack of special group authentication mechanism.</p><p>Chen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[31]</ref> propose a group authentication and key agreement protocol (G-AKA) for a group of MSs roaming from the same home network to a serving network. The protocol optimizes the performance of authentication of group communications, however, it also cannot provide enough security and is vulnerable to redirection, man-inthe-middle attacks, etc.</p><p>Different from above works, our focus is on providing a more secure, effective and universal AKA protocol for LTE networks. First, SE-AKA can resist all existing attacks found in previous works, and provide enhanced user's privacypreservation and KFS/KBS that cannot be guaranteed by previous works. Second, it can provide the group authentication mechanism which can efficiently authenticate devices in a group. Third, SE-AKA can fit in the LTE networks with all of the scenarios for performing groupbased authentication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Preliminaries</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Review of the EPS-AKA protocol</head><p>In this section, we first introduce EPS-AKA authentication procedure, which was proposed in the 3GPP release 9 for LTE networks. EPS-AKA can broadly be divided into two stages: (1) authentication data distribution, and (2) user authentication and key agreement. The former enables the home network (HN) of an mobile equipment (ME) to distribute authentication data to the serving network (SN) the ME device is visiting. The latter is to establish new session keys between the ME and the SN. The EPS-AKA protocol works as follows.</p><p>( </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Network architecture</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows our considered network architecture in the roaming scenario which is based on 3GPP standard <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[4]</ref>, and can be divided into three domains, namely access network domain, serving network domain and home network domain. The main entities involved in the network architecture are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1.">Access network domain</head><p>Access network domain mainly consists of MEs and base station (BS). An ME can be any kind of 3GPP standard mobile devices. Moreover, HeNB and eNB are two kinds of BSs for MEs to access 3GPP network. Different from the eNB, an HeNB is typically installed by a subscriber in residence or a small office to increase the indoor coverage for voice and high speed data service.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2.">Serving network domain</head><p>The serving network (SN) provides access services for MEs. In the LTE network, the MME locates in SN and provides access services for MEs. The MME is responsible for all the functions relevant to the users and the control plane session management. When an ME connects to the SN, the MME firstly contacts with the HSS to obtain the corresponding authentication data and then represents the SN to perform a mutual authentication with the ME.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3.">Home network domain</head><p>The home network (HN) provides authentication and management services for MEs. In the LTE network, the HSS locates in HN and provides authentication and management services for MEs. In addition, we add a new server to home network domain, named group management server (GMS), to manage the group that MEs form, e.g., in the MTC, MTC server can implement this function. The interfaces between GMS and HSS/MME are secure, since the GMS locates in the trusted HN regulated by the operator.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Elliptic Curve Diffie-Hellman</head><p>In this work, we use Elliptic Curve Diffie-Hellman (ECDH) to realize KFS/KBS. ECDH can be described as follows: Alice and Bob publicly agree on an elliptic curve E over a large finite field F q and a point P on that curve. Then, Alice and Bob each selects random numbers a and b, respectively. Using elliptic curve point-addition, Alice and Bob each publicly compute aP and bP on E. Then, Alice and Bob send their own computed values to each other. When Alice receives bP, she computes a(bP). Similarly, when Bob receives aP, he computes b(aP). Finally, Alice and Bob agree a shared secret abP. The shared secret calculated by both parties is equal, because a(bP) = abP = baP = b(aP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[32]</ref>. However, the original ECDH is insecure and  vulnerable to man-in-the-middle (MITM) attack. Krawczyk <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[33]</ref> proposed a provable secure and efficient DH key exchange approach, named SIGn-and-MAc (SIGMA) to solve this problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Proposed authentication protocol</head><p>In this section, we propose a secure and efficient authentication and key agreement protocol for LTE networks (SE-AKA) to facilitate the ME/MEs that have been subscribed in the HN to roam in an SN which is far from HN. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">2</ref> shows the used notations in the SE-AKA protocol.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Preparation and initialization</head><p>Each ME has an identity (PID ME /TID ME ) which is a private identity that identifies ME and should be installed in the ME by the supplier in order to allow the ME to register in a 3GPP network. Each ME has a pre-shared secret key with HN when it is first registered in HN. A lightweight public key infrastructure (PKI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[10]</ref> is adopted to provide each HN with a private/public key pair (Pub HN ,Pri HN ). The public key of HN can be stored in ME's trusted environment, Universal Subscriber Identity Module (USIM)/Universal Integrated Circuit Card (UICC). This public key makes it possible for an ME to encrypt privacy related information such as International Mobile Subscriber Identification Number (IMSI), and deliver them to the network in a confidential manner. The MEs form several groups based on certain principles (belonging to one and the same application/ within the same region/ having the same behavior), using the grouping algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">35]</ref>, then the supplier provides a group key (GK) to each group for authentication. As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">3</ref>, we create a Group Information Management List (GIML) to manage information of MEs and groups, the GIML contains fields of group identity, ME temporary identity (TID ME ) for each ME<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">2</ref> and the large and unique synchronization value SV which will behave as a sequence number for synchronization between the ME and its SN.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Protocol execution for the first equipment (a1)-(a5) describe how the MME distributes authentication data for the first ME of the group visiting the SN.</head><p>A secure communication channel between the SN and the HN has already been established (based on Diameter protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[36]</ref>) and can provide security services to the transmitted data. Let ME G1À1 be the first ME initiating authentication in the group G1. Our authentication protocol is shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>   The time stamp generated by x PID x</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">AUTH G1 ¼ ðID G1 kTID ME G1À1 kR G1À1 kMAC G1 kT G1 Þ, where MAC G1 is calculated as MAC G1 ¼ f 1 key G1À1 ðID G1 kTID ME G1À1</formula><p>The permanent identity of x TID x</p><p>The temporary identity of x key xÀy</p><p>The shared secret key between x and y GK Gi</p><p>The group authentication key of the ith group GTK Gi</p><p>The group temporary key of the ith group KGK MEGiÀj</p><p>The key generation key between ME GiÀj and SN  (1)  tion acknowledge to ME G1À1 , and the full authentication and key agreement procedure for the first ME is completed.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ME G1À1 computes GTK G1 ¼ f 2 GK G1 ðR HSS kAMFÞ; (2) ME G1À1 computes MAC 0 MME ¼ f 1 GTK G1 ðID MME kID G1 kTID ME G1À1 kR MME kR HSS kR G1À1 kAMFkapkSV G1À1 þ iÞ; (3)</formula><p>After a successful authentication, both ME G1À1 and its SN share a key generation key KGK ME G1À1 as essential material for subsequent key derivations. KGK ME G1À1 's function is the same as K ASME 's <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[4]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Protocol execution for the remaining equipments of the same group</head><p>When the second ME (ME G1À2 ) in the same group wants to access the serving network, the MME performs mutual authentication and key agreement with ME G1À2 locally using the existing GTK G1 .</p><p>Step  The remaining MEs perform the authentication and key agreement procedures similar to ME G1À2 's until all devices complete authentication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Group member joining/leaving the group</head><p>The group which formed by MEs requires backward and forward secrecy. Backward secrecy is required that a new ME cannot get messages exchanged before it joined the group. Forward secrecy is required that a leaving or expelled ME cannot continue accessing the group's communication (if it keeps receiving the messages).</p><p>In this paper, we can use the GMS to manage the group member joining/leaving the group. When an ME wants to leave the group, the GMS will revoke the binding relationship between the ME and the group that it belongs to, thus the ME cannot longer communicate with the SN as the group member. Moreover, in order to prevent the old ME to decrypt the new packets of the group which it was able to sniff, the group key must be updated when the old ME leaves the group. After the old ME leaves the group, all members of the group should share a new group key. Similarly, when an ME wants to join the group, an access control of the group is necessary for it, and it needs to perform a full AKA authentication procedure with the SN. Meanwhile, the group key must be updated when the new ME wants to join a group. After the new ME joins the group, all members of the group should share a new group key. In that case, the new ME cannot decrypt the old packets of the group before it joins in. The group key upgrade of group communication has been widely studied, and it is out of scope for this paper and specific technology can be found in reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">38]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Security analysis</head><p>In this section, both security analysis and formal verification are conducted to demonstrate that SE-AKA can meet the security requirements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Security analysis</head><p>The SE-AKA protocol adopts the same secured architecture as the EPS-AKA protocol. Therefore, it has the same security threshold in most situations. SE-AKA protocol can reach same security requirements with EPS-AKA protocol as follows:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1.">Entity mutual authentication</head><p>In the proposed SE-AKA protocol, an ME is identified by its PID ME /TID ME and group ID ID G i . The first ME ME GiÀ1 uses AUTH Gi to get AUTH HSS containing GTK for group G i from HSS in the HN and performs a mutual authentication with HN. MAC Gi is only generated by ME GiÀ1 using pre-shared key GiÀ1 with the HN, at the same time, ME GiÀ1 can authenticate the HN by the unique GTK sourced from the real HN. Moreover, a mutual authentication between ME GiÀ1 and its SN is also carried out. This is because ME GiÀ1 authenticates its SN by comparing its computed MAC MME with that in AUTH MME , the SN only acquires a correct GTK from the HN to prove itself legitimate. On the other hand, the SN can authenticate ME GiÀ1 by checking whether the returned MAC ME G iÀ1 from ME GiÀ1 is correct. Note that, a secure communication channel between the MME and the HSS has already been established and can provide security services to the transmitted data. For the remaining MEs in the same group, they only need to perform mutual authentications with their SN locally.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2.">Confidentiality</head><p>Confidentiality includes cipher algorithm agreement, cipher key agreement, confidentiality of user data and confidentiality of signaling data. Our SE-AKA protocol follows the mechanism of the EPS-AKA protocol and is successful with these demands. The SN carries the field of the AMF in the AUTH MME to meet the feature of cipher algorithm agreement. The random numbers and the identities collocate with a group key to make the feature of cipher key agreement (GTK, see Section 4.2). All the user data and signaling data will be encrypted with the subsequent key drived from KGK that the ME and the SN agree on in each time session.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.3.">Data integrity</head><p>Data integrity includes integrity algorithm agreement, integrity key agreement, data integrity and origin authentication of signaling data. Similar to the demand of confidentiality, the SN carries the field of the AMF in the AUTH MME to meet the feature of integrity algorithm agreement. The random numbers and the identities collocate with a group key to make the feature of integrity key agreement. All the user data will be verified with the subsequent key drived from KGK that the ME and the SN agree with in each time session. In addition, the original authentication of signaling data will be protected with the message authentication code (MAC).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.4.">Secure key derivation</head><p>In our SE-AKA protocol, the KGK is computed by an ME and its SN respectively. In addition, our protocol uses ECDH to generate KGK ME GiÀj without involving key GiÀj . Furthermore, all dedicated keys among entities will be derived from KGK on either peer side directly, without being transmitted over any communication channels. Therefore, the KGK and all dedicated keys are prevented from being disclosed, attacked, or intercepted by adversaries.</p><p>The security properties provided by the proposed SE-AKA are as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.5.">Enhanced privacy-preservation</head><p>To ensure user privacy, the permanent identity of an ME like IMSI should be confidentiality protected. It should never be transmitted without protection. In EPS-AKA, a GUTI (ME's temporary identity) is transmitted instead of the IMSI for identity presentation. In spite of this security arrangement, there are occasions when the IMSI may be transmitted in plain text. We discuss two typical cases.</p><p>(1) When the network cannot know the ME's temporary identity, it will require the ME's permanent identity. Thus, if the ME's permanent identity is transmitted in plain text, adversary can get it and launch the attacks related identity; and (2) In the case of MAC verification failure, the MAC failure message (Mac_Fail) contained ðFail; PID ME GiÀj ; randÞ will be sent to network to require a new MAC verification procedure. Therefore, ME's permanent identity also may be leak. These two cases can expose user privacy. In this paper, a lightweight public key infrastructure (PKI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[10]</ref> is adopted to provide each HN with a private/public key pair (Pub HN ,Pri HN ). When the network requires the ME's permanent identity PID ME GiÀj , such as Section 4.2-(a3) and 4.2-(a7), we can send PID ME GiÀj encrypted by Pub HN to the network instead of sending PID ME GiÀj in plain text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.6.">Key forward/backward secrecy (KFS/KBS)</head><p>To provide KFS and KBS between the ME and the SN, our protocol uses ECDH. While generating KGK ME GiÀj , our protocol uses aP and bPthat are not related with key GiÀj . Therefore, if disclosure of key GiÀj occurs, attackers cannot guess KGK ME GiÀj . In other words, guessing KGK ME GiÀj is a computationally difficult problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.7.">Perfect forward/backward secrecy (PFS/PBS)</head><p>To provide backward and forward secrecy (PFS/PBS), the Section 4.4 gives the details of the method.</p><p>PFS guarantees that when a new ME wants to join the group, an access control of the group is necessary, and it needs to perform a full AKA authentication procedure with the SN. The group key must also be updated when the new ME joins a group, so that even if the new ME is able to sniff the old packets of the group, it cannot decrypt them.</p><p>PBS guarantees that when an old ME leaves the group, the GMS will revoke the binding relationship between the ME and the group that it belongs to, thus the ME can no longer communicate with the SN as the group member. Moreover, the group key must be updated when the old ME leaves the group, so that the old ME cannot decrypt the new packets of the group after it leaves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Resistance to attacks</head><p>Besides the security properties mentioned above, our protocol can resist the following attacks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1.">Replay attack</head><p>In our protocol, random number R GiÀj generated by ME GiÀj , R HSS generated by the HSS and R MME generated by MME temporarily use in generating challenge messages toward the opposite side, respectively. Since these random numbers using in each authentication procedure are different, even if an attacker acquires a random number in an authentication procedure, it still cannot fake challenge messages by reusing the random number in a new authentication procedure. Meanwhile, IV ME GiÀj þ i generated by the ME can keep both sides involving the authentication synchronized throughout AKA processing. An out-of-sync situation will lead to authentication failure. Therefore, our SE-AKA protocol can prevent replay attacks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2.">Redirection attack</head><p>An adversary initiates a redirection attack by simulating a BS to obtain user information and by impersonating an ME to forward user messages to its destination. The redirection attack fails if the adversary fails to obtain user information by impersonating a BS. Without the user information, the adversary cannot impersonate any ME and connect to a legitimate BS. To impersonate a BS, the adversary either transmits signals with stronger power or jams the spectrum and tries to entrap the ME to establish the connection with the faked BSs. In SE-AKA, the first ME embeds the LAI of the BS in MAC G1 and sends MAC G1 to the MME in Section 4.2-(a3). The authentication request is rejected if the HSS fails to match the LAI reported by the MME and the LAI embedded in MAC G1 . When the remaining MEs want to access the SN, they embed the LAI of the BS in MAC G1Àj , and then send MAC G1Àj to the MME, since the MME knows the LAI of the BS forwarding AUTH ME G1Àj , it can verify whether the LAI 0 forwarded by the BS is the same as that recognized by the ME through checking MAC G1Àj . Similarly, the authentication request is rejected if the MME fails to verify MAC G1Àj .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3.">Man-in-the-middle (MitM) attack</head><p>If a member of a group is able to sniff AUTH G1 (Section 4.2-(a3)) and also AUTH MME (Section 4.2-(a6)), it still cannot compute the KGK. Although these messages are sent without protection and the attacker may be able to catch these data, it cannot use them against the network. For instance, in Section 4.2-(a3), the attacker reads the random number of the device (R G1À1 ) and AMF, while in Section 4.2-(a6), it reads the random number of the MME (R MME ) and the random number of HSS (R HSS ). With this information and the group key, it is not able to compute a MitM attack, because it cannot get the SV that prestored between MEs and the 3GPP network. SV is securely stored in related entities and not transmitted over insecure communication channels. Meanwhile, the process that generates KGK (Section 4.2-(a7) and (a8)) guarantees that KGK cannot be computed by adversary, even it can get all authentication data transmitted over the communication channels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.4.">DoS attack</head><p>During the authentication of the first ME, a malicious ME may launch a DoS attack either to its HSS or to the visited MME.</p><p>If the ME forges message in (a3), the forged message can be detected by the HSS through checking T G1 and comparing LAI contained in MAC G1 with LAI received from BS.</p><p>During the authentication of the remaining MEs, a malicious ME may launch a DoS attack to the visited MME.</p><p>If the ME forges message in (b3), the forged message can be detected by the visited MME through checking MAC G1Àj containing LAI sent by ME.</p><p>Because the proposed SE-AKA is designed for group communication scenario, therefore, this security mechanism can resist the DoS attack launched by multiple devices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.5.">Impersonate attack</head><p>In our protocol, all the MEs of a group share a common GTK. If an ME, without loss of generality, supposes that ME G1À1 intends to impersonate another ME in the same group, for example, ME G1Àj . ME G1À1 may eavesdrop traffic between ME G1Àj and the SN, but ME G1À1 cannot generate unique R G1Àj and SV ME G1Àj , thus ME G1À1 cannot generate a correct MAC ME G1Àj to impersonate ME G1Àj to perform a successful authentication with the SN. Similarly, ME G1À1 cannot get the KGK between ME G1Àj and the SN, therefore, it cannot decrypt traffic between ME G1Àj and the SN. In summary, the SN can easily distinguish one ME from another even though all MEs use the same GTK. In addition, one ME cannot decrypt traffic between any other ME and the SN.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Formal verification</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.1.">ProVerif</head><p>We will use ProVerif to verify the security of our protocol. ProVerif is a tool for automatically analyzing the security of cryptographic protocols. Cryptographic primitives are modeled as functions, and messages are represented by terms built over an infinite set of names a, b, c, . . ., an infinite set of variables x, y, z, . . . and a finite set of function symbols f 1 , . . . , f n . Function symbols represent cryptographic primitives that can be applied to messages. The effect of applying function symbols to terms is described by a set of reduction rules. The syntax of ProVerif calculus processes is given by the Table 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[22]</ref>. ProVerif can be run under Windows or Linux/Mac, in this paper, we conduct the experiments with ProVerif running on a 2.30 GHz-processor 4 GB-memory computing machine to test the proposed SE-AKA protocol under Windows. 3   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.2.">Specification of our protocol</head><p>The primary goal of our proposed protocol is to provide mutual authentication and key agreement services between MEs and the serving network (SN). Moreover, privacy-preservation (anonymity) and key forward/ backward secrecy (KFS/KBS) of our protocol are also need to be verified. The ability of our protocol to resist the typical attacks has been discussed in Section 5.2. Thus, the main security goals to be verified are as follows, and their individual specific requirements have been described in Section 5.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mutual authentication between MEs and the SN; Secrecy of KGK ME GiÀj ;</head><p>Privacy-preservation (anonymity); Key forward/backward secrecy (KFS/KBS).</p><p>Because the communication between the SN and the HN is secure, and all authentication procedures between MEs and their SN in a group can be considered the same, thus we only need to verify an authentication procedure among them, without loss of generality, between ME G1À1 and its SN.</p><p>First, we formalize the basic cryptographic primitives used by the SE-AKA protocol as follows. A symmetric encryption and an asymmetric encryption are defined in Tables A.1 and A.2, respectively; the Diffie-Hellman key agreement is given in <ref type="table">Table</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">A.3, see Appendix A.</formula><p>We further model four security goals in this paper:</p><p>(1) Mutual authentication between MEs and the SN: We declare the events: event acceptsMMEparam (key), which is used by the MME to record the belief that it has accepted to run the protocol with the ME and the supplied symmetric key. event termMMEparam (key), which denotes the MME's belief that it has terminated a protocol run with the ME with the symmetric key supplied as the first argument. event acceptsMEparam (key), which is used by the ME to record the belief that it has accepted to run the protocol with the MME and the supplied symmetric key. event termMEparam (key), which denotes the ME's belief that it has terminated a protocol run with the MME with the symmetric key supplied as the first argument. Next, we use the basic correspondence assertion event(termME(key)) = = &gt; event(acceptsMME(key)), and the injective correspondence assertion inj-event(term-MME(key)) = = &gt; inj-event(acceptsME(key)) to test if SE-AKA can achieve mutual authentication.</p><p>(2) Secrecy of KGK ME GiÀj and Key forward/backward secrecy (KFS/KBS): We first define a query attacker (s), where s is session key shared between the ME and the MME. Internally, ProVerif attempts to prove that a state in which the session key s is known to the adversary is unreachable (that is, it tests the query not attacker, and the query is true when the s are not derivable by the adversary). (3) Privacy-preservation (anonymity): Finally, we use observational equivalence, i.e., construct choice[PID me ,TID me ] to represent the terms that differ between PID me and TID me . If PID me and TID me are undistinguishable, we say that the SE-AKA satisfies anonymity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.3.">Results of analysis</head><p>The verification results are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> shows that RESULT event (termME (x_25)) ==&gt; event (acceptsMME (x_25)) is true and RESULT inj-event (term-MME (x_1957)) == &gt; inj-event (acceptsME (x_1957)) is true. We can conclude that there has been a successful mutual authentication between ME and its SN. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> shows that </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">if M = N then P else Q Conditional let M = D in P else Q Term evaluation R(M 1 , . . . , M k ) Macrousage</formula><p>3 User manual and tutorial can be downloaded in http://prosecco.gforge.inria.fr/personal/bblanche/proverif/manual.pdf.</p><p>RESULT not attacker (s []) is true. It manifests that secrecy of KGK GiÀj and FKS/FBS are hold. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref> shows that Observational equivalence is true hbad not derivablei. It indicates that the anonymity of our protocol is hold, because adversary cannot get ME's PID from the communication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.">Comparison</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">5</ref> lists the security properties among the 3GPP AKA protocols. We have demonstrated that our protocol can provide the most comprehensive security performance compared to the other AKA protocols.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Performance evaluation</head><p>In this section, we compare our SE-AKA protocol with the existing traditional protocols in terms of bandwidth consumption, authentication transmission overhead, computational and storage overhead. We have simulated the proposed SE-AKA in MATLAB running on a 2.30 GHz-processor 4 GB-memory computing machine.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.">Communication overhead</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bandwidth consumption</head><p>In order to analyze the bandwidth consumption, we assume that x AVs are transmitted every time the HSS successfully authenticates one ME, and there are n MEs forming m group. Table <ref type="table">6</ref> is the setting of parameters for evaluating bandwidth consumption.</p><p>The bandwidth consumption of AKA protocols are as follows, where bw first represents the bandwidth consumption of the authentication of the first ME. The specific calculation process of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">1</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">5</ref>) can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">39]</ref>, we give the concrete computation procedure of ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(7)</ref>. (1) Bandwidth Analysis of UMTS-AKA and EPS-AKA: The sizes of authentication messages are calculated as follows.</p><p>bw first ¼ X 5</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">i¼1 jMessage i j ¼ 704 þ 608x bits:<label>ð1Þ</label></formula><p>The overall bandwidth consumption for n devices is calculated as n⁄(704 + 608x).</p><p>(2) Bandwidth Analysis of S-AKA: The sizes of authentication messages are calculated as follows.</p><p>bw first ¼ X 5 i¼1 jMessage i j ¼ 1312 bits: ð2Þ  The overall bandwidth consumption for n devices is calculated as n ⁄ 1312.</p><p>(3) Bandwidth Analysis of AP-AKA: The sizes of authentication messages are calculated as follows.</p><p>bw first ¼ X 6</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">i¼1 jMessage i j ¼ 1250 þ 544x bits:<label>ð3Þ</label></formula><p>The overall bandwidth consumption for n devices is calculated as n⁄(1250 + 544x). ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">4</ref>) Bandwidth Analysis of X-AKA: The sizes of authentication messages are calculated as follows.</p><p>bw first ¼ X 5</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">i¼1 jMessage i j ¼ 1220 bits:<label>ð4Þ</label></formula><p>The overall bandwidth consumption for n devices is calculated as n Ã 1220.</p><p>(5) Bandwidth Analysis of Cocktail-AKA: The sizes of authentication messages are calculated as follows.</p><p>bw first ¼ X 3</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">i¼1 jMessage i j ¼ 640 þ 560x bits:<label>ð5Þ</label></formula><p>The overall bandwidth consumption for n devices is calculated as n⁄(640 + 560x). ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) Bandwidth Analysis of G-AKA: The sizes of authentication messages are calculated as follows.</p><p>bw first ¼ X 5 i¼1 jMessage i j ¼ 1888 bits: ð6Þ    different. Despite that SE-AKA is not the protocol that saves the most bandwidth, it can provide more security. The reason is that we use asymmetric cryptosystem to enhance the security, but the traditional protocols only use symmetric cryptosystem to achieve authentication in UMTS or LTE networks. Indeed, they cannot provide good security. From Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">5</ref>, the security of several protocols is weak, like X-AKA and G-AKA, they can barely resist the existing attacks. In fact, we need a hybrid cryptosystem to design authentication protocol in UMTS/LTE networks. On one hand, this can provide a higher security; on the other hand, the effectiveness of communication can also be guaranteed. As a matter of fact, even though our protocol adopts asymmetric cryptosystem, the bandwidth consumption of the protocol still does not increase rapidly. From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7</ref>(a) -(f), we can see that the bandwidth consumption of our protocol is close to that of S-AKA, G-AKA and X-AKA, and far better than that of UMTS-AKA, EPS-AKA and AP-AKA. Most importantly, our protocol can provide much better security compared to the other protocols.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Authentication transmission overhead</head><p>Let the overhead of authentication message delivery between the ME and the MME be a unit, and between the MME and the HSS be b unit, respectively. Since the MME locates the SN which is far away from the HSS, b ) a. We also assume that there are n MEs forming m groups, obviously, n &gt; m. We compare the overhead of authentication message delivery of SE-AKA with that of traditional protocols as shown in Table <ref type="table">7</ref>.</p><p>From Table <ref type="table">7</ref>, we can find that the authentication transmission overhead of the existing AKA protocols are similar; therefore, we set average authentication transmission overhead of all existing AKA protocols as 5na + 2nb.</p><p>According to Table <ref type="table">7</ref>, we draw Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8</ref> when a = 1, b = 100 and a = 1, b = 1000, respectively. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8</ref>, we can see that the overhead of authentication message delivery of SE-AKA (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8(b)</ref> and<ref type="figure">(d)</ref>) is lower than other existing AKA protocols (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8</ref>(a) and (c)). Therefore, our protocol owns the lowest authentication transmission overhead.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">Computational overhead</head><p>The time used for the primitive cryptography operations has been measured by using C/C++ OPENSSL library <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[40]</ref> tested on an Celeron 1.1 GHz processor as an UE and </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 7</head><p>Comparison of the authentication transmission overhead.</p><p>Reference schemes Authentication transmission overhead SE-AKA m(6a + 2b) + (n-m)(6a) = 6na + 2mb UMTS-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[2]</ref> 6na + 2nb EPS-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[4]</ref> 6na + 2nb AP-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[24]</ref> 5na + 2nb X-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[26]</ref> 5na + 2nb Cocktail-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[26]</ref> 4na + 2nb S-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[30]</ref> 7na + 2nb G-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[31]</ref> m(7a + 2b) + (n-m)(7a) = 7na + 2mb Comparisons of computational overhead of each entity among the 3GPP AKA protocols are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">8</ref>. From Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">8</ref>, we can find that the computational overhead of the existing AKA protocols are similar; therefore, we first set average computational overhead of HSS in all existing AKA protocols as 0.04n. According to Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">8</ref>, we plot the computational overhead of HSS in terms of ME numbers n and group numbers m, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">9</ref>. It can be seen that the proposed SE-AKA protocol always achieves lower computational overhead of HSS compared to other existing AKA protocols. Therefore, the computational overhead of HSS in our SE-AKA is the lowest in all protocols. This is because SE-AKA shifts some computational overhead in the HSS to the MME. This can make the HSS and the MME bear computational overhead together and reduce the overload of the HSS to some extent.</p><p>Furthermore, the computational overhead of all entities in SE-AKA are lager than that of other traditional protocols </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reference schemes</head><p>Storage overhead (bits) SE-AKA 432m UMTS-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[2]</ref> 608n EPS-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[4]</ref> 608n AP-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[24]</ref> 640n X-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[26]</ref> 368n Cocktail-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[26]</ref> 560n S-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[30]</ref> 368n G-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[31]</ref> 432m  except for the HSS. This is because ECDH is adopted to solve KFS/KBS in SE-AKA, while other traditional protocols only use symmetric cryptography. Despite SE-AKA is not the protocol that has the lowest computational overhead, compared with the scheme that is completely based on asymmetric cryptosystem, e.g., scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[21]</ref>, it costs about 17.2n + 57.3 ms, while the SE-AKA costs 4.2471n + 0.0242 m ms. To compare the total computation overhead between scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[21]</ref> and the SE-AKA, we plot the total computation overhead in terms of ME numbers n and group numbers m, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10</ref>. It can be seen that the proposed SE-AKA protocol achieves lower total computation overhead compared to scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[21]</ref>. Therefore, the proposed SE-AKA can provide good security with acceptable computation overhead.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3.">Storage overhead</head><p>In this section, we analyze the storage overhead of several AKA protocols. In addition, we consider that there are n MEs that are formed into m groups, n &gt; m.</p><p>For UMTS-AKA and EPS-AKA, each ME requires its SN to store a set of authentication vectors (AVs), the length of AV is 608 bits, therefore occupied storage space for authenticating n MEs is 608n bits. For X-AKA, n Â (Temporal Key (TK) + AUTH) bits space is occupied, where jTKj = 128 bits and jAUTHj = 240 bits. As to S-AKA, it will occupy n Â ((DK) + AUTN) bits storage space, where jDKj = 128 bits and jAUTNj = 240 bits. For AP-AKA, each ME requires its SN to store a set of authentication vectors (AVs), the length of AV is 640 bits, therefore occupied storage space for authenticating n ME is 640n bits. For Cocktail-AKA, it will occupy n Â jPAVj bits storage space, where jPAVj = 560 bits. G-AKA utilizes group authentication data, instead of maintaining each ME's authentication information, thus for m groups of MEs, the SN only uses mÂ (GTK + RN H + RN M1À1 + AMF + Index table entry) bits storage space, where jGTKj = 128 bits, jRN H j = jRN M1À1 j = 128 bits and jAMFj = 48 bits, jIndex table entryj can be negligible. While SE-AKA also utilizes group authentication data, instead of maintaining each ME authentication information, thus its storage overhead is basically the same as G-AKA's. Comparison of storage overhead on several AKA protocols is presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">9</ref>.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">11</ref>(a)-(d) compare the storage overhand of several AKA protocols, varying with the number of MEs. From the figures, we can see both the SE-AKA and G-AKA protocols have smaller storage costs than others. The reason that the storage overhand of the SE-AKA protocol does not change with n is that SE-AKA shifts the impact of the number of MEs to the impact of that of the number of ME groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Conclusion and future work</head><p>In this paper, we have proposed a secure and efficient AKA protocol SE-AKA to fit in the LTE networks with all of the group authentication scenarios. Compared with other authentication protocols, SE-AKA cannot only provide strong security properties including privacy-preservation and KFS/KBS, but also provide a group authentication mechanism which can effectively authenticate group devices. Extensive security analysis and formal verification by using proverif have shown that the proposed SE-AKA is secure against various malicious attacks. The elaborate performance evaluations in terms of communication, computational and storage overhead have been conducted, which demonstrate that the transmission overhead of the whole authentication is considerably reduced, the computational overhead of the HSS and the storage overhead in the serving network can also be decreased, and the bandwidth consumption is close to that of S-AKA, G-AKA and X-AKA, and far better than that of UMTS-AKA, EPS-AKA and AP-AKA.</p><p>In the group-based communication, group devices will face new challenges in authentication when they are moving. A long delay and large computational overhead may occur during handover or roaming. Therefore, the security research of group-based communication in the duration of handover or roaming will be further exploited in our future work.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Network architecture.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,103.46,543.26,327.47,129.91" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>1 k 2 k 3 k</head><label>123</label><figDesc>MAC xThe message authentication code computed by x LAI Location area identification AMF Authentication management field f MAC generation function using k f GTK generation function using k f KGK generation function using k</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The SE-AKA protocol.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. The authentication procedure of remaining MEs.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Verification result of mutual authentication between ME and its SN.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,85.04,54.71,368.56,399.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Verification result of privacy-preservation.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,89.35,414.94,368.79,155.57" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Verification result of secrecy of KGK and KFS/KBS.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,89.35,54.71,368.56,321.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Message 1 = 2 i¼1j 5 i¼1j 3 i¼1</head><label>1253</label><figDesc>2jIDj + jRNj + jMACj = 448 bits. Message 2 = Message 1 . Message 3 = 2jRNj + jAMFj + jGTKj = 432 bits. Message 4 = jAMFj + 3jRNj + jMACj = 496 bits. Message 5 = jMACj = 64 bits. bw remaining ¼ X Message i j¼ 880 bits: ð7Þ where bw remaining represents the bandwidth consumption of authentication of each remaining ME. Message 1 = 2jIDj + jRNj = 320 bits. Message 2 = jAMFj + 3jRNj + jMACj = 496 bits. Message 3 = jMACj = 64 bits. The overall bandwidth consumption for n devices is calculated as m⁄1888 + (n À m)⁄880. (7) Bandwidth Analysis of SE-AKA: The sizes of authentication messages are calculated as follows. bw first ¼ X Message i j¼ 2184 bits: ð8Þ Message 1 = jIDj + jRNj + jMACj = 320 bits. Message 2 = jMessage 1 j + jLAIj = 360 bits Message 3 = 2jRNj + jAMFj + jGTKj = 432 bits Message 4 = jIDj +jMACj + 3jRNj + jAMFj + jECDH keyj = 816 bits Message 5 = jMACj + jECDH keyj = 256 bits bw remaining ¼ X jMessage i j ¼ 1328 bits: ð9Þ where bw remaining represents the bandwidth consumption of authentication of each remaining ME. Message 1 = jIDj + jRNj = 256 bits. Message 2 = jIDj + jMACj + 3jRNj + jAMFj + jECDH keyj = 816 bits Message 3 = jMACj + jECDH keyj = 256 bits The overall bandwidth consumption for n devices is calculated as m⁄2184 + (n À m)⁄1328. Fig. 7(a)-(f) show the bandwidth consumption of several AKA protocols, when the number of the MEs is</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>x (the number of AVs) 10, m (the number of groups) 10 x (the number of AVs) 50, m (the number of groups) 2 (e) x (the number of AVs) 50, m (the number of groups) 5 (f) x (the number of AVs) 50, m (the number of groups) 10</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Comparison of the bandwidth consumption.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Comparison of the authentication transmission overhead.</figDesc><graphic coords="15,173.06,407.48,84.04,65.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Comparison of the computational overhead of HSS.</figDesc><graphic coords="16,79.70,286.58,173.62,134.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Comparison of the total computation overhead between scheme [21] and SE-AKA.</figDesc><graphic coords="16,311.36,286.58,173.62,134.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Main entities involved in the network architecture.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Entity</cell><cell>Abbreviation</cell></row><row><cell>Mobile Equipment</cell><cell>ME</cell></row><row><cell>Evolved Node B</cell><cell>eNB</cell></row><row><cell>Home Evolved Node B</cell><cell>HeNB</cell></row><row><cell>Mobile Management Entity</cell><cell>MME</cell></row><row><cell>Serving Gateway</cell><cell>S-GW</cell></row><row><cell>Home Subscriber Server</cell><cell>HSS</cell></row><row><cell>Group Management Server</cell><cell>GMS</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, and the detailed steps are as follows.</figDesc><table><row><cell>ME G1À1</cell><cell>generates</cell><cell>AUTH G1</cell><cell>as</cell><cell>follows:</cell></row></table><note><p>(a1) ME G1À1 ? MME: Access Request. (a2) MME ? ME G1À1 : Identity Request. (a3) ME G1À1 ? MME: (AUTH G1 ).</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>kR G1À1 kT G1 kLAIÞ. Since TID ME G1À1 represents ME G1À1 's temporary identity, if HN needs to require ME G1À1 's permanent identity ðPID ME G1À1 Þ when necessary, fPID ME G1À1 g Pub HN will be sent to HN. (a4) MME ? HSS: Authentication Data Request (AUTH G1 , LAI). When the HSS receives authentication data request message contained ME G1À1 's AUTH G1 , the HSS verifies the received MAC G1 in AUTH G1 using key G1À1 . Since the MME knows the LAI of the base station (BS) forwarding AUTH G1 , it forwards AUTH G1 to the HSS together with the BS's LAI. By checking MAC G1 , the HSS can verify whether the LAI reported by the MME is the same as that recognized by the ME.</figDesc><table /><note><p>(a5) HSS ? MME: Authentication Data Response (AUTH HSS ). Once verification passes, the HSS retrieves the corresponding group key GK G1 to generate a group temporary key GTK G1 ¼ f 2 GK G1 ðR HSS kAMFÞ. Then the HSS</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Protocol notation.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Notation</cell><cell>Definition</cell></row><row><cell>R x</cell><cell>The rand number generated by x</cell></row><row><cell>T x</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Group information management list. HSS kR G1À1 kAMFk GTK G1 ), and sends AUTH HSS together with G1's information stored in the Group Information Management List (Table3) to the MME. The MME receives and stores them for future use. AUTH HSS for group G1, the MME selects random number a and computes aP on E. Then the MME performs mutual authentication with ME G1À1 by generating AUTH MME as follows:AUTH MME ¼ ðID MME kID G1 kTID ME G1À1 kMAC MME kR HSS kR MME kR G1À1 kAMFkapÞ, where MAC MME ¼ f 1 GTK G1 ðID MME kID G1 kTID ME G1À1 kR MME kR HSS kR G1À1 kAMFkapkSV G1À1 þ iÞ,where SV G1À1 can be got from (a5) and i represents the ith run of mutual authentication with ME G1À1 .</figDesc><table><row><cell>Group</cell><cell>Group ID</cell><cell>ME ID</cell><cell>Synchronization value</cell></row><row><cell>G1</cell><cell>ID G1</cell><cell>TID G1À1</cell><cell>SV G1À1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>TID G1À2</cell><cell>SV G1À2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>. . .</cell><cell>. . .</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>TID G1Àn</cell><cell>SV G1Àn</cell></row><row><cell>G2</cell><cell>ID G2</cell><cell>TID G2À1</cell><cell>SV G2À1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>. . .</cell><cell>. . .</cell></row></table><note><p>generates AUTH HSS , AUTH HSS = (R (a7) ME G1À1 ? MME: Authentication Response (MAC G1À1 kbP). On receiving the message from the MME, ME G1À1 verifies the received MAC MME in AUTH MME as follows:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The ME G1À1 verifies whether MAC 0 MME equals MAC MME or not. If MAC 0 MME is not the same as MAC MME , the HSS or the MME server is not valid. Therefore, the ME G1À1 terminates the procedure and sends MAC failure (Mac_Fail) message. Meanwhile, the ME G1À1 will send fFAIL; PID ME G1À1 ; randg Pub HN to require a new MAC verification. If verification passes, ME G1À1 selects random number b and computes bP on E, and calculates KGK ME G1À1 ¼ f 3 MME kID G1 kTID ME G1À1 kR MME kabP kbPkSV G1À1 þ iÞ; GTK G1 ðID MME kTID ME G1À1 kR MME kR G1À1 kabPÞ. Then it checks whether ME G1À1 has generated the correct response. If verification is successful, it sends authentica-</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>GTK G1</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">ðID MME kTID ME G1À1 kR MME kR G1À1 kabPÞ for subsequent sessions</cell></row><row><cell>with</cell><cell>the</cell><cell cols="2">MME</cell><cell>and</cell><cell cols="2">MAC ME G1À1 ¼ f 1 KGK ME G1À1</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">(a8) MME ? ME G1À1 : Authentication Acknowledge.</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">When the MME receives an authentication response</cell></row><row><cell>message</cell><cell cols="2">carrying</cell><cell cols="2">MAC ME G1À1 ,</cell><cell>it</cell><cell>also</cell><cell>computes</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">KGK ME G1À1 ¼ f 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>ðID</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>AUTH ME G1À2 ¼ ðID G1 kTID ME G1À2 kR G1À2 Þ. Note that, ME G1À2 does not need to send MAC G1 to the MME, because the MME can authenticate ME G1À2 directly without the HSS's assistance, therefore MAC G1 does not need to be used. The ME can perform mutual authentication with MME directly. Similarly, TID ME G1À2 represents ME G1À2 's temporary identity, if HN needs to require ME G1À2 's permanent identity, fPID ME G1À2 g Pub HN will be sent instead. MME ). When the MME receives AUTH ME G1À2 , it first selects random number a and computes aP on E. Then, the MME begins to perform mutual authentication with ME G1À2 by generating AUTH MME as follows:AUTH MME ¼ ðID MME kID G1 kTID ME G1À2 kMAC MME kR HSS kR MME kR G1À2 kAMFÞ, where MAC MME ¼ f 1 GTK G1 ðID MME kID G1 kTID ME G1À2 kR MME kR HSS kR G1À2 kAMFkap kSV G1À2 þ iÞ. irepresents the i-th run of mutual authentication with ME G1À2 . (b5) ME G1À2 ? MME: Authentication Response (MAC G1À2 kbP). On receiving the message from the MME, ME G1À2 verifies the received MAC MME in AUTH MME as follows: (1) ME G1À2 computes GTK G1 ¼ f 2 GK G1 ðR HSS kAMFÞ; (2) ME G1À2 computes MAC 0 MME ¼ f 1 GTK G1 ðID MME kID G1 kTID ME G1À2 kR MME kR HSS kR G1À2 kAMFkapkSV G1À2 þ iÞ; (3) The ME G1À2 verifies whether MAC 0 MME equals MAC MME or not. If MAC 0 MME is not the same MAC MME , the HSS or the MME server is not valid. Therefore, the ME G1À2 terminates the procedure and sends MAC failure (Mac_Fail) message. PID ME G1À2 ; randg Pub HN to require a new MAC verification. If verification passes, ME G1À2 selects random number b and computes bP on E, and calculates KGK ME G1À2 ¼ f 3 GTK G1 ðID MME kTID ME G1À2 kR MME kR G1À2 kabPÞ for subsequent sessions with the MME and MAC ME G1À2 ¼ f 3 KGK ME G1À2 ðID MME kID G1 kTID ME G1À2 kR MME kLAIkbPkabPkSV G1À2 þ iÞ; (b6) MME ? ME G1À2 : Authentication Acknowledge. When the MME receives an authentication response message carrying MAC ME G1À2 , it also computes KGK ME G1À2 ¼ f 3 GTK G1 ðID MME kTID ME G1À2 kR MME kR G1À2 kabPÞ, then it checks whether ME G1À2 has generated the correct response. Since the MME knows the LAI 0 of the BS forwarding AUTH ME G1À2 , it can verify whether the LAI 0 forwarded by the BS is the same as that recognized by the ME G1À2 through by checking MAC G1À2 .</figDesc><table><row><cell>ME G1À2 (b4) MME (AUTH Meanwhile, generates AUTN ME G1À2 as follows: ?ME G1À2 : Authentication Request fFAIL;</cell><cell>the</cell><cell>ME G1À2</cell><cell>will</cell><cell>send</cell></row></table><note><p>(b1)-(b2) are similar to ME G1À1 's. (b3) ME G1À2 ? MME: ðAUTH ME G1À2 Þ.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Main process grammar.</figDesc><table><row><cell>P, Q::¼</cell><cell>Processes</cell></row><row><cell>0</cell><cell>Null process</cell></row><row><cell>PjQ</cell><cell>Parallel composition</cell></row><row><cell>!P</cell><cell>Replication</cell></row><row><cell>new n;P</cell><cell>Name restriction</cell></row><row><cell>in(M,x);P</cell><cell>Message input</cell></row><row><cell>out(M,N);P</cell><cell>Message output</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Comparisons of security properties among the 3GPP AKA protocols.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>SE-AKA</cell><cell>UMTS-AKA [2]</cell><cell>EPS-AKA [4]</cell><cell>AP-AKA [24]</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Type of cryptosystem Symmetric and ECDH Support group authentication No</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>Table 6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Setting of parameters.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Parameters</cell><cell>Value (bits)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PID/TID</cell><cell>128</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AMF</cell><cell>48</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>LAI</cell><cell>40</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>GTK</cell><cell>128</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hash value/MAC</cell><cell>64</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Random nubmer (RN)</cell><cell>128</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ECDH key</cell><cell>192</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Comparisons of computational overhead of each entity among the 3GPP AKA protocols. MME PM ¼ T HSS PM ¼ 0:475 ms. T H and T PM represent time cost of hash and time cost of point multiplication, respectively. Moreover, n represents the number of MEs, m stands for the number of groups.</figDesc><table><row><cell>ms</cell><cell>SE-AKA</cell><cell>UMTS-AKA [2]</cell><cell>EPS-AKA [4]</cell><cell>AP-AKA [24]</cell></row><row><cell>The first ME</cell><cell>4T H + 2T PM = 3.2964</cell><cell>5T H = 0.178</cell><cell>0.178</cell><cell>3T H = 0.1068</cell></row><row><cell>Remaining MEs</cell><cell>(n À 1)(3T H + 2T PM ) = 3.2608(n À 1)</cell><cell>0.178(n À 1)</cell><cell>0.178(n À 1)</cell><cell>0.0168(n À 1)</cell></row><row><cell>MME</cell><cell>n(3T H + 2T PM ) = 0.9863n</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>HSS</cell><cell>m(2T H ) = 0.0242m</cell><cell>n (5T H ) = 0.0605n</cell><cell>0.0605n</cell><cell>n (4T H ) = 0.048n</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>4.2471n + 0.0242m</cell><cell>0.2385n</cell><cell>0.2385n</cell><cell>0.1548n</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>X-AKA [26]</cell><cell>Cocktail-AKA [28]</cell><cell>S-AKA [30]</cell><cell>G-AKA [31]</cell></row><row><cell>The first ME</cell><cell>5T H = 0.178</cell><cell>8T H = 0.2848</cell><cell>6T H = 0.2136</cell><cell>4T H = 0.1424</cell></row><row><cell>Remaining MEs</cell><cell>0.178(n À 1)</cell><cell>0.2848(n À 1)</cell><cell>0.2136(n À 1)</cell><cell>0.1424(n À 1)</cell></row><row><cell>MME</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>nT H = 0.0121n</cell><cell>n (2T H ) = 0.0242n</cell><cell>n (3T H ) = 0.0363n</cell></row><row><cell>HSS</cell><cell>n(5T H ) = 0.0605n</cell><cell>n (5T H ) = 0.0605n</cell><cell>n (2T H ) = 0.0242n</cell><cell>m (2T H ) = 0.0242m</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>0.2385n</cell><cell>0.3574n</cell><cell>0.262n</cell><cell>0.1787n + 0.0242m</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>Dual-Core 2.6 GHz as an MME and an HSS in reference</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[41]</ref></p>: Time ME H ¼ 0:0356 ms;T MME H ¼ T HSS H ¼ 0:0121 ms. T ME PM ¼ 1:537 ms;T</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Comparison of storage overhead in the SN.</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>The KFS is that any preceding key could not be disclosed if the longterm secret key K is compromised, and the KBS is that any following key could not be disclosed if the long-term secret key K is compromised.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Please cite this article in press as: C. Lai et al., SE-AKA: A secure and efficient group authentication and key agreement protocol for LTE networks, Comput. Netw. (2013), http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.comnet.2013.08.003</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Note that, to ensure user identity privacy, the permanent identity of an ME like IMSI should be confidentiality protected. It should never be transmitted in plain text. In EPS-AKA, a Globally Unique Temporary Identity (GUTI, ME's temporary identity) is transmitted instead of the IMSI for identity presentation. In spite of this security arrangement, there are occasions when the IMSI may be transmitted in plain text. We will discuss the solutions when the IMSI needs to be transmitted in the channel later.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This work is supported by China Scholarship Council, the National Natural Science Foundation of China Grant 61272457, 61102056, and the National Science and Technology Major Projects (No. 2012ZX03002003).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>X-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[26]</ref> Cocktail-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[28]</ref> S-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[30]</ref> G-AKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[31]</ref> Type of cryptosystem</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A</head><p>The basic cryptographic primitives used by the SE-AKA protocol are formalized as follows (see Tables A. <ref type="bibr">1</ref>, A.2 and A.3). </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network aspects of the GSM system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Audestad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EUROCON</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Provably-secure enhancement on 3GPP authentication and key agreement protocol, Verizon Commun., Cryptology ePrint Archive Rep</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003/092, 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A man-in-the-middle attack on UMTS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wetzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 3rd ACM WiSe</title>
		<meeting>3rd ACM WiSe<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="97" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PPAB: a privacypreserving authentication and billing architecture for metropolitan area sharing networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2529" to="2543" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enabling pervasive healthcare with privacy preservation in smart community</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2012 IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">June 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3451" to="3455" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PEC: a privacypreserving emergency call scheme for mobile healthcare social networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Communications and Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New privacy issues in mobile telephony: fix and verification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Arapinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mancini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ritter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Golde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Redon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Borgaonkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2012 ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS &apos;12)</title>
		<meeting>the 2012 ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS &apos;12)<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="216" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<idno>GPP TR 23.888 V11.0.0</idno>
		<title level="m">System Improvements for Machine-Type Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-09">September 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GRS: the green, reliability, and security of emerging machine to machine communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Communications Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Security issues on machine to machine communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">KSII Transaction on Internet and Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="498" to="514" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PPGCV: privacy preserving group communications protocol for vehicular ad hoc networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wasef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE International Conference on Communications, 2008. ICC &apos;08</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-05-23">19-23 May 2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1458" to="1463" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine-to-machine communications for home energy management system in smart grid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Niyato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Communications Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cognitive machine-to-machine communications: visions and potentials for the smart grid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nekovee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gjessing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Network</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A groupbased communication scheme based on the location information of MTC devices in cellular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2012 IEEE International Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">June 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4899" to="4903" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An individual and group authentication model for wireless network services</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ngo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Le</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Srinivasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JCIT: Journal of Convergence Information Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Group authentication protocol for mobile networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Aboudagga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Quisquater</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eltoweissy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">WIMOB &apos;07 Proceedings of the Third IEEE International Conference on Wireless and Mobile Computing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel group-based handover authentication scheme with privacy preservation for mobile WiMAX networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Communications Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1744" to="1747" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A group-based authentication and key agreement for MTC in LTE networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Globecom</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Globecom</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Proverif: Cryptographic Protocol Verifier in the Formal Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Blanchet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://www.proverif.ens.fr/&gt;" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the security of wireless network access with enhancements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Harn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hsin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2003 ACM Workshop on Wireless Security</title>
		<meeting>the 2003 ACM Workshop on Wireless Security<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="95" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Security analysis and enhancements of 3GPP authentication and key agreement protocol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="734" to="742" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Extension of an efficient 3GPP authentication and key agreement protocol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Wireless Personal Communications</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authentication and key agreement protocol for UMTS with low bandwidth consumption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 19th IEEE international conference on advanced information networking and applications (AINA)</title>
		<meeting>19th IEEE international conference on advanced information networking and applications (AINA)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="392" to="397" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new authentication protocol for UMTS mobile networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Al-Saraireh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yousef</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EURASIP Journal of Communications and Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A cocktail protocol with the authentication and key agreement on the UMTS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Systems and Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="316" to="325" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Security analysis of a cocktail protocol with the authentication and key agreement on the UMTS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Pu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="366" to="368" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AKA: a provable and secure authentication key agreement protocol for UMTS networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Shieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4509" to="4519" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Group-based authentication and key agreement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Tseng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Wireless Personal Communications</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Special Publication 800-56A, Recommendation for Pair-Wise Key Establishment Schemes Using Discrete Logarithm Cryptography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Nist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SIGMA: the&apos;SIGn-and-MAc&apos; Approach Authnticated Diffie-Hellman and its Use in the IKE Protocols</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Krawczyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Cryptology -CRYPTO 2003, 23rd Annual International Cryptology Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Santa Barbara, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">August 17-21, 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2729</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="400" to="425" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive hysteresis using mobility correlation for fast handover</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Communications Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="152" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal handover decision algorithm for throughput enhancement in cooperative cellular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 2010 IEEE VTC -Fall</title>
		<meeting>2010 IEEE VTC -Fall</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Calhoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Loughney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Guttman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Arkko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3588.txt&gt;" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diameter Base Protocol</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of security issues in multicast communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rohatgi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Network</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Table A.1 Symmetric encryption</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Type key</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fun senc (bitstring, key): bitstring</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Reduc forall m: bitstring, k: key; sdec (senc (m, k), k) = m. Table A</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Asymmetric encryption</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Type skey</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fun pk (skey): pkey</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fun aenc (bitstring, pkey): bitstring</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Reduc forall m: bitstring, sk: skey; adec (aenc (m, pk (sk)), sk)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Type exponent</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Type</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of key management for secure group communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rafaeli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hutchison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Computing Surveys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="329" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel group access authentication and key agreement protocol for machine-type communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transactions on Emerging Telecommunications Technologies</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Openssl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://www.openssl.org/&gt;" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple and robust handover authentication between HeNB and eNB in LTE networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2119" to="2131" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
