<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Learning in Region-Based Image Retrieval</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Feng</forename><surname>Jing</surname></persName>
							<email>jingfeng00@mails.tsinghua.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">State Key Lab of Intelligent Technology and Systems</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100084</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mingjing</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<email>mjli@microsoft.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Microsoft Research Asia</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>49 Zhichun Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>100080</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lei</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<email>i-lzhang@microsoft.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Microsoft Research Asia</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>49 Zhichun Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>100080</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hong-Jiang</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<email>hjzhang@microsoft.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bo</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Microsoft Research Asia</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>49 Zhichun Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>100080</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">State Key Lab of Intelligent Technology and Systems</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100084</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Learning in Region-Based Image Retrieval</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A8A1B63EE62BB10C8FC3D25722920E3C</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T16:54+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this paper, several effective learning algorithms using global image representations are adjusted and introduced to region-based image retrieval (RBIR). First, the query point movement technique is considered. By assembling all the segmented regions of positive examples together and resizing the regions to emphasize the latest positive examples, a composite image is formed as the new query. Second, the application of support vector machines (SVM) in relevance feedback for RBIR is investigated. Both the one class SVM as a class distribution estimator and two classes SVM as a classifier are taken into account. For the latter, two representative display strategies are studied. Last, inspired by those feature re-weighting methods, a region re-weighting algorithm is proposed. Experimental results on a database of 10,000 general-purpose images demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed learning algorithms.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Most of the early researches on content-based image retrieval (CBIR) have been focused on developing effective global features Error! Reference source not found. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>[14] <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. While these researches establish the basis of CBIR, the retrieval performance is still far from users' expectations. The main reason is acknowledged to be the gap between low-level features and high-level concepts. To narrow down this semantic gap, two techniques have been widely used: region-based features to represent the focus of the user's perceptions of image content <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>[8] <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and learning techniques, e.g. relevance feedback (RF), to learn the user's intentions <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>[10] <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>[15] <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</p><p>Many early CBIR systems perform retrieval based primarily on global features. It is not unusual that users accessing a CBIR system look for objects, but the aforementioned systems are likely to fail, since a single signature computed for the entire image cannot sufficiently capture the important properties of individual objects. Regionbased image retrieval (RBIR) systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> attempt to overcome the drawback of global features by representing images at object-level, which is intended to be close to the perception of human visual system <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>One of the interactive learning techniques is relevance feedback (RF) initially developed in text retrieval <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. RF was introduced into CBIR during mid 1990's and has been shown to provide dramatic performance boost in retrieval systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>[15] <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. The main idea of RF is to let users guide the system. During retrieval process, the user interacts with the system and rates the relevance of the retrieved images, according to his/her subjective judgment. With this additional information, the system dynamically learns the user's intention, and gradually presents better results.</p><p>Although RF has shown its great potential in image retrieval systems that use global representations, it has seldom been introduced to RBIR systems. Minka and Picard performed a pioneering work in this area by proposing the FourEyes system <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. FourEyes contains three stages: grouping generation, grouping weighting and grouping collection. In spite of its many good characteristics, FourEyes system has two disadvantages. One is the use of region-to-region similarity measure <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, and the other is the re-clustering of all the features when a new image is added, which means that it is not very scalable.</p><p>The main purpose of this paper is to integrate region-based representations and learning techniques and allows them to benefit from each other. To do that, on the one hand, two RF methods are proposed. One is the query point movement (QPM) algorithm with speedup techniques. The other is to introduce three SVM schemes based on a new kernel. On the other hand, a novel region re-weighting scheme based on users' feedback information is proposed. The region weights that coincide with human perception improve the accuracy of both initial query and the following relevance feedback. Furthermore, the region weights could not only be used in a query session, but be also memorized and accumulated for future queries.</p><p>The organization of the paper is as follows: Section 2 describes the basic elements of a RBIR system including: image segmentation, image representation and image similarity measure. The RF strategies using QPM and SVM are described in Section 3 and Section 4 respectively. The region re-weighting scheme is presented in Section 5. In Section 6, we provide experimental results that evaluate all aspects of the learning schemes. Finally, we conclude in Section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Region-Based Image Retrieval</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Image Segmentation</head><p>The segmentation method we utilized is proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. First, a criterion for homogeneity of a certain pattern is proposed. Applying the criterion to local windows in the original image results in the H-image. The high and low values of the H-image correspond to possible region boundaries and region interiors respectively. Then, a region growing method is used to segment the image based on the H-image. Finally, visually similar regions are merged together to avoid over-segmentation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Image Representation</head><p>Currently, the spatial relationship of regions is not considered, and an image is represented by a set of its regions. To describe a region, we use two properties: the features of the region and its importance weight. Two features are adopted. One is the color moment 0 and the other is the banded auto-correlogram 0. For the former, we extract the first two moments from each channel of CIE-LUV color space. For the latter, the HSV color space with inhomogenous quantization into 36 colors 0 is adopted. Considering that the size of the regions may be small, we use b = d = 2 in the current computation 0. Therefore, the resulting 36 dimensional feature suggests the local structure of colors. Since color moments measure the global information of colors, the two features are complementary to each other and the combination enables them benefit from each other. The area percentage of regions is used as its importance weight in Section 2, 3, 4 temporarily. More satisfactory weighting methods are discussed in Section 5. The only requirement is that the sum of importance weights of an image should be equal to 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Image Similarity Measure</head><p>Based on the image representation, the distance between two images is measured using the Earth Mover's Distance (EMD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. EMD is based on the minimal cost that must be paid to transform one distribution into another. Considering that EMD matches perceptual similarity well and can operate on variable-length representations of the distributions, it is suitable for region-based image similarity measure.</p><p>In this special case, a signature is an image with all the regions corresponding to clusters, and the ground distance is the L 1 distance between the features of two regions. EMD incorporates the properties of all the segmented regions so that information about an image can be fully utilized. By allowing many-to-many relationship of the regions to be valid, EMD is robust to inaccurate segmentation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Query Point Movement</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">The Optimal Query</head><p>Inspired by the query-point movement (QPM) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, a novel relevance feedback approach to region-based image retrieval is proposed <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. The basic assumption is that every region could be helpful in retrieval. Based on this assumption, all the regions of both initial query and positive examples are assembled into a pseudo image, which is used as the optimal query at next iteration of retrieval and feedback process. The importance of the regions of optimal query is normalized such that the sum of them is equal to 1. During the normalization, regions of those newly added positive examples, which reflect the user's latest query refinement more precisely, are emphasized by given more importance. As more positive examples are available, the number of regions in the optimal query increases rapidly. Since the time required calculating image similarity is proportional to the number of regions in the query, the retrieval speed will slow down gradually. To avoid this, regions similar in the feature space are merged into larger ones together via clustering. This process is similar to region merging in an over-segmented image.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">RF Using QPM</head><p>The RF process using QPM technique is summarized as follows.</p><p>The initial query is regarded as a positive example for the sake of simplicity. At the first iteration of feedback, all regions of positive examples are assembled into a composite image, in which similar regions are grouped into clusters by k-means algorithm. Regions within a cluster are merged into a new region. The feature of the new region is equal to the average feature of individual regions, while the importance of it is set to the sum of individual region importance divided by the number of positive examples. This composite image is used as the optimal query example.</p><p>In the following iterations, only the optimal query is treated as a positive example with all other prior examples being ignored. That is, there is exactly one prior positive example, which is treated equally as newly added positive examples. This implies that the importance of the prior positive examples gradually decays in the optimal query, and the importance of the newly added ones is emphasized accordingly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">SVM-based RF</head><p>As a core machine learning technology, SVM has not only strong theoretical foundations but also excellent empirical successes <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. SVM has also been introduced into CBIR as a powerful RF tool, and performs fairly well in the systems that use global representations <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>[15] <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</p><p>Given the RF information, generally two kinds of learning could be done in order to boost the performance. One is to estimate the distribution of the target images, while the other is to learn a boundary that separates the target images from the rest. For the former, the so-called one-class SVM was adopted 0. A kernel based one-class SVM as density estimator for positive examples was shown in 0 to outperform the whitening transform based linear/quadratic method. For the latter, the typical form of SVM as a binary classifier is appropriate 00. A SVM captures the query concept by separating the relevant images from the irrelevant images with a hyperplane in a projected space.</p><p>When SVM is used as a classifier in RF, there are two display strategies. One strategy is to display the most-positive (MP) images and use them as the training sam-ples 0. The MP images are chosen as the ones farthest from the boundary on the positive side, plus those nearest from the boundary on the negative side if necessary. The underlying assumption is that the users are greedy and impatient and thus expects the best possible retrieval results after each feedback. It is also the strategy adopted by most early relevance feedback schemes. However, if we assume the users are cooperative, another strategy is more appropriate. In this strategy, both the MP images and the most-informative (MI) images are displayed. Additional user feedbacks, if any, will only be performed on those MI images, while the MP images are shown as the final results. Tong and Chang 0 proposed an active learning algorithm to select the samples to maximally reduce the size of the version space. Following the principle of maximal disagreement, the best strategy is to halve the version space each time. By taking advantage of the duality between the feature space and the parameter space, they showed that the points near the boundary can approximately achieve this goal. Therefore, the points near the boundary are used to approximate the MI points.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">EMD-Based Kernel</head><p>Unlike the global feature, the region-based representations of images are of variable length, which means both the inner product and the L p norm are not applicable. As a result, the common kernels, such as the polynomial kernel and Gaussian kernel are inappropriate in this situation.</p><p>To resolve the issue, a generalization of Gaussian kernel is introduced:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">) 2 ) , ( exp( ) , ( 2 σ y x d y x k GGaussian - =<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where d is a distance measure in the input space. Since the distance measure here is EMD, a particular form of the generalized Gaussian kernel with d being EMD is considered. More specific, the proposed kernel is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">) 2 ) , ( exp( ) , ( 2 σ y x EMD y x k GEMD - =<label>(2)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Region Re-weighting</head><p>Enlightened by the idea of feature re-weighting <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and the TF*IDF (Term Frequency * Inverse Document Frequency) weighting in text retrieval, we designed a RF*IIF (Region Frequency * Inverse Image Frequency) weighting scheme. It uses users' feedback information to estimate the region importance of all positive images. The basic assumption is that important regions should appear more times in the positive images and fewer times in all the images of the database. Before we go into details, we first introduce some notations and definitions that will be used to illustrate the region importance.</p><p>Two regions are deemed as similar, if the L 1 distance between their feature vectors is less than a predefined threshold.</p><p>A region R and an image I is defined to be similar if at least one region of I is similar to R. We use s(R, I) to denote this relationship: s(R, I) = 1 if R is similar to I, while s(R, I) = 0 otherwise.</p><p>Assume that there are totally N images in the database, which are represented by { } N I I ,..., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> . Also assume that we are calculating the region importance of I that con-</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">sists of regions { } n R R R ,..., ,<label>2 1</label></formula><p>. I is actually one of the positive examples identified by a user in feedback. Note that the original query image is also considered to be a positive example. Let all the positive examples be { }</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">+ + k I I ,..., 1</formula><p>For each region i R , we define a measure of region frequency (RF), which reflects the extent to which it is consistent with other positive examples in the feature space. Intuitively, the larger the region frequency value, the more important this region is in representing the user's intention. The region frequency is defined in the following way.</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">∑ = + = k j j i i I R s R RF 1 ) , ( ) (<label>(3)</label></formula><p>On the other hand, a region becomes less important if it is similar to many images in the database. To reflect the distinguishing ability of a region, we define a measure of inverse image frequency (IIF) for region i R :</p><p>) ) , (</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">= = N j j i i I R s N R IIF<label>log( ) ( 1 ∑</label></formula><p>which is analogous to the IDF (inverse document frequency) in text retrieval. Based on the above preparations, we now come to the definition of the region importance:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">∑ = = n j j j i i i R IIF R RF R IIF R RF R RI 1 )) ( * ) ( ( ) ( * ) ( ) (<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Basically, the importance of a region is its region frequency weighted by the inverse image frequency, and normalized over all regions in an image such that the sum of all region importance weights is equal to 1.</p><p>Since to "common" users the region importance is similar, it can be cumulated for future use. More specific, given a region i R , its cumulate region importance (CRI) after l (l &gt; 0) updates is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">l R RI l R CRI l l R CRI i i i ) ( ) 1 , ( * ) 1 ( ) , ( + - - =<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">) ( i R RI</formula><p>is the latest RI of i R calculated from formula (3) and ) 0 , ( i R CRI is initialized to be the area percentage (AP) of i R . Note that once the RI of a region is learned, its CRI will have nothing to do with its AP.</p><p>The algorithm was evaluated with a general-purpose image database of 10,000 images from COREL. 1,000 images were randomly chosen from totally 72 categories as the query set. All the experimental results are averages of the 1,000 queries. The implementation of SVM was based on the source code of LibSVM <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>We simulated users' feedback as follows. For a query image, 5 iterations of userand-system interactions were carried out. At each iteration, the system examined the top 20 images, excluding those positive examples labeled in previous iterations. Images from the same (different) category as the initial query image were used as new positive (negative) examples. At next iteration, all positive and negative images were placed in top and bottom ranks respectively, while others were ranked according to a certain criteria.</p><p>Considering that it is difficult to design a fair comparison with existing RBIR systems that use RF, such as the FourEyes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> system whose purpose is annotation, we compared our QPM-based RF method with the one proposed by Rui Yong in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> which uses both QPM and feature re-weighting. Since <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> requires global features, the auto-correlogram is adopted. As in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, we consider the RGB color space with quantization into 64 colors. The distance set D = {1, 3, 5, 7} is used for computing, which results in a feature vector of 256 dimensions. The results are shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. The accuracy in this and also other figures of this paper means the average precision within top 30 images, i.e. average P(30). As shown in the figure, before any feedback, the accuracy of region-based representation is higher than that of auto-correlogram by 6%., which suggests the advantage of region based representation. Furthermore, our method consistently yields better performance after one iteration and its accuracy after 5 interactions is higher than that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> by 22%.</p><p>The SVM-based RF methods using region representation and kernel k GEMD is evaluated by comparing with those using global representation and Laplacian kernel. All the three strategies mentioned in Section 4 are considered: one class SVM (SVM(OC)), two classes SVM displaying MP images (SVM(MP)), and two classes SVM displaying MI images (SVM(MI)). The Laplacian kernel is chosen because of its superiority over other kernels, e.g. Gaussian kernel, in histogram-based applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, 3, 4 show the comparison results. No matter what strategy is used, region-based algorithm consistently performs better than global-based one. Let us use Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> as an example, where SVM(MP) strategy is adopted. After five iterations of feedback, the region-based algorithm boosts its accuracy (56%) more than globalbased one (52%) using auto-correlogram by 4%.</p><p>The proposed RF methods are also compared with each other. The results are shown in Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>. Three conclusions could be drawn from the figure. First, two classes SVM performs better than both SVM(OC) and QPM. In this experiment, the accuracy of SVM(MP) is higher than that of QPM by 20% after five iterations of feedback. The results suggest that negative examples are helpful if appropriately used. Second, SVM(OC) performs almost the same as QPM. Last, there is neglectable difference between SVM(MP) and SVM(MI).</p><p>To evaluate the region re-weighting scheme, 5,000 random query and feedback sessions were carried out, during which the CRIs were cumulated and memorized.</p><p>The feedback process was performed by using SVM as a binary classifier and displaying the MP images, which is the best learning strategy of all the proposed ones. The influence of CRI on the proposed RF algorithms is shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref><ref type="figure">2</ref><ref type="figure">3</ref><ref type="figure">4</ref>. For example, in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, before any feedback, the one using CRI is better than that using AP by 6%. After five iterations of feedback, the difference remains to be 6%. The results show that CRI boosts those region-based RF techniques to a higher level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Conclusion</head><p>In this paper, three learning schemes for RBIR are proposed with the first one using QPM and speedup techniques, the second one enabling both one class and two classes SVMs by introducing a new kernel, and the third one borrowing ideas of feature reweighting to achieve region re-weighting. Experimental comparisons with the corresponding global representation-based algorithms on large scale database show the effectiveness of the proposed schemes. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .Figure 2 .Figure 3 .Figure 4 .Figure 5 .</head><label>12345</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Comparison of Rui's method and QPM using two weighting schemes</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blobworld: a system for region-based image indexing and retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Carson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Third Int. Conf. On Visual Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Training nu-support vector classifiers: theory and algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neural Computation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2119" to="2147" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Support vector machines for histogram-based image classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Chapelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Haffner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Vapnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1055" to="1064" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-09">Sept. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">One-class SVM for Learning in Image Retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Intl Conf. on Image Proc. (ICIP&apos;2001)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Thessaloniki, Greece</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">October 7-10, 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An Introduction to Support Vector Machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cristianini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shawe-Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image indexing using color correlograms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Comp. Soc. Conf. Comp. Vis. and Patt. Rec</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Comp. Soc. Conf. Comp. Vis. and Patt. Rec</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="762" to="768" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning in Content-Based Image Retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The 2nd International Conference on Development and Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Region-based relevance feedback in image retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised Image Segmentation Using Local Homogeneity Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems</title>
		<meeting>IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive Learning Using A Society Of Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Minka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Picard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="565" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-04">April 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Metric for Distributions with Applications to Image Databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rubner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1998 IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision</title>
		<meeting>the 1998 IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-01">January 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimizing Learning in Image Retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceeding of IEEE int. Conf. On Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</title>
		<meeting>eeding of IEEE int. Conf. On Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-06">Jun. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Automatic text processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Salton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similarity of Color Images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stricker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Orengo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Storage and Retrieval for Image and Video Databases, Proc. SPIE 2420</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="392" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Support vector machine active leaning for image retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Multimedia</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ottawa, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SIMPLIcity: Semantics-sensitive Integrated Matching for Picture Libraries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wiederhold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PAMI</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Support Vector Machine Learning for Image Retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE International Conference on Image Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-10">October, 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A CBIR method based on color-spatial feature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Region 10 Annual International Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="169" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
