<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">End-to-End Congestion Control Schemes: Utility Functions, Random Losses and ECN Marks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Srisankar</forename><surname>Kunniyur</surname></persName>
							<email>kunniyur@uiuc.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Coordinated Science Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Illinois</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Srikant</surname></persName>
							<email>rsrikant@uiuc.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Coordinated Science Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Illinois</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">End-to-End Congestion Control Schemes: Utility Functions, Random Losses and ECN Marks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5CE9268E0031435E12323E79D266A6F2</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T16:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We present a framework for designing end-to-end congestion control schemes in a network where each user may have a different utility function. We first show that there exists an additive increasemultiplicative decrease scheme using only end-to-end measurable losses such that a socially-optimal solution can be reached. We incorporate noncongestion-related random losses and round-trip delay in this model, and show that one can generalize observations regarding TCP-type congestion avoidance to more general window flow control schemes. We then consider explicit congestion notification (ECN) as an alternate mechanism (instead of losses) for signaling congestion and show that ECN marking levels can be designed to nearly eliminate losses in the network by choosing the marking level independently for each node in the network. While the ECN marking level at each node may depend on the number of flows through the node, the appropriate marking level can be estimated using only aggregate flow measurements, i.e., per-flow measurements are not required.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Recently there has been a surge of interest in designing besteffort service networks that can deliver low-loss, low-delay service by encouraging users to adapt to the network congestion using minimal information from the network. The potential advantages of such networks would be the ability to offer even realtime services with little or no interaction from the core network, i.e., without the need for a centralized admission control, resource reservation or complicated scheduling mechanisms. We are partly motivated by the recent works of Gibbens and Kelly <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> who have demonstrated the possibility of designing such networks using simple models. Some of the issues that have to be addressed when designing these networks include defining appropriate notions of fairness, designing a pricing scheme to induce non-cooperative users to work towards an equilibrium that is fair, designing a control mechanism for achieving this fairness using end-to-end measurable quantities such as lost packets, replacing losses with alternate indicators of congestion to evolve towards networks where congestion-related losses are negligible, and providing ways to combat spurious congestion indicators such as errors on wireless links. In this paper, our goal is to provide a simple framework based on deterministic fluid models that would provide insight into the effect of utility functions, random losses and explicit congestion notification on the design of end-to-end congestion controllers.</p><p>We start with the nonlinear programming formulation of a flow allocation problem suggested in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> from which a penalty function formulation is derived in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, it has been shown that a congestion controller can be designed such that Research supported by NSF Grants ANI-9813710 and ANI-9714685 the equilibrium point of the congestion controller is stable and converges to the unique solution of the penalty function form of the nonlinear program. We first show that by appropriately designing the penalty function, the resulting congestion controller for each user is a function of only its own loss rate and does not depend on any other information from the network. We also show that the penalty function can also be thought as a pricing scheme which steers a set of non-cooperative users to a socially optimal solution as in "smart-market" proposal <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. Our formulation is also closely related to the approach presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. While <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> uses duality theory to solve the nonlinear program formulation of the resource allocation problem, we use a penalty function approach as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. As we will see later, our primary motivation for doing this is that we want TCP to be a special case of our formulation and thus, any controller in the class that we study can be checked for TCP-friendliness <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Further, our ECN marking scheme described later becomes a straightforward modification to TCP where losses are simply replaced by marks in the congestion avoidance algorithm. For yet another related, but different, approach, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p><p>Our approach allows for different congestion controllers for different users which are directly derived from their utility functions. This allows one to model the heterogeneity in the needs of different applications. It is now well-established that various notions of fairness can be defined in terms of appropriate utility functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. While the well-known maxmin fairness <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> cannot be defined in terms of a single utility function, it can still be defined in terms of a sequence of utility functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Thus, another motivation for allowing different utility functions for different users is to develop a model that would potentially allow one to study interactions between different types of congestion controllers derived by starting with different notions of fairness.</p><p>We then incorporate the effects of random losses<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> in our model and study the effect of random losses and round-trip delay on different window flow control schemes that could be derived by starting with different utility functions. The effect of random losses and round-trip delay on TCP performance have been quantified in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Our results generalize these earlier works to the case of multiple nodes and to window flow controllers derived from other utility functions.</p><p>Finally we study the use of early congestion notification, prior to losses occurring, using ECN marks. We show that, in the fluid model framework, there is a notion of a marking level at each node and that marking levels for each node can be chosen in a decentralized manner to achieve loss-free service globally. The framework developed in this paper allows us to show that, with ECN marking, the deleterious effects of non-congestion-related losses can be nearly eliminated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. END-TO-END RATE-BASED CONGESTION CONTROL</head><p>Consider a network with a set of links L such that link l 2 L has capacity C l : The network is used by a set of users R: Associated with each user r 2 R is a route which is also denoted by r; and which consists of a subset of L: Now, consider a losssensitive user r which generates traffic at rate x r : Let x c r be a vector of rates of all the other users in the network. We think of a user as having a transmitter and a receiver. The transmitted rate is x r and the received rate is y r x r : The received rate could be less than the transmitted rate due to congestion in the network. For the moment, we ignore non-congestion-related losses, which we will consider later. The received rate y r is some function of x r and x c r and we denote it by f r (x r ; x c r ): The objective of user r is to maximize J r (x r ) = w r U r (x r ) ? r P(x r ; x c r );</p><p>(1) where U r is a utility function and P is some function of the transmitted rates of all the users. For example, since our goal is build a low loss, low delay network, P could be thought of as a penalty on the loss rate (x r ? y r ): The parameters w r and r attempt to trade-off between maximizing utility and minimizing loss rate.</p><p>The above problem is a game among the heterogeneous set of users R where each User r 2 R attempts to maximize its own objective given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Throughout this paper, we will refer to this as the congestion control game. Ideally we would like this game to have a unique equilibrium point and for the set of users to converge to this equilibrium point from any arbitrary initial condition. In this section, under the following assumptions, we show that there is an end-to-end rate-based congestion control scheme which achieves these goals with no feedback from the core network:</p><p>(i) The loss rate for user r on a link l 2 r is given by x r 0 @ X j:l2j</p><p>x j ? C l 1 A + X j:l2j</p><p>x j ;</p><p>where (x) + := max(x; 0): If there is any loss at a link, then we simply assume that the total loss is distributed among the users in proportion to their flow rates. For example, this would be a good approximation of FIFO queueing with small buffers and packets that are small compared to the capacity of the link, i.e., a fluid model for the traffic. Thus, we do not require any complicated per-flow scheduling mechanism at each node.</p><p>(ii) The total loss rate (x r ? y r ) for user r is given by X l:l2r</p><p>x r 0 @ X j:l2j</p><p>x j ? C l 1 A + X j:l2j</p><p>x j :</p><p>We will refer to this to as the "link independence" assumption for the loss. Thus, we assume that the same flow is presented by a user to all links on its route, even though the flow will actually be "thinned" in downstream links due to losses at upstream links. Later, we show through simulations that this assumption does not have a significant impact.</p><p>(iii) The "penalty" function is of the form P(x r ; y r ) = Z x r 0</p><p>x ? f r (x; x c r )</p><p>x dx:</p><p>Recall that f r (x; x c r ) is simply the received rate y r of User r when the transmitted rate of User r is x and x c r is the vector of transmitted rates of all the other users in the network. Later, we will argue that the penalty-per-unit flow has the interpretation of price.</p><p>(iv) U r ( ) is a continuously differentiable, strictly concave, increasing function in the interval (0; 1) and we assume that U r (x r ) is unbounded as x r ! 0: Examples of such a function include log x r and ?1=x r : An open issue is to incorporate non-concave utility functions such as those studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Proposition 1: The game admits a unique Nash equilibrium which is also the unique maximum of the following team problem, i.e., one where all users jointly optimize a single performance objective:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">max fx r g X r w r r U r (x r ) ? X l2L Z X l2j x j 0 (x ? C l ) +</formula><p>x dx; <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> subject to x r 0 8r: Proof: For proofs, please see <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.  From now on, for the purpose of simplicity, we consider only two classes of utility functions although the following results can be easily extended to all functions satisfying Assumption (iv) stated earlier. Let R 1 be the set of users who utility function is log x r ; and let the utility function of User r 2 R 2 = R n R 1 be ?1=x r r : If R 1 = R; then (3) defines the proportionally fair solution <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and if R 2 = R and r = 1 8r; then (3) defines the minimum potential delay fairness <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>.</p><p>Proposition 3: Suppose that each user r 2 R 1 employs the congestion-control algorithm _</p><p>x r = r w r r ? (x r ? y r ) ; <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> and each user j 2 R 2 employs the algorithm _ x j = j j w j j ? x j j (x j ? y j ) ;</p><p>where r ; j &gt; 0 are some constants. The above congestioncontrol scheme converges to the unique Nash equilibrium of Proposition 1.</p><p>The above proposition shows that, for each of the utility functions, in the class defined by Assumption (iv), there exists a congestion-control scheme which achieves the Nash equilibrium (or team-optimality) using only information available at the transmitter (x r ) and the receiver (y r ). Mo and Walrand   [25] have derived an alternate end-to-end control scheme where round-trip time measurements are explicitly accounted in their model. As we will see later, the window flow control approximation of our scheme is more along the lines of TCP which uses packet loss as the congestion indicator.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. NON-CONGESTION-RELATED LOSSES</head><p>The rate at which packets are received at the receiver for User r is, in general, not only a function of congestion, but is also a function of non-congestion-related losses such as hardware failures in a wireline network, or more frequently, due to errors on wireless links on the route. Typically, these are modeled as a random phenomena that are independent across users. In our deterministic fluid model, we simply let the received rate for User r be z r = r y r ; where (1 ? r ) is the fraction of packets lost due to non-congestion related reasons. These are typically referred to as random losses. Thus, our congestion control algorithms are modified as follows: each r 2 R 1 uses the algorithm _ x r = r w r r ? (x r ? z r ) ;</p><p>and each user j 2 R 2 uses the algorithm _ x j = j j w j j ? x j j (x j ? z j ) :</p><p>Proposition 4: In the presence of random losses, the congestion control algorithms converge to the unique Nash equilibrium of the following game: max x r w r r r U r (x r ) ? (1 ? r ) r x r ? P(x r ; x c r ):</p><p>The Nash equilibrium is also the unique optimal solution of the following team problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">max fx r g X r w r r r U r (x r ) ? (1 ? r ) r x r ? X l2L Z X l2j x j 0 (x ? C l ) +</formula><p>x dx:</p><p>Proof: The fact that the Nash equilibrium of the game and team-optimal solutions are unique and identical to each other follows along the lines of the proof of Proposition 1. It is easy to see that ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">8</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">9</ref>) can be rewritten as _ x r = r w r r ? r (x r ? y r ) ? (1 ? r )x r = r r w r r r ? (x r ? y r ) ? (1 ? r )x r r :</p><p>and each user j 2 R 2 uses the algorithm _</p><p>x j = j j j w j j j ? x j j (x j ? z j ) ? (1 ? j ) r x j +1 j Now, the convergence of the congestion-control scheme ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">8</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">9</ref>) follows along the lines of the proof of Proposition 3.</p><p>It was pointed out in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> that letting ! 1 is not advisable in the presence of feedback delay. The above proposition presents an alternate reason for not letting ! 1: When ! 1; all the bandwidth is shared only among flows with r = 1; the others have x r ! 0: When &lt; 1; the bandwidth allocation among users will depend on the relative values of r :</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. WINDOW FLOW CONTROL</head><p>Window flow control where the window size is modified upon receipt of acks or nacks is a more convenient implementation than a rate-based control scheme because it is inherently selfclocking, i.e., there is no need to decide parameters like measurement intervals, discretization time-steps, etc. To obtain a window flow control mechanism to reach our stable Nash equilibrium point, we start by discretizing ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">7</ref>) to obtain</p><p>x r (t + ) ? x r (t) = r w r r ? (x r ? z r ) ; r 2 R 1 (10) and</p><p>x j (t + ) ? x j (t) = j j w j j ? x j j (x j ? z j ) ; (11)  j 2 R 2 :</p><p>Now, let the round-trip delay for user r be d r and let W r (t) be its window size at time t: We make the following approximation relating data transmission rate and window size <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>:</p><p>x r (t) W r (t)=d r :</p><p>Let A r (t; t + ) denote the numbers of acks received by User r in the time interval t; t+ ) and let N r (t; t+ ) be the number of nacks received by User r in the same time interval. By acks, we refer to both positive and negative acknowledgments here. Thus, A r (t; t + ) N r (t; t + ): Although, we use the term nacks, loss of packets could be conveyed through other mechanisms such as duplicate acks or time-outs as in TCP. We further note that A r (t; t + ) x r (t) W r (t) d r :</p><p>Thus, we have</p><p>x r (t + ) ? x r (t) = W r (t + ) ? W r (t) A(t; t + ) A(t; t + ) d r = W r (t + ) ? W r (t) A(t; t + ) W r (t) d 2 r :</p><p>Also, note that (x r ? y r ) N r (t; t + )</p><p>Using these approximations, the congestion-control algorithms become</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">W r (t + ) ? W r (t) = 8 &lt; : r w r d 2 r r W r A r (t; t + ) ? r d r N r (t; t + ); r 2 R 1<label>(12)</label></formula><p>and W j (t + ) ? W j (t) = 8 &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt; &gt; : j j w j d 2 j j W j A j (t; t + )? j W j j d j ?1 j N j (t; t + ); j 2 R 2 :</p><p>(13) Remark 1: The discrete-time representation for the window flow control mechanism is simply used for convenience. It has to be interpreted as follows: r 2 R 1 : for each received ack, the window size is increased in proportion to 1=W r ; for each lost packet, the window size is decreased by a fixed amount; j 2 R 2 : the window size is increased again in proportion to 1=W j for each received ack; however, it is decreased in proportion to a function of the current window size W j j upon receiving each nack.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Relationship to TCP</head><p>We discuss the similarities between the above congestion control algorithms and most current versions of TCP. In fact, our results allow us to generalize many earlier observations regarding the performance of TCP-like congestion-control algorithms for the cases of a single link shared by multiple users with different round-trip delays and a single link utilized by a single user who suffers from random losses. To this end, we first note the striking similarity between current versions of TCP and the algorithm for users in the set R 2 when r = 1: The significant difference is that the increase term is dependent on d r :</p><p>Ignoring the rapid slow-start phase, most current versions of TCP employ the following algorithm: W j (t+ )?W j (t) = 1 W j A j (t; t+ )?0:5W j N j (t; t+ ): <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> Thus, a TCP source would correspond to a user in our framework whose parameters satisfy j = 1; j w j = j = 1=d 2 j and j = 0:5: A little care has to used in interpreting the discretization that resulted in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. The discretization was done assuming that we are considering very small intervals of units. However, nacks in TCP-type window flow control may not be frequent enough to assume that there would be several nacks in an interval of size : Thus, it is more reasonable to suppose that j is not exactly equal to 0:5: In fact, our simulations presented later suggest that when the window is reduced as in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">12</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">13</ref>), the value of that should be used in the corresponding continuoustime rate-control is considerably larger. Due to this reason, we will simply use ; instead of using 0:5 in approximating the dynamics of TCP-type congestion avoidance as a continuous-time rate control. Remark 2: A network of users using TCP-type congestion avoidance can be thought of as a team of users whose goal is to optimize the following objective:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">max fx j g 8 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; : X j ? 1 j d 2 j x j ? 0:5 (1 ? j ) j x j ! ? X l2L Z X l2j x j 0 (x ? C l ) + x dx 9 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; = &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; ;</formula><p>: <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, a different utility function has been suggested for TCP-type congestion avoidance. The starting point for their analysis is a stochastic model from which an ordinary differential equation is derived. Their results suggest that the utility function is of the form log x 1+x : For large x; log x 1 + x = log 1 1 + 1</p><p>x log(1 ? 1 x ) ? 1</p><p>x ;</p><p>thus recovering our result.</p><p>The impact of random losses on the performance of TCP and other transport protocols has been widely studied due to the emergence of mobile computing applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Typically, analytical results relating random losses and the delay-bandwidth product are available only for the case of a single link accessed by a single user. Remark 2 generalizes this to the case of multiple users in a network. To see this, let us specialize the result to the case of a single link and a single user. In this case, the objective of the single user is max fx j g ? 1 d 2 j x j ? (1 ? j ) j x j ? Z x j 0 (x ? C l ) +</p><p>x dx: (16)   For large values of d 2 j ; it is easily seen that the optimal solution x is less than C l : Thus, we get x j ( j ; d j ) = 1 p d j p 1 ? j ; <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> a fact observed even in the original TCP congestion avoidance paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and rediscovered later by many others. While Remark 2 extends this to a network with multiple users, Proposition 4 presents the general result when a window flow control scheme ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">12</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) is used in a network of heterogeneous users.</p><p>It is also instructive to compare the solution of ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) with j = 0 to the solution ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) obtained with r 6 = 0: The solution with j = 0 is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">x j ( j = 0; d j ) = 1 2 C l + s C 2 l + 4 d 2 j ! C l ; (18)</formula><p>for large d 2 j : Comparing ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>, it is easy to see that x j ( j = 0; d j ) &gt; x j ( j ; d j ) implies that</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">1 ? j &gt; 1 d 2 j C 2 l :</formula><p>Thus, the performance of the window flow control scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> deteriorates when the random loss probability is much larger than the inverse of the square of the delay-bandwidth product, a fact observed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. Thus, Remark 2 is a generalization of this fact observed earlier for a single-link, single-user case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Round-trip delay</head><p>As in TCP, suppose one ignores round-trip delay in the congestion control mechanism ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">12</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">13</ref>), we obtain the following window adaptation scheme:</p><p>W r (t + ) ? W r (t) = ( r w r r W r A r (t; t + ) ? r N r (t; t + ); r 2 R 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19</ref>) and W j (t + ) ? W j (t) = 8 &lt; : j j w j j W j A j (t; t + ) ? j W j j N j (t; t + ); j 2 R 2 :</p><p>(</p><p>Letting ! 0, this can written as dW r dt = r w r x r r W r ? (x r ? y r ) ; r 2 R 1 (21)   and dW j dt = j j w j x j j W j ? (x j ? y j ) W j j ; j 2 R 2 :</p><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">)<label>22</label></formula><p>Using the relation x r = W r =d r ; we can rewrite this in terms of rates as</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>_</head><p>x r = r d r w r r d r ? (x r ? y r ) ; r 2 R 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> and _</p><p>x j = j d j ?1 j j w j j d j +1 j ? (x j ? y j ) x j j ! ; j 2 R 2 :</p><p>(24) Remark 3: The window flow control scheme ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">20</ref>) obtained by ignoring round-trip times can be thought as a team of users attempting to converge to the unique solution of the following problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">max fx r g 8 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; : X r2R 1 w r r r d r U r (x r ) + X j2R 2 w j j j d j +1 j ! U j (x j ) ? (1 ? r ) r x r ? X l2L Z X l2j x j 0 (x ? C l ) + x dx: 9 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; = &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; ;<label>(25)</label></formula><p>V. ECN MARKS Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) has been recently proposed to provide early indication to sources about imminent congestion <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Current versions of TCP and the window flow control algorithms that we have discussed so far rely on loss as the congestion indicator. Clearly, this is not desirable if one wishes to operate the network at very low levels of loss. On the other hand, loss is a good indicator of congestion and one needs other signals from the network if we have to make congestion control decisions with very little or no loss. ECN marking is a mechanism to provide such information about the network to the users. We use the term ECN not to necessarily signify the implementations discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> or related works, but rather a simple marking scheme to serve as an early indicator of congestion before loss actually occurs at a node.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. No Random Losses</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, marking mechanisms have been suggested for stochastic models of a single node accessed by many sources.</p><p>To recast our fluid model to incorporate ECN marking, we simply have to interpret "lost" packets as "marked" packets. Since we have a bufferless model, we assume that, at each link l; a fraction of the packets are marked when the arrival rate exceeds some Cl ; where Cl C l : The fraction of packets marked is given (x ? Cl )=x where x is arrival rate on link l: First, we consider the case with no random losses, and instead of interpreting y r as the rate at which packets are received at the receiver r, we will now interpret y r as the rate at which "unmarked" packets are received at the receiver. Thus, Proposition 1-3 can now be interpreted in these terms, with C l replaced by Cl . Similarly, in the window flow control implementation, the window size should be reduced upon receipt of either a nack or a mark. In this framework, it is possible to offer a loss-free service if the marking level Cl is chosen appropriately for each link. In what follows, we characterize the level Cl at which marking should take place so that the total arrival rate on each link is less than the link capacity.</p><p>It is instructive to consider the case of a single link l of capacity C l accessed by N l sources, where the utility function of each user is U r (x r ) = log x r and w r = r = 1: The necessary and sufficient condition for the solution of ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) is given by ) Nx r = Cl + N : Thus, if Cl + N l C l ; then the solution to the optimization problem (2) results in zero loss. Interestingly, even in a network with multiple nodes, such a decentralized "marking" scheme, where the marking level on each link is obtained by considering it in isolation as above, results in zero loss. This is stated in the following proposition.</p><p>Proposition 5: For each l; suppose that the marking level Cl is chosen to satisfy the following inequality: C l ; <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> where R l = fr 2 Rjl 2 rg: (Recall that R 1 is the set of users who utility function is log x r ; and R 2 is the set of users whose utility functions are of the form ?1=x r r :) Then, the Nash equilibrium of the congestion control game satisfies X r:l2r</p><p>x r C l ; 8l:</p><p>Proof: We will prove the proposition by contradiction. Suppose there exists an l such that, at the Nash equilibrium point,</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">X s2R l x s &gt; C l : (27)</formula><p>Consider a route r 2 R 1 such that l 2 r: (If such an r doesn't exist, it is trivial to modify the proof.) From the necessary and sufficient condition for the Nash equilibrium of the congestion control game, we have </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C l :</head><p>We have removed the superscript '+' from the second equation above since we have assumed in (27) that P s2R l x s &gt; C l : The last inequality follows from the fact that x? Cl x is an increasing function of x and we have assumed that on link l; P s2R l x s &gt; C l : Thus, </p><p>From ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">29</ref>), the total flow on link l satisfies P s2R l \R 1 x s + P s2R l \R 2 x s 8 &gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt; :</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">P r2R l \R 1 w r r C l C l ? Cl + P r2R l \R 2 w r r r C l C l ? Cl 1=( r +1) 9 &gt; &gt; = &gt; &gt; ;</formula><p>From <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>, we have assumed that the marking level has been chosen such that this total flow on link l is less than or equal to C l : This contradicts (27).</p><p>A consequence of Proposition 5 is that the loss-based rate and window flow control algorithms described earlier can be used, along with appropriate marking, to provide loss free service by simply substituting marks for negative acknowledgments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. ECN Marks and Random Losses</head><p>In addition to nearly eliminating congestion-related losses, ECN marks can also be used to distinguish between congestionrelated losses and random losses. Thus, it could help eliminate the deleterious effect of random losses on end-to-end rate and congestion-control schemes. If there are no losses due to congestion, or at least if the congestion-related losses are a small fraction of random losses, then with negligible error all losses can be attributed to random losses. In other words, use only marks to reduce the rate of transmission and assume that all lost packets are due to non-congestion-related phenomena . This would be reasonable if the marking level is chosen to nearly eliminate congestion-related losses. Of course, some marked packets could also be lost to random losses. Thus, interpreting y r as the rate at which marked packets are received by User r; the congestion control scheme can be written as _ x r = r w r r ? r (x r ? y r ) ; r 2 R 1</p><p>x j = j j w j j ? j x j j (x j ? y j ) ; j 2 R 2 : (31)   This leads to the following proposition. x dx;</p><p>(32) subject to x r 0 8r: When f r g are small, we see from (32) that the effect of random losses are negligible despite the fact we may be losing some congestion indication signals by ignoring lost marks. In contrast, from Proposition 4, when losses are the indicators of congestion, even small values of f r g have a significant impact on the performance of the congestion controllers when is large. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Adaptive Algorithm for Setting the Marking Level</head><p>According to Proposition 5, computing C at each node requires the node to know the number of flows passing through it and the utility function of each user, or alternately the congestion control scheme used by each user. This is not practically feasible. From Proposition 5, it is clear that one can maintain the same C independent of the number of users, provided is scaled appropriately with N l : As we argue in the next section that may be interpreted as price-per-mark, this essentially amounts to "time-of-day" pricing. During peak hours, a larger price is charged than during off-peak hours. This requires a rough estimate of the number of users and their utility characteristics as a function of the time-of-day. Any uncertainty in this can be handled using an adaptive algorithm to estimate the appropriate marking level.</p><p>We propose the following adaptive algorithm for setting the marking level at link l :</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">d C dt = 8 &lt; :</formula><p>( C l ? x); 0 &lt; Cl &lt; C l max(0; ( C l ? x)); Cl = 0 min(0; ( C l ? x)); Cl = C l where x is the total flow through link l and is a step-size parameter which can be adjusted to regulate how fast Cl is changed. The basic idea behind the above algorithm is to attempt to regulate the total flow to C l : thus, Cl is increased when x is less than C l and it is decreased when x is larger than C l : We note that the above algorithm can be used with or without time-of-day pricing or even without interpreting as a price parameter, but simply treating it as a congestion-control parameter. Simulations indicate that a discretized version of this update equation converges for sufficiently small values of under very general conditions. The only assumption required is that a positive Cl given by Proposition 5 exists. Clearly, for a fixed ;</p><p>if the number of users is very large, then there may not exist a marking level that ensures loss-free operation. Thus, increasing the available capacity through provisioning or increasing are the only options to ensure loss-free service.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. PRICING AND TCP-FRIENDLINESS</head><p>Suppose is the price per mark charged by the network. Then the cost incurred by User i at node/link l is f l x i ; where f l is the fraction of packets marked by node l: Therefore, the total cost incurred by User i (by the link independence assumption) is P l:l2i f l x i : However, the utility of rate x i to User i is w i i U i (x i ): Therefore, since User i cannot estimate the impact of its own flow on the marking rate, it solves the following optimization problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">max g i (x i ) = w i i U i (x i ) ? X l:l2i f l x i :</formula><p>Differentiating g i (x i ) with respect to x i ; we get,</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">dg i dx i = w i i U 0 i (x i ) ? X l:l2i f l = w i i U 0 i (x i ) ?</formula><p>X l:l2i ( P s:l2s x s ? Cl ) + P s:l2s x s :</p><p>Thus, the first-order necessary condition is the same as that of the original game that we considered. A gradient ascent procedure to find the maximum in the above optimization problem again leads to the same additive increase-multiplicative algorithm as before.</p><p>Our results also provide an justification of the definition of TCP-friendliness in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> in the context of the nonlinear program formulation of the congestion control problem. A flow is TCPfriendly if its arrival rate does not exceed the arrival of a conformant TCP connection in the same circumstances <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. In particular, if the arrival rate of a flow exceeds K d p 1? ; where K is some constant and 1 ? is the packet drop probability, then the flow is NOT TCP-friendly.</p><p>From <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, we see that the steady-state throughput of a TCP flow is equal to 1 p d p 1? ; where d is the round-trip delay of the flow and 1 ? is the packet loss probability experienced by the flow. From (25) using the same type of argument used in obtaining <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> for TCP-type congestion avoidance schemes, it is easy to see that any congestion controller j whose throughput is proportional to 1 d j (1? j ) 1=( j +1) can be thought as a User j with the following utility function:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">U j (x j ) = ( 1 x j j ;</formula><p>j &gt; 0 log x j ; j = 0: Thus, we can associate utilities with any congestion control algorithm and solve the optimization problem given in (2) to find whether the flow is TCP-friendly or not. Now, consider a link of capacity C = 300 units that is shared by 100 flows, 50 of which are TCP users and the rest employ an additive increase-multiplicative decrease congestion controller whose throughput is proportional to x j 300; and x i 0 8i: Solving this problem yields x i = 4:0; i 50 and x j = 2:0; j &gt; 50: Thus, we see that the users with throughput proportional to 1 d j (1? j ) get a larger share of the bandwidth compared to TCP flows. On the other hand if these non-TCP-friendly users were replaced by users whose throughput is proportional to 1 d j (1? j ) 1=3 ; then the corresponding op- timization problem would be one where log x i is replaced by ? 1</p><p>x 2 i : In this case, the solution yields x i = 2:76; i 50 and x j = 3:24; j &gt; 50: Thus, users whose throughput is proportional to 1 d j (1? j ) 1=3 are not TCP-competitive, i.e., their share of the bandwidth is smaller than that obtained by TCP. In either case, the users using a larger share of the bandwidth will receive more marks. If the price charged is proportional to the marks received by a user, then users using a larger fraction of the resources will pay more than the rest of the users.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. SIMULATIONS AND NUMERICAL RESULTS</head><p>In this section, we perform three different experiments. In the first experiment, we use the software package ns to simulate various window flow control schemes. This is a detailed simulation taking into account finite packet sizes, round-trip delay and window-flow control, and is designed to study the accuracy of the fluid model predictions for different utility functions with packet-level implementations of the congestion controller. In the second experiment, we consider ECN marks and random losses in the model. Finally, we study the adaptive algorithm for setting the marking level such that the resulting steady-state throughput is less than the node's capacity, thus ensuring lossfree operation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experiment 1: Packet Model Simulations with different congestion controllers</head><p>We use a packet model with round-trip delays to simulate the window flow control. The simulations were done using ns-2. Due to space limitations, we present only one among a set of simulations that we have conducted to validate our results.</p><p>Consider the network shown in the The idea is to make the links between n0 and n1 and between n1 and n2 as the bottleneck links. All other links are access links and hence have a much higher bandwidth and much lower delay than the bottleneck links.</p><p>User 0 traverses the links connecting nodes n4 and n8 and passes through both the bottleneck nodes. User 1 is between nodes n3 and n6 and User 2 is between nodes n5 and n7: Therefore, Users 1 and 2 passes through only one bottleneck node.</p><p>The queue size at each node is limited to 100 packets. The packet sizes are taken to be 32 bytes long while the acks are 16 bytes long, though the packet sizes and acks can be taken to be arbitrary as long as we scale the bandwidth appropriately. All the flows are assumed to experience no random losses. We also let w 1 = w 2 = w 3 = 1 and = 0:5: We use the utility function ?1 p x for User 0, log x for User 1 and ?1</p><p>x for User 2:</p><p>It is known that using a simple FIFO queue with drop-tail mechanism results in users with longer round-trip times being starved of bandwidth. Therefore, random scheduling mechanisms like RED <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> have been developed to combat this problem. In our simulations too, we face the same problem in that the users with shorter round-trip delays fill up the entire buffer and packets of the users with long round-trip delays never enter the buffer. This is more pronounced when using utility functions like ?1 p x or log x as the decrease in the window sizes for these users when congestion is detected is not as aggressive as it is for users with the utility function ?1</p><p>x : Since, in our simulations we are trying to approximate the fluid model in which losses are proportionally distributed among all users, any mechanism which randomizes the drop (like RED) at the queue will work. However, for our simulation purposes drop-front FIFO queuing works well and in all our simulations we assume that all queues employ a drop-front scheduling mechanism.</p><p>We now implement the window flow control scheme given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">12</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) with increments and decrements measured in units of packets. From our network model, User 0 has a roundtrip delay of approximately 0:04 seconds, while Users 1 and 2 have a round-trip delay of 0:02 seconds, ignoring the buffering at each node. For round-trip delays in the window flow control scheme, we use the values 2 for User 0 and 1 for Users 1 and 2: Thus, we are normalizing time such that 1 unit is 0:02 secs.</p><p>The throughputs of the users should thus be measured in packets per 0:02 seconds. Also, since the rates are measured in packets per (0:02) seconds, the bandwidth of the link between nodes n0 and n1 becomes 156:25 packets per (0:02) seconds and the bandwidth of the link between nodes n1 and n2 becomes 78:125 packets per (0:02) seconds.</p><p>The steady state rates of this system should be equal to the optimum rates that solve the optimization problem given in Proposition 2. The rates obtained by solving the non-linear program are x 0 = 16:56; x 1 = 139:69; x 3 = 61:57; whereas the average rates obtained in the simulation are x 0 = 16:81; x 1 = 140:83; x 2 = 60:34:</p><p>It can be seen that the rates obtained by solving the optimization problem and the rates obtained in the simulation match each other closely. The window sizes of the three flows are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>. While the window size fluctuates, the average behavior of the windows is close to the predicted values after a very short initial transient period.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experiment 2: ECN Marks and Random Losses</head><p>In this experiment, we will use a packet-level implementation to simulate the effects of random loss on the performance of the users using the ?1</p><p>x utility function. We will then provide results which show that with ECN marking and the users reacting only to marks, the performance improves dramatically as compared to the case of using losses for congestion control.</p><p>Consider a single node with three users having the same utility function, ?1</p><p>x : The bandwidth at the node is 1 Mbps and the queue size at the node is assumed to be 40 packets. The round trip delay of each user is assumed to be 40 msec. This would roughly correspond to the source and destination being 4; 000 km apart. We assume a random loss probability of 0:05 for each of the users.</p><p>In the first scenario, packet losses are indicators of congestion and the users react to packet loss. In the second scenario, the users use ECN marks as indicators of congestion in the network and attribute all packet losses to random losses. Therefore, the system decreases its window on receiving marks, but does not do so with packet losses. The marking level C is chosen to be 0:99C: A marking level of C corresponds to using a virtual queue whose capacity is C and marking packets in the real queue when the virtual queue exceeds its buffer capacity <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the throughput of each user for a duration of 200 seconds for each of the above two scenarios.</p><p>From Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>, we can see that the throughput of an user using ECN marks is much better (about 5 times) than a user without ECN marks. This improvement in performance is due to the user attributing all losses to random losses in the network. Since, the marking level makes sure that there are very few congestion related losses, most of the packet losses seen by the user are indeed due to random losses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experiment 3: Adaptive estimation of marking level with 300 sources</head><p>In the previous experiment, we saw that with a suitable Cl ; we can have improved performance even when there are random losses in the system. However, the expression for Cl depends upon N l ; the number of users using link l; which is not available to the node. In Section V-C, we gave an update equation for With ECN No ECN Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. Throughput for all users with and without ECN marking determining the value of Cl at the node. In this section, we will provide some simulation results which indicate that it is possible to estimate Cl ; without the knowledge of the number of flows through the node. We perform a packet-level simulation using ns for this purpose. From the update equation, we see that C is updated as a function of the difference between C and the total arrival rate : In a packet-level simulation, we calculate the total arrival rate at the node every K packets that come into the node.</p><p>Note that unlike the discretized version of the update equation, this does not depend on any measurement interval. Therefore, C is updated every K packets received at the node.</p><p>We consider the network as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">1</ref>, but with 300 users, in three different classes. Class 1 consists of users that traverse both Links 1 and 2, while Class 2 users use only Link From Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">4</ref> and<ref type="figure">5</ref>, we can see that C1 and C2 converge to their steady state values quickly. More importantly, we also observed in the simulation that none of the users experience any packet drops after a short initial transient period. This can further be controlled by varying the utilization factor : Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref> shows the window size of a typical user from a user class with time. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VIII. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have presented a fluid model of a network of noncooperative users using a pricing scheme based only on endto-end measurements which leads to end-to-end loss-based flow control schemes. TCP-type congestion avoidance is a special case which arises when the users have a utility function ?1=x r :</p><p>We showed the impact of random losses on window flow control schemes derived from various utility functions. We also showed that ECN marking schemes can be designed for each node independently while achieving loss-free operation for the entire network. While our theoretical results assume a fluid model with zero buffers, the simulation results show a good agreement between our models and packet-level implementations of the congestion controllers in networks with non-zero buffers at the nodes and non-negligible propagation delays on the links.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Proposition 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>As ! 1; the Nash equilibrium of Proposition 1 converges to the unique optimal solution of</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>for each r: By symmetry it is clear x r = x s for any r; s:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Proposition 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Consider the congestion-control scheme given in (30)-(31) and suppose that, for each link l; Cl has been chosen such that there are no losses. Then the users' rates fx r g converge to the unique solution of</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Remark 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>A window flow control implementation of (30)-(31) obtained by ignoring the round-trip delays can be interpreted as a discrete-time version of the rate control algorithm that converges to the solution of max fx</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>1 d</head><label>1</label><figDesc>j (1? j ) : The throughput seen by each user can be obtained by solving the following optimization problem:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 1 .Fig. 1 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Network used for packet simulations in ns-2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>2 Fig. 2 .</head><label>22</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Window size evolution for all users</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>packets/sec) for User 3Round Trip Delay (in msec)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>1 and 1 x</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Class 3 users use only Link 2. Each class has 100 users. Within each class, 50 users have a log x utility function, and the remaining 50 users have a ? utility function. Link 1 has a capacity of 2 Mbps and a delay of 10 msec. Link 2 similarly has a capacity of 1 Mbps and a delay of 10 msec. Thus, users in Class 1 have a round-trip delay of 40 msec, while users in Class 2 and Class 3 have a round-trip delay of 20 msec ignoring the queueing delays and we let K = 1000 and = 1:0: Figures 4and 5 show the evolution of C1 and C2 with time.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 4 .Fig. 5 .</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Adaptive marking level C1 (in packets-per-second) for Link 1 in Experiment 3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Window sizes as a function of time for a typical user from each user class in Experiment 3</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>We use the term random losses to indicate non-congestion-related losses such as errors on wireless links. However, in our fluid models used throughout the paper, we do not explicitly model the stochastic behavior of the loss process. We simply reduce the number of packets by a certain fraction to account for non-congestion-related losses.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving TCP/IP performance over wireless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seshan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Amir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bertsekas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gallager Data</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Networks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Best-effort versus reservations: a simple comparative analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Breslau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Computer Communications Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-09">September 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TCP and Explicit Congestion Notification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Floyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Computer Communication Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-10">October 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Promoting the use of end-to-end congestion control in the Internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Floyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="458" to="472" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-08">August 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Connections with multiple congested gateways in packet-switched networks, Part 1: One-way traffic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Floyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Jacobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Computer Communications Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-08">August 1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Random early detection gateways for congestion avoidance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Floyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Jacobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-08">August 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed connection acceptance control for a connectionless network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gibbens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 16th Intl</title>
		<meeting>of the 16th Intl<address><addrLine>Edinburgh, Scotland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Teletraffic Congress</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999-06">June 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Resource pricing and the evolution of congestion control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gibbens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999-12">December 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>To appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A class of end-to-end congestion control algorithms for the Internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Golestani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Conference on Network Protocols</title>
		<meeting>the International Conference on Network Protocols</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-10">October 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on the fairness of additive increase and multiplicative decrease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hurley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Le</forename><surname>Boudec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thiran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 16th Intl</title>
		<meeting>of the 16th Intl<address><addrLine>Edinburgh, Scotland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Teletraffic Congress</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999-06">June 1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="478" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Congestion avoidance and control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Jacobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Sigcomm</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Charging and rate control for elastic traffic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Transactions on Telecommunications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rate control in communication networks: shadow prices, proportional fairness and stability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Maulloo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Operational Research Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="252" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative performance analysis of versions of TCP in a local network with a lossy link</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fairness of congestion avoidance schemes in heterogeneous networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kunniyur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Srikant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 16th Intl</title>
		<meeting>of the 16th Intl<address><addrLine>Edinburgh, Scotland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Teletraffic Congress</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999-06">June 1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="508" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kunniyur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Srikant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.comm.csl.uiuc.edu/srikant/pub.html" />
		<title level="m">Longer version of the paper</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The performance of TCP/IP for networks with high bandwidth-delay products and random loss</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Lakshman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Madhow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimization Flow Control, I: Basic Algorithm and Convergence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lapsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-12">Dec. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A transport protocol for heterogeneous packet flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dwyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bharghavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>INFOCOM<address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-03">March 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Linear and Nonlinear Programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Luenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Second Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bandwidth sharing: Objectives and algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Massoulie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>INFOCOM<address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-03">March 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pricing congestible network resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mackie-Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Varian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE journal on selected areas in communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1141" to="1148" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-09">September 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The macroscopic behavior of the TCP congestion avoidance algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Semke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mahdavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Communication Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fair end-to-end window-based congestion control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Walrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Total acknowledgments: A feedback mechanism for end-to-end congestion control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Waldby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Madhow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Lakshman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Sigmetrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
