<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Aerospace Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Indian Institute of Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>560 012</postCode>
									<settlement>Bangalore</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7681E73A4DF80CB8A58312C1CF39C4B9</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T17:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Obstacle Avoidance in a Dynamic Environment: A Collision Cone Approach Animesh Chakravarthy and Debasish Ghose</head><p>Abstract-A novel collision cone approach is proposed as an aid to collision detection and avoidance between irregularly shaped moving objects with unknown trajectories. It is shown that the collision cone can be effectively used to determine whether collision between a robot and an obstacle (both moving in a dynamic environment) is imminent. No restrictions are placed on the shapes of either the robot or the obstacle, i.e., they can both be of any arbitrary shape. The collision cone concept is developed in a phased manner starting from existing analytical results-available in aerospace literature-that enable prediction of collision between two moving point objects. These results are extended to predict collision between a point and a circular object, between a point and an irregularly shaped object, between two circular objects, and finally between two irregularly shaped objects. Using the collision cone approach, several strategies that the robot can follow in order to avoid collision, are presented. A discussion on how the shapes of the robot and obstacles can be approximated in order to reduce computational burden is also presented. A number of examples are given to illustrate both collision prediction and avoidance strategies of the robot. Index Terms-Collision cone, dynamic environments, obstacle avoidance, path planning.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>O BSTACLE avoidance is a fundamental requirement in motion planning of a mobile robot. Several papers addressing this issue have appeared in robotics literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. Motion planning can be categorized <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> as static (when the obstacles are stationary in the environment) or dynamic (when the obstacles are capable of movement and may even change shape and size). The environment could be completely known (when the trajectory of the obstacles is known a priori) or partially known (when obstacle trajectory is unknown or information about it is incomplete). This classification is not universal and an alternative classification is available in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. To date, a major research effort in this area has been applied to analyze and solve the problem of motion planning in a completely known environment with largely static and, to some extent, moving obstacles <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. Their primary goal was to determine a collision-free path from a starting point to a goal point while optimizing some performance criterion. Configuration space approach, Voronoi diagrams, retraction methods, potential functions, visibility graphs, accessibility graphs, tangent graphs, etc. ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>) are some of the techniques which have been reasonably successful in achieving this goal. While these approaches are justifiable for a completely known environment, a partially known dynamic environment-which is a more realistic framework in situations where obstacle motion cannot be predicted-requires a different approach. In fact, dynamic motion planning is more difficult than static motion planning even when complete information about the environment is available. This is shown by several available complexity results for motion planning <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p><p>Recent advances in robotics technology has made possible the development of autonomous and semiautonomous robotic systems for land, air, and underwater operations. These robots use sophisticated onboard sensors to perceive their environment and use this information to plan and execute tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Their primary use is in uncertain environments characterized by the presence of moving obstacles with unpredictable trajectories. Motion planning of robots in uncertain and unpredictable environments has attracted the attention of robotics researchers only recently <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</p><p>In this paper, we present a novel approach called the collision cone approach which is ideally suited for automated guided vehicles or autonomous mobile robots. The method is new in the sense that it uses concepts which have their roots in aerospace literature rather than in robotics. The only relevant paper in the robotics literature that uses a similar concept is that by Tychonievich et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>.</p><p>The specific problem considered in this paper is that of a mobile robot avoiding one or more moving obstacles with unknown trajectories, based on sensor information collected by the robot. The robot and the obstacles are both assumed to move only by translation in a two-dimensional (2-D) space. Unlike previous literature, no assumptions are made on the shape of the robot or obstacles (i.e., they need not be polygons-convex, or otherwise). They can be of any arbitrary shape but with the constraint that each is a single rigid body without relative motion between points on the body. Thus, this approach is more suitable for the problem of obstacle avoidance of an automated guided vehicle or a mobile robot in a workspace consisting of moving obstacles, rather than for motion planning of robotic manipulators.</p><p>This paper is motivated by the conviction that collision avoidance and collision achievement are, in principle, two aspects of the same problem. In the robotics literature, the problem of collision avoidance has attracted a considerable amount of attention. On the other hand, collision achievement (or interception) has been of primary concern mainly in the aerospace guidance literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. For example, some of the problems addressed in the guidance literature involve the guidance of a missile to intercept an aircraft, guidance of a torpedo to intercept a ship, etc. The problem of achieving collision or interception is a long-standing area of research in the aerospace literature and has evolved into a reasonably complete theory, especially in the missile guidance literature, over the past five decades. Though the problem of collision avoidance in the robotics literature is of a more recent vintage, it has also witnessed intense research activity in recent years. However, to date there has been almost no cross-fertilization of ideas between the two areas. The main reason for this is the apparent dichotomy between them in terms of their objectives, operating environments, vehicle dynamics, sensor systems, performance capabilities, etc. With the present day technological advances (especially in sensor systems) and the stringent performance requirements on intelligent robotic vehicles <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, it is felt that many of the advances in the area of aerospace guidance theory has considerable relevance in robotics too.</p><p>Our purpose is to show that the fundamental concepts used for achieving intercept between bodies in motion can also be used to formulate strategies for collision avoidance. In doing so we extend these fundamental concepts to situations relevant to the collision avoidance problem in robotics, and derive several results that are new not only in robotics but also in aerospace guidance.</p><p>The literature on interception problems has mainly focussed upon conditions of collision between two moving point objects based on their instantaneous velocities. In the context of collision avoidance between robots it is not sufficient to consider an object as a point mass. Its physical shape and size, and its position and orientation in space, are of prime importance. We first extend the existing theory for predicting collision between point objects to obtain more general conditions to predict collision between objects of arbitrary shapes and sizes. Based on these results the collision cone is presented as a fundamental concept used for the purpose of collision avoidance. We restrict our study to the 2-D planar case in this paper.</p><p>This paper is organized as follows. In Section II, we review some results well-known in the aerospace guidance literature and illustrate some basic concepts through simple examples which also show how the collision cone can be obtained for a simple initial geometry between a point robot and a Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. A typical (V ; V r ) trajectory. circular object. In Section III, we formalize the concept of the collision cone and present analytical results to obtain the exact collision cone between a point and a circular object, between a point and an irregularly shaped object, between two circular objects, and finally, between two irregularly shaped objects. In Section IV, we discuss some simple strategies for collision avoidance based on the collision cone concept. In Section V, we examine the possibility of simplifying the computation of the collision cone by approximating irregularly shaped objects as a collection of circular objects. We conclude the paper in Section VI with a general discussion on the applicability of the collision cone approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. COLLISION BETWEEN POINT OBJECTS</head><p>The engagement geometry for an interception problem is given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. Here, and are two point objects, moving at constant velocities and respectively. The behavior of the line-of-sight (LOS) is characterized by the following kinematic equations:</p><p>(1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> where and are the relative velocity components (with respect to along, and perpendicular to, the LOS, respectively. Since we consider only the instantaneous velocities of the point objects, and are assumed to be constants. Differentiating (1) and (2), we get (3) (4) Dividing ( <ref type="formula">3</ref>) by ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) and cross-multiplying, we get <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> which, on integration, yields the following relation: <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> where and are the relative velocity components at some initial time Equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> shows that the trajectory on the plane is a circle with center at the origin and radius equal to the initial relative velocity between and This also implies that the relative velocity is a constant with respect to time. Also, from (3), (4), and (6), it is evident that the trajectories in the plane have a time history shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Next, we state the following well-known results ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>).</p><p>Lemma 1: The set of points satisfying the condition (for example, point in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>) are stationary points on the plane.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proof:</head><p>implies that Substituting this in (3) and (4) yields and Lemma 2: If two point objects are moving with constant velocities (i.e., constant speed and direction), then and together form a necessary and sufficient condition for collision.</p><p>Proof: From Lemma 1, and implies that and for all future time. But implies that the LOS does not rotate in space and implies that distance between the two objects reduces until collision occurs, thus proving sufficiency.</p><p>To prove necessity, let the two objects collide at time In the time preceding the distance between the objects was obviously decreasing, thus implying that If the positions of the objects are projected back to any time the resulting figure formed is a triangle with the LOS at as one side and the collision point as the opposite vertex so that successive lines of sight at times are parallel to each other. Thus,</p><p>From Lemma 1, we can see that implies that thus proving necessity.</p><p>Example 1: Consider an initial geometry between a point object and a circle with and Let be a point on the circle at an angle with reference to Then, by using ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>), and the conditions indicated in Lemma 2, it can be shown that is on a collision course with point if See Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(a</ref>). If we now consider all the points on the circle then, by using ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) and (2) (and Lemma 2) for each such point, we get a corresponding value of that causes to collide with that point. The collection of all the values of defines a cone such that if lies in this cone then will eventually collide with</p><p>We refer to this cone as the collision cone. In this example, it is found that the collision cone is defined by See Fig. Again, if we consider collision between and each point on and consider the collection of all such values of we find that the collision cone is now split into two cones, and is defined by See Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(c</ref>). We call this a split collision cone.</p><p>Lemma 3: If two point objects and are moving with constant velocities and (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>), and the initial position of only is fixed; then, as long as there exists a for which is on a collision course with Proof: Let Then, the collision condition (indicated in Lemma 2) is defined by Substituting for and from ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>), we get <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> Therefore,</p><p>Thus, from ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>), as long as there exists a that satisfies the conditions for collision. When we get which is not a collision condition. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. THE COLLISION CONE</head><p>In the previous section, we illustrated the concept of a collision cone with the help of two examples. The collision cone can be used to predict the possibility of collision between two objects and to design collision avoidance strategies. In this section, we shall derive the necessary and sufficient conditions that enable the determination of the collision cone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Collision Between a Point and a Circular Object</head><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>, is a point object, while is a circle of radius and with center at The velocities of and are denoted by and respectively. For any point (parametrized by the angle on the circle we can write the relative velocity components of as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(10) (<label>11</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">)</formula><p>Lemma 4: The point object is headed for a collision with the circle if and only if there exists a ray passing through for which is called the collision point).</p><p>Proof: Follows from Lemma 2. Now, let us define the relative velocity components of (the upper tangent to the circle from point as and and those of (the lower tangent to the circle from point as and These expressions are obtained from ( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">11</ref>) by substituting and respectively. Lemma 5: At any given time, if then there exists exactly one ray where is a point on the circle that satisfies Proof: Consider an arbitrary point on the circle defined by the angle From <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, it is obvious that is a continuous function of Thus, implies that there exists at least one for which It remains to be shown that this point is unique. Putting in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(12)</formula><p>Since is a periodic function with period successive that satisfy occur at intervals of The angle is always bounded in the sense that where For we have and obviously this interval is insufficient to allow for more than one value of for which We now convert the condition into an equivalent condition with reference to for which and are obtained from ( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">11</ref>) by putting Now, consider the inequality <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> Substituting the expressions for and by putting and respectively in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, we get (</p><p>Substituting and simplifying, we get,</p><p>We omit the subscript in the above equation for convenience, and henceforth denote and simply by and Thus, ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">15</ref>) can be written as ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>)</p><p>Lemma 6: If a point and a circle of radius are moving with constant velocities such that they satisfy (16) at any given instant in time, then they will continue to satisfy <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> for all future time.</p><p>Proof: Define a function as <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> Differentiating <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> with respect to we get <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> Using ( <ref type="formula">5</ref> This implies that the collision point lies on the line (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>), i.e., is a straight line. So, is a stationary point on the plane (Lemma 1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case 2:</head><p>In this case, a trajectory originating from the third (fourth) quadrant moves into the second (first) quadrant, crossing the line. At the crossing point implying that is an extremum at that instant (say at time Since is negative for and positive for all is also a minimum at Let We have to determine the conditions for which since this implies collision. Multiplying both sides of (4) by we get <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> which, on integration, yields <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> where</p><p>If the initial conditions are such that they satisfy then, from Lemma 6, we know that even at But Therefore, These results automatically lead to the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 1: If a point and a circle are moving with constant velocities such that their initial conditions satisfy and <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> then they are headed for a collision. The above conditions are both necessary and sufficient for a collision to occur. Proof: Follows from the analysis given above. Putting <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> reduces to and which are the conditions for collision between two point objects (Lemma 2). Substituting and from ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) in ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>), we get <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> Equation ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>) can be interpreted as follows. Given and there exists a range of that satisfy <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> and for which Let us denote this range by Now, if has a velocity vector at an angle such that then collision is inevitable. We call this cone, with vertex at and angular limits defined by and as the collision cone. To determine the collision cone we first rewrite ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) as <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> Also, we define the following quantities: <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> The collision cone comprises of those values of that satisfy <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> and yield</p><p>We define a set as <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> and we rewrite ( <ref type="formula">24</ref>) as ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>)</p><p>We now define two more sets and as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">(29) (<label>30</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">)</formula><p>The collision cone is then obtained as a set defined as (31</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">)</formula><p>The set is obtained through the following cases. A representation of the collision cone in the space can be obtained by rearranging the terms in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> to yield the initial conditions that lead to collision as and (51) Equation ( <ref type="formula">51</ref>) represents a sector-shaped region in the plane, and is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Equation (31) gives the collision cone between a point and a circle</head><p>Let be an open circle containing all the points in the interior of Then the collision cone between and is the open cone obtained by removing the boundaries of the collision cone given by (31). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Collision Between a Point and an Irregularly Shaped Object</head><p>It is possible to adapt Theorem 1 [and (31)] to obtain equivalent conditions that can be used to predict collision between a point and an irregularly shaped object. Before doing so, we give a few useful definitions <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. A set in a linear vector space is said to be a cone with vertex at the origin if implies that for all Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref> shows three different types of cones and each with vertex angle</p><p>These cones differ from one another in the following manner:</p><p>is convex and has is nonconvex and has is nonconvex and has We shall use the notations and respectively, to define these three different types of cones.</p><p>Consider Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>(a) and (b), each of which shows the engagement geometry between a point object and an irregularly shaped object</p><p>We can construct a cone with vertex at such that is the smallest cone that contains the object i.e., is the intersection of all cones that contain and have vertices at</p><p>The vertex angle of is denoted by and its boundaries are and It can be seen that the cone in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>(a) is of the type and that in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>(b) is of type These cases are now considered separately.</p><p>Case 1: . We construct a circle contained in such that and are tangential to Let have radius and center at a distance from Note that any choice of and should satisfy This is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>(a). Assuming that moves with a velocity identical to that of we can state the following lemma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 7: If is on a collision course with if and only if is on a collision course with</head><p>Proof: From Lemma 4, for to be on a collision course with it is both necessary and sufficient that there exists a ray passing through that has It can be seen that the ray will always pass through thus implying that is on a collision course with This proves sufficiency.</p><p>The necessity is proved similarly. Let be on a collision course with This implies that there exists a point D on which is the point of collision [see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7(a)</ref>]. The ray obviously must pass through As mentioned earlier, from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>(a), we can see that (52)</p><p>For a given any circle with radius and with center at a distance from A satisfying (52) will satisfy Lemma 7. Case 2: . See Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>  <ref type="formula">54</ref>) is necessary and sufficient condition for collision between and Thus (54), with the inequality replaced by a strict inequality, is the necessary and sufficient condition for collision between and These conditions can thus be used as necessary and sufficient condition for collision between and (in the manner stated by Lemmas 7 and 8). Since these conditions are invariant with respect to the choice of the circles or (so long as (52) or ( <ref type="formula">53</ref>) is satisfied), we can discard or entirely, and take and to represent the initial relative velocity components of the angular bisector of for and of the angular bisector of the complement of for The case when is a limiting case for both and and the corresponding collision cone can be obtained by using either Case 1 or Case 2 above with appropriate modifications for the limiting value.</p><p>Theorem 2: The collision cone between a point and an irregularly shaped object, both moving at constant velocities on a plane, is obtained as follows. Let in (35) and (43) be replaced by Now 1) If then the collision cone is obtained from (31), with as the initial angle of the angular bisector of the cone 2) If then the collision cone is the complement of the cone obtained from (31) with as the initial angle formed by the angular bisector of the complement of the cone Proof: Follows from Lemmas 7 and 8, and the arguments given above.</p><p>Example 5: Let the values of and be the same as in Example 2, but let the now be replaced by some irregularly shaped object such that Then from (31) and Theorem 2, we see that is headed for a collision with if its velocity vector lies inside the angular bounds If then the collision cone is defined by If then the collision cone is defined by</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Collision Between Two Circular Objects</head><p>Theorem 2 can be extended to enable detection of collision between two circular objects. Consider the engagement geometry in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref>, where and are two circles of radii and moving with velocities and respectively. The lines and are the common tangents to the circles, intersecting at Note that these tangents form a cone of the type Theorem 3: The collision cone between two circles moving with constant velocities on a plane is given by (31) with in ( <ref type="formula">35</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">43</ref>) equal to and as the initial angle of the line joining the centers of the two circles. Proof: Superposing onto the problem reduces to one of collision prediction between a point and a circle of radius It is easy to see that the angle subtended by the enlarged circle at the reduced point [i.e., as defined in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7(a)</ref>] is equal to defined in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref>. The proof then follows from 1) in Theorem 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Collision Between Two Irregularly Shaped Objects</head><p>We now extend Theorem 3 to predict collision between two irregularly shaped objects and moving with constant velocities on a plane. Note that when and are both irregularly shaped, it is difficult to superpose the shape of onto that of We therefore adopt a different approach. Consider the irregularly shaped objects as given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref>. Several possibilities then arise.</p><p>Case 1: Refer Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref>(a). Here, the objects are well separated and we can construct a cone of the type with the smallest vertex angle such that and are each contained on opposite sides of the vertex. Let denote the vertex angle, and and be the boundaries that intersect at vertex We can then draw two circles, one contained in the cone and the other contained in the cone Let and be these circles, of radii and with centers at a distance of and respectively, from This is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref> . In this case, we can construct a cone of type such that 1) The boundaries of the cone touch both and 2) The whole of is enclosed in the closed cone and the whole of is enclosed in the closure of the complement of This is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9(b</ref>). Before we obtain the collision cone between and some construction is necessary [see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref> The sufficiency part is then proved as follows. We know from Lemma 3 that as long as there exists a ray (where is a point on such that If is not on a collision course with then can never pass through and will therefore pass through any point lying in the complement of Now, if (where is a point on denotes any general ray parallel to, and in the same direction as then It can be seen that will always pass through thus implying that is on a collision course with Theorem 4: The collision cone between two irregularly shaped objects and moving with constant velocities on a plane is obtained as follows: Let in ( <ref type="formula">35</ref>) and (43) be equal to Now 1) If then the collision cone is obtained from (31), with as the initial angle formed by the angular bisector of the cone .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) If</head><p>then the collision cone is the complement of the cone obtained from (31), with as the initial angle formed by the angular bisector of the complement of the cone .</p><p>3) If will collide with for any heading direction of except when . Proof: From Lemmas 9, 10, and Theorem 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. OBSTACLE AVOIDANCE</head><p>The collision cone concept described thus far provides a convenient means to determine whether any two moving objects are on a collision course. The collision cone concept also helps to reduce the engagement between two irregularly shaped objects into an equivalent engagement between a point and a circle. In practice, the method by which the robot determines an imminent collision would depend on its onboard sensors. For example, suppose the robot can measure the relative velocity components with respect to the moving obstacle, then it can directly use <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> to predict a collision. However, note that it is not easy to obtain the relative velocities by using simple Doppler radars (as is done in aerospace applications) when the physical size of the objects are significant compared to the distance between them. In the case of automated vehicles in a factory environment, relative velocities may be obtained by using an overhead sensor to track the vehicle movements and transmit information to the robot <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. Alternatively, if the robot is equipped with an inertial platform which provides it with its own velocity information, and radar sensors which provide it with the obstacles' instantaneous velocity information then the results given in Section III can be directly used to obtain the collision cone and thus predict an imminent collision.</p><p>If a robot is headed for a collision with some object in its environment (i.e., the robot's velocity vector lies inside the collision cone), it can adopt any of the following three strategies to avert collision.</p><p>1) The robot can maintain its heading direction constant; but change its speed so as to make its velocity vector lie outside the collision cone. This is equivalent to the robot speeding up, slowing down, or reversing to avoid colliding with the obstacle. 2) The robot can keep its speed constant; but change its heading direction until its velocity vector lies outside the collision cone. This is equivalent to the robot turning away from its original path.</p><p>3) The robot can change both its speed and its heading direction until its velocity vector lies outside the collision cone. For 1) the robot has to apply a longitudinal acceleration (i.e., an acceleration along its heading direction); for 2) it has to apply a lateral acceleration (i.e., an acceleration perpendicular to its heading direction); while for 3) both longitudinal and lateral acceleration are required. The precise strategy to adopt would depend on the longitudinal/lateral acceleration limits of the robot, its kinematic constraints, and the time within which the robot should pull its heading out of the collision cone.</p><p>From the preceding discussion, it is evident that the range of speeds of the robot that will make its current heading direction lie outside the collision cone is given by where is defined as (55) <ref type="bibr">(</ref> and also So, Case 2(2) above is used to determine or Therefore, the robot must either increase its speed beyond 3.815 or reverse its direction and increase its speed beyond 0.408, to avoid a collision with the obstacle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. APPROXIMATING IRREGULARLY SHAPED OBJECTS</head><p>Use of the conditions of Theorem 4 to detect collision between irregularly shaped objects requires measurement of the angle This in turn requires construction of the cone which could pose practical difficulties due to the arbitrary shapes of the objects under consideration. Therefore, when the measurement of is difficult, we propose another method. We can approximate the irregularly shaped objects and by a collection of circles each. Let be approximated by circles and be approximated by circles Then, by using Theorem 3 for collision between each of the circles of with each of the circles of we can obtain a total of collision cones. The union of all these cones then can be meaningfully used to predict collision between the irregularly shaped objects and This type of approximation is standard in robot collision avoidance literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>It is obvious that the success of this method depends on the choice of circles used to approximate and</p><p>The collision cone thus obtained is inexact, in contrast to the exact collision cone that can be obtained using Theorem 4. In the following analysis, we shall show that this inexact collision cone can still be used effectively for motion planning if the original objects are either both over-approximated or both under-approximated.</p><p>Examples of over-and under-approximation are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">10(a)</ref> and<ref type="figure">(b)</ref>. Suppose and are the moving objects. Let and be the over-approximations and and be the under-approximations of these objects, respectively. If represents the exact collision cone (obtained from Theorem 4), and and represent the collision cones obtained after over-and under-approximating, respectively, then (66)</p><p>In the event of using circles to approximate irregularly shaped objects, it is difficult to obtain conditions that are both necessary and sufficient to predict collision. Over-approximation of and yields a collision cone that contains the exact collision cone. As a result, keeping the heading direction of outside such a cone is a sufficient condition for to avoid Similarly, since under-approximation of and yields a collision cone that is contained in the exact collision cone, keeping the heading direction of outside such a cone becomes a necessary condition for to avoid We now present three methods each of over-and underapproximating an object by circles. For this we define (67) where Co denotes the convex hull of the set Note that (69) is automatically satisfied by the approximation adopted in Method 1, although an approximation using Method 2 may not satisfy (68). Thus Method 2 imposes a less stringent condition than Method 1.</p><p>Method 3: Choose the circles and such that any straight line intersecting both and must also intersect both and Note that this condition is automatically satisfied by the approximations adopted in Methods 1 and 2. Thus Method 3 imposes a condition that is less stringent than either Methods 1 or 2.</p><p>Thus, if we denote the exact collision cone by and the cones obtained by Methods 1, 2, and 3 as and respectively, then for every over-approximation according to Method 1, there exists an over-approximation according to Method 2 and an over-approximation according to Method 3, such that (70) Note that approximations according to Methods 1 and 2 can be used independent of the configuration of the objects in space. But an approximation according to Method 3 is valid only for a specific configuration of the objects.   Example 8: Consider an engagement between two irregularly shaped objects and shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11</ref>(a), with and Then, by using the conditions of Theorem 4, the exact collision cone is given by If we now over-approximate and by each of the three methods discussed in the above section, we get the following results.</p><p>Method 1: Refer to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11(a</ref>). We approximate by three circles and of radii 2.3, 2.2, and 2.3 units and by two circles and of radii 2.2 units each. The total number of pairs is thus six (see Table <ref type="table">I</ref>). Taking a union of all the six collision cones, the final collision cone is found to be Method 2: Refer to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11(b</ref>). We approximate by three circles of radii 1.8 each; and by two circles of radii 2 each. Again, six pairs are formed (see Table <ref type="table">II</ref>). Taking a union of all the six collision cones, the final collision cone is found to be Method 3: Refer to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11(c</ref>). In this case, we approximate by two circles of radii 2.1 each; and by a single circle of radius 1.7. The total number of pairs is thus two (see Table <ref type="table">III</ref>). Taking a union of the two collision cones, the final collision cone is found to be It is seen that ( <ref type="formula">70</ref>) is satisfied. By choosing a larger number of circles to approximate and an even closer approximation to the exact collision cone can be obtained.   <ref type="formula">71</ref>), but the converse is not true. Hence, Method 2 imposes a less stringent condition than Method 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Under-Approximation</head><p>Method 3: Choose the circles and such that any straight line intersecting both and must also intersect both and Note that this condition is automatically satisfied by the conditions used in Methods 1 and 2, although the converse is not true. Thus, method 3 imposes a less stringent condition than either of Methods 1 and 2.</p><p>As in the case of over-approximation, for every underapproximation according to Method 1, there exists an under-approximation according to Method 2 and an underapproximation according to Method 3, such that (73) Again, approximations according to Methods 1 and 2 can be used independent of the configuration of the objects in space, whereas an approximation according to Method 3 is valid only for a specific configuration of the objects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Most of the earlier literature on collision avoidance strategies were restricted to static environments. Although there has been considerable interest in recent times on the more realistic dynamic environment, even these impose restrictions on the shapes of the robot and the obstacle (i.e., they are assumed to have some regular shapes such as circles or convex polygons). In this paper, we have relaxed the assumptions on static environments, and on the regularity of the obstacles' and the robot's shapes, and proposed the collision cone as an aid to collision detection and avoidance. An important contribution of this paper is that well-known results from guidance theory in the aerospace literature have been suitably modified and extended to yield concepts directly useful in the context of robot collision avoidance problems. These results are generalized to enable collision prediction between two irregularly shaped moving objects. Using the collision cone concept, some simple strategies by which collision can be avoided, are discussed.</p><p>This paper gives a preliminary-but fairly in-depth-study of the novel collision cone approach as a viable collision detection and avoidance tool in a 2-D dynamic environment. To allow this approach to be used in a practical situation we need to examine how the collision cone concept, and the avoidance strategies arising out of it, can be extended to a realistic situation where the robot tries to circumvent several moving obstacles while attempting to reach a specified stationary or moving goal point.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Collision geometry between two point objects.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,59.94,59.58,217.44,116.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of correspond to collision occurring at different points in space and at different instants of time.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. (a) Collision geometry for Example 1, (b) collision cone for Example 1, and (c) collision cone for Example 2.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,322.56,414.24,218.16,118.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Collision geometry between a point and a circle.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,35.40,59.58,266.40,161.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig.6. Definition of cones E 1 ; E 2 ; E 3 :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Collision geometry between a point and an irregularly shaped object (a) &lt; and (b) &gt; :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Collision geometry between two circles.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Collision geometry between two irregularly shaped objects (a) &lt; and (b) &gt; :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Over-and under-approximations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Example 8 (a) Method 1, (b) Method 2, and (c) Method 3.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Debasish Ghose received the B.Sc.(Engg.) degree in electrical engineering from the Regional Engineering College, Rourkela, India, in 1982, and the M.E. and Ph.D. degrees, also in electrical engineering, from the Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, in 1984  and 1990, respectively. From 1984 to 1987, he was a Scientific Officer in the Joint Advanced Technology Programme, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, where he is presently an Associate Professor in the Department of Aerospace Engineering. His research interests are in the areas of guidance of aerospace vehicles, dynamic game theory, distributed computing, and robotics. He is a coauthor of the recent book Scheduling Divisible Loads in Parallel and Distributed Systems (Los Alamitos, CA: IEEE Computer Society Press).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimum speed motions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Aronov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fortune</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wilfong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="228" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-06">June 1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inertial navigation systems for mobile robots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Barshan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Durrant-Whyte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="342" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-06">June 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to the special section on perception-based real-world navigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhanu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Fagueras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sridhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Thorpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="725" to="727" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-12">Dec. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collision detection and avoidance: A collision cone approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chakravarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ghose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>AE/GI/05-96</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dept. Aerospace Eng., Indian Inst. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-06">June 1996</date>
			<pubPlace>Bangalore, India</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithmic and Geometric Aspects of Robotics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chazelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Robotics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yap</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hillsdale, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">I</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="185" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Approximation and decomposition of shapes</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fujimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Tokyo, Japan</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motion planning amid transient obstacles</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-10">Oct. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gross motion planning-A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ahuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Comput. Surv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-09">Sept. 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient collision prediction among many moving obstacles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-04">Apr. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward efficient trajectory planning: The pathvelocity decomposition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Avoidance of obstacles with unknown trajectories: Locally optimal paths and periodic sensor readings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>De Lamadrid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="496" to="507" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-12">Dec. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path tracking through uncharted moving obstacles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>De Lamadrid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst., Man, Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1408" to="1422" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-12">Nov./Dec. 1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Robot Motion Planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-C</forename><surname>Latombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-F</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Modern Navigation, Guidance, and Control Processing. Englewood Cliffs</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Locke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Guidance</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1955">1955</date>
			<publisher>Van Nostrand</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Princeton, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial planning: A configuration space approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lozano-Perez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="1983-02">Feb. 1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Linear and Nonlinear Programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Luenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Reading, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A quad-tree based path planning algorithm for a mobile robot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Noborio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Naniwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Robot. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="555" to="574" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-07">July 1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic optimal control of moving vehicles in a dynamic environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Papageorgiou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bauschert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="343" to="354" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-08">Aug. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidance laws for short-range tactical missiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pastrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Seltzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Warren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Guid. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="1981-04">Mar./Apr. 1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motion planning in the presence of moving obstacles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Reif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sharir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Assoc. Comput. Mach</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="764" to="790" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-07">July 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inertial navigation sensor integrated motion analysis for autonomous vehicle navigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhanu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Robot. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="817" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-11">Nov. 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of motion planning and related geometric algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sharir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Artif. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-12">Dec. 1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Robotics Vol I: Algorithmic and Geometric Aspects of Robotics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yap</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hillsdale, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated architecture for robot motion planning and control in the presence of obstacles with unknown trajectories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Spence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hutchinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst., Man, Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-01">Jan. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An algorithm with real-time response for avoiding moving obstacles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P H</forename><surname>Steele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Conf. Systems, Man, Cybernetics</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conf. Systems, Man, Cybernetics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="556" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A maneuvering-board approach to path planning with moving obstacles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tychonievich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 11th Int. Joint Conf. Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>11th Int. Joint Conf. Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1017" to="1021" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collision avoidance by a modified leastmean-square-error classification scheme for indoor autonomous land vehicle navigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L.-L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-H</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Robot. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="698" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-09">Sept. 1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mobile robot map making using sonar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zelinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Robot. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="577" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-09">Sept. 1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Animesh Chakravarthy received the Bachelor&apos;s degree in mechanical engineering in 1990 from Bangalore University, Bangalore, India, and the Master&apos;s degree in aerospace engineering in 1994 from the Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zarchan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">He is presently a Scientist in the Flight Mechanics and Simulation Division, Aeronautical Development Agency, Bangalore. Apart from guidance and control theory, he has active interest in rigidbody/flexible structure dynamics, control of flexible structures, and robotics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AIAA</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Tactical and Strategic Missile Guidance</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
