<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Two-Way AF Relaying in the Presence of Co-Channel Interference</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Student Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Ehsan</forename><surname>Soleimani-Nasab</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Michail</forename><surname>Matthaiou</surname></persName>
							<email>michail.matthaiou@chalmers.se</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mehrdad</forename><surname>Ardebilipour</surname></persName>
							<email>mehrdad@eetd.kntu.ac.ir</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Senior Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">George</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Karagiannidis</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">K. N</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Toosi University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box</postBox>
									<postCode>16315-1355, 1431714191</postCode>
									<settlement>Tehran</settlement>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Signals and Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chalmers University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>412 96</addrLine>
									<settlement>Gothenburg</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Aristotle University of Thessaloniki</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>54 124</addrLine>
									<settlement>Thessaloniki</settlement>
									<country key="GR">Greece</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Two-Way AF Relaying in the Presence of Co-Channel Interference</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9110F742A6FA9364BE4B70F6B5E45070</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TCOMM.2013.053013.120840</idno>
					<note type="submission">received November 3, 2012; revised February 1, March 20, and May 14, 2013. The editor coordinating the review of this paper and approving it for publication was Y. Chen. submitted for potential publication to the IEEE Global Communications Conference (GLOBECOM), Dec. 2013. Digital Object Identifier 10.1109/TCOMM.2013.053013.120840</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T11:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Amplify-and-forward</term>
					<term>interference limited systems</term>
					<term>outage probability</term>
					<term>two-way relaying</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this paper, we investigate the performance of twoway interference-limited amplify-and-forward relaying systems over independent, non-identically distributed Nakagami-m fading channels. Our analysis generalizes several previous results, since it accounts for interference affecting all network nodes. In particular, tight lower bounds on the end-to-end outage and symbol error probability are derived in closed-form, while a useful expression is presented for the asymptotically low outage regime. Some special cases of practical interest (e.g., no interference power and interference-limited case) are also studied. Using the derived lower bounds as a starting point and for the case of Rayleigh fading, we formulate and solve analytically three practical optimization problems, namely, power allocation under fixed location for the relay, optimal relay position with fixed power allocation, and joint optimization of power allocation and relay position under a transmit power constraint. The numerical results provide important physical insights into the implications of model parameters on the system performance; for instance, it is demonstrated that relay position optimization offers significant performance enhancement over the non-optimized case for an asymmetric interference power profile, whilst the optimization gains are marginal for a symmetric one.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>T HE increasing data rate demands of concurrent and future wireless applications have fostered the development of cooperative diversity schemes. Many cooperative strategies have been proposed in the literature based on different relaying techniques, such as amplify-and-forward (AF) and decodeand-forward (DF). More specifically, in AF relaying schemes, the relay simply amplifies the received signal from the source before retransmitting it to the destination (without performing any demodulating and decoding of the received signal) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. On this basis, AF relaying systems have low implementation complexity and are anticipated to be deployed in future vehicular and sensor networks among others. For this reason, we henceforth assess the performance of AF relaying schemes.</p><p>As wireless networks evolve towards high load deployments with aggressive cellular frequency reuse, a dominant factor is inter-cell co-channel interference (CCI). For this reason, CCI has been recently investigated in the context of wireless relaying (see e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> and references therein). In <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, however, the main aim was to study the effect of CCI in unidirectional relay links. For example, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, the outage probability (OP) was derived in closed-form in the presence of CCI at the destination. Considering CCI at the relay, the OP was obtained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> for Rayleigh fading channels. An extension of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> to Nakagami-m fading channels was presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. More recently, the impact of feedback delay with beamforming and CCI at the relay was investigated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, the OP and bit error rate (BER), with a single interferer impairing both the relay and the destination, were analyzed. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, the OP for dual-hop interference-limited relaying systems was deduced, where both the relay and destination nodes are subject to interference.</p><p>The spectral efficiency (SE) in unidirectional relaying systems is inherently low since the communication occupies two time slots. Therefore, the coded bidirectional or twoway relaying techniques have recently received significant attention, since they can improve the SE <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. In two-way relaying systems, in the first time slot, two nodes transmit simultaneously to the relay, and the relay will transmit data to the designated destinations in the second time slot. The authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> obtained the OP and symbol error probability (SEP) of interference-limited systems over Rayleigh fading channels, where they worked with the upper bound of the harmonic mean. However, they introduced an assumption on independency of two dependent random variables (RVs) to derive their closed-form results for the OP and SEP. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, the authors derived the OP and SEP of two multiple-input multiple-output two-way relaying schemes over Nakagami-m fading channels, in an interference-free network. The authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> investigated the SEP of two-way relaying systems using network coding schemes, though they did not consider any interference in the network. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, the authors derived an approximation for the end-to-end OP of a fixed gain AF two-way relay network, suffering from CCI and over Rayleigh fading channels. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the authors examined the outage performance of dual-hop AF relaying systems with CCI over independent, non-identically distributed Nakagami-0090-6778/13$31.00 c 2013 IEEE m fading channels. They extended their work to two-way relaying systems in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, where they considered the impact of interference only at the relay; in addition, they approximated the probability distribution function (PDF) of the sum of interferers' powers by a gamma RV. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, the authors examined the OP of two-way AF relaying systems with CCI over Nakagami-m fading channels, where the relay was not subject to interference. While all previous works have improved our knowledge on the performance characterization of two-way interference-limited AF relaying, the most important differences between our work and <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref> are: 1) In <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, interference affects only the source nodes, whilst the relay is subject to noise only; moreover, all analytical results are limited to the OP and closed-from results were derived only for Rayleigh fading, 2) In <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, interference affects only the relay, while the relay gain does not contain the interferers' effect.</p><p>Motivated by the above mentioned limitations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, we herein pursue a detailed and generalized performance analysis of dual-hop two-way AF relaying systems, where CCI is considered at all nodes in the network (i.e. both the source nodes and relay). In this light, we derive tight lower bounds on the OP and SEP of two-way interference limited AF relaying networks over Nakagami-m fading channels, at arbitrary signal to interference plus noise ratios (SINRs), along with asymptotic expressions in the low outage regime. The contributions of this paper can be summarized as follows:</p><p>• We consider a two-way dual-hop configuration, where the single-antenna source nodes and relay are affected by multiple interferers. This is a practical but complicated setup which has scarcely appeared in the literature. We focus on the Nakagami-m fading model, that has been extensively used for the performance analysis of wireless communication systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. In particular, tight closedform lower bounds on the OP and SEP are derived that extend and complement several previous results in the literature (e.g., those in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>). • Based on the derived lower bounds and for the case of Rayleigh fading, we formulate three interesting optimization problems which seek to minimize the OP. In particular, we consider power allocation under fixed location for the relay, optimal relay position with fixed power allocation, and joint optimization of power allocation and relay position under a transmit power constraint. • In order to get some additional insights into the impact of system parameters, such as fading parameters and number of interferers, we consider the asymptotically low outage regime and obtain the diversity order and coding gain. Finally, we particularize our results to the cases of no interference power and interference-limited case. The rest of the paper is organized as: Section II introduces the system model. In Section III, we derive closed-form lower bounds for the OP and SEP. The asymptotic analysis and optimization results are given in Section IV and V, respectively. Section VI particularizes the results of Section III to some special cases of interest. Finally, Section VII presents our numerical results, while Section VIII concludes the paper.</p><p>Notation: We use f h (.) and F h (.) to denote the PDF and cumulative distribution function (CDF) of a RV h, respec-. . . . . . . . . <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Schematic illustration of the cooperative system under consideration.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">g f 1 S 2 S R 1 ,1 S h 1 , s S N h ,1 R h , r R N h 2 ,1 S h 2 , t S N h Fig.</formula><p>tively. We consider that g (a, b) demonstrates the Gamma distribution, with a and b being its shape and scale parameters. Recall that the PDF and CDF of a Gamma RV are respectively</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">f γ (γ) = γ a-1 b a Γ (a) e -γ b and F γ (γ) = 1 - Γ a, γ b Γ (a)<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Γ(n) = ∞ 0 e -t t</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. SYSTEM MODEL AND FADING STATISTICS</head><p>We consider a cooperative relaying system with two singleantenna source nodes (S 1 and S 2 ), which exchange information via the relay R (see Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>). Moreover, R, S 1 and S 2 are impaired by N r , N s and N t sources of CCI from other users in the network. Additionally, f is the channel coefficient between S 1 and R and viceversa (i.e., the S 1 → R and R → S 1 links) and g is the channel coefficient between S 2 and R which is reciprocal (i.e., the S 2 → R and R → S 2 links). Also, h R,i , h S1,j and h S2,k are the channel coefficients between R, S 1 and S 2 and the i-th (i = 1, ..., N r ), j-th (j = 1, ..., N s ) and k-th (k = 1, ..., N t ) interferer at R, S 1 and S 2 , respectively. Additionally, P R , P S1 and P S2 are the transmitted powers of R, S 1 and S 2 , respectively. Furthermore, P Ri , P S1j and P S2k is the power of the i-th, j-th and k-th CCI signal impairing R, S 1 and S 2 , respectively and σ 2 denotes the noise variance at all nodes. Hence, the instantaneous SNRs for the S 1 → R, S 2 → R, R → S 1 , and R → S 2 links are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">γ 1 = PS 1 |f | 2 σ 2 , γ 2 = PS 2 |g| 2 σ 2 , γ 3 = PR|f | 2 σ 2</formula><p>and γ 4 = PR|g| 2 σ 2 , respectively. Also, the instantaneous interference-to-noise ratio for the i-th CCI at R, j-th CCI at S 1 and k-th CCI at S 2 is given by γ</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">R,i = PRi|hR,i| 2 σ 2 , γ S1,j = PS 1 j |hS 1 ,j | 2 σ 2 and γ S2,k = P S 2 k |h S 2 ,k | 2 σ 2</formula><p>, respectively. As was previously mentioned, we assume that the amplitude of all links follows the Nakagami-m distribution, where m ≥ 0.5 represents the fading severity parameter <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. As such, the distribution of the corresponding SNRs are Gamma RVs, where the shape parameter is m and the scale parameter is Ω/m, where Ω is the mean value of Gamma RVs. As such, the distributions of |f | 2 , |g| 2 , γ S1,j , γ S2,k and γ R,i can be expressed, via the corresponding parameters, as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">|f | 2 d ∼ g (m 1 , 1/a) , |g| 2 d ∼ g (m 2 , 1/b) , γ S1,j d ∼ g (m s , 1/α) , γ S2,k d ∼ g (m t , 1/η) , γ R,i d ∼ g (m r , 1/β)<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where the symbol</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">d ∼ denotes "distributed as". Moreover, a m1 Ω1 , b m2 Ω2 , α msσ 2 ΩsPS 1 j , β mrσ 2</formula><p>ΩrPRi and η</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">mtσ 2</formula><p>ΩtP S 2 k . The signal received at the relay is as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">y R = P S1 f x S1 + P S2 gx S2 + Nr i=1 P Ri h R,i x R,i + n R</formula><p>(3) where x S1 , x S2 and x R,i are the signals generated from S 1 , S 2 and the i-th interferer affecting the relay, respectively, while n R is the additive white Gaussian noise (AWGN) at the relay. After amplification at the relay by a variable gain factor G, the signal received at S 1 can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">y S1 = P r Gf y R + Ns j=1 P S1j h S1,j x S1,j + n S1 (4)</formula><p>where x S1,j is the signal generated from the j-th interferer affecting S 1 and n S1 is the AWGN noise at S 1 , while</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">G -1 P S1 |f | 2 + P S2 |g| 2 + Nr i=1 P Ri |h R,i | 2 + σ 2 . (<label>5</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">)</formula><p>Since S 1 knows its transmitted signal, it can eliminate the selfinterference term. 1 Then, the signal received at S 1 becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">y S1 = P R P S2 Gf gx S2 + Gf P R Nr i=1 P Ri h R,i x R,i + Ns j=1 P S1j h S1,j x S1,j + P R f Gn R + n S1 .<label>(6)</label></formula><p>The received SINR at S 1 can then be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">γ S1 = P R P S2 G 2 |f | 2 |g| 2 G 2 P R |f | 2 Nr i=1 P Ri |h R,i | 2 + Ns j=1 P S1j |h S1,j | 2 +σ 2 G 2 P R |f | 2 + 1 . (<label>7</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">)</formula><p>After some algebraic manipulations, the SINR at S 1 becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">γ S1 = PRPS 2 |f | 2 |g| 2 Ns j=1 PS 1 j |hS 1 ,j | 2 +σ 2 Nr i=1 PRi|hR,i| 2 +σ 2 PS 1 |f | 2 +PS 2 |g| 2 Nr i=1 PRi|hR,i| 2 +σ 2 + PR|f | 2 Ns j=1 PS 1 j |hS 1 ,j | 2 +σ 2 + 1 . (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_16">)</formula><p>By assuming P S1 = P S2 = P S <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>, without significant loss of generality, the SINR at S 1 further simplifies to</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">γ S1 = γ1γ2 Ns j=1 γS 1 ,j +1 Nr i=1 γR,i+1 γ1+γ2 Nr i=1 γR,i+1 + γ1 Ns j=1 γS 1 ,j +1 + 1<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where PR PS . Likewise, the received SINR at S 2 is</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">γ S2 = γ1γ2 N t k=1 γ S 2 ,k +1 Nr i=1 γR,i+1 γ1+γ2 Nr i=1 γR,i+1 + γ2 N t k=1 γ S 2 ,k +1 + 1 . (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">)</formula><p>Moreover, the instantaneous SNR for S 1 → R and S 2 → R 1 We have implicitly assumed that the channel coefficient between S 1 and R is known at S 1 . Likewise, the channel coefficient between S 2 and R is known at S 2 . For a detailed discussion about this assumption, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. are given by γ 1 = γ|f |<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> and γ 2 = γ|g| 2 , respectively, where γ = PS σ 2 is the average SNR per symbol. Note that in the following section, we analytically investigate the OP and SEP, starting from the expressions in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_17">9</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. PERFORMANCE ANALYSIS</head><p>By setting γ S Ns j=1 γ S1,j + 1 and γ R Nr i=1 γ R,i + 1, the received SINR at S 1 can be tightly upper bounded in the interference-limited regime, according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">γ S1 ≤ γ1γ2 γS γR γ1+γ2 γR + γ1 γS = γ 1 γ 2 γ 1 (γ S + γ R ) + γ 2 γ S = γ1γ2 (γS + γR) γ 1 + γ2 (γS+ γR) γ S = γ1γ2 (γS + γR)γS γ1 γS + γ2 (γS + γR) = XY X + Y (11)</formula><p>where  2 As such, the upper bounded SINR at S 1 and S 2 can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">X</formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">γ up S1 = min γ 1 γ S , γ 2 γ S + γ R (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">γ up S2 = min γ 2 γ T , γ 1 γ T + γ R . (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">)</formula><p>Finally, the end-to-end SINR of this system can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">γ e2e = min (γ S1 , γ S2 ) ≤ min γ up S1 , γ up S2 γ up e2e . (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">)</formula><p>Note that some works, such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, derived analytical expressions based on γ S1 , which is not the true end-to-end SINR of two-way relaying systems. To compute the OP of the end-toend SINR, we first need to derive the CDFs of the intermediate variables X and Y . In general, it is known that the sum of L i.i.d. Gamma RVs with shape parameter k and scale parameter θ, is also a Gamma RV with parameters kL and θ. By defining</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">γ s Ns j=1 γ S1,j , γ t Nt k=1 γ S2,k and γ r Nr i=1 γ R,i , the distri- butions of γ s , γ t and γ r are respectively as g (N s m s , 1/α), g (N t m t , 1/η) and g (N r m r , 1/β).</formula><p>The CDFs of X and Y are given by the following proposition: Proposition 1: The CDFs of X and Y are respectively</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">F X (z) = 1 - α Nsms Γ (N s m s ) e -az γ m1-1 i=0 i j=0 i j (az) i γi i! × Γ (j + N s m s ) az γ + α j+Nsms (<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_31">F Y (z)=1- α Nsms Γ (N s m s ) β Nr mr Γ (N r m r ) m2-1 i=0 i j=0 i-j k=0 i j i -j k k (az) i γi i! ( + 1) i-j-k e 2bz γ Γ (j + N s m s ) bz γ + α j+Nsms Γ (k + N r m r ) bz γ + β k+Nrmr .</formula><p>(16) Proof: See Appendix I. From ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_29">15</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>), it is clear that m 1 and m 2 should be integers. After computing the CDFs of X and Y , we now proceed to derive the CDFs of γ up S1 and γ up S2 : Proposition 2: The CDFs of γ up S1 and γ up S2 are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">F γ up S 1 (z)=1 - α msNs Γ (m s N s ) β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) e -(( +1)b+a) z γ m1-1 i=0 m2-1 j=0 j k=0 i l=0 j-k t=0 ( + 1) j-k-t i!j! j k j -k t i l (az) i (bz) j i+j-t γi+j Γ (m s N s + l + k) az γ + bz γ + α msNs+l+k Γ (m r N r + t) β + bz γ mr Nr+t . (<label>17</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">F γ up S 2 (z) = 1 - η mtNt Γ (m t N t ) β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) e -(( +1)a+b) z γ m2-1 i=0 m1-1 j=0 j k=0 i l=0 j-k t=0 ( + 1) j-k-t i!j! j k j -k t i l (az) j (bz) i i+j-t γi+j Γ (m t N t + l + k) az γ + bz γ + η mtNt+l+k Γ (m r N r + t) β + az γ mr Nr+t .</formula><p>(18) Proof: See Appendix II. As before, from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_32">17</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>, it is clear that m 1 and m 2 should be integers. With these results in our hands, we can now evaluate the CDF of the upper bounded end-to-end SINR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposition 3:</head><p>The CDF of the upper bounded end-to-end SINR, γ up e2e , is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">F γ up e2e (z)= 1-P 11 (z) + P 12 (z) P 21 (z) + P 22 (z)<label>(19)</label></formula><p>where P 11 (z), P 12 (z), P 21 (z) and P 22 (z) are defined in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_47">20</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_53">23</ref>) at the top of next page. Proof: See Appendix III. Note that m 1 , m 2 , m s N s and m t N t should have integer values. Hereafter, we investigate the most important performance metrics i.e. the lower bounded OP and SEP for twoway interference-limited systems based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Outage Probability</head><p>The OP is the probability that either the S 1 -to-relay link SINR or the S 2 -to-relay link SINR falls bellow a certain threshold, γ th = γ0 γ . By using <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>, we can now obtain the following lower bound on the exact OP of the system</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">P out (γ th ) ≥ P lb out (γ th ) = 1 -P 1 (γ 0 )P 2 (γ 0 )<label>(24)</label></formula><p>where P 1 (γ 0 ) P 11 (γ 0 ) + P 12 (γ 0 ), P 2 (γ 0 ) P 21 (γ 0 ) + P 22 (γ 0 ). Note that ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_36">24</ref>) can be efficiently evaluated, as it includes finite summations of elementary functions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Symbol Error Probability</head><p>We now turn our attention to the SEP, which for most digital communication modulations can be expressed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> P</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">lb e = c 2 d π ∞ 0 e -dγ √ γ F γ up e2e (γ) (γ)dγ<label>(25)</label></formula><p>where the constants c and d depend on the type of the modulation. For example, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">T = a γ msNs+mrNr α + az γ msNs α + az γ + β mrNr = msNs i1=1 τ i1 z + αγ a i1 + mr Nr i2=1 λ i2 z + (α+β)γ a i2 (<label>26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">τ i1 lim z→-αγ a ∂ msNs-i1 (m s N s -i 1 )!∂z msNs-i1 z + αγ a msNs T λ i2 lim z→-(α+β)γ a ∂ mrNr-i2 (m r N r -i 2 )!∂z mrNr -i2 z + (α+β)γ a mr Nr T.</formula><p>We also invoke the following identity [22, Eq. (2.1.</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">3.1)] ∞ 0 x μ e -sx (x + z) v dx = Γ (μ + 1) z μ-v+1 Ψ (μ + 1, μ -v + 2; sz)<label>(27)</label></formula><p>where Ψ(•; •; •) is the Tricomi confluent hypergeometric function [18, Eq. (9.210.2)]. By substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_35">19</ref>) into (25), using partial fractions expansions as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> and utilizing <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>, a lower bound on the SEP of two-way interference-limited relaying systems can be derived in closed-from; however, the derived expression is omitted due to space limitations. The SEP for some special cases is investigated in Section IV.</p><p>IV. ASYMPTOTIC OUTAGE ANALYSIS Since the exact results of the previous section provide limited physical insights, we now focus on the low outage regime. The threshold value of the OP is defined as γ th = γ0 γ , where γ 0 is a finite threshold value. As SNR γ increases, γ th tends to zero and we can approximate the PDF distribution of the end-to-end SINR around the origin via a Taylor's series. The following approximations will be useful in our analysis</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">(1 + γ th ) -n = K i=0 -n i γ i th + o γ K th (<label>28</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_43">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">e γ th = K i=0 γ i th i! + o γ K th , as γ th → 0<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where n and K are positive integers. Recall that, in the low outage regime the proposed upper bound on the end-to-end SINR becomes exact and we can precisely predict the diversity order and coding gain, with the aid of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_44">29</ref>): Proposition 4: The asymptotic OP of the end-to-end SINR is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">P ∞ out (γ th ) = G c γ G d th + o γ G d th (<label>30</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_46">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_47">P 11 (z) β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) η mtNt Γ (m t N t ) α msNs Γ (m s N s ) e -( az γ ( 1 +1)+ α) m1-1 l=0 l r=0 msNs+r-1 i=0 i j=0 i-j k=0 l r i j i -j k a l z l l+k-i γl l!i! × Γ (m s N s + r) α + az γ msNs+r-i Γ (m r N r + j) α + az γ + β mrNr+j Γ (m t N t + k) α + az γ + η mtNt+k (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_48">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">P 12 (z) β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) η mtNt Γ (m t N t ) e -az γ ( 1 +1) m1-1 l=0 l j=0 l-j k=0 l j l -j k a l z l ( + 1) l-j-k l-j γl l! Γ (m r N r + j) az γ + β mr Nr+j Γ (m t N t + k) az γ + η mtNt+k - η mtNt Γ (m t N t ) β mrNr Γ (m r N r ) e -( az γ ( 1 +1)+ α) m1-1 l=0 l r=0 msNs-1 i=0 i j=0 l-r w=0 i-j k=0 i j l r l -r w i -j k × a l z l α i ( + 1) l-r-w l+k-i-r γl l!i! Γ (m r N r + j + r) az γ + α + β mr Nr+j+r Γ (m t N t + k + w) az γ + α + η mtNt+k+w (<label>21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_50">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_51">P 21 (z) β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) α msNs Γ (m s N s ) e -2bz γ ( 1 +1) m2-1 l=0 l j=0 l-j k=0 l j l -j k b l z l ( + 1) l-j-k l-j γl l! Γ (m r N r + j) bz γ + β mrNr+j Γ (m s N s + k) bz γ + α msNs+k - β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) α msNs Γ (m s N s ) e -( bz γ ( 1 +1)+ η) m2-1 l=0 l r=0 mtNt-1 i=0 i j=0 l-r w=0 i-j k=0 i j l r l -r w i -j k × b l z l η i ( + 1) l-r-w l+k-i-r γl l!i! Γ (m r N r + j + r) bz γ + η + β mrNr+j+r Γ (m s N s + k + w) bz γ + α + η msNs+k+w (<label>22</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">P 22 (z) β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) η mtNt Γ (m t N t ) α msNs Γ (m s N s ) e -( bz γ ( 1 +1)+ η) m2-1 l=0 l r=0 mtNt+r-1 i=0 i j=0 i-j k=0 l r i j i -j k b l z l l+k-i γl l!i! × Γ (m t N t + r) η + bz γ mtNt+r-i Γ (m r N r + j) η + bz γ + β mrNr+j Γ (m s N s + k) α + bz γ + η msNs+k . (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">)</formula><p>where the diversity order and coding gain are respectively</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">G d = min (m 1 , m 2 ) G c = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ G c1 m 2 &gt; m 1 G c2 m 1 &gt; m 2 G c1 + G c2 m 1 = m 2 (31)</formula><p>while G c1 and G c2 are given at the top of next page.</p><p>Proof: At high SNRs, where γ → ∞, we have 1 - <ref type="bibr">[22,</ref> Eq. (06.06.06.0001.02)]. Following the proof of Proposition 3, we can get <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">Γ(m, az γ ) Γ(m) → ( az γ ) m Γ(m+1)</formula><p>The above result implies that, when all interferers' powers (i.e. P Ri , P S1j and P S2k ) are kept constant, interference does not affect the diversity order. However, when the interference power is growing large while the ratio of transmit powers of both sources versus the interferers' powers is kept constant (a scenario corresponding to the special case b in Section VI), the performance of the system cannot be improved due to the interference becoming dominant; as such, the diversity order in this case is equal to 0. These results are consistent with <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. For the sake of simplicity, we now elaborate on the case of Rayleigh fading, by setting all m parameters to one, while the interference power is assumed constant; then, the asymptotic OP becomes equal to</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">P ∞ out (γ th ) = (a + b) + 1 + N r β + aN t η + bN s α + β Nr Γ (N r ) η Nt Γ (N t ) e -α Ns-1 i=0 i j=0 i-j k=0 aα i-1 (N s -i) k-i+1 i! i j × i -j k Γ (N r + j) ( α + β) Nr+j Γ (N t + k) (η + α) Nt+k + β Nr α Ns Γ (N r ) Γ (N s ) × e -η Nt-1 i=0 i j=0 i-j k=0 bη i-1 (N t -i) k-i+1 i! i j i -j k × Γ (N r + j) ( η + β) Nr+j Γ (N s + k) (α + η) Ns+k γ th + o(γ th ).<label>(34)</label></formula><p>Note that ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_57">34</ref>) is different from [10, Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_22">12</ref>)] since, as previously mentioned, the authors therein worked on the OP of γ S1 and assumed that X and Y are independent. In this paper, however, this assumption has been relaxed. In the asymptotic regime, by substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_57">34</ref>) into ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_37">25</ref>), the SEP for Rayleigh</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">G c1 = β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) η mtNt Γ (m t N t ) a m1 Γ (m 1 + 1) ⎡ ⎣ msNs-1 i=0 i j=0 m1 l=0 i-j k=0 m1-l w=0 i j m 1 l i -j k × m 1 -l w α i ( + 1) m1-l-w m1+k-i-l i! e -α Γ (m r N r + l + j) (α + β) mrNr +l+j Γ (m t N t + k + w) (α + η) mtNt+k+w - m1 l=0 m1-l w=0 m 1 -l w × ( + 1) m1-l-w m1-l Γ (m r N r + l) β mr Nr+l Γ (m t N t + w) η mtNt+w - α msNs Γ (m s N s ) m1 r=0 msNs+r-1 i=0 i j=0 i-j k=0 i j × m 1 r i -j k α i m1+k-i i! e -α Γ (m s N s + r) α msNs+r Γ (m r N r + j) (α + β) mr Nr+j Γ (m t N t + k) (α + η) mtNt+k (<label>32</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_60">G c2 = β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) α msNs Γ (m s N s ) b m2 Γ (m 2 + 1) ⎡ ⎣ mtNt-1 i=0 i j=0 m2 l=0 i-j k=0 m2-l w=0 i j m 2 l i -j k × m 2 -l w η i ( + 1) m2-l-w m2+k-i-l i! e -η Γ (m r N r + l + j) (η + β) mr Nr+l+j Γ (m s N s + k + w) (α + η) msNs+k+w - m2 l=0 m2-l w=0 m 2 -l w × ( + 1) m2-l-w m2-l Γ (m r N r + l) β mr Nr+l Γ (m s N s + w) α msNs+w - η mtNt Γ (m t N t ) m2 r=0 mtNt+r-1 i=0 i j=0 i-j k=0 i j × m 2 r i -j k η i m2+k-i i! e -η Γ (m t N t + r) η mtNt+r Γ (m r N r + j) (η + β) mrNr+j Γ (m s N s + k) (α + η) msNs+k . (<label>33</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_61">)</formula><p>fading channels can be obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">P ∞ e = c 4dγ (a + b) + 1 + N r β + aN t η + bN s α + β Nr Γ (N r ) η Nt Γ (N t ) e -α Ns-1 i=0 i j=0 i-j k=0 aα i-1 (N s -i) k-i+1 i! i j × i -j k Γ (N r + j) ( α + β) Nr+j Γ (N t + k) (η + α) Nt+k + β Nr α Ns Γ (N r ) Γ (N s ) × e -η Nt-1 i=0 i j=0 i-j k=0 bη i-1 (N t -i) k-i+1 i! i j i -j k × Γ (N r + j) ( η + β) Nr+j Γ (N s + k) (α + η) Ns+k + o γ -1 . (<label>35</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_63">)</formula><p>As anticipated, the diversity order is equal to 1 for the particular Rayleigh case under consideration. When interference exists only at the relay (i.e. N s = N t = 0), <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> and (35) reduce respectively to</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">P ∞ out (γ th ) = (a + b) + 1 + N r β γ th + o(γ th ) P ∞ e = c(a + b) +1 + Nr β 4dγ + o γ -1 . (<label>36</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">)</formula><p>The above expressions reveal straightforwardly the impact of the model parameters on the system performance. More specifically, we can see that by increasing N r and the nodes' power or by reducing the interference power, the OP and SEP will reduce. For the interference-free system (i.e. N s = N r = N t = 0), <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> and (35) reduce respectively to</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">P ∞ out = + 1 (a + b)γ th + o(γ th ) (<label>37</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_67">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_68">P ∞ e = c +1 (a + b) 4dγ + o γ -1 . (<label>38</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_69">)</formula><p>Note that, in this case γ up e2e = min γ1 +1 , γ2 +1 , while the diversity order is 1, which is in agreement with min(m 1 , m 2 ), predicted by Proposition 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. RELAY POSITION OPTIMIZATION</head><p>The optimal placement of relays and/or the optimal power allocation for improving the system performance (e.g., minimizing the OP) has been a very hot area of research. For example, recently the authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> investigated an optimization problem based on the error probability for one-way relaying networks over Rayleigh fading channels. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, they extended their work to Nakagami-m fading channels, where they worked with the high SNR approximation of the OP. In the context of two-way relaying, the authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> minimized the individual OPs of the source nodes at high SNRs. The authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> derived the optimal achievable endto-end rate of two-way interference-free systems. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, the authors presented optimal power allocation results in order to maximize the sum of the achievable rates of both hops, when interference is present in the network. The authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> worked out some optimal power allocation results for the OP of DF two-way relay networks. Note that, to the best of our knowledge, the work presented here on two-way interferencelimited relaying networks, where CCI affect all nodes, is new. In the following, we consider some optimization problems which seek to optimally allocate power to the network nodes and also find the optimal relay position, in order to minimize the OP for constant interference power. Note that an arbitrary SINR analysis is intractable and for this reason we elaborate on the asymptotically low outage regime and assume the case of Rayleigh fading for the S 1 → R and R → S 2 links (i.e. m 1 = m 2 = 1). 3   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Optimization of OP at S 1 and S 2</head><p>In our first optimization formulation we seek to minimize the OP at S 1 . 4 Referring back to <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, the lower bound on the OP at S 1 , P lb outS 1 , should be minimized according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">min dS 1 ,R , dS 2 ,R P lb outS 1 (γ th ) subject to 0 &lt; d S1,R , 0 &lt; d S2,R , 2P S + P R = P tot (39)</formula><p>where d S1,R and d S2,R are the distances between S 1 and the relay and S 2 and the relay, respectively, while P tot is the total power of the system. We now make the standard assumption that the average SNR, Ω, decays exponentially with the distance such that a = m1</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">PS d -v S 1 ,R , b = m2 PS d -v S 2 ,R</formula><p>. Note that v is the path-loss exponent, whose value is normally in the range of 2 to 6. By setting m 1 = m 2 = 1 in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_32">17</ref>), we have i = j = k = l = t = 0. By doing so, the lower bound on the OP at node S 1 can be simplified as</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">P lb outS 1 (γ th ) = 1 - α msNs β mr Nr e -(b( 1 +1)+ a )γth a+b γ th + α msNs (bγ th + β) mrNr . (<label>40</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_73">)</formula><p>In the low outage regime, a+b α and b β tend to zero. Thus, using <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>, and by keeping only the dominant term, the lower bound in (40) becomes exact and equal to</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">P ∞ outS 1 (γ th ) L(γ th ) = ( + 1)b + a γ th + a + b α m s N s γ th + b β m r N r γ th + o(γ th ).<label>(41)</label></formula><p>Hereafter, our objective function is L(γ th ) which, fortunately, lends itself to algebraic manipulations; 5  1) Power Allocation Optimization under Fixed Relay Location: By substituting the path-loss based definition of a and b and assuming a fixed location for the relay, (41) can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">L(γ th ) = A 1 d v S1,R P R + A 1 d v S2,R P R + B 1 d v S2,R P S (<label>42</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_76">)</formula><p>where A 1 1 + msNs α γ th and B 1 1 + mr Nr β γ th . The second derivative of (42) with respect to P S is equal to</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">∂ 2 L(γ th ) ∂P 2 S = 8A 1 d v S1,R P 3 R + 8A 1 d v S2,R P 3 R + 2B 1 d v S2,R P 3</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S</head><p>&gt; 0 (43) 3 We emphasize the fact that in order to analytically find the optimal values for the case of arbitrary m 1 and m 2 , the optimization problem can be solved only numerically. 4 We should note that several previous works have considered deriving the OP at S 1 as well <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31]</ref>. 5 Note that a similar optimization problem can be defined based on SEP by using <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>, where the optimization results are the same with the only difference pertaining to the replacement of</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">A 1 , B 1 with Ā1 = c 4 dA 1 , B1 = c 4 dB 1 .</formula><p>which is, of course, strictly positive. As such, the optimization problem is convex. By introducing the Lagrangian multipliers and applying the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) conditions, we can obtain the optimal powers as ∂L(γ th )</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">∂P S = 2A 1 d v S1,R P 2 R + 2A 1 d v S2,R P 2 R -B 1 d v S2,R P 2 S = 0 ⇒ P * S = P tot 2 + 2A1 d v S 1 ,R +d v S 2 ,R B1d v S 2 ,R . (<label>44</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_80">)</formula><p>It can be seen that, if the relay is closer to S 2 , S 1 needs more power to achieve the same performance. Interestingly, the optimal power allocation is independent of γ th . For i.i.d. fading and symmetric interference channels (i.e., m s = m r = m t , Ω s = Ω r = Ω t and N s = N r = N t ), where the optimum relay position is in the middle of the two source nodes' distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, the optimal power allocation solution becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">P * R = 2P * S = Ptot 2 .</formula><p>By substituting the optimal values from (44) into (42) and setting d S1,R = d S2,R = 0.5, the minimum value of OP at S1, can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">L * sc1 (γ th ) = A 1 d v S1,R P * R + A 1 d v S2,R P * R + B 1 d v S2,R P * S = √ A 1 √ A 1 + √ B 1 2 v-1 P tot + √ B 1 √ A 1 + √ B 1 2 v-1 P tot . (<label>45</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">)</formula><p>The minimum value of OP at S 1 , for this first scenario, is</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">L * sc1 (γ th ) = A 1 + 2 √ A 1 B 1 + B 1 2 v-1 P tot . (<label>46</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_85">)</formula><p>It is obvious that by decreasing m s , m r , N s , N r and γ th and also by increasing α, β, v and P tot , L * sc1 (γ th ) will decrease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Relay Position Optimization under Fixed Power Allocation:</head><p>To minimize the effects of path-loss, it is obvious that the relay should be aligned between S 1 and S 2 . This is reasonable since the direct line link between any two nodes minimizes the loss of transmitted power <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. By setting d S1,R = d and d S2,R = 1d, the OP in (41) can be simplified as</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">L(γ th ) = A 1 d v + (1 -d) v P R + B 1 (1 -d) v P S + o(γ th ). (<label>47</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_87">)</formula><p>The second derivative of (47) with respect to d is equal to</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">∂ 2 L(γ th ) ∂d 2 =A 1 v (v -1) d v-2 P R + A 1 v (v -1) (1 -d) v-2 P R +B 1 v (v -1) (1 -d) v-2 P S &gt; 0 (48)</formula><p>which is, of course, strictly positive. By introducing the Lagrangian multipliers and applying the KKT conditions, we obtain the optimal relay position as</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">∂L(γ th ) ∂d = A 1 vd v-1 P R -A 1 v(1 -d) v-1 P R -B 1 v(1 -d) v-1 P S = 0 ⇒ d * = 1 1 + A 1 P R A 1 P R + B 1 P S 1 v-1 . (<label>49</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_90">)</formula><p>By observing (49), it is obvious that if the allocated power to S 1 and S 2 decreases and also if m r or N r increase, the relay should be closer to S 2 ; this is reasonable since the quality of the R → S 2 link needs to be improved to avoid being in outage. An interesting result appears for i.i.d. fading and symmetric interference channels (i.e., m s = m r = m t , Ω s = Ω r = Ω t and N s = N r = N t ), for which A 1 = B 1 ; this states that the optimal relay location is near to in the S 2 , which is in agreement with <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. This is rather intuitive: referring back to (40), we can see that the OP at S 1 includes exponential terms depending on the S 1 → R and S 2 → R links. Given that the former term scales twice as fast as the latter, the relay node should be close to S 2 . By substituting the optimal value from (49) into (47), and setting P R = 2P S = Ptot 2 , the minimum value of OP at S 1 can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">L * sc2 (γ th ) = A 1 d * v + (1 -d * ) v P R + B 1 (1 -d * ) v P S = 2A 1 P tot 1 + A1 A1+2B1 1 v-1 v + 2 A1 A1+2B1 v v-1 (A 1 + 2B 1 ) P tot 1 + A1 A1+2B1 1 v-1 v .</formula><p>(50) Hence, the minimum value of OP at S 1 can be obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">L * sc2 (γ th ) = 2A v v-1 1 (A 1 + 2B 1 ) + 2A 1 (A 1 + 2B 1 ) v v-1 P tot A 1 v-1 1 + (A 1 + 2B 1 ) 1 v-1 v . (51)</formula><p>We can see that by decreasing m s , m r , N s , N r and γ th and also by increasing α, β, v and P tot , the minimal value of OP in (51) will be reduced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) Joint Power Allocation and Relay Position Optimization:</head><p>The joint optimization problem can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">min PS , PR, d L (γ th ) = A 1 d v P R + A 1 (1 -d) v P R + B 1 (1 -d) v</formula><p>P S subject to 2P S + P R = P tot , and 0 &lt; P S , P R , 0 &lt; d &lt; 1.</p><p>(52) Proposition 5: The optimization problem in (52), when v ≥ 2, d ∈ [0, 1] and P S ∈ [0, P tot ], is convex.</p><p>Proof: By differentiating the objective function in (52) twice with respect to P S and d, we can show that the Hessian matrix is positive semi-definite when v ≥ 2, d ∈ [0, 1] and P S ∈ [0, P tot ].</p><p>By differentiating (41) with respect to P S and d and setting both derivatives equal to zero, we end up with</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">d v-1 (1 -d) v-1 = 1 + B 1 P R A 1 P S , B 1 P 2 R 2A 1 P 2 S -1 = d v (1 -d) v . (53)</formula><p>We can now obtain the optimal power allocation and relay position by numerically solving the following equations</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">d v-1 (1 -d) v-1 -1 2 = 2B 1 A 1 d v (1 -d) v + 1 , P * S = P tot A1 B1 d v-1 (1-d) v-1 -1 + 2 . (<label>54</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_96">)</formula><p>Our numerical results show that joint optimization and relay position optimization yield almost the same performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Optimization of OP at S 1 with constrained OP at S 2</head><p>The previous optimization problem focuses on the OP at S 1 by ignoring the OP at S 2 . Alternatively, we can define a new problem which seeks to minimize the OP at S 1 by considering the OP at S 2 . The main advantage of this approach is that we can adaptively select this threshold to meet some stipulated OP tolerance. By assuming = 1, we now have</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">min d P ∞ outS 1 (γ th ) = A 1 P S d v + C 1 P S (1 -d) v subject to P ∞ outS 2 (γ th ) = C 2 P S d v + A 2 P S (1 -d) v ≤ OP S2 , and, 0 &lt; d &lt; 1 (<label>55</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_98">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">A 2 1 + mtNt η γ th , C 1 A 1 + B 1 and C 2 A 2 + B 1</formula><p>, while OP S2 is the maximum tolerable OP at S 2 . Note that P ∞ outS 2 (γ th ) is derived by using <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> and in a similar way as (41). Using the Lagrange multiplier definition, we can prove that the optimization problem in (55) is convex.</p><formula xml:id="formula_100">L(γ th ) = A 1 P S d v + C 1 P S (1 -d) v + λ C 2 P S d v + A 2 P S (1 -d) v -OP S2 (56) ∂ 2 L(γ th ) ∂d 2 = v (v -1) A 1 P S + λC 2 P S d v-2 + C 1 P S + λA 2 P S (1 -d) v-2 &gt; 0. (<label>57</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_101">)</formula><p>Hence, by using the Lagrange multiplier, the KKT conditions are as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_102">(A 1 + λC 2 ) d v-1 = (C 1 + λA 2 ) (1 -d) v-1 (58) λ ≥ 0, 0 &lt; d &lt; 1 (59) λ C 2 P S d v + A 2 P S (1 -d) v -OP S2 = 0<label>(60)</label></formula><p>where λ is the Lagrangian coefficient. Here, we have two cases:</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">1. λ = 0 ⇒ d * = 1 1+ A 1 C 1 1 v-1 . 2. λ = 0 ⇒ d * = arg d C2 PS d v + A2 PS (1 -d) v -OP S2 = 0 .</formula><p>Assuming v = 4, the optimal value is the solution to the following 4-th order polynomial</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">d 4 - 4A 2 A 2 + C 2 d 3 + 6A 2 A 2 + C 2 d 2 - 4A 2 A 2 + C 2 d + A 2 -P S OP S2 A 2 + C 2 = 0.<label>(61)</label></formula><p>Using [32, Sec. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">5</ref>)], we can solve this polynomial analytically, though the results are omitted due to space limitations.</p><p>We can now take a closer look into the actual impact of relay position optimization. We begin with the optimization scheme in (47). For i.i.d. fading and symmetric interference channels (i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">m s = m r = m t , N s = N r = N t and Ω s = Ω r = Ω t ) for which A 1 = B 1 , we have L non-opt (γ th ) = L * sc1 (γ th ) = A 1 P tot 2 v-3 v=4 = 0.5A 1 P tot L * sc2 (γ th ) = 6A 1 P tot 1 + 3 1 v-1 v-1 v=4 ≈ 0.41A 1 P tot<label>(62)</label></formula><p>where L non-opt (γ th ) indicates the OP at S 1 where no optimization is being performed; in this non-optimized case, we set P R = 2P S = Ptot 2 and d S1,R = d S2,R = 0.5 in (47). Note that (62) implies that in the case of identical fading conditions, the system performance cannot improve via power optimization.</p><p>We can now compare the cases of symmetric and asymmetric interference power with the same total interference power constraint. In the case of symmetric interference power profile, where N s = N r , Ω s = Ω r , we have A 1 = B 1 and as such there is no need for optimization. On the other hand, in the asymmetric interference power profile, if we consider that the interference at the relay is stronger than at S 1 (i.e., we increase P Ri while P S1j is kept fixed, and hence B 1 is increasing while A 1 is kept fixed), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_86">47</ref>) and (51) simplify respectively to</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">L non-opt (γ th ) ≈ B 1 P tot 2 v-2 , L * sc1 (γ th ) ≈ B 1 2 v-1 P tot L * sc2 (γ th ) ≈ 2A 1 P tot . (<label>63</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_107">)</formula><p>Note that for the non-optimized case we have assumed d = 0.5 and</p><formula xml:id="formula_108">2P S2 = P R = 2P S1 = Ptot 2 .</formula><p>As can be observed from (63), significant performance enhancement can be attained via the use of relay position optimization. This verifies the importance of optimization for the asymmetric interference profile case. In fact, by increasing B 1 , while A 1 is kept fixed (i.e. by increasing the SNR), the OPs in (63) are proportional to B 1 , B 1 and B 0 1 , respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. PRACTICAL CASES OF INTEREST</head><p>In this section, we particularize the previously reported results to some practical cases of interest.</p><p>a) Interference-free (N s = N r = N t = 0) When we set (P S1j = P S2k = P Ri = P I = 0), (24) simplifies to</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">P lb out (γ th ) = 1 -e -( +1)(a+b)γ th m1-1 i=0 m2-1 j=0 ( + 1) i+j a i b j γ i+j th i!j! (64)</formula><p>where, in this case, γ up S1 = min γ 1 , γ2 +1 , which is a tight upper bound for γ1γ2 ( +1)γ1+γ2 while γ up S2 = min γ 2 , γ1 +1 . Note that the derived CDF in (17), when N s = N r = 0, is a tight lower bound for [29, Eq. ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>)].</p><p>b) Interference-limited case: For simplicity, we assume that a = b, α = β = η, m 1 = m 2 , m s N s = m t N t . By setting P S1j = P S2k = P Ri = P I , P S = P R and PS PI = ρ ≥ 1 where P S , P I → ∞, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> after some manipulations simplifies to</p><formula xml:id="formula_110">P lb out (γ th ) = 1 -P 3 (γ th ) + P 4 (γ th ) 2<label>(65)</label></formula><p>where </p><formula xml:id="formula_111">P 3 (γ th ) 1 Γ (m r N r ) 1 [Γ (m s N s )] 2 m1-1 l=0 msNs+l-1 i=0 i j=0 i j m1Ωs ρmsΩ f l γ l th l!i! Γ (m s N s + l) 1 + m1Ωs ρmsΩ f γ th msNs+l-j-k × Γ (m r N r + j) 2 + m1Ωs ρmsΩ f γ th mrNr+j Γ (m s N s + i -j) 2 + m1Ωs ρmsΩ f γ th msNs+i-j</formula><formula xml:id="formula_112">P 4 (γ th ) 1 Γ (m r N r ) 1 Γ (m s N s ) m1-1 l=0 l j=0 l j γ l th l! × Γ (m r N r + j) m1Ωs ρmsΩ f γ th + 1 mr Nr+j Γ (m s N s + l -j) m1Ωs ρmsΩ f γ th + 1 msNs+l-j × m 1 Ω s ρm s Ω f l - m1-1 l=0 l r=0 msNs-1 i=0 i j=0 i j l r × m1Ωs ρmsΩ f l γ l th l!i! Γ (m r N r + j + r) m1Ωs ρmsΩ f γ th + 2 mrNr+j+r × Γ (m s N s + l -r + i -j) m1Ωs ρmsΩ f γ th + 2 msNs+l-r+i-j</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_113">Ω s E[|h S1,j | 2 ] and Ω f E[|f | 2 ]</formula><p>. The diversity order is equal to 0 which means that the OP will saturate when the ratio of signal to interference power is constant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. SIMULATION RESULTS</head><p>In this section, the presented theoretical results are validated by a set of Monte-Carlo simulations, where we assume that N t = N r = N s = N . Note that all curves are plotted as a function of the average SNR γ.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> demonstrates the analytical lower bound for the OP in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> along with the low outage approximation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref>, where P I is a constant (i.e. a scenario corresponding to high SNR as well). For the sake of completeness, we also consider the case of Rayleigh fading, where all m parameters are equal to 1 while = 1. As expected, the diversity order for Nakagamim and Rayleigh fading channels is respectively equal to 2 and 1 (i.e. minimum of m 1 and m 2 ). As can be seen, the OP increases as the power of interference, P I , increases. The proposed analytical lower bound yields excellent tightness across the entire SNR range and becomes exact at high SNRs. Likewise, the asymptotic outage approximation can very efficiently predict the exact OP.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> illustrates the analytical lower bound for the OP, where P S /P I is kept constant, while = 1. We observe that by increasing the number of interferers, the OP increases too.</p><p>As the SNR increases, the OP reaches an error floor since the effect of interference becomes dominant, while for the interference-free case the error floor does not occur. Note that the diversity order in the former case is equal to 0.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> shows the analytical lower bound for the SEP for BPSK modulation (c = d = 1) and different values of the m 1 parameter where we have assumed that = 1. As observed, by increasing m 1 the SEP reduces systematically. Also, it can be seen that the relative distance between the curves reduces for higher values of the m 1 factor. This implies that the impact of m 1 becomes increasingly less pronounced. This is consistent with the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. Similar observations can be made when m 2 increases and m 1 is kept fixed. For example, m 2 = 2m 1 = 2 has the same SEP value as m 1 = 2m 2 = 2.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> elaborates on the optimization scenarios outlined in Section V, where PS PI is a constant. Note that, in this case, all curves are plotted against P tot . Since the objective function is the OP at S 1 , we have that 2P S1 = 2P S2 = 2P S = P R = P tot /2 which means = 2. In the first case P S -P S1j = 30 dB, P S -P Ri = 0 dB, P S -P S2k = 0 dB, which represents an asymmetric interference power profile, while in the other case P S -P S1j = 15 dB, P S -P Ri = 15 dB, P S -P S2k = 15 dB, which represents a symmetric interference power profile. In the asymmetric case, the OP of relay position optimization is decreased by approximately 10 orders of magnitude compared to the non-optimized case. Our results show that the asymmetric power case outperforms the symmetric case according to (62), Also, in the symmetric case, the power allocation optimization and nonoptimized case (d = 0.5, P R = 2P S = P tot /2) have the same values. This means that performing optimization, leaves the OP unaffected. As a result, in the low SNR regime, if we want to optimize the OP at S 1 , the best choice of powers and relay position are d = 0.5, P R = 2P S = P tot /2.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> presents the outage optimization results at S 1 , where the OP at S 2 is kept under a fixed threshold OP S2 = 10 3 γ . In this case, P S1 = P S2 = P S = P R = Ptot 3 ( = 1). The graph also depicts the following curves: the OP at S 2 , which is obtained by substituting the optimal value of d into the constraint in (55), and the non-optimized OP at S 1 by setting d = 0.5 in the objective function in (55). In the first case P S -P S1j = 20 dB, P S -P Ri = 10 dB, P S -P S2k = 0 dB, which represents an asymmetric interference power profile, while in the other case P S -P S1j = P S -P Ri = P S -P S2k = 10 dB, which represents a symmetric interference power profile. In the former case, the OP at S 1 is smaller than in the symmetric case. For the symmetric profile, the optimized OP at S 1 has a marginal performance gain against the non-optimized one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VIII. CONCLUSION</head><p>We assessed the performance of a dual-hop two-way AF relaying system over Nakagami-m fading channels, where all nodes are impaired by CCI. More specifically, we have derived new tight lower bounds for the OP and SEP of the system at arbitrary SINRs. Moreover, simplified asymptotic results in the low outage regime were deduced. For the case of Rayleigh fading, we examined three practical optimization problems, where we observed that relay position optimization yields substantial performance improvement. Finally, the distribution of the interferers' power can significantly affect the OP, since the asymmetric interference profile case yields lower OP than the symmetric profile case in the low outage regime. Note that all the presented expressions herein can be easily evaluated and efficiently programmed. We finally point out that the presented results complement and extend several previous results reported in the literature over the past years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX I: PROOF OF PROPOSITION 1</head><p>To begin with, the CDFs of X and Y are equal to</p><formula xml:id="formula_114">F X (z) = Pr (X ≤ z) = Pr (γ 1 ≤ zγ S |γ S ) = F γ1 (zγ S |γ S ) F Y (z) = Pr (Y ≤ z) = Pr (γ 2 ≤ z (γ S + γ R ) | γ S , γ R ) = F γ2 (z (γ S + γ R ) | γ S , γ R ) .</formula><p>The CDFs of X and Y can be written in integral form as</p><formula xml:id="formula_115">F X (z) = ∞ 0 F γ1 (zγ S |γ S ) f γS (γ S )dγ S (66) F Y (z) = ∞ 0 ∞ 0 F γ2 (z (γ S + γ R ) |γ S γ R ) × f γS (γ S )f γR (γ R )dγ S dγ R . (<label>67</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_116">)</formula><p>Defining γ S = γ s + 1 and γ R = γ r + 1, substituting the PDFs of γ s and γ r and the CDF of γ 1 from (2) into (66), we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_117">F X (z)= α Nsms Γ (N s m s ) ∞ 0 ⎡ ⎣ 1- Γ m 1 , az γ (x + 1) Γ (m 1 ) ⎤ ⎦ x Nsms-1 e αx dx.</formula><p>(68) Using <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr">Eq. (8.352.2)</ref>] for integer m 1 , (68) becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_118">F X (z) = 1 - α Nsms Γ (N s m s ) m1-1 i=0 (az) i γi i! × ∞ 0 e -az γ (x+1) (x + 1) i x Nsms-1 e -αx dx. (<label>69</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_119">)</formula><p>Using the definition of binomial coefficients, (69) becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_120">F X (z) = 1 - α Nsms Γ (N s m s ) m1-1 i=0 i j=0 (az) i γi i! i j e -az γ × ∞ 0 e -( az γ +α)x x j+Nsms-1 dx. (<label>70</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_121">)</formula><p>Using <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr">Eq. (17.13.3)</ref>], (70) can be written as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>. Defining γ T = γ t + 1, (67) can be expanded, for integer m 2 , as</p><formula xml:id="formula_122">F Y (z) = 1 - α Nsms Γ (N s m s ) β Nrmr Γ (N r m r ) m2-1 i=0 i j=0 (bz) i γi i! i j × Γ (j + N s m s ) bz γ + α j+Nsms ∞ 0 ( y + + 1) i-j e bz γ ( y+ +1)</formula><p>y Nrmr-1 e βy dy. (71)</p><p>Once more, by using the definition of binomial coefficients and [18, Eq. (17.13.3)], (71) simplifies to <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>.</p><p>APPENDIX II: PROOF OF PROPOSITION 2</p><p>The CDF of S 1 , by considering r = γ1 γs+1 and w = γ2 γs+ γr + +1 , can be mathematically expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_123">F γ up S 1 (z) = Pr ( min(r, w) &lt; z) = 1 -Pr ( min(r, w) &gt; z) = 1 -Pr ( r &gt; z, w &gt; z) .</formula><p>The above probability can be alternatively evaluated as f γ1 (x)f γs (y) dxdy .</p><formula xml:id="formula_124">F γ up S 1 (z) = 1 -E γs,γr Pr γ 1 &gt; z (γ s + 1) γ s , γ r × Pr γ 2 &gt; z (γ s + γ r + + 1) γ s , γ r = 1 -1 -E γs,</formula><p>(76) Utilizing <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr">Eq. (2.33.10)</ref>] and <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr">Eq. (8.350.4)</ref>], the first term in (76) can be obtained as we arrive to P 11 (z) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>. Likewise, P 12 (z), P 21 (z) and P 22 (z) can be derived for integer m 2 and m t N t .</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>m = 1 ,Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Outage probability at S 1 (P I is a constant) for m 1 = mt = 2, m 2 = ms = 3, mr = 2.5, Ω 1 = Ω 2 = 1, Ωs = Ωr = Ωt = 0.01, γ 0 = 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>N = 10 ,Fig. 3 . 2 m 1 = 4 m 1 = 1 Fig. 4 .</head><label>103214114</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Outage probability at S 1 (P S /P I is a constant) for m 1 = mt = 2, m 2 = ms = 3, mr = 2.5, Ω 1 = Ω 2 = 1, Ωs = Ωr = Ωt = 0.01, γ 0 = 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Outage probability optimization at S 1 for m 1 = m 2 = ms = mr = 1, Ns = Nr = 6, γ 0 = 3, υ = 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>PΓα</head><label></label><figDesc><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> (z) = E γt,γr α msNs Γ (m s N s )a m1 γm1 Γ (m 1 ) ∞ γt+ γr + ∞ -1 z(y+1)x m1-1 e -ax γ dxy msNs-1 e -αy dy= E γt,γr α msNs Γ (m s N s ) ∞ γt+ γr + Γ m 1 , az γ (y + 1) Γ (m 1 )y msNs-1 e -αy dy .For integer values of m 1 , the above expression becomesP 11 (z) = E γt,γr α msNs Γ (m s N s ) l e -az γ(y+1) y msNs-1 e -αy dy = E γt,γr α msNs e -az γ Γ (m s N s ) az γ +α)y y msNs+r-1 dy (77) where the second equality is obtained by using the definition of binomial coefficients. By solving the integral in (77) utilizing [18, Eq. (2.33.10)], and assuming integer values for m s N s and applying [18, Eq. (8.352.2)]), we haveP 11 (z) = E γt,γr α msNs e -az γ Γ (m s N s ) m s N s + r, α + az γ (γ t + γ r + ) msNs e -az γ Γ (m s N s ) (γ t + γ r + ) i Γ (m s N s + r) α + az γ msNs+r-i e -(α+ az γ )(γt+ γr + ) . (78)By using [34, Eq. (2.1.3.2)], (78) can be written asP 11 (z) = E γt β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) l l-j γl l!i! α msNs e -az γ -(α+ az γ )(γt+ ) Γ (m s N s ) Γ (m s N s + r) α + az γ +β)x x mr Nr+j-1 dx .The above expression admits the following manipulationsP 11 (z)= E γt β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) l l-j γl l!i! α msNs e -az γ -(α+ az γ )(γt+ ) Γ (m s N s ) (γ t + ) r N r + j) α + az γ + β mrNr+j = β mr Nr Γ (m r N r ) η mtNt Γ (m t N t ) α msNs Γ (m s N s ) × e -az γ -( α+ az γ ) r N r + j) α + az γ + β mrNr+j × a l z l l+k-i γl l!i! ∞ 0 e -(α+ az γ +η)y y mtNt+k-1 dy. (79) By integrating over γ t in (79) using [18, Eq. (3.351.3)],</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>n-1 dt is the gamma function [18, Eq. (8.310.1)], and Γ(b, x) =</figDesc><table><row><cell>∞ x e -t t b-1 dt is the upper</cell></row><row><cell>incomplete gamma function [18, Eq. (8.350.2)]. The operator</cell></row><row><cell>E[.] stands for expectation.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Since X and Y are dependent to each other, we utilize the following methodology,F γ up e2e (z) = 1 -Pr min γ up S1 , γ up γs,γt,γr Pr γ 1 ≥ z (γ t + γ r + + 1) , γ t + γ r + + 1 ≥ γ s + 1 γ s , γ t , γ r P 2 (z) = E γs,γt,γr Pr γ 2 ≥ z (γ s + γ r + + 1) , γ s + γ r + + 1 ≥ γ t + 1 γ s , γ t , γ r</figDesc><table><row><cell>APPENDIX III: PROOF OF PROPOSITION 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="9">S2 γ 2 γ s + γ r + + 1 ≥ z S2 ≥ z S1 ≥ z, γ up = 1 -Pr γ up = 1 -Pr min γ 1 γ s + 1 , min γ 2 γ t + 1 , γ 1 γ t + γ r + + 1 = 1 -Pr γ 1 γ s + 1 ≥ z, γ 2 γ s + γ r + + 1 ≥ z, ≥ z, ≥z γ 2 γ t + 1 ≥ z, γ 1 γ ∞ γt+ γr + + E γt,γr γt+ γr + 0 -1 z(γt+ γr+ +1) ∞ -1 z(y+1) ∞</cell><cell>f γ1 (x)f γs (y) dxdy</cell></row><row><cell>F γ up S 1</cell><cell cols="8">(z) = 1 -E γs,γr e -az γ (γs+1)-bz γ (γs+ γr + +1)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">m1-1</cell><cell cols="3">m2-1</cell><cell>(az)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>i=0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">j=0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">m1-1</cell><cell>m2-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>i</cell><cell>j</cell><cell>j-k</cell><cell>i</cell><cell>j</cell><cell>j -k</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">i=0</cell><cell>j=0</cell><cell cols="2">l=0</cell><cell>k=0</cell><cell>t=0</cell><cell>l</cell><cell>k</cell><cell>t</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">×</cell><cell cols="4">(az) i (bz) j ( γ) i+j i!j!</cell><cell cols="2">γ l+k s</cell><cell>t γ t r ( + 1) j-k-t .</cell><cell>(74)</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">By integrating (74) over γ s and γ r , (17) is derived. The proof</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">for F γ up S 2</cell><cell cols="5">(z) follows a similar line of reasoning.</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p>γr F γ1 -1 z (γ s + 1) × 1 -E γs,γr F γ2 -1 z (γ s + γ r + + 1) . (</p>72</p>)</p>By assuming integer values for m 1 and m 2 , we get i (bz)</p>j ( γ) i+j i!j! (γ s + 1) i (γ s + γ r + + 1) j . (</p>73</p>)</p>Using the definition of binomial coefficients, (73) becomes</p>F γ up S 1 (z) = 1 -E γs,γr e -az γ (γs+1)-bz γ (γs+ γr + +1) t + γ r + + 1 ≥ z = 1-E γs,γt,γr Pr γ 1 ≥ z (γ s + 1) , γ 1 ≥ z (γ t + γ r + + 1) γ s , γ t , γ r × E γs,γt,γr Pr γ 2 ≥ z (γ s + γ r + + 1) , γ 2 ≥ z (γ t + 1) γ s , γ t , γ r = 1 -P 1 (z)P 2 (z)</p>(75)</p>where P 1 (z) and P 2 (z) can be expressed as</p>P 1 (z) = E γs,γt,γr Pr γ 1 ≥ z (γ s + 1) , γ s + 1 ≥ γ t + γ r + + 1 γ s , γ t , γ r + E + E γs,γt,γr Pr γ 2 ≥ z (γ t + 1) , γ t + 1 ≥ γ s + γ r + + 1 γ s , γ t , γ r .</p>Now, P 1 (z) can be written in integral form according to P 1 (z) = E γt,γr</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Note that this is a standard methodology in the performance analysis of unidirectional and bidirectional relaying systems affected by interference, which facilitates the, otherwise tedious, mathematical manipulations<ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. More importantly, it guarantees that our asymptotic results are exact.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cooperative diversity in wireless networks: efficient protocols and outage behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Laneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N C</forename><surname>Tse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3062" to="3080" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-12">Dec. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">User cooperation diversitypart I: system description</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sendonaris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Erkip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Aazhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1927" to="1938" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-11">Nov. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dual-hop systems with noisy relay and interference-limited destination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="764" to="768" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-03">Mar. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance analysis of two hop amplify-and-forward systems with interference at the relay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Suraweera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Garg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nallanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="692" to="694" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-08">Aug. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interference-limited relaying transmissions in dual-hop cooperative networks over Nakagami-m fading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Da Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="503" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-05">May 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beamforming amplify-and-forward relay networks with feedback delay and interference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Phan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Duong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Elkashlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-J</forename><surname>Zepernick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Process. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-01">Jan. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance analysis of fixed gain relay systems with a single interferer in Nakagamim fading channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Suraweera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Michalopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yuen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1457" to="1463" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-03">Mar. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outage probability for dual-hop relaying systems with multiple interferers over Rayleigh fading channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="338" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-01">Jan. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spectral efficient protocols for halfduplex fading relay channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rankov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wittneben</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-02">Feb. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance analysis of two-way amplifyand-forward relaying in the presence of co-channel interferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ikki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aïssa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="933" to="939" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-04">Apr. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twoway relaying with multi-antenna sources: beamforming and antenna selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Yeoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Elkashlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Collings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3996" to="4008" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-11">Nov. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Practical physical layer network coding for two-way relay channels: performance analysis and comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H Y</forename><surname>Louie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Vucetic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="764" to="777" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-02">Feb. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beamforming in two-way fixed gain amplify-and-forward relay systems with CCI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Duong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Suraweera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-J</forename><surname>Zepernick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yuen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 2012 IEEE Int. Conf. Commun</title>
		<meeting>2012 IEEE Int. Conf. Commun</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3621" to="3626" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outage performance of two hop AF relaying systems with co-channel interferers over Nakagami-m fading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Da Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Yacoub</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="980" to="982" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-09">Sept. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two-way relaying in interference-limited AF cooperative networks over Nakagami-m fading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Da Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Yacoub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3766" to="3771" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-10">Oct. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outage probability of amplify-and-forward two-way relay interference-limited systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3038" to="3049" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-09">Sept. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-S</forename><surname>Alouini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Digital Communication over Fading Channels</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gradshteyn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ryzhik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Table of Integrals, Series and Products</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The m-distribution-a general formula of intensity of rapid fading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nakagami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Statistical Methods in Radio Wave Propagation</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="36" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two birds with one stone: exploiting direct links for multiuser two-way relaying systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Da Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1362" to="1367" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-05">May 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Upper and lower bounds of two-way opportunistic amplify-and-forward relaying channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1180" to="1183" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-08">Aug. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Wolfram functions site</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wolfram</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://functions.wolfram.com" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance evaluation and optimization of dual-hop communication over Nakagami-m fading channels in the presence of co-channel interferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ikki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aïssa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1149" to="1152" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-11">Nov. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance evaluation and optimization of dual-hop communication over Nakagami-m fading channels in the presence of co-channel interferences</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1149" to="1152" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-08">Aug. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power allocation for bidirectional AF relaying over Rayleigh fading channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tafazolli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-02">Feb. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy-efficient relay selection and power allocation for two-way relay channel with analog network coding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jantti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="816" to="819" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">June 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of channel estimation errors and power allocation on analog network coding and routing in two-way relaying</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tabataba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sadeghi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hucher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pakravan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3223" to="3239" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-09">Sept. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outage performance for decode-and-forward two-way relay network with multiple interferences and noisy relay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="531" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-02">Feb. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exact performance of twoway AF relaying in Nakagami-m fading environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Duong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="980" to="987" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-03">Mar. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance analysis of two-way AF relaying systems over cascaded Nakagami-m fading channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ilhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Process. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="332" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">June 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Error probability analysis of two-way amplifyand-forward relaying in the presence of imperfect channel estimations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ikki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aïssa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 2011 IEEE Int. Symp</title>
		<meeting>2011 IEEE Int. Symp</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1963" to="1967" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Schaum&apos;s Mathematical Handbook of Formulas and Tables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Speigel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lipschutz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>M. G. Hill</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Harmonic mean and end-to-end performance of transmission systems with relays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Hasna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-S</forename><surname>Alouini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-01">Jan. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Prudnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brychkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Marichev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Integrals and Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Direct Laplace Transforms. CRC Publisher</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
