<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Signals, Sensors, and Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Royal Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Stockholm</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D8E1D93E28A87FBDABBFC6D1843371F7</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T03:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Effects of Local Scattering on Direction of Arrival Estimation with MUSIC David Astély, Student Member, IEEE, and Björn Ottersten, Member, IEEE Abstract-In wireless communication scenarios, multipath propagation may cause angular spreading as seen from a base station antenna array. Environments where most energy incident on the array is from scatterers local to the mobile transmitters are considered, and the effects on direction of arrival (DOA) estimation with the MUSIC algorithm are studied. Previous work has studied rapidly time-varying channels and concluded that local scattering has a minor effect on DOA estimation in such scenarios. In this work, a channel that is time-invariant during the observation period is considered, and under the assumption of small angular spread, an approximate distribution for the DOA estimates is derived. The results show that local scattering has a significant impact on DOA estimation in the time-invariant case. Numerical examples are included to illustrate the analysis and to demonstrate that the results may be used to formulate a simple estimator of angular spread. An extension to more general Rayleigh and Ricean fading channels is also included. In addition, results from processing experimental data collected in suburban environments are presented. Good agreement with the derived distributions is obtained. Index Terms-Array signal processing, direction-of-arrival estimation, multipath channels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>T HE USE OF antenna arrays at the base stations of wire- less communication systems has gained much interest. By using multiple antennas and receivers/transmitters, the spatial dimension can be utilized more efficiently. Among the possibilities are improved range, diversity against fading, interference suppression, and spatially selective transmission to reduce interference in the down link <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>Multipath propagation is common in cellular systems. Several replicas of the signal will, in general, be incident on a receiving array. If there is line of sight between the transmitter and the array, most incident energy is likely to concentrate in a single plane wave. When there is no line of sight to the transmitter and energy is received via multipath propagation, the signal can be seen as emitted from a distributed source. In macrocellular environments, base station antennas are placed above rooftops, thereby reducing the near field scattering. In addition, in suburban and rural environments, it may be reasonable to assume that most energy incident on the array originates from scattering local to the mobile <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. The angular spreading of the source as seen from the base station is then likely to be small under most circumstances <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. The scattered signals are received from a narrow angular region.</p><p>Here, time-invariant scenarios with small angular spreading due to local scattering in the vicinity of the mobile are studied. The narrowband case is considered, with the channels modeled as nonfrequency selective. As mentioned above, this would be reasonable for narrowband systems in rural and suburban environments with high antenna placement and limited nearfield scattering. The effects of local scattering at the mobile on DOA estimation with the conventional MUSIC algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> is studied <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The observation period is assumed to be short in comparison with the coherence time of the channel so that the channel may be modeled as time-invariant. Finite sample effects are neglected, and the influence of local scattering on DOA estimation accuracy is analyzed. Local scattering may be viewed as a form of model error. This is because the plane wave model used by the MUSIC algorithm will not describe the observations accurately.</p><p>Local scattering models were first used in studies aimed at determining the separation required between two antennas to obtain effective spatial diversity, i.e., sufficiently low fading correlation <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. It is assumed that there is no direct line of sight between the mobile user and the base station, and the signal is modeled as a superposition of a large number of independent and identically distributed waves. The same approach has been used in, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> to generalize flat Rayleigh fading narrowband channels to the multiple antenna case. With increasing angular spread, the fading tends to decorrelate between the elements of the array. This is advantageous from a diversity point of view <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Several statistical distributions have been proposed for the angles of the incident scattered rays. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, a Gaussian distribution was considered, whereas a uniform distribution is used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Several other distributions may be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, the radius of the local scattering area is estimated to be of the order of 50-100 wavelengths in a suburban area.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the bias and variance of DOA estimates for timevarying channels are studied. The angular spread is assumed small, and the channel realization changes from snapshot to snapshot; thus, the mobile must travel a certain distance between the samples. However, for a system operating in burst mode, like the well-known GSM system <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, the observation periods are short, and the array is sampled at symbol rate. The time variation of the channel between the snapshots may then be neglected, and the analysis in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> is not applicable.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, beamforming using DOA information in time-invariant scattering environments is studied. It is concluded that significant gains in signal quality may be obtained if the DOA is allowed to vary from burst to burst, as compared with using the nominal, actual DOA to the transmitter. Thus, DOA estimation from burst to burst is motivated, and the analysis herein shows how the direction of the steered beam may change from burst to burst.</p><p>This study is motivated by the fact that previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> do not explain the results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> or experimental data results, as those presented in this paper. The effects of local scattering on DOA estimation with a single realization of the channel are studied. The phenomenon may be observed in experimental data collected with test beds, as will be exemplified, and is also of importance for DOA-based beamforming. In addition, the results show how the angular spread may be determined from an ensemble of DOA estimates, which in turn may be useful for downlink beamforming with antenna arrays <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Another possible application where DOA estimates may be used is mobile localization for emergency services. The analysis is applicable to stationary terminals in rural and suburban environments, and it shows how reliable the DOA estimate from a single base station is. Since the estimated DOA varies significantly, one conclusion is that several channel realizations are needed for accurate localization.</p><p>A large number of propagation models <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> and direction of arrival estimators <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> may be found in the literature. The study is limited to the well-known MUSIC algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and to relatively simple channels. Note that one way to model an urban, frequency-selective channel is to use several clusters of local scatterers (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>) to describe the propagation between each mobile transmitter and the receiving array. Several DOA's are then to be associated with each mobile, and the analysis presented holds in this case. For simplicity, the nonfrequency selective case is considered in this initial study, but a possible extension to frequency-selective channels appears straightforward.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows. In Section II, local scattering is described, and the data model is introduced. In Section III, the approach of <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> is followed in the sense that finite sample effects are neglected, and a first-order analysis is carried out. The angular spread is assumed to be small, and the spatial signature is approximated as a linear combination of the nominal array response due to a plane wave and its derivative, which is similar to the generalized array manifold (GAM) model in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Then, using results on projection matrices from <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, the perturbation of the noise subspace caused by the scattering is established. The perturbations of the DOA estimates may then be determined. The central limit theorem is used in Section IV to derive an approximate distribution of the DOA estimates for Rayleigh and Ricean fading. The analysis is then illustrated in Sections V and VII, which contains results from processing experimental data collected in suburban environments. In Section VI, fading environments are considered, and a more general class of perturbations to the assumed plane wave model is studied. It is shown that the DOA estimates will have the same approximate distribution also in this case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PRELIMINARIES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Data Model</head><p>A scenario with mobile transmitters emitting narrowband signals is considered. The speed of the mobiles is assumed to be low so that the coherence time is large compared with the length of the observation period. The scenario may then be viewed as time-invariant. The time dispersion introduced by the multipath propagation is further assumed to be small in comparison with the reciprocal of the bandwidth of the emitted signals. For an array of antennas, the observations may then be modeled as <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> where The th column of , which is denoted , represents the spatial signature, or channel, associated with the signal from transmitter</p><p>The additive noise is modeled as spatially white E and independent of the signals. Furthermore, the signals are spatially noncoherent in the sense that E has full rank. In contrast to <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, scenarios in which may be regarded as constant during the observation period are considered. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the sampling period is large in comparison with the coherence time so that the spatial signatures change from snapshot to snapshot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Local Scattering</head><p>To justify the nonfrequency selective model of (1) and to show how the spatial signatures depend on the spatial distribution of the multipath propagation, consider the contribution from the th user to the array output It is modeled as  is assumed that the smallest time delay is 0. The phenomenon is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>. If all the time delays are small in comparison with the reciprocal of the bandwidth of the signal , the approximation may be used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> where</p><p>This agrees with the model of (1) if the spatial signature is modeled as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(3)</formula><p>The assumption of local scattering near the th user means that (see also Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>) is assumed to be small. In what follows, the angular spread is defined as and the case where , which is the angular spread of all transmitters, is small is considered. Another commonly used measure of angular spread is the standard deviation of the DOA's of the scatterers <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. It may be observed from (3) that the summation of the incident waves will cause the received signal power to vary with the particular realization of the spatial signature, and this phenomenon is a form of fading. When the elements of are modeled as complex Gaussian random variables with zeromean, the channel is said to experience Rayleigh fading <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. This is so because the magnitudes of the elements are Rayleigh distributed. For the nonzero mean case, the magnitudes are Ricean distributed <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. DOA Estimation</head><p>With observations of the array output sampled at times , the sample covariance may be formed. From an eigenvalue decomposition of this sample covariance matrix, an estimated basis for the noise subspace may be formed with the eigenvectors associated with the smallest eigenvalues. The MUSIC algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> calculates the DOA estimates using this estimated basis.</p><p>The aim of the paper is to study how the local scattering will affect the DOA estimates calculated with the MUSIC algorithm. To isolate the effects of the scattering, finite sample effects are neglected. This means that the estimates are calculated using the covariance matrix</p><p>given by E (4)</p><p>Note that the expectation is conditioned on the spatial signatures as a time-invariant scenario is assumed. An estimated basis for the noise subspace may be calculated from the eigenvalue decomposition of the covariance matrix in (4) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> where the eigenvalues have been ordered so that is a diagonal matrix containing the largest eigenvalues of in decreasing order, and the columns of are the corresponding eigenvectors. The columns of are the remaining eigenvectors.</p><p>The MUSIC algorithm calculates the DOA estimates as the minimizing values of the cost function <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> The goal is to describe the distribution of given some statistical assumptions on the channels III. A FIRST-ORDER ANALYSIS In this section, a first-order analysis is carried out. First, each spatial signature is approximated as a linear combination of the nominal array response due to a plane wave and its first order derivative. The first-order perturbation of the sample covariance matrix may then be determined, and from this, the perturbation of the estimated subspace may be established. Finally, the perturbation of the DOA estimate is determined.</p><p>In the general case, the deviation of the sample covariance matrix from the modeled covariance matrix may be due to several phenomena, such as finite sample effects and calibration errors. In here, only the effects of local scattering are studied, and calibration errors and finite sample effects are not considered.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Approximation of the Spatial Signature</head><p>Define the gradient so that a first-order Taylor series expansion of (3) yields <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> This approximation assumes that is small, which is the case when since the neglected terms are of order The framework for additive model errors proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> will be used. To fit the approximate spatial signature model of ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) into this framework, the gain will be associated with the th signal, and it is assumed that This is reasonable since for , means that no signal energy is received from the th transmitter. The received signal is modeled as <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> where and <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> The matrix is diagonal: diag Note that is of order and that it is assumed that the derivatives exist and that they are bounded.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Perturbation of Subspaces</head><p>For the case when the local scattering causes no angular spreading but only fading, it holds that The limiting covariance matrix when the number of observations goes to infinity and the angular spread goes to zero will be referred to as the nominal covariance matrix. It may be written as <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> A basis for the nominal signal subspace may be defined from the eigenvalue decomposition of <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> where is a diagonal matrix containing the largest eigenvalues in decreasing order, and the columns of are the corresponding eigenvectors. Note that is the estimated projection matrix onto the noise subspace for zero angular spread Below, it is shown that the estimates calculated with the nominal covariance matrix will coincide with the nominal DOA's as the scattering will only affect the signal powers. Under the assumption of an unambiguous array, this has no effect on the DOA estimates.</p><p>When local scattering with small angular spread is present, (10) applies, and the observed, limiting sample covariance matrix in (4) may be written as <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> where</p><p>The DOA estimates are calculated using (6) with an estimated basis for the noise subspace Such an estimate is calculated from the the eigenvalue decomposition of in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>. It is now assumed that the angular spreading is small, and the limit as is studied. This means that is small, and It may then be concluded that the difference between the nominal covariance matrix and the observed covariance matrix is small. To see this, note that expansion of ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) gives <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> where terms of order have been neglected. In Appendix A, the projection matrix onto the perturbed noise subspace is related to , and it is shown that if terms that tend to zero faster than are neglected, then</p><p>From ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">16</ref>), it may be seen that the projection of the array response vector onto the estimated noise subspace is approximately equal to the projection of the negative perturbation onto the nominal noise subspace. This relation agrees with <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> and is later used to determine the perturbation of the DOA estimates. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Consistency</head><p>In this section, it is shown that the MUSIC estimates are consistent in the sense that This is the case if the MUSIC cost function obtained from <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> with calculated from an eigenvalue decomposition of as given by ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> converges uniformly to where are calculated from the eigenvalue decomposition of <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. Since estimates calculated with coincide with the nominal DOA's; consistency is then established (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> and the references therein). Consider the difference</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tr</head><p>The norm of the first projection matrix is bounded, and from (32) in Appendix A, it is seen that the second term is Thus, the estimates are consistent in the sense that</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. The MUSIC Estimates</head><p>The DOA estimates calculated with the MUSIC algorithm are given as the minimizing arguments of defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. The estimate of the th DOA calculated with MUSIC therefore satisfies <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> where</p><p>For small angular spread, as , it follows from the consistency that the estimate will only deviate slightly from the nominal DOA. Similar to, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, an approximate expression for may thus be obtained via a first-order Taylor expansion of <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. Equation ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>) may be expanded as <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> where terms that tend to zero faster than have been neglected, and is the limit of as the angular spread tends to zero Using <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> and , it follows that Re and Re The deviation from the nominal DOA is thus proportional to the ratio between the amplitude of the direct wave and the derivative term. The result appears natural since</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Re Im</head><p>Moreover, it may be seen that according to the first-order approximations, the th DOA estimate is affected only by the spreading of the th signal. In the next section, the distribution of the DOA estimate is derived using this expression.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. DISTRIBUTION OF ESTIMATES</head><p>Thus far, the perturbation term has been considered deterministic but small, and in the previous section, the deviation of the estimated DOA from the nominal DOA was shown to be related to the real part of the ratio , where and are related to the parameters of the scattered rays.</p><p>For a fixed position of the mobile transmitter, a certain set of scatterers is seen from the array, and a DOA may be estimated. If the experiment is repeated with the source at another location, a new set of scatterers may be seen. When the transmitter is moved only a small distance (on the order of a wavelength), the power and the DOA's of the scattered rays may be the same, but the phases of the rays will change, and this will change the DOA estimate. Although it is possible to calculate the actual DOA estimate for each scattering scenario, it is more interesting to consider the ensemble of all possible scattering scenarios and model the parameters as random. The induced probability density function (pdf) of the DOA estimate may then be determined.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Rayleigh Fading</head><p>In this case, as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, the number of scattered signals is assumed to be relatively large, and the parameters of the rays are assumed independent and identically distributed (iid). In addition, the amplitude and the phase of each scattered signal are modeled as independent, and the phase is uniformly distributed over Such assumptions are usually made to motivate Rayleigh fading <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, as the elements of the spatial signature in (3) then are approximately complex Gaussian random variables with zero mean, which corresponds to Rayleigh distributed magnitudes.</p><p>In addition to the above-mentioned common assumptions, it is assumed that the DOA of each ray is independent of the other parameters. Let the power be normalized so that all rays Under the stated assumptions, it is reasonable to approximate and in (9) as complex Gaussian random variables. From ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>), it is straightforward to show that E E</p><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">E E E E</formula><p>As in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, assume that is uniformly distributed over the interval Then,</p><p>As mentioned in the introduction, there are many possible DOA distributions to chose from. For small angular spread, the choice of distribution appears not to be critical. For the first-order theory, it is the variance of the perturbations that shape the distribution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Ricean Fading</head><p>The case with a stronger direct wave corresponding to lineof-sight (LOS) with DOA equal to the nominal DOA will also be considered. In a rural environment, this component may be dominant. The amplitude of the received signal will have a Ricean distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, and it is noted that a similar model has appeared in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>.</p><p>The amplitude of the direct wave is modeled as deterministic but unknown, and without loss of generality, it is assumed that is real. Under the assumptions in the previous section, this means that and are approximately Gaussian with means and correlations</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">E E (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">)</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">E E E (<label>24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">)</formula><p>Note that E as the DOA of the direct wave coincides with the nominal DOA. The Rice factor is the ratio between the power in the direct wave and power of scattered paths <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Thus,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Probability Density Functions</head><p>A reasonable modeling assumption is that the rays carrying different emitter signals are independent. For this case, and are independent for From <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>, it follows that the DOA estimates also to first order are independent.</p><p>Define the deviation between the estimated DOA and the nominal DOA as From <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>, is approximately distributed as the real part of the ratio between two independent complex Gaussian variables. In Appendix B, this pdf is derived, and it has the where is the confluent hypergeometric function <ref type="bibr">[28, ch. 13</ref>]. This function is also known as Kummer's function, and a definition is given in (33) in Appendix B. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>, the pdf's for some different values of are plotted. As expected, the pdf becomes narrower with increasing amplitude of the direct wave.</p><p>In the case with Rayleigh fading , the pdf in (25) simplifies to <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3,</ref><ref type="figure">P</ref> is plotted for different in the Rayleigh fading case</p><p>As is seen, in 30% of the cases, the DOA estimate will deviate from the nominal DOA more than</p><p>The estimate will thus vary considerably. To first order, the estimate is unbiased in the sense that the expected value of the DOA estimates will coincide with the nominal DOA's E In Appendix B, the expected value of the magnitude of the angular perturbation E is calculated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">E M (<label>27</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">)</formula><p>which in the Rayleigh fading case is : the standard deviation of the angular multipath distribution. MUSIC and any practical DOA estimator will restrict its search over, at most, the interval</p><p>As is commonly done in the literature on analysis, this restriction has been neglected in order to obtain an approximate expression for the pdf. However, since the tails of the distribution in ( <ref type="formula">26</ref>) decays relatively slowly, as , it is not possible to calculate the second-order moment by integrating over the entire real line, as this would yield infinite variance.</p><p>The behavior is explained in view of Rayleigh fading. For a Rayleigh-fading channel with no angular spreading, it may be shown that the burst SNR has a single sided exponential distribution. The finite sample analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> of the MUSIC algorithm states that the variance is inversely proportional to the SNR. In this case, averaging over all possible SNR's would also give an infinite variance unless the fact that the estimates are restricted to lie in a bounded interval is taken into account.</p><p>As mentioned above, the analysis in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> assumes a small coherence time in comparison with the sampling time so that a large number of realizations of the spatial signatures are observed. The conclusion in that work, which thus addresses a different problem, is that the only effect of local scattering on direction-of-arrival estimation is a bias, which in most cases Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>. Histogram of 1 = 1 0 1 for 5000 estimates compared to the relative frequencies calculated using the derived distribution 24 1 = 5 : is very small. To calculate the bias in the time-invariant case, which is studied in this work, a second-order expansion of the spatial signatures in (3) is needed.</p><p>It is interesting to note that whereas angular spread asymptotically has a minor effect on DOA estimation in the timevarying case <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, it has a significant impact in the timeinvariant case studied here. There is, however, no contradiction between the results presented in here and the work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> since the analysis in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> is not applicable to the problem studied in here.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. NUMERICAL EXAMPLES</head><p>In the simulations, each transmitter was modeled with multipath propagation from iid local scatterers. Each scatterer had a fixed amplitude , a random phase uniformly distributed over , and an angular perturbation from a uniform distribution of width In the Ricean case, a direct wave with amplitude was added.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Single Transmitter</head><p>In the first example, a ULA with six elements and a single transmitter at broadside with nominal DOA was considered. For this case, the estimated signal subspace is simply spanned by the spatial signature</p><p>The DOA was estimated with MUSIC for 2000 realizations of the spatial signature. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>, the average value of is plotted for different values of</p><p>The solid line is the approximate expression for E</p><p>given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">27</ref>), which for this case is The sample averages from the simulations agree well with the theory for small angular spread. In general, the approximation improves as array size decreases.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>, simulation results for the Ricean case are shown. From <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, as M , which means that the curve decays as for large In Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>, a histogram with 5000 DOA estimates calculated with MUSIC is plotted. A six-element ULA was considered, and a single Rayleigh fading transmitter with nominal DOA and angular spread was present. The solid line represents the relative frequencies predicted by the derived pdf. The derived expressions give a relatively good prediction of the pdf of the estimates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Simple Angular Spread Estimator</head><p>In the last example, a noisy scenario was considered, and the problem of estimating the angular spread is addressed. This parameter may be of interest for downlink beamforming in a frequency division duplex (FDD) system <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> as the transmission weights have to be formed using statistics of the signals at another frequency, as compared with the uplink observations.</p><p>Three sources with nominal DOA's and were present. All sources had an average SNR of 10 dB measured at a single sensor. A ULA with eight elements was used, and bursts of length 100 snapshots were collected. For each burst, the spatial signatures were generated as above and held constant during the observation period. In addition, the realizations were modeled as independent from burst to burst. The angular spreads, as seen from the array, were and The MUSIC algorithm was used, and the MUSIC spectrum was calculated only for a region around each nominal DOA. In this way, some of the outliers that appear during fading dips are removed. A total of 5000 bursts were simulated, and the averaged DOA estimates were and which agrees with the previous results. In addition, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> states that E The sample mean of the absolute value of the angular perturbations may be used to form an estimate of the angular spread Using all 5000 bursts, the estimated spreads calculated in this way were and Finite sample effects probably add to the variations of the DOA estimates, and this partially compensates for the discrepancy between theory and experiments for larger spreads.</p><p>Finally, a window of length 100 was considered, meaning that only the estimates from the last 100 bursts were used to estimate the angular spread and average DOA. The sample mean was subtracted from the estimates to determine the angular perturbations. The mean of the absolute value of the angular perturbations was then calculated. By multiplying this sample mean by , an estimate of was calculated. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref>, the transient behavior is neglected, and the estimated angular spreads are plotted. The solid lines represent the true values for</p><p>The DOA estimates may thus be used to calculate rough estimates of the angular spread. VI. GENERALIZATION TO FADING CHANNELS Consider <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> again. In the development so far, the spatial signatures were assumed to approximately satisfy <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref> where, for the special case with local scattering from <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> An extension is now considered in which has a more general form. This includes Rayleigh and Ricean fading scenarios in which the multipath propagation is not confined to local scattering only. If the norm of is small compared with the norm of , the same first-order analysis may be carried out, and the expression for the perturbation of the DOA estimate will be, as given by ( <ref type="formula">20</ref>) Re <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref> It is now assumed that and are independent and complex Gaussian in distribution. The expression in (29) may be recognized as the real part of the ratio of two independent complex Gaussian random variables. It then follows that the estimate will have the same pdf as in the local scattering case given by ( <ref type="formula">25</ref>) but with given by where the relation has been used, and E Thus, the analysis applies to a wide variety of scenarios in which a dominant fading direct wave is present in addition to arbitrary scattering, such as near-field scattering in the vicinity of the array and multipath propagation, that may be modeled as complex Gaussian. However, recall that the channel is nonfrequency selective, meaning that all incident rays are coherent.</p><p>As mentioned previously, one way to model frequencyselective channels is to associate several clusters of local scatterers with each transmitters (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>). In this case, several DOA's are estimated for each mobile (one for each cluster), and the analysis holds for the DOA of each such cluster.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Numerical Example</head><p>Consider a scenario with a two-ray channel with a direct wave 30 dB stronger than a reflection. Both rays are independently Rayleigh fading, meaning that the amplitudes of the two rays are modeled as independent and complex Gaussian. In addition, the rays are coherent. The DOA of the first ray is , and the DOA of the second ray is varied. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8,</ref><ref type="figure">E</ref> is plotted using the result in this section together with sample averages of simulated values. Each sample average was calculated with 1000 MUSIC estimates. This demonstrates that local scattering is not the only phenomenon that causes the DOA estimate to approximately obey the derived pdf.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS</head><p>Data collected in suburban environments from two test beds have been processed. The first system was a test bed for GSM operating at a carrier frequency of about 1800 MHz <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. In the data studied, a single transmitter was present. The second system operated at a carrier frequency of about 800 MHz with FM modulated signals. In the data processed, two transmitters were present on the air simultaneously. The results obtained agreed very well with the developed theory, and the results from the first test bed only, which was the test bed for GSM, are presented.</p><p>A six-column dual polarized patch antenna array with columns spaced 0.47 wavelengths was used. The signals from each polarization were connected to a Butler beamforming network, and the outputs from the center four beams of one polarization were used. The antenna array was mounted on a roof of a building about 40 m above ground, in Düsseldorf, Germany. The environment was suburban with 2-6 floor buildings, and a terminal at a distance of 800-1000 m transmitted GSM bursts. The sampling rate was 270 kHz, and for each burst, 167 samples were taken. The antenna array was calibrated in the sense that the responses of the beamforming network were measured prior to deployment. By examining the eigenvalues of the sample covariance matrix of the array output, it was clear that the signal subspace had rank one and that the SNR was approximately 23 dB. The MUSIC algorithm was applied to estimate one DOA for each burst.</p><p>The power level received in the different beams are different depending on the nominal DOA of the source and the fading. The received power must then be estimated from the multidimensional signal using some sort of model. Angleindependent power estimates such as the average energy of the beams or the maximum eigenvalue will, in the general case with nonzero angular spread, not correspond to a Rayleighdistributed envelope. However, in addition to the antenna array, signals from a reference sector antenna with dual polarization mounted beside the array antenna were collected. The signal from one polarization of this antenna was used to estimate the power level and envelope in each burst. The reason for this is that the envelope will be Rayleigh distributed in a Rayleigh fading environment. A comparison with the Rayleigh distribution may then be made to verify that the signals were collected in a Rayleigh fading environment. Note that the instantaneous power received by the sector antenna is not the same as the power received by the elements of the array as they are placed some wavelengths apart.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9</ref>, a plot of estimated DOA's and power for over 4000 GSM bursts are shown. This corresponds to a measurement time of about 30 s. During this time, there was no direct line of sight between the receiving antenna array and the terminal.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10</ref>, a histogram of the estimated envelopes from the last 3000 bursts is shown. The modulated signal has constant modulus, and the SNR was high. The root of the average received power was therefore taken as an estimate of the envelope. For comparison, the relative frequencies calculated with the Rayleigh distribution are also plotted.</p><p>As the transmitter moved during the experiment, a linear trend was removed from the estimated DOA's. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">11</ref>, a histogram of the detrended DOA estimates for all bursts is shown. For comparison, the relative frequencies calculated with the derived pdf for the Rayleigh fading case are plotted. The parameter was estimated from the DOA estimates by formulating a maximum likelihood estimator using the derived distribution and estimated to be This corresponds to an angular spread of As can be seen from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">11</ref>, the derived distribution gives a good description on how the DOA estimates will behave in an angular spread environment. Data from other bursts were also processed, showing a similar behavior. When multipath propagation from other more distant objects caused frequency selective fading, the situation became more involved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VIII. CONCLUDING REMARKS</head><p>The effects of local scattering on DOA estimation with the MUSIC algorithm were studied. The analysis considered only the effects of the local scattering and neglected finite sample effects and calibration errors. The results show that local scattering has significant impact on DOA estimation for time-invariant scenarios. Numerical examples were included to illustrate the analysis and to demonstrate that the results may be used to formulate simple estimators of angular spread as well. Such an estimate may be used for spatially selective downlink transmission with antenna arrays <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p><p>The results clearly demonstrate that for accurate transmitter localization, the angular spread needs to be taken into account. Examples of how this may be done are found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. One possible approach involves averaging the DOA estimates from several bursts. It may also be possible to form a covariance matrix with data from several bursts. However, care needs to be taken if the system employs frequency hopping  since the array response is frequency dependent. Frequency hopping is an option in the GSM system in which the carrier frequency may be changed between the bursts <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</p><p>The real data processed agreed very well with the theoretical development. However, some care is needed in order to interpret the results. Multipath propagation from local scatterers is</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>amplitude of the th scattered signal; response of the array to a single unit amplitude signal with DOA ; total number of local scatterers associated with the th source. The nominal DOA of the th user is denoted and corresponds to the location. The quantities and denote the arrival angle and time delay of the th scattered signal, respectively, and is the carrier frequency. Without loss of generality, it</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Local scattering.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,128.22,55.02,343.68,194.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Pdf of 1 = 1 0 1 for a 1 = 0; 1; 2; and 4 1 = 2 p 3 :</figDesc><graphic coords="5,97.68,55.02,404.88,324.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig.3. Probability that j 1 0 1 j &lt; for Rayleigh fading a 1 = 0:</figDesc><graphic coords="6,111.72,54.96,376.80,296.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Theoretical and simulated values of Efj 1 0 1 jg for a single Rayleigh fading transmitter.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,120.36,55.02,359.52,285.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Theoretical and simulated values of Efj 1 0 1 jg: Ricean case for different amplitudes a 1 : 24 1 = 5 p 3 8:7 :</figDesc><graphic coords="8,111.90,54.96,376.32,294.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Simple tracking of angular spread. Three Rayleigh fading transmitters.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,113.34,55.02,373.44,289.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Two-ray example. Derived approximate value for Efj 1 jg plotted together with simulated values as the DOA of the second ray is varied. The DOA of the first ray is 0 :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Estimated DOA's and power levels from experimental data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Histogram of estimated envelopes compared to relative frequencies calculated using the Rayleigh distribution.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Histogram of detrended DOA estimates compared to the relative frequencies calculated with the derived distribution ;1 = 2:7 ; a i = 0:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="9,113.34,54.99,373.42,295.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the Swedish National Board for Industrial and Technical Development (NUTEK). The associate editor coordinating the review of this paper and approving it for publication was Prof. Kon Max Wong.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>not the only phenomenon giving rise to such a distribution, which was demonstrated in Section VI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A PERTURBATION OF SUBSPACES</head><p>From the results on projection matrices in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, it is known that <ref type="bibr">(30)</ref> where terms of order have been neglected, and the diagonal matrix is defined as Using <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> and the fact that in (30) gives (31)</p><p>It is straightforward to show that Since , and has full rank so that , it follows that where Using this in (31) leads to (32) and which is <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX B RATIO OF COMPLEX GAUSSIAN VARIABLES</head><p>The pdf of the real part of the ratio of two independent complex Gaussian variables Re with moments given by ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">24</ref>) is derived.</p><p>Note that conditioned on is also complex Gaussian, and as and are independent, we have that given is Gaussian with zero mean and variance Note that this conditional pdf is a function of the magnitude of and that has a Ricean distribution (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>)</p><p>where we used the fact that the variance of is one, and is the modified Bessel function of order zero. The pdf of may then be written as From <ref type="bibr">[28, formula 11.4.28]</ref>, this integral may be written as M which is <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>. Here, M stands for the confluent hypergeometric function <ref type="bibr">[28, ch. 13]</ref>. A second notation is F , and the definition is</p><p>The expected value of may also be calculated as follows. Since E it follows that E M which is <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors are grateful to Ericsson Radio Systems AB, Kista, Sweden, for providing data collected in field trials from their adaptive antenna test bed.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Array processing for wireless communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ottersten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 8th IEEE Signal Process</title>
		<meeting>8th IEEE Signal ess</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-07">July 1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="473" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Space-time processing for wireless communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Paulraj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Papadias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Processing Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-11">Nov. 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Mobile Communications Design Fundamentals</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles of Mobile Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Stuber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of nominal direction of arrival and angular spread using an array of sensors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Trump</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ottersten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Signal Subspace Approach to Multiple Emitter Location and Spectral Estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981-11">Nov. 1981</date>
			<pubPlace>Stanford, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Stanford Univ</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of local scattering on direction of arrival estimation with MUSIC and ESPRIT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Asztély</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ottersten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Acoust., Speech, Signal Process. (ICASSP)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Acoust., Speech, Signal ess. (ICASSP)<address><addrLine>Seattle, WA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-05">May 1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3333" to="3336" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects on correlation between two mobile radio basestation antennas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1214" to="1224" />
			<date type="published" when="1973-11">Nov. 1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross correlation between the envelopes of 900 MHz signmals received at a mobile radio base station site</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Adachi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Feeney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Parsons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Inst. Elect. Eng., F</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="506" to="512" />
			<date type="published" when="1986-10">Oct. 1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simulation performance of a blind adaptive array for a realistic mobile channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Agee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hsia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Veh</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Veh</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-05">May 1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="100" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of fading correlation on adaptive arrays in digital mobile radio</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Salz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Winters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1049" to="1057" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-11">Nov. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The spectrum efficiency of a base station antenna array for spatially selective transmission</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zetterberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ottersten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="651" to="660" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-08">Aug. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An adaptive array for mobile communication systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Millnert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Viberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wahlberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="230" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-02">Feb. 1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of multipath-induced angular spread on direction of arrival estimators in array signal processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Moses</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Söderström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sorelius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE/IEE Int. Workshop Signal Process</title>
		<meeting>IEEE/IEE Int. Workshop Signal ess</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-04">Apr. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The GSM System for Mobile Communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mouly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Pautet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<pubPlace>Palaiseau, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Jitter diversity in multipath environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Norklit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C F</forename><surname>Eggers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Veh</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Veh</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modified array manifold for signal waveform estimation in wireless communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Asztély</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ottersten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 30th Asilomar Conf. Signals, Syst., Comput</title>
		<meeting>30th Asilomar Conf. Signals, Syst., Comput<address><addrLine>Monterey, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-11">Nov. 1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="738" to="741" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overview of spatial channel models for antenna array communication systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ertel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cardieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Sowerby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Personal Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-02">Feb. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two decades of array signal processing research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Krim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Viberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Processing Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-07">July 1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A flexibly configurable spatial model for mobile radio channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Blanz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="371" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-05">May 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A performance analysis of subspacebased methods in the presence of model errors-Part I: The MUSIC Algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Swindlehurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kailath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1758" to="1773" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-07">July 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A generalized array manifold model for communication channels with local scattering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Astély</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ottersten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Swindlehurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Inst. Elect. Eng., Radar, Sonar, Navigation, Special Issue: Antenna Array Process. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">145</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-02">Feb. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Projections on unstructured subspaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Krim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Forster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2634" to="2637" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-10">Oct. 1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">VTS Committee on Radio Propagation, Appendix III-Received Signal Fading Distribution</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-02">Feb. 1988</date>
			<publisher>IEEE Vehicular Technology Society</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Min-norm interpretations and consistency of MUSIC, MODE and ML</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ottersten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Comments On</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2262" to="2263" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-08">Aug. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MUSIC, maximum likelihood, and Cramér-Rao bound</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nehorai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Acoust., Speech, Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="720" to="741" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-05">May 1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameter estimation using a sensor array in a Ricean fading channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V S</forename><surname>Hari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ottersten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPCOM</title>
		<meeting>SPCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-08">Aug. 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Abramovitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stegun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Mathematical Functions</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1964-06">June 1964</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>U.S. Dept. Commerce, Nat. Bureau Stand.</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ericsson/Mannesmann GSM field-trials with adaptive antennas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Forssén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Karlsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Witzschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krug</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Veh</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Veh<address><addrLine>Phoenix, AZ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-05">May 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1587" to="1591" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stockholm, and he is currently head of the Department of Signals, Sensors, and Systems at KTH. His research interests include wireless communications, stochastic signal processing, sensor array processing, and time series analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Astély</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">;</forename><forename type="middle">M S</forename><surname>Licentiate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ph</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">1989, he received the Ph.D. degree in electrical engineering from Stanford University</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lindome, Sweden; Stockholm, Sweden; Provo, UT; Linkoping, Sweden; Stanford, CA; San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ArrayComm Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970. 1995. 1997. 1999. May 1998 to August 1998. 1986. 1996 to 1997. 1991</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Royal Institute of Technology ; Brigham Young University ; Linkoping University ; Department of Electrical Engineering, Linkoping University, the Royal Institute of Technology (KTH), Stockholm, and the Information Systems Laboratory, Stanford University ; Royal Institute of Technology,</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>His research interests include sensor array signal processing and signal processing for wireless communications. Björn Ottersten (S&apos;87-M&apos;89) was born in Stockholm, Sweden, in 1961. Dr. Ottersten is an Associate Editor for the IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON SIGNAL PROCESSING. In 1993, he received the IEEE Signal Processing Society Paper Award</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
