<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">93CBE1272601DAB8179C01D74DB1B066</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TAC.2008.2010897</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T13:15+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flocking of Multi-Agents With a Virtual Leader</head><p>Housheng Su, Xiaofan Wang, Senior Member, IEEE, and Zongli Lin, Fellow, IEEE Abstract-All agents being informed and the virtual leader traveling at a constant velocity are the two critical assumptions seen in the recent literature on flocking in multi-agent systems. Under these assumptions, Olfati-Saber in a recent IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON  AUTOMATIC CONTROL paper proposed a flocking algorithm which by incorporating a navigational feedback enables a group of agents to track a virtual leader. This paper revisits the problem of multiagent flocking in the absence of the above two assumptions. We first show that, even when only a fraction of agents are informed, the Olfati-Saber flocking algorithm still enables all the informed agents to move with the desired constant velocity, and an uninformed agent to also move with the same desired velocity if it can be influenced by the informed agents from time to time during the evolution. Numerical simulation demonstrates that a very small group of the informed agents can cause most of the agents to move with the desired velocity and the larger the informed group is the bigger portion of agents will move with the desired velocity. In the situation where the virtual leader travels with a varying velocity, we propose modification to the Olfati-Saber algorithm and show that the resulting algorithm enables the asymptotic tracking of the virtual leader. That is, the position and velocity of the center of mass of all agents will converge exponentially to those of the virtual leader. The convergent rate is also given. Index Terms-Distributed control, flocking, informed agents, nonlinear systems, virtual leader.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>F LOCKING is the phenomenon in which a large number of agents, using only limited environmental information and simple rules, organize into a coordinated motion. Flocking behavior exists in nature in the form of flocking of birds, schooling of fish, swarming of bacteria, and so on <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Flocking problems have attracted much attention among researchers in biology, physics and computer science for decades <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Recently, there has also been a surge of interest among control theorists in flocking problems, partly due to the wide applications of flocking in many control areas including cooperative control of mobile robots and design of mobile sensor networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. H. Su and X. Wang are with the Department of Automation, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai 200240, China (e-mail: wwwshs@sjtu.edu.cn; xfwang@sjtu.edu.cn).</p><p>Z. Lin is with the Charles L. Brown Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22904-4743 USA (e-mail: zl5y@virginia.edu).</p><p>Color versions of one or more of the figures in this paper are available online at http://ieeexplore.ieee.org.</p><p>Digital Object Identifier 10.1109/TAC.2008.2010897</p><p>The classical flocking model proposed by Reynolds <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> in 1980s consists of three heuristic rules: 1) Separation: avoid collision with nearby flockmates; 2) Alignment: attempt to match velocity with nearby flockmates; 3) Cohesion: attempt to stay close to nearby flockmates. Over the years, many variants of these three rules and additional rules have been suggested, including obstacle avoidance and goal seeking. Many algorithms to realize these rules have also been proposed <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. For example, graph theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and Lyapunov-based approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> have been used to investigate consensus (alignment) problem, local attractive/repulsive potential between neighboring agents to deal with separation and cohesion problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, and artificial potentials <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> and gyroscopic forces <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> for obstacle avoidance. Leader (virtual leader)/follower approach to goal seeking (tracking) problem has also been investigated <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</p><p>Recently, flocking algorithms based on Reynolds flocking model were proposed by a combination of a velocity consensus component with a local artificial potential field <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. In particular, Olfati-Saber <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> provided a theoretical and computational framework for design and analysis of scalable flocking algorithms. This framework includes three flocking algorithms. The first algorithm embodies the three rules of Reynolds and the third algorithm has obstacle avoidance capabilities. The second algorithm is the main flocking algorithm for a group of agents moving in a free space and is aimed at causing the group to track the path of a virtual leader by including a navigational feedback mechanism to every agent. It is assumed in the second algorithm that every agent in the group is an informed agent which has the information of the virtual leader. The benefit of this assumption is that it guarantees that all agents remain cohesive and eventually move with the same velocity. However, such an assumption is in contrast with some phenomena in the nature and may be difficult to implement in engineering applications.</p><p>In some nature examples, few individuals have the pertinent information, such as knowledge of the location of a food source, or of a migration route. For example, a few informed individuals within a fish school are known to be able to guide the school to navigate towards a target, and only about 5% of the bees within a honeybee swarm can lead the group to a new nest site <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. Recently, using a simple discrete-time model of group formation, Couzin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> revealed through simulation that only a very small proportion of informed individuals is required to achieve a great accuracy of group motion in a preferred motion.</p><p>The first objective of this paper is to show that most agents will move with the desired velocity even when only a very small fraction of agents are informed agents in a large group of agents. In particular, under the assumption that the desired velocity is a constant vector, we will prove that the Olfati-Saber algorithm enables all the informed agents to move with the desired velocity, and an uninformed agent to also move with the same desired velocity if it can be influenced by the informed agents 0018-9286/$25.00 © 2009 IEEE from time to time during the evolution. These results will not only help to understand flocking behaviors in the nature, but also provide a framework for guiding the design of engineering multi-agent systems with a small fraction of agents being informed.</p><p>Showing that some uninformed agents can also approach the same desired velocity even when they do not have constant access to one informed agent turns out to be rather involved. Due to the existence of a nonlinear gradient-based term in the control protocol, the graph theory and related stochastic matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> and Lyapunov-based approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, which have been used to study the consensus problems under the assumption of frequent enough network connectivity of the underlying topology, cannot be directly applied to the flocking problems studied in this paper.</p><p>A key step in establishing these results is the application of the LaSalle Invariance Principle, which establishes convergence properties once the boundedness of the trajectories of all agents is guaranteed. When all agents are informed agents, such boundedness property of the trajectories is relatively straightforward consequence of the negative semi-definiteness of the derivative of a certain positive semi-definite function , which is the total artificial potential energy and the total relative kinetic energy between all agents and the virtual leader. However, when not all agents are informed agents, the boundedness of trajectories of those uninformed agents no longer follow directly from the negative semi-definiteness of . A careful examination of the intricate behaviors of these uninformed agents is required. A coordinate system for the collective dynamics of all agents is also adopted which makes the virtual leader as a reference. Such a coordinate system also facilitates the proof that the velocities of the agents eventually match that of the virtual leader as the time goes by.</p><p>In the situation when the velocity of the virtual leader is not a constant vector, Olfati-Saber <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> has shown that his second algorithm is able to cause all the agents in the group to eventually achieve the same velocity, which, however, is in general not equal to the velocity of the virtual leader. This motivates us to propose modification to the Olfati-Saber second algorithm so that the resulting algorithm will enable the asymptotic tracking of the virtual leader. That is, the position and velocity of the center of mass (COM) of all agents will converge exponentially to those of the virtual leader. In establishing this result, we will also obtain the rate of convergence.</p><p>The remainder of the paper is organized as follows. Section II recalls some background materials and motivates the problems to be solved in this paper. Section III establishes flocking results when only a fraction of agents are informed. Section IV deals with the situation when the virtual leader does not move with a constant velocity. Section V includes the results from the simulation study. Finally, Section VI draws a conclusion to the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. BACKGROUNDS AND PROBLEM STATEMENT</head><p>We consider agents moving in an dimensional Euclidean space. The motion of each agent is described by two integrators as <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> where are respectively the position and velocity vectors of agent , and is the (acceleration) control input acting on agent . For notational convenience, we also define . . . . . .</p><p>Each agent has a limited communication capability and it can only communicate with agents within its neighborhood region.</p><p>The neighboring set of agent at time is denoted as:</p><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">)<label>3</label></formula><p>where is the Euclidean norm. In the above definition, we have assumed that all agents have an identical influencing/sensing radius . During the course of motion, the relative distances between agents may vary with time, so the neighbors of each agent may change. We define the neighboring graph to be an undirected graph consisting of a set of vertices , whose elements represent agents in the group, and a set of edges , containing unordered pairs of vertices that represent neighboring relations at time . Vertices and are said to be adjacent at time if . A path of length between vertices and is a sequence of distinct vertices starting with and ending with such that consecutive vertices in the sequence are adjacent.</p><p>In his second algorithm, Olfati-Saber <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> proposes a distributed controller for each agent which only utilizes the information of other agents in its neighborhood and that of the virtual leader. Under his control scheme, agent is steered via its acceleration input that consists of three components <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref> The first component of ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>), , is used to regulate position between agent and its flockmates. This term is responsible for collision avoidance and cohesion in the group and is derived from the field produced by a collective potential function , which depends on the relative distance between agent and its flockmates, and is defined as <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> where the -norm of a vector is a map defined as with a parameter . Unlike the norm , which is not differentiable at , the map is differentiable everywhere. This property of -norm enables the construction of smooth collective potential functions for agents. The function (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>) is a nonnegative smooth pairwise potential function of the distance between agents and , such that reaches its maximum as , attains its unique minimum when agents and are located at a desired distance , and is constant for . The second component of ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>), regulates the velocity of agent to the weighted average velocity of its flockmates. This term is responsible for velocity alignment. The third component of ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>), , is a navigational feedback term, which drives agent to track the virtual leader with the following model of motion, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> where are position, velocity and control input (acceleration) of the virtual leader with . More specifically, the control protocol in the second Olfati-Saber flocking algorithm of <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> is given by, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> where is the adjacent matrix which is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">if if (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">)</formula><p>with the bump function , , being</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">if if otherwise. (<label>9</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">)</formula><p>It is then clear that if and if but . The two positive constants and represent weights of the navigational feedback. We observe that the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> requires all agents to have the knowledge of the virtual leader, . Under the reasonable assumption that the initial velocity mismatch and inertia are finite, Olfati-Saber proved that three rules of Reynolds hold for a group of agents under the influence of the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. In particular, it was established in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> that, the control protocol (7) enables a group of agents to track a virtual leader moving at a constant velocity.</p><p>Motivated by these results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, we will examine in this paper to what extent the control protocol (7) can still perform when not all agents are informed with the knowledge of the virtual leader and how to strengthen this control protocol when the virtual leader moves at a varying velocity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. FLOCKING WITH A MINORITY OF INFORMED AGENTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Algorithm Description and Main Results</head><p>In the flocking control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, it is assumed that each agent is an informed agent who has the information about the virtual leader (i.e., its position and velocity). In this section, we assume that only some, but not all, of the agents are informed agents who are given the information about the virtual leader. Consequently, the control input for agent , <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, is modified as <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> where if agent is informed and otherwise. Without loss of generality, we assume that the first agents are informed agents, that is, for , and for . We further assume that the virtual leader moves along a fixed direction with a constant velocity . Therefore, the dynamic (6) for the virtual leader can be simplified to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> We are interested in the behavior of the whole group of agents in the situation when only a small fraction of the agents are informed agents (i.e.,</p><p>). As an informed agent not only is influenced by the virtual leader but might also be influenced by some uninformed agents, it is not obvious that an informed agent will definitely track the virtual leader, not to mention those uninformed agents. A careful analysis will however show that not only all the informed agents but also some uninformed agents will track the virtual leader. Furthermore, we will carry out extensive simulation to reveal that the majority of the uninformed agents will indeed track the virtual leader even when only a small fraction of a large group of agents are informed agents.</p><p>Before stating the main results of this section, we need the following definition. Denote the union of all neighboring graphs across a nonempty finite time interval , as , whose edges are the union of the edges of those neighboring graphs. For an uninformed agent, if there is a path between this agent and one informed agent in the union , then we say that there exists a joint path between the uninformed agent and the informed agent during the finite time interval</p><p>. We divide all the uninformed agents into two types. An uninformed agent is called a type I uninformed agent if there exists an infinite sequence of contiguous, nonempty and uniformly bounded time-intervals , , such that across each time interval there exists a joint path between this agent and one informed agent. Otherwise, it is called a type II uninformed agent.</p><p>It is important to note that a type I uninformed agent is not required to stay in touch with an informed agent all the time. It only requires to be linked with an informed agent through a joint path during each time interval . Such a joint link is established as long as this type I uninformed agent is connected with an informed agent at any given time instant during the time interval , or it is connected at a time instant during with another type I uninformed agent which is connected with an informed agent at a different time instant during . In other words, a type I uninformed agent is only required to get in touch, directly or indirectly, with an informed agent from time to time.</p><p>As the intervals s are uniformly bounded, a type I uninformed agent will not stay out of touch with an informed agent for a period longer than the bound on these intervals. Thus, there exists a sufficiently large such that, for all , there does not exist any joint path between any type II uninformed agent and any informed agent. This assumption implies that an uninformed agent that is disconnected from all informed agents for a long enough period of time will stays disconnected from them forever. Under this assumption, all the informed agents and type I uninformed agents cannot be influenced by type II uninformed agents directly or indirectly for all . This assumption is reasonable in that it appears to represent a real situation. For example, the probability of a bird that has gone astray for a week coming back to the flock is very low.</p><p>To state the main results of this section, we define the sum of the total artificial potential energy and the total relative kinetic energy between all agents and the virtual leader as follows, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> We note that is a nonnegative valued function.</p><p>Our analysis results can then be summarized in the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 1: Consider a system of mobile agents, each with dynamics (1) and steered by the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>. Suppose that the initial energy is finite. Then the following statements hold:</p><p>i) The distance between each informed agent and the virtual leader is not greater than for all ; ii) The velocities of all informed agents and type I uninformed agents approach the desired velocity asymptotically. iii) If the initial energy of the group is less than , , for some , then at most distinct pairs of agents could possibly collide ( guarantees a collision free motion).</p><p>The proof is carried out next in Sections III-B-III-D. Before we carry out this proof, we define the Laplacian of graph with adjacent matrix as , where the degree matrix is a diagonal matrix with the th diagonal element being</p><p>. Denote the eigenvalues of as . Then, and is the corresponding eigenvector. Moreover, if is a connected graph, then <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. The corresponding dimensional graph Laplacian is defined as , where is the identity matrix of order and stands for the Kronecker product. This multi-dimensional Laplacian satisfies the following sum of squares property <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> where . . . and for .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Cohesive Analysis</head><p>We first carry out the cohesiveness analysis, which contains the proof of Part i) of Theorem 1.</p><p>Denote the position difference vector and the velocity difference vector between agent and the virtual leader as and , respectively. We have <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> Let and . Clearly, , and hence the collective potential function ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) can be rewritten as <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> Similarly, the control protocol for agent is rewritten as <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> and the nonnegative valued energy function ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>) can be rewritten as and by ( <ref type="formula">15</ref>),</p><p>where . Therefore, the derivative of along the trajectories of the agents and the virtual leader is given by, is also a positive semi-definite matrix. Therefore, , which implies that is a non-increasing function of time and thus for all . It then follows from ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>) that for any informed agent . Hence, the distance between an informed agent and the virtual leader is not greater than for all .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Velocity Matching Analysis</head><p>We now continue with the asymptotic velocity matching analysis, which contains the proof of Part ii) of Theorem 1.</p><p>From Part i) of Theorem 1, the distance between any informed agent and the virtual leader is finite for all . It follows from ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>) that , , or equivalently, , . That is, the velocity difference between any agent and the virtual leader is not greater than for all . Since there exists a joint path between a type I uninformed agent and one informed agent in each finite time-interval , , the distance between any type I uninformed agent and virtual leader is also finite for all .</p><p>Let , , be the total number of informed agents and Type I uninformed agents in the group. Without loss of generality, we label type I uninformed agents from to . By definition, all the informed agents and the type I uninformed agents cannot be influenced by a type II uninformed agents directly or indirectly for all . For any , we consider the positive semi-definite function <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> and . . . . . . From ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>), it is clear that . The derivative of along the trajectories of the agents and the virtual leader is given by, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> where with if if and . . . . . . . . . . . .</p><p>Following the similar analysis that led to , we can arrive at that and consequently, for all , where . Clearly, the set of all such that , that is is an invariant set. We next show that it is also a compact set. By ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">24</ref>), , for all , and hence all , , are bounded. Similarly, all , , are bounded, that is, the positions of all informed agents are bounded. We next consider , . Each of these 's is the position of a type I uninformed agent, whose distance to an informed agent is, by the definition of the type I uninformed agents, bounded, due to the facts that the velocity of each agent is bounded and that the time intervals are uniformly bounded. Consequently, the positions of all type I uninformed agents are also bounded. This shows that the set is compact. It then follows from the LaSalle Invariance Principle <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> that all trajectories of the agents that start from will converge to the largest invariant set inside the region Denote the set of all the informed agents and type I uninformed agents as . During the evolution, the graph , , may not always be connected. Suppose that consists of , connected subgraphs for any and there are agents in the th, , connected subgraph at time . Clearly, . A connected subgraph is called an informed connected subgraph if it includes at least one informed agent. We assume that the graph consists of , informed connected subgraphs.</p><p>As in the earlier analysis, we have that both and are positive semi-definite. Thus, it follows from ( <ref type="formula">25</ref> </p><p>Clearly, if and only if <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref> By the sum of squares property <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>,</p><p>Therefore, ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>) is equivalent to <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref> Similarly, for any , we have 0 pT H(t) I n p = 0 ( p1 ) T 1 11 pm (t) T 1 11 </p><p>where is the diagonal matrix associated with the th connected subgraph with the th diagonal element , which is equal to one for an informed agent and zero for an uninformed agent.</p><p>Clearly, if and only if <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref> which implies that the velocity difference between all informed agents and the virtual leader is zero. Since there is at least one informed agent in each informed connected subgraph, without loss of generality, we assume that the first agent in each informed connected subgraph is an informed agent. We have <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref> In view of ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>), ( <ref type="formula">31</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">32</ref>),</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>if and only if and</head><p>We next show that, for , all connected subgraphs are informed connected subgraphs, i.e., for large enough. This would imply that the velocities of all informed agents and type I uninformed agents approach the desired velocity asymptotically. To this end, let us assume that the interaction network switches at time , i.e., at time , either an agent is disconnected from another agent or an agent is connected with another agent . In either case, we have . It then follows from ( <ref type="formula">25</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">27</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">30</ref>) that which contradicts with the fact that . Thus, we conclude that the interaction network will not switch for all . By their definition, all type I uninformed agents must have a path to one informed agent in the fixed interaction network for all . Consequently, for all .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Collision Avoidance Analysis</head><p>Finally, we proceed to carry out the collision-avoidance analysis, which contains the proof of Part iii) of Theorem 1.</p><p>In view of ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>), is a non-increasing function of time and thus for all . The rest of the proof of this part is similar to that of part (iv) of Theorem 2 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Suppose that the initial energy is less than and more than distinct pairs of agents collide at a given time , i.e., at least distinct pairs of agents collide at time . Then, at time , the collective potential of the system is at least . Recalling that for all , we have which contradicts the assumption that . This shows that no more than distinct pairs of agents can possibly collide at any time . Consequently, if , no collision will occur.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. FLOCKING WITH A VIRTUAL LEADER OF VARYING VELOCITY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Algorithm Description and Main Result</head><p>In the situation where all agents are informed agents and the virtual leader move with a constant velocity , Theorem 1 guarantees that all agents will finally move with the desired velocity . In the situation where the velocity of the virtual leader varies with time, even though it has been established in Theorem 2 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> that all agents in the group can finally achieve a common velocity, this common velocity in general does not match . In this section, we focus on the situation where the virtual leader move with a varying velocity. In order for the common velocity of all the agents to match that of a virtual leader of varying velocity, , we propose to incorporate the information of acceleration of the virtual leader into the protocol (7) as follows, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> Denote the position and velocity of the center of mass (COM) of all agents in the group as The sum of the total artificial potential energy and the total relative kinetic energy between all agents and the virtual leader in this case is defined as follows, (</p><p>Note that is a nonnegative valued function. Our main results on the tracking of the virtual leader can then be stated in the following theorem, whose proof will be carried out in Section IV-B below.</p><p>Theorem 2: Consider a system of mobile agents, each with dynamics (1) and steered by the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>. Suppose that the initial energy is finite. Then the following statements hold:</p><p>i) The distance between any agent and the virtual leader is not greater than for all ; ii) The velocity of each agent approaches the desired velocity asymptotically; iii) If both the initial velocity and position of the COM are equal to the initial velocity and position of the virtual leader, then the velocity (or position) of the COM will be equal to the velocity (or position) of the virtual leader for all ; otherwise the velocity (or position) of the COM will converge exponentially to the velocity (or position) of virtual leader with a time constant , where if if ; iv) Almost every configuration the system approaches is a local minimum of the total artificial potential energy ; v) If the initial energy of the group of agents is less than , , for some , then at most distinct pairs of agents could possibly collide ( guarantees a collision-free motion).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Theoretical Analysis</head><p>We first prove Part i) of Theorem 2. Denote the position difference vector and the velocity difference vector between agent and the virtual leader as and , respectively. Then, (36) for , (47) and for , see (48), shown at the bottom of the page, where and are initial position and velocity of the COM of the group, and and are the initial position and velocity of the virtual leader. The solution (46)-(48) indicates that, if and , then the position and velocity of the COM will be equal to those of the virtual leader for all , otherwise they will converge exponentially to those of the virtual leader with a time constant of when , or when . This completes the proof of Part iii).</p><p>We now prove Part iv) of Theorem 2. From (44), we see that, in steady state, which implies that . It thus follows from (37) and ( <ref type="formula">40</ref>) that (49) Thus, the configuration converges asymptotically to a fixed configuration that is an extremum of . If the solution of (49) starts at the an equilibrium, which is local maxima or saddle points, the solution will invariant at all time. Then, not all solutions of (49) converge to local minima. However, any point but a local minimum is an unstable equilibrium <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Thus, almost every configuration the system approaches is a local minimum of the total artificial potential energy . Finally, we prove Part v) of Theorem 2. From the earlier analysis, we recall that . The results then follow the same arguments as used in the proof of Part iii) of Theorem 1. This completes the proof of Theorem 2.</p><p>By comparing the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> with the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>, we observe that the information of both the acceleration and velocity of the virtual leader is sufficient to guarantee every agent to track a virtual leader of varying velocity.</p><p>The information of velocity alone cannot guarantee the group to achieve desired velocity.</p><p>We recall that Shi et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> proposed another algorithm to track a virtual leader, in which every agent in the group only knows the information of velocity of the virtual leader. With the assumption of the neighboring graph is always connected, all the agents can achieve stable flocking motion, but can only track a desired constant velocity. This assumption is also difficult to implement in practice. Without the information of position of the virtual leader, convergence cannot be guaranteed in arbitrary switching information exchange topology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. SIMULATION STUDY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Flocking With a Fraction of Agents Informed</head><p>Simulation was performed on 100 agents moving in a 2-dimensional space under the influence of the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>. Initial positions and initial velocities of the 100 agents were chosen randomly from the boxes [0,55] [0,55] and [0,0.01] [0,0.01], respectively, and the initial position and velocity of the virtual leader were set at and . The influencing/sensing radius was chosen as , the desired distance , for the -norm, for the bump function , and . Some simulation results are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>. In the figure, the solid lines represent the neighboring relations, the solid lines with arrows represent the velocities, and the hexagram represents the desired position, which is where the virtual leader is. There are ten informed agents which are chosen randomly from the group and marked with circles. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>(a) shows the group initial state which is highly disconnected. As time evolves, the size of the largest cluster increases and more and more agents move with the same velocity. Eventually, 86 of the 100 agents move with the desired velocity (see plot (f)).</p><p>To further substantiate the results shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>, we ran extensive simulations on groups of different sizes. In order for the comparison to be reasonable, initial positions of the agents were chosen randomly from a box so that the density is fixed at . Initial velocities of the agents were chosen randomly from [0,4] [0,4], and the initial position and velocity of the virtual leader were set at and . The influencing/sensing radius was set at , the desired distance , for the -norm, for the bump function , and . We randomly select a fraction of the agents as the informed agents. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3</ref> shows the relationship between the frac-tion of the agents that eventually move with the desired velocity and the fraction of the informed agents with , 300, 500 and 1000, respectively. All estimates are the results of averaging over 50 realizations. Obviously, for any given group size , the fraction of agents that move with the desired velocity is an increasing function of the fraction of informed agents. Furthermore, the larger the group, the smaller the fraction of informed agents is needed to guide the group with a given fraction . For example, in order for 80% of the agents to move with the same desired velocity, about 27% of the agents should be informed agents when the group size is , but only about 10% of the agents need to be the informed agents when the group has agents. Thus, for sufficiently large groups, only a very small fraction of informed agents will guide most agents in the group.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Flocking With a Virtual Leader of Varying Velocity</head><p>Simulations for protocol (7) (algorithm 2 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>) and protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> were performed with ten agents moving in a 3-dimensional space, and a virtual leader whose acceleration function satisfies the Lorenz equation (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4</ref>), Simulation results are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref>. In the simulation, initial positions and velocities of the ten agents were chosen randomly from the same cube , and the initial position and velocity of the virtual leader were set at and . The influencing/sensing radius was chosen at , the desired distance , for the -norm, for the bump function , and . The solid lines in the figures represent the neighboring relations, the dotted lines with arrows represent the agent velocities, and the hexagram represents the desired position. In both Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref>, plot (a) shows the initial states of the agents; plot (b) presents the configuration and velocities of the group of agents at ; plot (c) depicts the motion trajectories of all agents from to 30 seconds; plot (d) shows the convergence of velocity, from which we can see that all the agents eventually achieve the same velocity; plots (e) and (f) depict the position and velocity difference between the COM and the desired position and velocity , respectively.</p><p>It is obvious from Figs. 5 and 6 that both control protocols ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">33</ref>) are capable of achieving stable flocking motion. Under the protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, the position and velocity of the COM fluctuate around those of the virtual leader (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>, plots (e) and (f)). However, under the protocol (33), the position and velocity of the COM converge exponentially to those of the virtual leader [see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref>, plots (e) and (f)].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Flocking With a Fraction of Agents Informed and a Virtual Leader of Varying Velocity</head><p>This section presents simulation results for the situation when only a fraction of agents are informed agents and in the same time, the velocity of the virtual leader is varying with time. The control protocol for agent is naturally chosen as, where if agent is an informed agent, and otherwise. Simulation results are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7</ref>. In the simulation, the acceleration vector of the virtual leader was selected as and all other parameters were chosen as those in the simulation shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>. Plot (a) shows the group initial state, which is highly disconnected. As time evolves, the size of the largest cluster increases and more and more agents move with the same velocity. Eventually, 89 of the 100 agents move with the desired velocity [see plot (f)].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, a flocking algorithm proposed by Olfati-Saber for a group of agents to track a virtual leader is extended from two directions. First, the flocking algorithm is generalized to the case that only a fraction of agents are informed agents. We established that all the informed agents will move with the desired velocity. Furthermore, if an uninformed agent can be influenced by the informed agents from time to time during the evolution, this uninformed agent will also move with the desired velocity. We demonstrate numerically that a very small proportion of informed agents can make most of agents move with the desired velocity, and the larger the group the higher is the proportion of agents that will eventually move with the desired velocity. Second, we modified the algorithm for a group of agents in order to track a virtual leader of varying velocity.  Moreover, we established that the position and velocity of the COM will converge exponentially to those of virtual leader. The convergent rate was also given.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Manuscript received January 04, 2008. Current version published February 11, 2009. This work was supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under Grants 60521002 (the Creative Research Groups Program), 70431002, 60674045, and 60428303 (Outstanding Young Investigator Program, Class B: Overseas Collaboration). Recommended by Associate Editor C. Abdallah.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Smooth pairwise potential function .</figDesc><graphic coords="3,47.34,66.78,232.00,189.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>semi-definite function of . Due to the symmetry of the pairwise potential function and the adjacent matrix , we have (20)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. 2-D flocking for 100 agents applying algorithm (10) with 10 informed agents.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Fraction of agents with the desired velocity as a function of the fraction of informed agents. All estimates are the results of averaging over 50 realizations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. The attractor of Lorenz system.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. 3-D flocking for 10 agents applying Algorithm 2 in [29]. (a) Initial state; (b) configuration and velocities at t = 30 s; (c) trajectories of all agents; (d) velocity convergence; (e) position difference between the COM and q (t); (f) velocity difference between the COM and p (t).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. 3-D flocking for 10 agents applying Algorithm (33). (a) Initial state; (b) configuration and velocities at t = 30 s; (c) trajectories of all agents; (d) velocity convergence; (e) position difference between the COM and q (t); (f) velocity difference between the COM and p (t).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. 2-D flocking for 100 agents with 10 informed agents and a virtual leader of varying velocity.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors would like to thank the Associate Editor and the reviewers for their insightful comments and suggestions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We will also denote . . . . . . Thus, the control protocol for agent , <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>, can be rewritten as (37)</p><p>From the previous analysis, we recall that the collective potential function (5) can be rewritten as</p><p>Also, the nonnegative valued function (34) can be rewritten as </p><p>Therefore, the derivative of along the trajectories of the agents and the virtual leader is given by, (42) Recalling that is a positive semi-definite matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, we have , which implies that is a nonincreasing function of time and thus for all . From (39) and (40), we have for any agent . Therefore, the distance between any agent and the virtual leader is not greater than for all . We now proceed to prove Parts ii) and iii) of Theorem 2. Since is positive definite and , the set is a compact invariant set. It then follows from the LaSalle Invariance Principle that all trajectories of the agents that start from converge to the largest invariant set inside the region From (42), we have The solution of (45) can be obtained in three separate cases. For ,</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fish in schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Natural History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical aspects of animal grouping: Swarms, schools, flocks and herds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Okubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Biophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flocks, herds, and schools: A distributed behavioral model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Comput. Graphics, ACM SIGGRAPH&apos;87 Conf</title>
		<meeting>Comput. Graphics, ACM SIGGRAPH&apos;87 Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="34" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel type of phase transition in a system of self-deriven particles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vicsek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cziro'ok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ben-Jacob</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shochet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1226" to="1229" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self organization in systems of self-propelled particles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rappel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective motion in a system of motile elements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shimoyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sugawara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mizuguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hayakawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3870" to="3873" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatio-temporal order in populations of self-aligning objects: Formation of oriented patches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mogilner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Edelstein-Keshet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="367" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A non-local model for a swarm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mogilner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Edelstein-Keshet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="534" to="570" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flocks, herds, and schools: A quantitative theory of flocking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Toner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4828" to="4858" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrodynamics and phases of flocks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Toner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">318</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="244" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey on sensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Akyildiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sankarasubramniam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cayirci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-08">Aug. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flocking of autonomous unmanned air vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Crowther</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aeronaut. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1068</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavior-based formation control for multirobot teams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Balch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Arkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robotics Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="926" to="939" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-12">Dec. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus problems in networks of agents with switching topology and time-delays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Olfati-Saber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1520" to="1533" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-09">Sep. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus seeking in multi-agent systems under dynamically changing interaction topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="655" to="661" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-05">May 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lyapunov-based approach to multi-agent systems with switching jointly-connected interconnection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="943" to="948" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-05">May 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability analysis of swarms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Passino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="692" to="697" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-04">Apr. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability analysis of M-dimensional asynchronous swarms with a fixed communication topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Passino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Polycarpou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-01">Jan. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time obstacle avoidance for manipulators and mobile robots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Khatib</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flocking with obstacle avoidance in switching networks of interconnected vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tanner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Automat</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Automat</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-04">Apr. 2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3006" to="3011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flocking with obstacle Avoidance: Cooperation with limited communication in mobile networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Olfati-Saber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 42nd IEEE Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>42nd IEEE Conf. Decision Control</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-12">Dec. 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2022" to="2028" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collision avoidance for multiple agent systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shadden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Marsden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Olfati-Saber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 42nd IEEE Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>42nd IEEE Conf. Decision Control</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-12">Dec. 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="543" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coordination of groups of mobile agents using nearest neighbor rules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jadbabaie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="988" to="1001" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-06">Jun. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual leader approach to coordinated control of multiple mobile agents with asymmetric interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">213</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Formation with a mission: Stable coordination of vehicle group maneuvers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ogren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Symp. Math. Theory Network Syst</title>
		<meeting>Symp. Math. Theory Network Syst</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-08">Aug. 2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="22" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual leaders, artificial potentials and coordinated control of groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Leonard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Friorelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 40th IEEE Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>40th IEEE Conf. Decision Control<address><addrLine>Orlando, FL</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-12">Dec. 2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2968" to="2973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable flocking of mobile agents, part I: Fixed topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tanner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jadbabaie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pappas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 42nd IEEE Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>42nd IEEE Conf. Decision Control</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-12">Dec. 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2010" to="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable flocking of mobile agents, part II: Dynamic topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tanner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jadbabaie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pappas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 42nd IEEE Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>42nd IEEE Conf. Decision Control</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-12">Dec. 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2016" to="2021" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flocking for multi-agent dynamic systems: Algorithms and theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Olfati-Saber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-03">Mar. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effective leadership and decision-making in animal groups on the move</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Couzin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krause</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Franks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">433</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="516" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Algebraic Graph Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Godsil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Royle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">207</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Horn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Matrix Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, U.K.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Khalil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Nonlinear Systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Upper Saddle River, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He received the B.S. degree in automatic control and the M.S. degree in control theory and control engineering from Wuhan University of Technology</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">His research interests lie in the areas of multi-agent coordination control theory and its applications to autonomous robotics and mobile sensor networks</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>China; Wuhan, China; Shangai, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2002 and 2005, respectively, and is currently pursuing the Ph.D. degree in control theory and control engineering at Shanghai Jiao Tong University</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">His research interests include analysis and control of complex dynamical networks. Dr. Wang received the National Science Fund for Distinguished Young Scholars of China Award in 2002 and the Best Transactions Paper Award from the IEEE Circuits and Systems Society in 2005. Zongli Lin (S&apos;90-M&apos;94-SM&apos;98-F&apos;07) received the B.S. degree in mathematics and computer science from Xiamen University</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Xiaofan</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lin was an Associate Editor of the IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON AUTOMATIC CONTROL (2001-2003) and the Corresponding Editor for Conference Activities of the IEEE CONTROL SYSTEMS MAGAZINE</title>
		<title level="s">the M.Sc. degree in computational mathematics from Nanjing Normal University</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Jiangsu, China; Nanjing, China; Nanjing; Shanghai, China; Xiamen, China; Pullman</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Control Systems Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986. 1996. 1994. 2005-2007</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Shanghai Jiao Tong University ; Washington State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>He currently serves on the editorial boards of several journals, including Automatica, Systems &amp; Control Letters. He is an elected member of the Board of Governors of the</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
