<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Variational Approach for Edge-Preserving Regularization Using Coupled PDE&apos;s</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Sylvie</forename><surname>Teboul</surname></persName>
							<email>teboul@alto.unice.fr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laure</forename><surname>Blanc-Féraud</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gilles</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Michel</forename><surname>Barlaud</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire Informatique Signaux et Systèmes de Sophia Antipolis</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06560</postCode>
									<settlement>Valbonne</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire J. A. Dieudonné</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">URA 168 du CNRS</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Université de Nice-Sophia Antipolis</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06108, Cedex 2</postCode>
									<settlement>Nice</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Variational Approach for Edge-Preserving Regularization Using Coupled PDE&apos;s</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">83254793863F4F64A6C4993B0B150A32</idno>
					<note type="submission">received November 1, 1996; revised March 13, 1997.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T14:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Anisotropic diffusion</term>
					<term>edge-preserving regularization</term>
					<term>Mumford-Shah functional</term>
					<term>segmentation</term>
					<term>systems of coupled PDE&apos;s</term>
					<term>variational approach</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper deals with edge-preserving regularization for inverse problems in image processing. We first present a synthesis of the main results we have obtained in edge-preserving regularization by using a variational approach. We recall the model involving regularizing functions ' and we analyze the geometry-driven diffusion process of this model in the threedimensional (3-D) case. Then half-quadratic theorem is used to give a very simple reconstruction algorithm. After a critical analysis of this model, we propose another functional to minimize for the edge-preserving reconstruction purpose. It results in solving two coupled partial differential equations (PDE's): one processes the intensity, the other the edges. We study the relationship with similar PDE systems in particular with the functional proposed by Ambrosio-Tortorelli [1], [2] in order to approach the Mumford-Shah functional [3] developed in the segmentation application. Experimental results on synthetic and real images are presented.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>T HIS PAPER deals with edge-preserving regularization for inverse problems in image processing. During the last few years, much work has been done in nonlinear regularization for image reconstruction, often involving stochastic models such as Markov random fields (MRF's) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, or variational approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> with partial differential equations (PDE's) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. The regularization of the inverse problem requires smoothing homogeneous areas of the object without degrading edges (which are an important attribute of the object). Clearly, the location of these edges are unknown and must be detected at the same time as the object is reconstructed and regularized.</p><p>In the second section of this paper, we analyze the main results that we have obtained in edge-preserving regularization using a variational approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. We invoke the model involving regularizing functions , as well as the half-quadratic theorem which yields a very simple reconstruction algorithm. We then add an analysis of the geometry-driven diffusion process of this model in the three-dimensional (3-D) case.</p><p>In the next section of the paper, we propose a new functional minimization for edge-preserving reconstruction. In this case, two coupled PDE's must be solved: one dealing with image intensity and the other with the edges. We study the relationship with similar PDE systems already proposed by several authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. We also show the relationship between our model and the functional proposed by Ambrosio and Tortorelli <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> in order to approximate the minimum of the Mumford-Shah functional <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> developed for segmentation applications. Finally, experimental results on synthetic and real images are given.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. EDGE-PRESERVING REGULARIZATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Statement of the Problem</head><p>In this paper we consider the general problem of recovering unknown data from noisy observed data . In many computed imaging applications, unknown data are related to observed data through a linear model of the form <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> where is assumed to be white Gaussian noise, and is a linear operator defined on or respectively depending on image or object reconstruction. Regardless of the application, solving (1) is an ill-posed problem and regularization is necessary. For simplicity, we hereafter assume that . However, all results presented in this paper (theoretical and experimental) can be achieved in the more general framework of image or object reconstruction (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> for a fully 3-D cone-beam reconstruction in nuclear medicine).</p><p>In order to estimate from , we minimize a criterion of the form <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> where is an open bounded set in or , is the modulus of the gradient of , and is a regularization parameter which balances the influence between the two terms of (2). The choice of the function as an edge-preserving regularization function is addressed next in Section II-B. In the following, is assumed to be an even function of class . Note that in the Markov model, is the potential function of the Gibbs energy and minimizing defined in (2) corresponds to statistical MAP (maximum a posteriori) estimation <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>It is shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> that a function convex and linear at infinity ensures the existence and uniqueness of a solution of (2) in BV( ) (the space of functions with bounded variation). Similar results for total variation case are shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Of course, the nonconvexity of will give an ill-posed problem; for example Min <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref> does not have solution. The analysis of this section is justifiable only if is convex however we use nonconvex functions later in our experiments because of their better results, even if the theory is not in favor of this idea.</p><p>In the discrete case, the problem is quite different: when is nonconvex, the solution of Min ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>)</p><p>for example, is known to exist, while uniqueness and stability of this solution remains an open problem. Yet, the following study is presented for the continuous case for reasons of clarity. Minima of (2), if they exist, formally verify the Euler-Lagrange equation div <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> where represents a vector normal to the boundary of , and div stands for the divergence operator defined by div <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> The nonlinear equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) is closely related to the anisotropic diffusion equation of Perona and Malik <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, and extensive work on anisotropic diffusion using nonlinear PDE's <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, a noisy image is restored by solving a dynamic equation of the form div <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> Equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) can be solved by using a gradient-descent method or, equivalently, by using a dynamic scheme wherein is a scale parameter div <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> The nonlinear PDE (8) corresponds to the anisotropic diffusion equation of Perona and Malik <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, where an additional term forces the solution to remain close to the data . Due to this term, any initial condition for can be taken in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>. In literature using the PDE approach, the weighting function is called the conduction coefficient, which corresponds in our case to the weighting function .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Edge-Preserving Functions</head><p>In order to encourage smoothing within a region and discourage smoothing across boundaries, we have proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> the following conditions on the weighting function . i)</p><p>: isotropic smoothing in homogeneous areas. ii)</p><p>: preservation of edges. iii) strictly decreasing: to avoid instabilities. must be finite: an infinite value of would introduce numerical problems in the algorithm given in Section II-C. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, a thresholding property is added in order to have a forward diffusion (smoothing) in homogeneous areas and a backward diffusion (sharpening) around edges. In this case, the corresponding criterion is nonconvex, leading to edge enhancement <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, while conditions i-iii can include both convex or nonconvex functions.</p><p>Let us now define properties on the functions inspired by geometry-driven diffusion for the 3-D case. Let be the unit vector in the gradient direction if and let be two orthonormal vectors in the plane orthogonal to the gradient. Locally, an edge of the volume (which generates a strong gradient), is represented by a level surface . The vector is orthogonal to and the plane is tangential to . It can be shown (see Appendix) that the Euler equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) can be formally developed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> where stands for the second derivative of in thedirection. Equation ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) is independently mentioned in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. If is small, we assume the region be locally homogeneous; thus, in order to have isotropic 3-D smoothing, the weights of and should be equal. We assume and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> which is equivalent to condition i, as follows:</p><p>(11)</p><p>Then, since we have , (9) reduces to <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> which corresponds to isotropic diffusion as given by the standard heat equation.</p><p>In the neighborhood of an edge, is high across the level surface. To preserve edges, the diffusion process must SUMMARY OF SOME ' FUNCTIONS be stopped in the gradient direction while the smoothing remains only in the tangential plane . Since ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) can be written for any orthonormal vectors in the tangential plane, the smoothing will be isotropic in the tangential direction of the level surface. We would like to have and (</p><p>However, these two conditions are conflicting. We relax the second condition, and we assume that the smoothing coefficient in the -direction vanishes more rapidly than the coefficient in the direction, i.e., and ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) The third equality of ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) defines an additional condition on according to conditions i)-iii). This property is investigated for several functions in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref>.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref> lists some commonly used regularizing functions together with some of their properties. The convexity property is, of course, important in regards to the minimization process, as it ensures existence and uniqueness of the minimum.</p><p>The first function is quadratic and corresponds to the Tikhonov standard regularization which is obviously not edge-preserving.</p><p>The second function leads to the minimization of the total variation of , which is a common regularizing criterion <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The second and the third functions define edge-preserving regularization but are not included in the class of functions defined by conditions i)-iii) because of their infinite limits violate condition i). These functions do not have quadratic behavior near zero.</p><p>Next, we have some nonconvex and convex edge-preserving functions satisfying conditions i)-iii). Only the convex functions satisfy the additional condition of ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>). In the nonconvex case, the decreasing rate of and as are equal and the second derivative of tends to zero by a negative value. Using nonconvex functions results in edge enhancement <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> by inversing the diffusion in the gradient direction, which is an ill-posed problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Half-Quadratic Regularization</head><p>In this section, we recall that the properties i)-iii) imply that the potential can be represented as the infimum of quadratic functions. This property is used to derive the fast deterministic minimization algorithm, algebraic reconstruction technique using regularization (so-called ARTUR).</p><p>Relaxing the asymptotic-constant-behavior constraint on the functions, results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> have been extended in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> to the class of functions satisfying the conditions i)-iii). It has been shown that the nonquadratic criterion (2) can be represented as the infimum of quadratic functionals by introducing an auxiliary variable defined on and a convex function as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>: Inf <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> where and . The minimum on when is fixed is unique and given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> The variable weights the quadratic smoothing on : when is small, tends to (by construction we take ) and the regularization is quadratic; when is high, tends to zero and the smoothing term vanishes. Thus gives a representation of the edges of the image. The function is defined from the function and acts as a penalty for introducing an edge (</p><p>). Finally a new criterion is defined, depending on both the intensity and the edges , as follows:</p><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">)<label>17</label></formula><p>This criterion must be minimized with respect to . While the criterion ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) is nonquadratic with respect to [which leads to the nonlinear Euler equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>)], the new criterion is quadratic with respect to as is fixed. Therefore, is called a half-quadratic criterion. Then, as is fixed, the minimization with respect to is a linear problem. Consequently, we use an algorithm based on alternate minimizations on and .</p><p>initialize repeat with fixed. solve div in with fixed until convergence. Some results on the convergence of ARTUR are given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> in the discrete case for convex functions . Convergence results in this case are also available in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. The continuous case was thoroughly studied by several authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Limitations of the Model</head><p>In edge-preserving regularization, there are, in fact, two parameters to tune: and . The parameter has already been introduced in previous sections as the regularizing parameter. The parameter is introduced in the criterion as follows: <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> It allows the threshold to be fixed on the gradient modulus of the solution, and allows elimination of most of the spurious oscillations in the image.</p><p>All results are presented with empirically estimated parameters. Let us show two results on a synthetic piecewise constant grey-scale object [Fig. <ref type="figure">1(a)</ref>]. white noise was added [Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>(b) and (c)], resulting in a noisy image with a signal to noise ratio (SNR) of 15 dB (variance ratio). In Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, we present the two following results.</p><p>• A sharp edge-restored image [Fig. <ref type="figure">2(a)</ref>]: ( , ). However, the variable is noisy [Fig. <ref type="figure">2(c</ref>)], and we can see on the image of the cross-section of [Fig. <ref type="figure">2(b)</ref>] that homogeneous areas are oscillating.</p><p>• A smoother edge-restored image [Fig. <ref type="figure">2(d)]: (</ref> ). In this case, we can see on both the crosssection of [Fig. <ref type="figure">2(e)</ref>] and the variable [Fig. <ref type="figure">2(f)</ref>] that some edges are lost. In particular, note the little disc on the bottom left side of the object [Fig. <ref type="figure">2(d)]</ref>. This part of the image is difficult to restore because of the high spatial resolution of the detail together with a low local contrast. The limitation of this model lies in the quality of the edge model. The algorithm smooths small variations on (assuming they are due to noise) and preserves high variations (assuming they are generated by edges). Of course, noise can produce high variations, while edges with low contrast will generate a low gradient modulus. In order to improve the model, we propose in the next section the addition of a new segmentation constraint on . Hence, tends to be a real-edge model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. COUPLED SYSTEMS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Introduction/Principle</head><p>Actually, denoising an image assumes some information on the edges, which will be given by a segmentation constraint. Moreover, edge detection requires a noise free image obtained by Gaussian smoothing. Thus, we propose processing both restoration and edge detection on the noisy image. In order to indicate that is the edge image, we add to (17) a segmentation constraint on</p><p>. The main idea is to smooth only in the parallel direction to the edges. We can make a link between this constraint and the interaction constraint on the line process in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Thus our new edge model is characterized by adding a regularizing term on the auxiliary variable into the criterion , such as</p><p>where is a function that can differ from the function . is minimized with respect to : first with respect to with fixed, and then with respect to with fixed. If the solution of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">19</ref>) exists, we obtain the following system of PDE's:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">div (20a) div (20b)</formula><p>Unfortunately, in many cases, (20b) is difficult to solve numerically due to the infinite limit of when tends to 0. For example, if the function associated with is the Geman and McClure function (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref>), we have . In order to overcome this difficulty, we propose to make a change of variable-we use rather than -and becomes  and so criterion ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">19</ref>) becomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> The first advantage to the regularization by the addition of appears when is nonconvex. In this case, though (2), and hence <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>, do not have solutions, it can be shown <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> that <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> has a solution when is quadratic. The PDE system associated with the minimization of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">19</ref>) is div (23a) div (23b)</p><p>We take nonquadratic in order to have an anisotropic diffusion on with (23b), despite the fact that the existence and uniqueness of a solution is an open problem in this case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Related Works</head><p>The diffusion defined by the system (23a), (23b) is anisotropic both in intensity and edges <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. A similar model of a coupled PDE system is proposed by Nitzberg and Shiota in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> where the diffusion on the edge variable is isotropic.</p><p>In a variational approach with isotropic diffusion on the auxiliary variable , a new family of criteria has been proposed, as follows: <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> • If</p><p>, March <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and Nesi <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> use Ambrosio and Tortorelli -convergence results <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> to minimize the  <ref type="formula">24</ref>) is the segmentation functional used by Shah in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. It seems that Shah wants to find some that minimizes the total variation of the image, without penalizing the discontinuities corresponding to large jumps more than smaller discontinuities. Unfortunately, there is no proof of the existence of the solution in this case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Proposed Method</head><p>We enlarge our previous model by embedding the functional defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> in a one-parameter family of functionals <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> Equation ( <ref type="formula">26</ref>) is similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> but it involves a more general regularizing term on the auxiliary variable : is not necessary quadratic. Of course if and , ( <ref type="formula">26</ref>) is nothing else than <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>.</p><p>By minimizing , the coupled system becomes as follows.</p><p>• If (quadratic norm of the gradient) div (27a) div (27b) In both cases, we have a coupled system of two anisotropic diffusion equations. Note that in our case, the diffusion equation in is anisotropic, unlike in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. For the equation in , the data consistency term is . For the one in , the data term is</p><p>. Thus, we have tends to 1 when tends to a.e. (almost everywhere). Note that, by developing the div-operator in (28a), we invoke the following curvature operator, often used in image processing <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">div div (<label>29</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">)</formula><p>where is the usual Euclidian scalar product in or .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Algorithms</head><p>The proposed algorithms consist of solving two coupled PDE's: one involves the intensity image, the other the edges. These equations are solved alternately as By computing the second directional derivatives , , and , we get <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> where is the Hessian matrix of . Thus <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref> It is easy to show that, for any being two orthonormal vectors in the plane orthogonal to the gradient, we also have </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Synthetic piecewise constant grey-scale object. (a) Original. (b) Cross-section of f (original and noisy). (c) Noisy (15 dB).</figDesc><graphic coords="4,82.20,213.36,435.84,111.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Segmentation and restoration based first algorithm results (r = 2) with a nonconvex functional at the first step (k = 1). (a) Restored image (SNR = 28:4 dB). (b) Cross-section of f (original and restored). (c) Edges (variable b). At the ultimate step (k max = 5). (d) Restored image (SNR = 31:7 dB). (e) Cross-section of f (original and restored). (f) Edges (variable b).</figDesc><graphic coords="5,80.10,191.82,439.92,112.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Segmentation and restoration based second algorithm results (r = 1) with a nonconvex functional at the ultimate step (k max = 32): (a) restored image (SNR = 25:8 dB); (b) cross section of f (original and restored); (c) edges (variable b).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Segmentation and restoration based first algorithm results (r = 2) with the quadratic functional (k max = 4): (a) restored image (SNR = 25:2 dB); (b) cross section of f (original and restored); (c) edges (variable b). With a convex functional (kmax = 5): (d) restored image (SNR = 30:8 dB); (e) cross section of f (original and restored); (f) edges (variable b).</figDesc><graphic coords="6,86.10,361.98,427.92,111.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Real picture of the city of Nîmes (France).</figDesc><graphic coords="7,70.92,59.58,195.36,194.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. ARTUR results (without constraint on b) on the edge image.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,333.78,59.58,195.60,193.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Segmentation and restoration based first algorithm results (r = 2) on the edge images with a nonconvex functional. Evolution with parameter k. (a) k = 1. (b) k = 4. (c) k = 6. (d) k = 7. (e) k = 11. (f) k = 12.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="3,124.08,74.82,352.08,212.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,85.92,55.02,428.40,191.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,86.40,279.00,427.44,190.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,86.64,502.08,426.96,191.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE I</head><label>I</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors would like to thank the Centre National d' Études Spatiales for providing the image of Nîmes.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We use the conjugate-gradient method to solve our PDE's. We can note that, when is fixed and , we solve the system <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Related Algorithms using PDE's</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, the parameter is fixed. For example, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, the solution is computed by solving dynamic equations in the case (with the data term , and fixed. Reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> solves the dynamic scheme div <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref> obtained by multiplying the first equation by .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Piecewise Constant Object</head><p>The following results are presented for two-dimensional (2-D) images. The original image is a grey-level piecewiseconstant object. The SNR between the original and the noisy image is 15 dB (see Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</p><p>We present for all algorithms the restored image as well as a horizontal cross-section of this restored image (crossing the little disc on the left of the image). The edge image is also presented (variable ).</p><p>Using the ARTUR algorithm, the SNR (variance ratio) between the original and the restored image is 27.4 dB for the first set of parameters, and 24.5 dB for the second set of parameters (see Section II-D) (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</p><p>Using the constraint on the auxiliary variable (the algorithm presented in Section III-D, we increase at each step on the loop on in order to increasingly smooth the image as the edges are well-restored. Best results are obtained with the nonconvex Geman and McClure function of Table <ref type="table">I</ref>. For the first algorithm ( ), the SNR between the original and restored image is 28.4 dB after the first loop on [Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> We present also with the first algorithm ( ) (see Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>) some results with the quadratic function : The final SNR between the original and the restored image is 25.2 dB, and with the Green function of Table <ref type="table">I</ref> the final SNR between the original and the restored image is dB.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Real-Image Data</head><p>The original image is a real satellite image of the city of Nîmes (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>). We add a noise to the original image, so that, the SNR between the original image and the noisy image is 15 dB. The improvements are better illustrated in the edge images rather than on the images themselves so we present the edge image results for the ARTUR algorithm (see Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>) and for the first algorithm presented in Section III-D ( ) (see Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>). We show how the edge image evolves with parameter [Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>(a)-(f)]. The problem is to choose the parameter to optimize the results. In our case, when &gt; the resulting image becomes too smooth [Fig. <ref type="figure">8(f)</ref>]. Thus we stop the loop on (</p><p>) for a good trade-off between smoothing and edge-preservation [Fig. <ref type="figure">8(e)</ref>].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSION</head><p>This paper presents several minimization functionals for edge-preserving reconstruction. In this paper, we have proposed two algorithms and have shown by experimental results that regularizing the edges is very efficient. The coupled PDE's associated with the functionals are linked to the ones used by other authors. Using a variational approach for edge-preserving regularization naturally results in the elliptic functional proposed by Ambrosio and Tortorelli <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> as an approximation to the Mumford-Shah segmentation functional. Perhaps this paper sheds new light on this approximation, via the different viewpoint of the half-quadratic regularization of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Current work is including to this coupled PDE system a segmentation based on the curve evolution theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head><p>The goal of this appendix is to show that div <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref> where is a unit vector in the gradient direction and are two orthonormal vectors in the plane orthogonal to the gradient. We suppose that . By developing the div-operator, we obtain div <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> Let be two orthonormal vectors in the plane orthogonal to the gradient, with <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> Sylvie Teboul was born on <ref type="bibr">May 12, 1971</ref>, in Casablanca, Morocco. She is a Ph.D. student in the Laboratoire d'Informatique Signaux et Systèmes de Sophia Antipolis, Valbonne, France.</p><p>Her research interests include nonlinear partial differential equations for edge preserving regularization and deformable models. Applications are in 2-D: deconvolution for satellite images; and in 2-D and 3-D: segmentation, restoration, and reconstruction in medical imaging.</p><p>Laure Blanc-Féraud received the Ph.D. degree in image restoration from Nice-Sophia Antipolis University, Nice, France, in 1989.</p><p>She is currently working with the Centre National de Recherche Scientifique, Sophia Antipolis. Her research interests include inverse problems, variational approach for edge-preserving regularization, nonlinear partial differential equations, Markov random field models, parameter estimation, multiresolution image analysis. Fields of application include image restoration, segmentation, deconvolution for satellite images, motion estimation, 2-D and 3-D reconstruction in medical imaging (SPECT) or in microwave inverse diffraction. He is currently a Professor at the Nice-Sophia Antipolis University, Nice, France. His research interests include calculus of variations, nonlinear partial differential equations, and numerical analysis; fields of application include nonlinear elasticity and image processing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gilles</head><p>Michel Barlaud (M'88) was born in France on November 24, 1945. He received the Doctorat d'Etat degree from the University of Paris XII, France.</p><p>He is currently a Professor of image processing at Ecole Supèrieure en Sciences Informatiques, University of Nice-Sophia Antipolis, Nice, France. He is also Head of the Image Processing Group of the Laboratoire d'Informatique Signaux et Systèmes de Sophia Antipolis. His research interests are image compression using wavelets, lattice vector quantization, image restoration, segmentation, 2-D and 3-D reconstruction, and motion estimation. His contributions to the field include biorthogonal wavelengths, a method for counting lattice points on a pyramid, and a new edge adaptive quantization method.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximation of functionals depending on jumps by elliptic functionals via 0-convergence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ambrosio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V.-M</forename><surname>Tortorelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. Pure Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="999" to="1036" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the approximation of free discontinuity problems</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bull. Un. Mat. Ital</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal approximations by piecewise smooth functions and associated variational problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mumford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. Pure Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="577" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic relaxation, Gibbs distributions and the Bayesian restoration of images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Geman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Geman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Machine Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="721" to="741" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-11">Nov. 1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constrained restoration and the recovery of discontinuities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Geman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Machine Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="383" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-03">Mar. 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A generalized Gaussian image model for edge-preserving MAP estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bouman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="296" to="310" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-07">July 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visual Reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Blake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zisserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A variational method in image recovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Vese</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Numer. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1948" to="1979" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-06">June 1995. Oct. 1997</date>
			<pubPlace>Dieudonné, University of Nice-Sophia Antipolis, France, Res</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Note 423</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deterministic edge-preserving regularization in computed imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Charbonnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Blanc-Féraud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barlaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997-02">Feb. 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of bounded variation penalty methods for ill-posed problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Acar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-R</forename><surname>Vogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inv. Prob</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1217" to="1229" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-12">Dec. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear total variation noise removal algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L.-I</forename><surname>Rudin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fatemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual reconstruction with discontinuities using variational methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>March</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Image Vis. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A common framework for curve evolution, segmentation, and anisotropic diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Proc. Conf. Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-06">June 1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="142" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scale-space and edge detection using anisotropic diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Perona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Machine Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="629" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear image filtering with edge and corner enhancement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nitzberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shiota</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Machine Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="826" to="833" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image selective smoothing and edge detection by nonlinear diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Catte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-L</forename><surname>Lions</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Morel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Coll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Numer. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-02">Feb. 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image selective smoothing and edge detection by nonlinear diffusion II</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Alvarez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-L</forename><surname>Lions</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-M</forename><surname>Morel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Numer. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="845" to="866" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Geometry-Driven Diffusion in Computer Vision</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ter Haar Romeny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ed</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From active contours to anisotropic diffusion: Connections between basic PDE&apos;s in image processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Proc. 3rd Int. Conf. Image Processing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lausanne, Switzerland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-09">Sept. 1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">I</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="477" to="480" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">in Three-Dimensional Image Reconstruction in Radiology and Nuclear Medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Laurette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">the Int. Meeting Fully 3D Image Reconstruction in Radiology and Nuclear Medicine</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Amans</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Grangeat</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, MA; Aix-les-Bains, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995-07">1995. July 1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="73" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cone-beam algebraic reconstruction using edgepreserving regularization</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study in the BV space of a denoising-deblurring variational problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lazaroaía</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>prepubl. no. 439</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Laboratory J-A. Dieudonné</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<pubPlace>France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Nice-Sophia Antipolis</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>URA 168 du CNRS</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Image recovery via total variation minimization and related problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chambolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-L</forename><surname>Lions</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<pubPlace>Paris, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>CERE-MADE, Univ. Paris-Dauphine</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Research note 95-09</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biased anisotropic diffusion-A unified regularization and diffusion approach to edge detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nordström</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dept. Elect. Eng. Comput. Sci., Univ. Calif</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<pubPlace>Berkeley, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavioral analysis of anisotropic diffusion in image processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-L</forename><surname>You</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tannenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kaveh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1539" to="1553" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-11">Nov. 1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two deterministic half-quadratic regularization algorithms for computed imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Charbonnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Blanc-Féraud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barlaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Proc.1st Int. Conf. Image Processing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Austin, TX</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-11">Nov. 1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="172" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear image processing: Modeling and fast algorithm for regularization with edge detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Blanc-Féraud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Charbonnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barlaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Proc. 2nd Int. Conf. Image Processing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="474" to="477" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Directional anisotropic diffusion applied to segmentation of vessels in 3D images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Krissian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Malandain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayache</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. First Conf. Scale-Space Theory in Computer Vision</title>
		<meeting>First Conf. Scale-Space Theory in Computer Vision<address><addrLine>Utrecht, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Convergence of an iterative method for total variation denoising</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D.-C</forename><surname>Dobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-R</forename><surname>Vogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted for publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A fast, robust algorithm for total variation based reconstruction of noisy, blurred images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-R</forename><surname>Vogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-E</forename><surname>Oman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted for publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear regularization using constrained edges in image reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Blanc-Féraud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Teboul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barlaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Proc. 3rd Int. Conf. Image Processing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lausanne, Switzerland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-09">Sept. 1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="452" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variational approach to optical flow estimation managing discontinuities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nesi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Image Vis. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-09">Sept. 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Geometric Measure Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Federer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Segmentation and edge-preserving restoration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Teboul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Blanc-Féraud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barlaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 4th IEEE Conf. Image Processing</title>
		<meeting>4th IEEE Conf. Image essing<address><addrLine>Sophia Antipolis, France; Santa Barbara, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10">1997. Oct. 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="470" to="473" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Laboratory I3S, Univ. Nice-</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian image analysis: An application to single photon emission tomography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Geman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D.-E</forename><surname>Mcclure</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Stat. Comput. Sect</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Amer. Stat. Assoc.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A generalized EM algorithm for 3-D Bayesian reconstruction from Poisson data using Gibbs priors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Leahy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Med. Imag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="194" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-06">June 1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian reconstruction from emission tomography data using a modified EM algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-J</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Med. Imag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
