<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A MUCH RICHER EXPERIENCE. BY LEARNING TO PLAY THE (AND DEEPER UNDERSTANDING 00 MUSIC</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mitchel</forename><surname>Resnick</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">MIT Media Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>20 Ames Street Cambridge</addrLine>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Amy</forename><surname>Bruckman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">MIT Media Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>20 Ames Street Cambridge</addrLine>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fred</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">MIT Media Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>20 Ames Street Cambridge</addrLine>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A MUCH RICHER EXPERIENCE. BY LEARNING TO PLAY THE (AND DEEPER UNDERSTANDING 00 MUSIC</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D8857087F267D23729B05D5637184261</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T16:20+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>that, like pianos, enable people to express themselves in increasingly ever-more complex ways, deepening their relationships with new domains of knowledge.</p><p>To guide the development of these computational construction kits, we are developing a theory of constructional design. Whereas the traditional field of instructional design focuses on strategies and materials to help teachers instruct, our theory of constructional design focuses on strategies and materials to help students construct and learn. Constructional design is a type of metadesign: it involves the design of new tools and activities to support students in their own design activities. In short, constructional design involves designing for designers [ 121.</p><p>In recent years, a growing number of researchers and educators have argued that design projects provide rich opportunities for learning <ref type="bibr">[3, 5,</ref>  In this article, we discuss three of our computational construction kits. In each case, we discuss how the kit aims to facilitate both personal and epistemological connections-and, as a result, support rich learning experiences. StarLogo makes these ideas accessible to younger students by providing them with a stronger personal connection to the undcrlying models. Traditional differential-equation approaches are "impersonal" in two ways. The first is obvious: they rely on abstract symbol manipulation. The second is more subtle: They deal in aggregate quantities. In the termite example, differential equations would describe how the density of wood chips evolves over time. There are now some' very good computer modeling tools--such as Stella <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref> and Model-It <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>-based on diC ferential equations. These tools eliminate the need to manipulate symbols, focusing on more qualitative and graphical descriptions. But they still rely on aggregate quantities.  Developers of design-oriented learning environments cannot "program" learning experiences directly. The challenge, instead, is to create frameworks from which strong connections-and rich learning experiences-are likely to emerge. @</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>S</head><label></label><figDesc>o, too, with computers. Educational technology has too heavily emphasized the equivalent of stereos and CDs and not emphasized computational pianos enough. In our research group at the MIT Media Lab, we are developing a new generation of "computational construction kits"</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>141. In particular, Papert [S] has argued for a 'constructionist" approach to learning. There are many reasons for this interest in design-based learning. Design activities involve people as active participants, giving them a greater sense of control over (and personal involvement in) the learning process. Moreover, the things that people design (be they sand castles, computer programs, LEG0 constructions, or musical compositions) serve as external shadows of the designer's internal mental models. These external creations provide an opportunity for people to reflect on-and then revise and extend-their internal models of the world. Of course, not all design experiences (or all construction kits) are created equal. Some provide richer learning opportunities than others. What criteria should guide the design of new construction kits and activities? The concept of learning-by-doing has existed for a long time. But the literature on the subject tends to describe specific activities and gives little attention to the general principles governing the kinds of "'doing" most conducive to learning. From our experiences, we have developed two general principles to guide the design of new construction kits and activities, These constructional-design principles involve two different types of "connections": l Personal connections. Construction kits and activities should connect to users' interests, passions, and experiences. The point is not simply to make the activities more "motivating." When activities involve objects and actions that are familiar, users can draw on their previous knowledge, connecting new ideas to their preexisting intuitions. 9 Epistemological connections. Construction kits and activities should connect to important domains of knowledge-and, more significantly, encourage new ways of thinking (and even new ways of thinking about thinking). A welldesigned construction kit makes certain ideas and ways of thinking particularly salient, so that users are likely to connect with those ideas in a natural way in the process of designing and creating, The challenge of constructional designand it is a significant challenge-is to create construction kits with both types of connections. Many learning materials and activities offer one type of connection but not the other.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>computers in the world, StarLogo enables them to construct worlds in the computer. In particular, StarLogo is designed to help students model and explore the behaviors of decentralized systems-such as ant colonies, traffic jams, market economies, immune systerns, and computer netrvorks. In these systems, orderly patterns arise without centralized control. In ant colonies, for example, trail patterns are determined not by the dictates of the queen ant but by local interactions among the worker ants. In market economies, patterns arise from interactions among millions of buyers and sellers in distributed marketplaces. Decentralized systems are important throughout the sciences and social sciences, but most people have difficulty understanding the workings of such systems. People seem to have strong attachments to centralized ways of thinking. When people see patterns in the world (such as the foraging patterns of an ant colony), they generally assume that there is some type of centralized control (a queen ant). According to this way of thinking, a pattern can exist only if someone (or something) creates and orchestrates the pattern. StarLogo is designed to help students make a fundamental epistemological shift, to move beyond the "centralized mindset" to more decentralized ways of thinking [ 10, 111. StarLogo allows students to construct and experiment with decentralized systems. They write simple rules for thousands of objects (e.g., artificial ants), then observe the patterns (e.g., colony-level foraging patterns) that arise from all of the interactions. By creating their own StarLogo models, students can build on personal connections. For example, two high-school students who had recently received their drivers' licenses used StarLogo to model the formation of traffic jams on the highway-a topic of great interest to them. They discovered (counter to their initial intuitions) how traffic jams can form through simple, decentralized interactions among cars, without any centralized cause such as an accident, radar trap, or broken bridge. Another high-school student named Callie used StarLogo to model the workings of a termite colony (see Figure 2). Callie had seen a television program that showed termites building intricate structures on the plains of AfZca. She wondered how creatures as simple as termites could build such elaborate structures. She decided to program a colony of virtual termites to gather wood chips into a pile. At first, Callie tried to put one termite in charge and programmed that termite to tell all of the other termites where to put the wood chips. But it is difficult to establish that type of centralized control in StarLogo. We discussed some of the drawbacks of a centralized leader: What would happen, for instance, if the leader termite was killed? Callie experimented with more decentralized approaches (more in line with the underlying structure of StarLogo) and found that the colony didn't need a leader after all. In her final model, each termite followed the same set of simple rules: wander randomly until you bump into a wood chip, pick up the wood chip, wander randomly until you bump into another wood chip, put down the wood chip you're carrying, start over. This strategy uses only local sensory information and a simple control strategy, but the group as a whole accomplishes a sophisticated task. Traditionally, these types of complex decentralized systems have been studied only at the university level, using differential equations and other advanced mathematical techniques. StarLogo enables much younger students to explore these systems-and to gain an understanding of the underlying ideas of self-organizing [lo] and probabilistic [ 191 behavior.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>StarLogo, by contrast, lets students think about the actions and interactions of individual objects. StarLogo is not simply a computerization of a traditional mathematical model; it supports what we call 'computational models"-models that wouldn't make sense without a computer. In the terniitc example, students think not about aggregate quantities but about individual termites and individual wood chips. They can imagine themselves as termites and think about what they might do. In this way, StarLogo cnablcs learners to "dive into" the model, making a more personal connection. Future versions of StarLogo will enable users to zoom in and out, making it easier for users to shift back and forth in perspective from the individual level to the group level.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>typically build new language (MOOSE) and new client interface worlds on their own or in pairs, MOOSE Cross-(MacMOOSE) designed to make learning to ing provides a way for children to build virtual program easier for kids. For each object that worlds together as part of an online community. kids create, they write a combination of text MOOSE Crossing gives children the oppor-and computer code to describe the properties tunity not only to "talk" with one another and behaviors of the object. For example, one online, but also to collaboratively construct, 1 a-year-old girl created a baby penguin that is with words and computer programs, the virtu-always hungry. It responds differently when al world in which they interact [I]. MOOSE you offer it different kinds of food, and it Crossing is similar to existing MUD environ-won't eat certain foods if it is on a diet. A 9ments [2], but it includes a new programming year-old girl made a magical room at the end 'look again i just changed the discription' You see alexs shop keeper and Pumpernickel here. Alexander is here. Alexander says, ' to' Alexander says, " sap great! Looks verp nice! You say 'great! Looks very nice!' Alexander says, 'you can buy a dog, parrot, flopdisky, sport i ball, or sports bag here' g . . . . . . Alexander says, 'sports ball that is' 9 --&gt; look L --&gt; say great! --&gt; say neat !I Looks very nice! El because it draws on their personal connection to computer games, to elements of popular culture, and to socializing with each other. The environment has the feel of a text-based adventure game (and historically has its roots in such games), but it opens up greater intellectual challenges. You not only can experience the world but also build it. Children often choose popular culture as the subject of their conversations and an inspiration for their creations: for example, one afternoon, two 12-year-old girls started talking about Star Trek and decided to build themselves spaceships. Commercial culture is also a popular starting point for projects. One 1 l-year-old girl first made a vacation resort called Paradise Island, then set up a travel agency to sell people trips there, and last added a car rental agency. Several factors gave her a very personal connection to the project. It's important that she decided what she wanted to make: Rather than being assigned a project, she chose one that was personally meaningful to her. Her entire participation in MOOSE Crossing was voluntarychildren participate in their spare time as an after-school activity. She was especially motivated by a desire to share her creation with other children. On finrshing Paradise Island, she immediately invited all her online friends over for a swim. A successful project gives a child social capital within the community. In each of these projects, children are doing creative writing and computer programming in their spare time for fun. MOOSE Crossing draws from children's natural interests to involve them in these intellectually valuable activities. They establish a new relationship to reading, writing, and programming. They begin to see them not just as something they are forced to do in school, but as expressive media through which they r;ln make personally significant meanings In other words, they establrsh a new eprstemologicdl relationship to these ways of understandrng the world and expressing themselves. MOOSE Crossing establishes new conncctions between different ways of knowing th&amp; are often separated and isolated In school activities. Making a successful MOOSE object is equal parts creatrve writing and computer programming. Making a MOOSE object helps children with a greater initial strength in one area develop greater confidence and competence in the other. One g-year-old girl who says that she hates math and math-like ,rctrvrties loves programmrng on MOOSE Crossrnrr because she sees it as a form of writing. Asked if she likes to write, she replred yes-in school she's writing stories about Imaginary people, on MOOSE Crossing, she's writing programs. The only difference between these two krnrls of writing is that "programmrng it everythrnq has to be right so the thing you're making can work." She is bridging from her strong verbal skills to develop greater interest and skill in more analytic activities The children participating in MOOSE Cros+ ing are mostly between 9 and 13 years old; rl few children are as young as 7. Adults mav apply to be "rangers." While we otiginally expected rangers to help children with thcrr projects, in practice it more often works the other way around. Children have much more time to devote to MOOSE Crossing and getserally understand better than adults how things work. Assrsting an adult wrth a technrcal question is a real thrill for many kids and challenges some of their basic assumption\ about learning. On MOOSE Crossing, everyone is playing, teaching, and learning all &lt;It the same time, rather like Seymour Papert's vision of activity In a "technologrcal sambcr school" [8]. Knowledge is not passed from teachers to students but is developed bv everyone through their activitres and rnteractions with one another Emergent Learning Experiences while also connecting to important intellectu-Programmable bricks, StarLogo, and MOOSE al ideas. Crossing are three very different types of com-But the process of constructional design is putational construction kits. The first involves not a simple matter of "programming in" the interaction with the physical world, the sec-right types of connections. As students have ond involves the construction of virtual col-used programmable bricks, StarLogo, and laborations, and the third involves MOOSE Crossing, their learning experiences collaboration on virtual constructions. What have been somewhat different than we (as unites these three diverse environments is developers) expected. This unpredictability is their attempt provide both personal and epis-characteristic of constructional design. Develtemological connections. Each of these kits opers of design-oriented learning environconnects to student interests and experiences ments need to adopt a relaxed sense of ACKNOWLEDGMENTS research. 'tontrol." Educational designers cannot and should not control exactly what or when or how students will learn. The point is not to make a precise blueprint. Rather, practitioners of constructional design can only create "spaces" of possible activities and experiences. What we can do as constructional designers is to try to make those spaces dense with personal and epistemological connections-making it more likely for learners to find regions that are both appealing and intellectually interesting. In some ways, the design of a new learning environment is like the design of a StarLogo simulation. In creating StarLogo simulations, users write simple rules for individual objects, then observe the large-scale patterns that emerge. Users do not program the patterns directly. So too with constructional design.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>interactions... seprcmber</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bruckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Crossing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="ftp://ftp.media.mit.edu/pub/~b/papers/moose-cro~ing-proposal.{ps,rtf,txt}" />
		<title level="m">Creating a Learning Culture</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>MIT Media Lab</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation proposal</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mudding: Social Phenomena in Tat-Based Virtual Realities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Curris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of DIAC &apos;92</title>
		<meeting>DIAC &apos;92<address><addrLine>Berkeley, Cahf</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Children Designers. Ablex Publishing, Norwood</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Harel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N.J</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stratford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krajcik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Soloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Learner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Centered Tool for Students Building Models</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="49" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authors of knowledge: Patterns of hypermedia design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lehrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computers as Cognitive Tools</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lajoie</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Derry</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lawrence Erlbaum, Hillsdale, N.J.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Circuits to Control: Learning Engineering by Designing LEG0 Robots</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>MIT Media Laboratory</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ideal and real systems: A study of notions of control in undergraduates who design robots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Lawrence Erlbaum</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<pubPlace>Hillsdale, N.J.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Children&apos;s Machine. Basic Books</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Paperr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavior construction kits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Resnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Resnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Turtles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Xaffic</forename><surname>Termites</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond the centralized mindset</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Resnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Learning Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a Practice of Constructional Design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Resnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Innovations in Learning: New Environments for Education</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schauble</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Glaser</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><surname>Erlbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mahwah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Computer Simulation: A System Dynamics Modeling Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Deal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Garet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shaffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Reading, Mass</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Soloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Guzdial</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leamer-Centered Design. interactions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-04">April 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Second Self Basic Books, New Yark</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Turkie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational Reticence: Why Women Fear The Intimate Machine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Turkle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Technology and Women&apos;s Voices</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kramerae</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pergamon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The computer for the 21st century</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific American</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">265</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some computer science issues in ubiquitous computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Wdensky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Connected Mathematics: Building Concrere Relationships with Mathematical Knowlcdgc</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, Mass.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>MIT Media Lab</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
