<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Canada</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Intelligent Machines</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McGill University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Montréal</settlement>
									<region>PQ</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">40612DFFEA39CE4084548D79D2AFEB71</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T12:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phase Control Approach to Hysteresis Reduction</head><p>Juan Manuel Cruz-Hernández, Member, IEEE, and Vincent Hayward, Member, IEEE, Abstract-This paper describes a method for the design of compensators able to reduce hysteresis in transducers, as well as two measures to quantify and compare controller performance. Rate independent hysteresis, as represented by the Preisach model of hysteresis, is seen as an input-output phase lag. The compensation is based on controllers derived from the "phaser," a unitary gain operator that shifts a periodic signal by a single phase angle. A "variable phaser" is shown to be able to handle minor hysteresis loops. Practical implementations of these controllers are given and discussed. Experimental results exemplify the use of these techniques.</p><p>Index Terms-Compensation, hysteresis, intelligent materials, phase control, piezoelectric transducers, smart materials, transducers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>H YSTERESIS relates to looping graphs which associate two scalar time-dependent quantities other than in terms of a single valued function [see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1(a)</ref>]. Hysteresis is of interest in many different areas: ferromagnetics, superconductivity, spin glasses, semiconductors, economics <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, and physiology <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, to mention a few. It is characteristic of transducers based on "smart materials," because these transducers rely on modifications of stress-strain relationships invariably associated with hysteretic behavior.</p><p>Loops are created when an input is varied back and forth between two consecutive extrema. This is not the essence of hysteresis however, it is a particular case of "branching," which occurs at the reversals of an input [see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1(b)</ref>] and where memory is encoded.</p><p>There is no agreement on a general definition of hysteresis. Since the present work is motivated by systems engineering, a black box representation of the system is adopted (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>) along with the following definition <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>.</p><p>Definition 1: At any time , the output of a system depends not only on the input , but also on its previous trajectory (memory). The input-output relationship is invariant with respect to changes in the time scale (rate independence). When a system has memory and is rate independent, it is said to have hysteresis.  This definition also includes hysteresis with nonlocal memory, which implies the existence of minor loops. This will be further discussed in Section III. Hysteresis is often part of a more complex system with dynamics, but in this paper we focus on a case which applies to transducers having hysteresis.</p><p>Information available in the input-output behavior may be used to characterize hysteresis. In this paper, we attempt to summarize it using a small set of parameters, possibly just one, for the design of practical compensators that can cope with hysteresis. This desire for simplicity is motivated by economical and computational considerations. While the method developed in this paper is primarily intended for electromechanical transducers, it could probably also be applied in some other areas.</p><p>The Preisach model of hysteresis is a general model of rate independent hysteresis. It represents well the electromechanical behavior of a number of "smart materials" <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. We will use some of its properties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PAST WORK</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, Ge and Jouaneh used a combination of a feedforward controller including a nonlinearity with a proportional integral derivative (PID) feedback loop to reduce hysteresis in an actuator represented by the Preisach model. The inverse of this model was used as part of the controller stored in a lookup table. This technique was also used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> to compensate for hysteresis in solid-state actuators. While hysteresis in a piezoelectric actuator is reduced if the charge is regulated instead of the voltage <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, the implementation complexity of this technique prevents a wide acceptance <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, feedforward control was used to reduce scanning errors due to hysteresis modeled as "deterministic hysteretic paths." The controller depends on large amounts of experimental data.</p><p>Banning et al. used a feedback linearization approach once a model of the system with hysteresis was obtained <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Then a model-based state feedback control is proposed.</p><p>Korson and Helmicki used an design method to develop a controller which explicitly deals with the model uncertainty of the thermal dynamics of a shroud combined with the hysteresis of a valve <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. A model of hysteresis was obtained from the describing function method. The main concern was the possible occurrence of limit cycles in closed loop. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> a robust controller was applied to a bimorph actuator, which achieved disturbance decoupling with a small steady-state tracking error and fast settling time. A nonlinear model was first linearized, then an design was used to find a controller, however only simulation results are presented in this reference.</p><p>Attempts were made to use artificial neural networks to compensate for the hysteresis caused by backlash in mechanical systems, as in Seidl et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. Physical analysis of the system nonlinearities and optimal control were used to design the neural network structure.</p><p>Adaptive control is also an approach to the control of plants with hysteretic behavior. Tao and Kokotovic ´developed such controllers to reduce the effects of hysteresis-like nonlinearities <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. The plant model consists of a linear part preceded by a hysteresis block representing the actuator. An adaptive hysteresis inverse was cascaded with the plant so that the rest of the controller could be linear. Tao used a similar idea, but the plant was represented by two nonlinearities, one at the input and one at the output <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. All these ideas were collected in a recent book by Tao and Kokotovic ´ <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. Adaptive control applied to a linearized Preisach-like model was also described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>.</p><p>Model-based nonlinear control methods for magnetostrictive materials were presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> because transducers based on these materials exhibit significant hysteresis. The control method consists of a linear perturbation feedback law used in combination with an optimal open-loop nonlinear controller. The feedback control is constructed through linearization of the perturbed system and is efficient for on-line implementation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. THE PREISACH MODEL OF HYSTERESIS</head><p>This model is extensively discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, references on which this section is based. The Preisach model represents well the behavior of hysteresis encountered in transducers and provides insights for the design of compensators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Succinct Description</head><p>The model can represent hysteresis with "nonlocal memory." In other words, the future values of the output depend not only on but on past extrema of the input <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. The special case of "local memory" implies that the value of the output at some instant and the value of the input at all subsequent instants in time uniquely determine the future value of . The Preisach model considers an infinite set of relay operators (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>), where and correspond to the up and down switching values of the input where the output switches between and . The weighted response of an infinite collection of relays is summed over all possible switching values (1)  where is the Preisach function. In the -plane, each point of the half plane , is identified with one relay. Each relay has only local memory, but collectively, they create nonlocal memory.</p><p>The limiting triangle in the -plane, graphically described in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>, corresponds to closed major loops, so is equal to zero outside except on the line which may extend indefinitely to describe degenerate relays that yield no memory.</p><p>At any time , the triangle is subdivided into two sets: consisting of the points for which the corresponding -operators are in the up position, and consisting of the points for which the -operators are in the down position. The interface between and is a staircase line whose vertices have and coordinates coinciding with the local maxima and minima of input at previous instants in time.</p><p>The subdivision of the limiting triangle as the input varies is what describes the Preisach model's memory state. Past input extrema are encoded in the shape of the staircase and this is what gives it nonlocal memory. In particular, alternating series of dominant input extrema are sorted and all other input extrema are "wiped out." Moreover, minor hysteresis loops corresponding to back-and-forth variations of inputs between the same two consecutive extremum values are congruent up to a translation and closed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Relationship with Phase</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref> shows a minor loop created after an input signal is varied between and . The triangle is added to the positive set (subtracted from ) when the input reaches , and subtracted from (added to ) when reaches . When the input is at the interface line is just a line parallel to the axis, creating a set of past extrema (one corner at the intersection and ). When it is at , the interface line is a step as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>, creating a different set of past extrema (same as before plus the corner at</p><p>). This difference is what causes the loop to trace two different paths (ascending and descending) according to the state of the interface line . In Sections V and VI, we will develop controllers motivated by the resemblance of hysteresis with phase lag. The Preisach model would then predict that, unlike input-output phase in linear systems, lag due to hysteresis depends on the amplitude of the input, and more generally on past input extrema, but not on frequency.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. PLANT MODEL</head><p>Hysteresis is often part of a system having other dynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. In practice, the input to the hysteresis model may not be accessible, and that its output may be hidden. However, we consider the input and output of a transducer to be accessible by observation or by other techniques. A transducer having hysteresis is such that the gain and phase both are functions of the magnitude of the input signal, in addition to being a function of frequency and</p><p>(2)</p><p>A representation may have the structure of a Volterra series (a sum of operators), and may be limited to a finite number of terms <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. If only two are considered <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref> where represents a linear time invariant filter, and represents rate independent hysteresis. This is illustrated in block diagram form by Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>, where hysteresis is connected in parallel to a linear filter.</p><p>Transducers containing hysteresis, as observed in real systems, fall in one of the following cases:</p><p>• nonsaturated and rate independent (e.g., ceramic actuators <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>); • saturated and rate independent; • nonsaturated and rate dependent (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>); • saturated and rate dependent (e.g., shape memory alloy actuators (SMA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>). The block diagram in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref> may be augmented with a saturation at the output or at the input. Loops can also be symmetric or asymmetric. Piezoceramic actuators usually yield symmetric loops <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, while SMA actuators yield asymmetric loops <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. The controllers described in this paper achieve significant hysteresis reduction under most of the conditions mentioned above because they are designed to act on phase alone, even if a transducer does not satisfies all the conditions needed by the representation theorem of the Preisach model <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</p><p>The Preisach model maps a Sobolev space into itself, the space of truncated functions for which the Sobolev norm is finite <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Since a linear time invariant system also maps signals in this space into itself the configuration of the plant above will map into itself as well.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. THE "PHASER"</head><p>The notion of "apparent phase shift" between input and output motivates the design of controllers which act specifically on phase. When a periodic input signal with period is applied to a system with hysteresis, the output has in general the same period. This can be viewed as a point which travels along a loop, where the time spent by the point to return to the initial position is also . For systems with rate independent hysteresis, if , with , then , with . The output has the same period as the input but is shifted in phase; so the phase is produced by the nonoverlapping ascending and descending paths in the loop.</p><p>Periodic signals which are square integrable over a single period can be decomposed in terms of a Fourier series <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. If a system maps the Sobolev space into itself, as it is the case here, the condition above is satisfied <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref> If is referenced to the input , all the components of the output are shifted by some angle. It is possible to speak of phase shift between the input and the output. In particular, for the Preisach model, this phase shift does not depend on the frequency of the input signal.</p><p>Definition 2: (Localized Phase): For a periodic input signal of arbitrary frequency applied to a system having rate independent hysteresis, the frequency invariant localized phase is defined as the phase between the input and the output , i.e., . This definition must be regarded as tentative since phase is not well defined for nonlinear systems. In practice, we use phase estimates based, for example, on the first harmonic, as in Section VIII. The phase shift is a distortion acting on a periodic input. In other words, hysteresis can be seen as a phase lag between a periodic input and the corresponding output. The natural way of correcting this problem is to reverse its effect.</p><p>Definition 3: (Phaser): A phaser is an operator that shifts a periodic input signal by a constant angle , and has unity gain.</p><p>The phaser can be viewed as the counterpart of a gain which modifies the magnitude of an input signal but not its phase. The operator maps into itself. In the frequency domain and (5)</p><p>In the time domain, the system is the product of an impulse function with the complex number . The phaser has two important properties, superposition and noncausality. Superposition follows from linearity. Noncausality prevents direct online implementation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Compensation</head><p>In the low frequencies, where hysteresis dominates, a bandlimited phaser can be used to produce the inverse phase function of the hysteresis between and , as in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref>, where is shifted by an angle with respect to and will be shifted also, but by an angle with respect to . The angle is the localized phase for . The phase angle between and is reduced. The phase introduced by is neglected in the low frequencies since it is a linear filter, it must be zero or a multiply of . Since both and are in phase, the fundamental component of is similar to the input , and the difference is smaller than the uncompensated error . It should be small since higher harmonic components of the output usually have decreasing coefficients. The main component will be in phase with the reference . is a distortion or noise on the output that can be compensated for, as other distortion signals, by feedback. Moreover, the higher components are phase shifted the same way. For the same compensation and compared to the input signal, they will be all shifted by the same phase angle. Note that the composite system in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref> has hysteresis but it is now hidden.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Nonlinear Phaser</head><p>In practice, the angle varies with the magnitude of the input signal, so a fixed phaser will yield an imperfect compensation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, typically as in Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>. Depending on the input amplitude, there is over or undercompensation.</p><p>Imperfect compensation yields an input-output phase plot having several loops with different phase angles. However, the result can be further improved by successive approximations. The second approximation involves the use of another phaser to provide a positive angle for the middle loop, and a negative angle for the others. These angles, can be obtained considering each loop independently from the others, and estimating the phase between input and output. The control strategy is now as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>.</p><p>A nonlinear phaser has a phase angle which varies from to if if (6)  where and , and is illustrated on Fig. <ref type="figure">8(c</ref>) where a change in the orientation of the loop occurs. The angle is still independent of frequency but depends on the magnitude. The phase angle of the phaser can be designed to meet any variation of the loops, since it depends on the input signal only. Such a nonlinear phaser will be termed a "variable phaser."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>The phaser is noncausal, so an approximation must be found to use it online. Filters can be built which add phase over a limited frequency range, at the expense of a small variation in gain. We propose to use one of the three methods described below.</p><p>The angle is the sole parameter needed for design. It can be estimated from the phase plot of the empirical transfer function starting in the quasistatic range as will be shown in Section VIII. A linear system in the quasistatic range has a zero phase angle or a multiple of . For a system with hysteresis, the phase angle will be finite in the quasistatic range, close to either zero degrees or a multiple of degrees. The linear part of the plant will yield an experimental transfer function, but the phase plot will always appear to be shifted by degrees over the whole range (a hallmark of hysteresis). This is illustrated by Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">19</ref> which shows a quasi constant phase over a range of two decades in the low frequencies for a piezoceramic actuator (the phase varies with amplitude from 1.5 to 4 ), or by Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">14</ref> which starts at 38 for a SMA actuator.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Implementation Based on the Hilbert Transform</head><p>A similarity exists between the phaser and the Hilbert transform commonly used in communication systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. It is a filter that shifts a signal by for positive frequencies and for negative ones. What is needed is specify any phase , that is <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> in which case, the impulse response is <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> Equation ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>) is a representation of the phaser in terms of the Hilbert transform. In the time domain <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> The output of the system is a linear combination of the input signal and of its Hilbert transform . This can be implemented as a finite impulse (FIR) response filter, a FIR Hilbert transformer <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Let be its ideal transfer function, then, to have unity gain response and phase lag at all frequencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> To have real weights, the transfer function must equal its own conjugate from frequencies from to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> The ideal impulse response of extends infinitely in both directions from the sample and is found as the sampled inverse Fourier transform of even odd <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> is included in the category where is even. The FIR Hilbert transformer differs in three ways from the ideal of ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>). First, it is of finite extent , where is odd. Second, it is causal, with weights centered around instead of . Finally, since in ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>) is truncated, a data window is applied to improve the gain characteristic of the practical transformer. The introduction of causality simply adds a delay of samples, which is easy to compensate for, by using a delay at the input signal. Despite its constant angle at , the implementation depends highly on the number of samples taken per cycle, and if a signal with unknown frequency is used, poor results can be obtained.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. PD Implementation</head><p>Equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) can be rewritten as <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> (13) or in the time domain <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> This resembles a PD controller, . If the angle varies with the input magnitude, ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) becomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> to yield a variable phaser. This implementation was used experimentally in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The controller must be designed for a specific input frequency. If the input contains more than one frequency, the controller will not compensate well for that signal, but if the system is to operate in a narrow band (e.g., a scanning head operated at a fixed frequency).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Phase Lead Implementation</head><p>The phaser can also be approximated by a linear filter of the form <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> It must be such that the phase of the filter varies minimally around the design parameter within an operational range of frequencies and (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">10</ref>), where the zeros are located. The poles are determined to achieve a phase angle centered around , between and . The frequency range must be carefully selected since the nonunitary gain amplifies noise at high frequency. The wider the frequency range, the greater the magnitude distortion given by this approximation. Note that the controller can be connected in closed loop to minimize the distortion of the output signal. In the low range, interference with the linear part of the model that produces a widening behavior should be avoided.</p><p>The stability of such connection was established but the proof is beyond the scope of this paper.</p><p>Next, the denominator can be made to depend on the magnitude of the input signal, yielding a variable phaser The coefficients are derived from predesigned phasers with different angles corresponding to different magnitudes of the input signal . . . . . . An interpolation is fitted over the values corresponding to each magnitude , for and , where is the order of the filter and the number of input magnitudes considered. If individual phasers are stable such that poles and zeros are located in the left-hand side of the complex plane, with proper interpolation, the resulting variable phaser will be stable too since the poles will never leave the left-hand side of the complex plane.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. MEASURES OF PERFORMANCE</head><p>The approximations that were made to design hysteresis reducing compensators lead us to expect-as with any other type of control-that performance will be lower than an ideal one. With a measure of performance, different controllers can be compared under given operating conditions. Alternatively, it becomes possible to trade performance for operating frequency range and input magnitudes variations, or even to check the robustness of a controller against plant variations and other sources of uncertainty.</p><p>Given a set of input signals, performance can be expressed by a measure of similarity of an input-output hysteresis loop to a singular linearity or nonlinearity. Two measures are developed. The first can be easily estimated online directly from measurements. The second gives more insight into the behavior of a system, but requires to log measurements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Length Measure</head><p>Consider the continuous mapping between a time interval and an arc of a loop in the input-output plane, with , such that the image points are ordered according to increasing values of , and where , and . The interval is partitioned into subintervals of equal length , for . The length of the polygonal line joining the successive points is <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> The mean value theorem gives us , where and lie between and . The length of the approximating polygonal line is (18) The directed distance along the curve from to is is positive if and negative otherwise <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> We define now the mapping , by , which measures vector functions . The function will be called the "arc length measure" of hysteresis loops, using a time interval needed to trace one loop, that is the smallest interval such that . In practice, only discrete points are obtained, and a discrete version of the arc length measure is used as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. One problem associated with this measure is the effect of noise which produces over-estimates. To alleviate this problem, filtering the input and the output signals with the same filter shifts the two signals by the same amount and preserve the input-output phase relationship.</p><p>For an arbitrary input signal, hysteresis loop hysteresis phaser loop . The measure for such a loop will be bounded under by the length of the corresponding segment of a function (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11</ref>), i.e., when there is no hysteresis in the loop. While this measure can be easily estimated online, it is hard to know what the ultimate limit of reduction is.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Average Measure</head><p>The area inside a loop is a candidate for an average measure. However, it would be cumbersome to use it, should the ascending and descending paths cross. It is better to take advantage of the ordering of the points traced by the input-output trajectory.</p><p>A loop created by an oscillating input is divided according to the extrema of the input into: the ascending path, and the descending path. Consider a point on , and denote the Euclidean distance from this point to , see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12</ref>. If and overlap, the distance is zero. Each path is divided time-wise into equal segments, from time to time for the ascending path, and from time to time for the descending path. The distances from points to the points are measured and summed for . For a finitely sampled loop, is expressed using as <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> It is easily computed directly from logged measurements. If the limit exists where and are distances from the ascending to the descending path in the and coordinates.</p><p>is such that , since a distance is always positive, and it will be zero when is such that the paths overlap, which is precisely when a rate independent system does not have memory. This provides us with an additional property. It is possible to use the average measure to obtain a metric space, where the elements are loops, the distance function is and the zero element is defined.</p><p>This measure gives a better insight into the similarity of the loop to function, which was not the case for the measure . If the measure is zero for all possible inputs, then a perfect reduction has been achieved, and the controller is said to have the best performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Remarks</head><p>does not give a sense of how much reduction in the loop can possibly be achieved, while is bounded by zero, but both can be used to measure the performance of a given controller for a range of inputs. With a specified magnitude, the input-output response can be measured while varying the frequency, say from to . If the performance is evaluated in terms of the amplitude instead, while keeping the frequency constant, a set of measures will be obtained for all possible amplitudes within a certain range from to . If the performance of controller is to be measured for different , and , then the following expression is proposed: <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VIII. EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS</head><p>The design parameters were derived from phase shift estimation in the frequency domain. The experimental plots were obtained using a Siglab Model 2022 system analyzer. The identification procedure used a sine sweep excitation signal. The output signal was processed by a narrow band-pass filter to detect the first harmonic. Phase and amplitude were estimated by input-output cross-correlation. Amplitudes were always peak-to-peak.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Fixed Phaser</head><p>An antagonist configuration using two SMA actuators was used at McGill University for experiments. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> for details. Two different hysteresis loops at different frequencies are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">13</ref>. They exhibit 1) hysteresis; 2) saturation; and 3) a dead-band.</p><p>The empirical open-loop frequency response shown on Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">14</ref> clearly exhibits a phase lag of 38 at low frequency.</p><p>The operational range of the actuator is selected to be . A fourth-order linear approximation to the phaser, with the operational range mentioned above is designed and applied to this system. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">15</ref> shows the frequency response of the controller <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> The approximation to an ideal phaser is not very precise since it is a low-order approximation, but it provides the angle needed. The closed-loop response using the phaser designed above, produces a frequency response as in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">16</ref>.</p><p>The phaser in closed loop reduces the phase lag from 38 to almost nothing over the operating frequency range. The bandwidth is now wider by an order of magnitude. To further examine its effect, some input-output plots are obtained (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">17</ref>). Further efforts with a variable phaser had little effect on the final result.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Variable Phaser</head><p>A variable phaser was designed to reduce hysteresis in a 4-cm lead zirconate titanate bimorph piezoceramic actuator. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">18</ref> shows the input-output response for an alternating signal decreasing in amplitude and increasing in frequency. The frequencies are in the flat range of the actuator, limited upward by a sharp resonance. Each loop has a different phase angle, according to the magnitude of the input. This can be better seen in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">19</ref>, where experimental transfer function estimates are presented for two different input amplitudes. The Bode phase plot shows an almost constant angle over the low-frequency range for each input amplitude.</p><p>The lead filter was designed to provide a phase of between Hz and Hz. The order was (24)</p><p>A variable phaser was also designed to compare its performance with the fixed one. The order is and the number of input amplitudes . The variation of the phase angle with magnitude is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">20</ref>. The expression of the variable  phaser is for <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> The same input signal was used to observe the effects of the phaser and of the variable phaser. The responses are plotted on Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">21</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">22</ref>.</p><p>There seems to be an improvement over the fixed compensator, but of course, it is hard to appreciate graphically: an additional justification for the use quantitative measures (see Section IX). The empirical transfer function Bode plots are presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">23</ref>. The amplitude and phase uncertainties between and are smaller. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Performance</head><p>These results were obtained without any tuning other than the selection of a loop gain, according to the following design procedure.</p><p>1) Obtain experimental Bode plots for several amplitudes.</p><p>2) Determine phase lag(s) in the quasistatic range.</p><p>3) Select an operational range. For small ones, use the Hilbert FIR transformer implementation, for narrow ones use the PD implementation, otherwise use a lead approximation and trade filter order with phase and gain accuracy. 4) Select the loop gain to be as high as the control authority and the phase margin allow. In our experience, control authority was the limiting factor, not stability. and were calculated for cases in the two previous sections, see Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_0">II</ref>.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IX. CONCLUSION</head><p>We have proposed a design methodology based on a phase operator for compensation of hysteresis in systems that can be represented by a parallel connection of a linear filter and a rate independent hysteresis block. Such a representation is applicable to transducers based on smart materials. We then proposed three causal approximations for the implementation of this ideal operator. The sole parameter needed for the design of the compensator is an estimate of the phase angle . Making the phase depend on input magnitude allowed us to generalize this approach to address minor loops.</p><p>Two different measures have been introduced to quantitatively describe performance. One measure, , depends on the length of the loop arc, and the other, , on the average distance between the two paths of a loop. gives a better insight on the reduction of the hysteresis loop, but cannot be easily computed online.</p><p>The effectiveness of the approach could then be demonstrated for two types of actuators based on smart materials. It is expected that open-loop compensators of the type described would also effective at correcting hysteresis in sensors with hysteresis, such strain gauge force sensors.</p><p>Experimental studies were also carried out with more general signals, namely band-limited random signals and good results were obtained as well. In such cases, the performance of the compensators was examined in the time domain. These results are left to future reports.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Hysteresis loop and branching.</figDesc><graphic coords="1,363.06,136.44,127.20,58.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. A black box representation of hysteresis.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Relay as a basic hysteresis operator.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,397.44,62.28,61.44,72.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Limiting triangle for the Preisach model.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,374.10,173.28,108.24,98.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Hysteresis loops and their limiting triangles.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,62.28,62.28,202.80,101.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Block representation of a transducer with hysteresis.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Phaser in tandem connection with the plant.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,349.74,62.28,156.96,58.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .Fig. 9 .</head><label>89</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. (a) Hysteresis with saturation. (b) Phaser. (c) Composite loop.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,325.80,160.08,204.72,88.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Frequency response. (a) Ideal phaser. (b) Approximation.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,327.66,62.28,198.00,99.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. (a) Hysteresis loops with and without saturation, top, and bottom. (b) Compensated loops.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,364.44,62.28,127.44,93.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Average measure M .</figDesc><graphic coords="7,74.46,62.28,178.32,58.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13. Displacement versus current hysteresis of antagonist SMA actuators. Left: 0.01 Hz. Right: 0.1 Hz.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,317.52,199.50,218.40,172.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 15 .</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Fig. 15. Phaser controller for the SMA actuator ( = 38 degrees).</figDesc><graphic coords="8,57.72,62.28,214.80,170.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 16 .</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Fig. 16. Closed-loop frequency response using a constant phaser.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,58.80,271.14,212.64,170.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 17 .</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Fig. 17. Compensated phase loops at 0.01 and 0.1 Hz.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,302.64,62.28,257.52,108.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 19 .</head><label>19</label><figDesc>Fig. 19. Open-loop transfer functions. Inputs are in a 1:7 ratio.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,327.00,338.64,202.32,170.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 20 .Fig. 21 .Fig. 22 .</head><label>202122</label><figDesc>Fig. 20. Variation of the phase angle as a function of the input magnitude ju(t)j.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Fig. 23 .</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Fig. 23. Closed-loop transfer function for small and large input. Dashed line: fixed phaser; continuous line: variable phaser.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE I COMPARISON</head><label>I</label><figDesc>OF MEASURES FOR THE SMA ACTUATORTABLE II COMPARISON OF MEASURES FOR THE PIEZOCERAMIC ACTUATOR</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors would like to thank the reviewers for their constructive comments.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by an operating grant from NSERC, the Natural Science and Engineering Council of Canada and in part by IRIS (Phase II), the Institute for Robotics and Intelligent Systems part of Canada's Centers of Excellence Program (NCE), project "MSA-4." J. M. Cruz-Hernández was with the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, and the Center for Intelligent Machines, McGill University,Montréal, PQ, Canada. He is now with Immersion Canada Inc., Montréal, PQ,</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hysteretic control influence operators representing smart material actuators: Identification and approximation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kurdila</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Conf. Decision Contr</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conf. Decision Contr</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3711" to="3716" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis and control of dynamic system with hysteresis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Banning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Koning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M T</forename><surname>Adriaens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Conf. Decision Contr</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conf. Decision Contr</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2011" to="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analytical foundations of Volterra series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Chua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Desoer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IMA J. Math. Contr. Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brokate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sprekels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Hysteresis and Phase Transitions</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An H almost disturbance decoupling robust controller design for a piezoelectric bimorph actuator with hysteresis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Weerasooriya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Contr. Syst. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="160" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-03">Mar. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the linear compensation of hysteresis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cruz-Hernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">36th IEEE Conf. Decision Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1956" to="1957" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An approach to reduction of hysteresis in smart materials</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">1998 IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1510" to="1515" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Hysteresis Effects in Economic Models</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Physica-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking control of a piezoceramic actuator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jouaneh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Contr. Syst. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-05">May 1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavioral implications of piezoelectric stack actuators for control of micromanipulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goldfarb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Celanovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Automat</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Automat</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="231" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability of control for the Preisach hysteresis model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gorbet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 1997 IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Automat</title>
		<meeting>1997 IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Automat</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="247" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variable structure control of shape memory alloy actuators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Syst. Contr. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preisach modeling and compensation for smart material hysteresis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SPIE, Active Materials Smart Struct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2427</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preisach modeling of a piezoceramic and shape memory alloy hysteresis</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Conf. Contr. Applicat</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1086" to="1091" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improvement of scanning accuracy of PZT piezoelectric actuators by feed-forward model-reference control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Precision Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simple way to reduce hysteresis and creep when using piezoelectric actuators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kaizuka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Siu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Japan. J. Appl. Phys. Part 2-Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="773" to="776" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-05">May 1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An H based controller for a gas turbine clearance control system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Korson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Helmicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">IEEE Conf. Contr. Applicat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1154" to="1159" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mathematical Models of Hysteresis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mayergoyz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the linearity of piezoelectric ceramic actuators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Newcomb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Flinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electron. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="442" to="444" />
			<date type="published" when="1982-05">May 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Oppenheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Willsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Signals and Systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Communications Systems Engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Proakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salehi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ruch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Patton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiology and Biophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="733" to="759" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
			<publisher>Saunders</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonlinear System Theory: The Volterra/Wiener Approach, ser. Johns Hopkins series in information science and systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
			<publisher>Johns Hopkins Univ. Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compensation of hysteresis in solid state actuators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schafer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Janocha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sensors Actuators A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Volterra and Wiener Theories of Nonlinear Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schetzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural network compensation of gear backlash hysteresis in position-controlled mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Seidl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Putman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lorenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Applicat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1475" to="1482" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-11">Nov. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Nonlinear Model-Based Control Method for Magnetostrictive Actuators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>CRSC-TR97-25</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Center Res. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-09">Sept. 1997</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>North Carolina State Univ</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Nonlinear Physics-Based Optimal Control Method for Magnetostrictive Actuators</title>
		<idno>CRSC-TR97-33</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Center Res. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10">Oct. 1997</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>North Carolina State Univ</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stearns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Signal Processing Algorithms</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Engelwood Cliffs, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive control of systems with nonsmooth input and output nonlinearities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 34th Conf. Decision Contr</title>
		<meeting>34th Conf. Decision Contr</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3429" to="3434" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive control of plants with unknown hysteresis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kokotovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">´</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-02">Feb. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adaptive Control of Systems with Actuator and Sensor Nonlinearities</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Visintin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Differential Models of Hysteresis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hysteresis modeling of SMA actuators for control applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Webb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lagoudas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kurdila</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Intell. Material Syst. Structures</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="432" to="448" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-06">June 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
