<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012-11-14">November 14, 2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Samuel</forename><surname>Drapeau</surname></persName>
							<email>drapeau@math.hu-berlin.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Humboldt University Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-10099</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Kupper</surname></persName>
							<email>kupper@math.hu-berlin.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Humboldt University Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-10099</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">0364-765X (print)</idno>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2012-11-14">November 14, 2012</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">226DE4DBA9138E61AFFDB3F0E73A2F47</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1287/moor.1120.0560</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received September 29, 2011; revised May 3, 2012. Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T06:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>risk perception</term>
					<term>risk measures</term>
					<term>robustness MSC2000 subject classification: Primary: 91B06, 49N15</term>
					<term>secondary: 91B08, 91B30 OR/MS subject classification: Primary: utility/preference theory</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>http://www.mathematik.hu-berlin.de/ ~kupper/} To address the plurality of interpretations of the subjective notion of risk, we describe it by means of a risk order and concentrate on the context invariant features of diversification and monotonicity. Our main results are uniquely characterized robust representations of lower semicontinuous risk orders on vector spaces and convex sets. This representation covers most instruments related to risk and allows for a differentiated interpretation depending on the underlying context that is illustrated in different settings: for random variables, risk perception can be interpreted as model risk, and we compute among others the robust representation of the economic index of riskiness. For lotteries, risk perception can be viewed as distributional risk and we study the "value at risk." For consumption patterns, which excerpt an intertemporality dimension in risk perception, we provide an interpretation in terms of discounting risk and discuss some examples.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction.</head><p>Risk is now a colloquial and widely used term. Nevertheless, its emergence in history is relatively recent. 1 Actually, "the late apparition in history of circumstances indicated by means of the new term 'risk' is probably due to the fact that it accommodates a plurality of distinctions within one concept, thus constituting the unity of this plurality," Luhmann <ref type="bibr">[41, p. 16]</ref>. Many scientific areas ranging from economics and finance to sociology or medicine have now laid claim to this concept with their own instruments, language, and objectives focusing on different types of risk such that, even today, when it comes to specifying this notion, ways are parting and no real consensus emerges. Yet, at the beginning of the twentieth century, discussing in an economical context his famous distinction between measurable uncertainty, where an objective probability can be assigned to uncertain outcomes, and unmeasurable uncertainty, where no a priori probability can be provided, Knight proposed to identify risk with measurable uncertainty. 2 This Knightian distinction between unmeasurable uncertainty and his notion of risk identified with measurable uncertainty has strongly influenced modern economic thought; in particular the subsequent developments of decision theory where properties reflecting a normative view of rationality in the expression of preferences in face of uncertainty are studied.</p><p>Von Neumann and Morgenstern <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> initiated this approach with their work on preferences over lotteries, which under some conditions admit a numerical representation in terms of an expected utility. An important milestone though, beyond this paradigm of expected utility for which many extension were given, is the axiomatic approach of Gilboa and Schmeidler <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. Motivated from a decision theoretical viewpoint, they obtain a representation in terms of the worst expected utility of a random variable evaluated with respect to different probability models. Such a robustification of the expected utility has further been extended by Klibanoff et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, Maccheroni et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, and Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. From another viewpoint, motivated by the need of regulatory agencies for a method of specifying capital requirements for financial institutions, Artzner et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> introduced an axiomatic framework to describe the risk of financial products. This led to the concept of coherent cash additive risk measures that are characterized by representations taking the worst of expected losses of a random variable evaluated with respect to different probability models. This concept has been further extended to the concept of convex cash additive risk measures introduced independently by Föllmer and Schied <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, Frittelli and Rosazza Gianin <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, and Heath <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>.</p><p>In view of these normative approaches, let us come back to the Knightian identification between risk and measurable uncertainty. Actually, the developments in the theory of preferences and cash additive risk measures suggest to separate these two notions. Indeed, the well-founded use of the term risk in the theory of cash additive risk measures does not match Knight's notion of risk. By way of their representation, cash additive risk measures 2 Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. <ref type="bibr">1-35, © 2012 INFORMS</ref> turn out to address risk in the sense of unmeasurable uncertainty, because different probability models, rather than a single one, are taken into account just as in Gilboa and Schmeidler's robustification of expected utility. Throughout this work, in line with Knight <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> and Keynes <ref type="bibr">[37, pp. 213-214]</ref>, uncertainty describes merely the fact that a situation might have more than one possible outcome, for instance, situations of prospective nature. Unmeasurable uncertainty corresponds to situations where we simply can not know, and measurable uncertainty applies to situations where some quantification can take place. Such a quantification might for instance involve a set of probability models as illustrated in §4.1 or a set of discounting functions, as in §4.3. Now, even if risk is intimately related to uncertainty, in contrast to Knight, we do not identify it with measurable uncertainty. Indeed, although uncertainty, measurable or not, is an inherent quality of a situation, risk is not. Risk is definitively a subjective notion because "causal terms and terms like risk or danger are not indications of ontological facts about which one can have only true or false opinions.</p><p>Risk evaluation is not simply a problem of avoiding an error. The question rather is who uses which frame to guide his observations; and then, who observes others handle causal distinctions and how they discriminate external and internal attribution depending upon whether they themselves or others make the decisions" (Luhmann <ref type="bibr">[40, p. 6]</ref>). Luhmann underlines thereby also that risk is rather a matter of perception that clearly depends on one's perspective and the surrounding context.</p><p>These different considerations on uncertainty and risk are our primary motivations to approach the risk perception of uncertainty in a sense that firstly reflects its subjective nature and secondly allows for a context and perspective dependent interpretation. The emphasis on the subjective dimension is the reason to consider the risk perception of elements subject to uncertainty by means of a preference order where the relation x y means "the element x is perceived to be less risky than the element y." To characterize this preference order as a perception of risk while keeping track of the context dependency, we concentrate on invariant key features commonly related to risk. These are expressed by the normative statements "diversification should not increase the risk" and "the better for sure, the less risky." A preference order reflecting such properties will be called a risk order. Beyond the fact that there is a broad consensus that diversification and monotonicity capture crucial features of risk perception, they leave full latitude in which setting they are considered and how they might be specified. Because monotonicity is formulated by means of an arbitrary preorder 3 and diversification by an arbitrary convex structure, their specification induces different notions and interpretations.</p><p>The first advantage of our approach is that it covers most of the instruments related in one way or another to risk: von Neumann and Morgenstern's expected utilities, Markowitz's <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> mean variance, Sharpe's <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref> ratio and "value at risk," Gilboa and Schmeidler's <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> robustification of expected utilities and monetary risk measures, Aumann and Serrano's <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> economic index of riskiness, or Cherny and Madan's <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> performance measures, to name but a few. As for the second advantage, our approach provides the key instruments for the interpretation of risk perception under different perspectives by means of our main result, a robust representation of risk orders on general convex sets of the form x = sup</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">x * R x * x * -x<label>(1)</label></formula><p>In this representation, the risk measure is a numerical representation of the considered risk order and R is a uniquely characterized maximal risk function. As for the general meaning of such a representation, the risk of the "losses" of an uncertain element x is estimated under an evaluation x * by means of the operation x * -x . However, because a risk perceiver is not sure which evaluation is adequate to estimate the losses, other evaluations are considered weighted according to their plausibility by means of the maximal risk function R. Finally, a precautious approach is adopted by taking the maximum of those estimations justifying henceforth the terminology "robust." This schema is generic as for the expression of risk perception; as for the key instruments for the interpretation, they are given by the nature of the uncertain elements x and the corresponding set of evaluations x * . Let us briefly illustrate this robust representation for different settings for which diversification and monotonicity correspond to radically different notions and interpretations. On the level of random variables X with the standard notion of monotonicity "greater than almost surely," the robust representation reduces to</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">X = sup Q R Q E Q -X<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where the evaluations Q are probability measures allowing to view risk perception as model risk. On the level of lotteries , where diversification corresponds to some additional randomization, and the monotonicity is specified by the first stochastic order, the risk perception is characterized by a robust representation 3 where the evaluations l are increasing loss functions. Risk perception may here be interpreted as distributional risk. On the level of consumption patterns c, the intertemporal dimension in the risk perception has a representation of the form c = sup R -1 0 s dc s <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref> where the evaluations are some discounting functions yielding a risk perception in terms of discounting risk.</p><p>In conclusion, our approach to risk perception is in accordance with Luhmann's quotation in the first paragraph of the introduction, because it allows for a plurality of interpretations within one framework depending on the context and one's perspective.</p><p>We next discuss and compare related results to our robust representation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Penot and Volle <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> have obtained some duality results of the form (1) for quasiconvex functionals. However, they do not address the issues of monotonicity and uniqueness, the latter being crucial for comparative statics in terms of the risk function R. Recently, Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref> proved the uniqueness of the representation (1) under the denomination of a complete quasiconvex duality result. We wish to point out that their results and the signification of quasiconvexity in preferences theory were a crucial source of inspiration for the present work. Whereas their results address a complete quasiconvex duality for evenly or upper semicontinuous functions in the setting of M-spaces 4 or p spaces, our main result is a complete quasiconvex duality for lower semicontinuous functions on convex subsets of general locally convex vector spaces. One of the advantages of the technical assumption of lower semicontinuity is that it is often a consequence of the monotonicity (see <ref type="bibr">Remark 7)</ref>. Our approach allows us in particular to consider other types of risk perceptions besides the setting of bounded random variables such as lotteries or consumption patterns as studied in §4. In the specific setting of lotteries, a related representation has independently been achieved by Cerreia-Vioglio <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. There, convex preferences on the set of simple lotteries over a general set are considered. He furthermore investigates convex preferences over sets of so called menus, yielding a maxmin representation. In contrast, in §4.2, we study lower semicontinuous risk orders over general lotteries with compact support on the real line, which are monotone with respect to the first stochastic order.</p><p>The subsequent work is structured as follows. In the first section, we introduce the concept of risk orders on convex sets of uncertain elements. We further introduce risk measures, which are quasiconvex monotone functions playing the role of numerical representation of risk orders, and define risk acceptance families. The main result of the first section is Theorem 1, which clarifies the one-to-one correspondence between risk orders, risk measures, and risk acceptance families. In § §2.1 and 2.2, we study additional properties of risk measures such as convexity, positive homogeneity, scaling invariance, affinity, and cash additivity or cash subadditivity. In the second section, we give a dual representation of lower semicontinuous risk orders in the setting of locally convex topological vector spaces. The main Theorem 3, shows that any lower semicontinuous risk measure of a lower semicontinuous risk order admits a robust representation of the form 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Furthermore, we characterize the class of maximal 6 risk functions R for which the uniqueness in this representation holds. If the monotonicity preorder satisfies a regularity condition, Theorem 4 states that the supremum in (1) can actually be taken over a smaller set of normalized evaluations. 7 The delicate question of the existence and uniqueness of a robust representation on a convex subset of a vector space is addressed in §3.1. Indeed, we provide an example where the uniqueness in the class of maximal risk functions is no longer ensured when considering risk measures on a convex subset. Under the assumption of continuous extensibility, which automatically holds for many convex sets, we provide in Theorem 5 a characterization of a smaller class of maximal risk functions for which a complete quasiconvex duality result holds on convex sets. This result covers the important settings of lotteries, or consumption patterns. In the third section we study how our robust representation applies in several illustrative settings. Beside the interest in terms of a differentiated interpretation of risk perception, it also illustrates how the risk acceptance family plays a central role in explicit computations of maximal risk functions. In the setting of random variables, we discuss how the Fatou property provides a robust representation of the form (2) in terms of probability measures. As an example, we compute robust representations of various certainty equivalents, and the economic index of riskiness. In the setting of lotteries, we derive a unique robust 4 A typical example of an M space is the set of bounded random variables. 5 The set of evaluations over which the supremum in (1) is taken is the polar cone determined by the preorder used to define the monotonicity of the risk order. 6 The term "maximal" risk function is justified in a pointwise sense by Proposition 5. 7 In the case of bounded random variables with monotonicity preorder "greater than almost surely," the normalized subset corresponds to the set of probability measures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref> where the set of maximal risk functions is remarkably identical with the one of the respective vector space. A discussion and a robust representation of the value at risk illustrates then the importance of the setting because it is quasiconvex on the level of lotteries but not on the level of random variables. Diversification on the level of consumption patterns excerpts another interesting dimension of risk perception, namely, the one related to intertemporal relations. We derive a robust representation on this convex set of the form (4), which we illustrate by an intertemporal risk measure inspired by Hindy et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. Finally, Theorem 9 in §4.4 illustrates the interplay between model risk and distributional risk in the setting of Anscombe and Aumann <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The appendix collects standard mathematical concepts and all the technical proofs.</p><p>2. Risk orders, risk measures, and risk acceptance families. Throughout, we study the risk of elements x in some nonempty space . The risk perception is specified by a total preorder 8 on denoted by . As usual, the notations ≺ = and and ∼ = and , respectively, correspond to the antisymmetric and equivalence relation. A numerical representation of a total preorder is a mapping F → -+ , such that</p><p>x y if and only if</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">F x ≤ F y<label>(5)</label></formula><p>for all x y ∈ . It is well known (see Debreu <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref>) that a total preorder admits a numerical representation if and only if it is separable. 9 It is also straightforward to check that a numerical representation of is unique up to increasing transformation, that is, for any two numerical representations F F of there exists an increasing function h Im F → Im F such that F = h F . Our aim is to characterize those total preorders that deserve the denomination "risk." As evoked in the introduction, the main properties related to risk perception are the diversification and some form of monotonicity. To diversify risky elements, we need to express convex combinations, thus, is from now on a convex subset 10 of a vector space . As for the monotonicity, we need a relation specifying that some elements are "better for sure" than others, which is expressed by a preorder on . Throughout, we assume that is even a vector preorder. 11 A total preorder that reflects the diversification and monotonicity properties is called a risk order.</p><p>Definition 1 (Risk Order). A total preorder on is a risk order if it is • quasiconvex: x + 1 -y y for any ∈ 0 1 whenever x y;</p><p>• monotone: x y whenever x y.</p><p>Here, the relation x y means "x is less risky than y." The quasiconvexity axiom reflects exactly that the diversification between two alternatives keeps the risk below the worse one. The monotonicity axiom states that the risk order is compatible with the preorder . In the following, x = y ∈ y x consists of those elements that are less risky than x ∈ . Note that a total preorder is quasiconvex exactly when</p><p>x is convex for all x ∈ .</p><p>Remark 1. Note that the monotonicity can be ruled out if the vector preorder is trivial, that is, the relation x y holds if and only if x = y. In that case, we say that the risk order is monotone with respect to the trivial preorder.</p><p>The abstractness of the setting agrees with our declared intention to concentrate solely on the properties characterizing the risk perception as such. This allows us to appreciate and interpret it under different lights depending on the underlying context. We precise this thereafter with several illustrative settings that will be studied in §4.</p><p>• Random variables. In finance, risky positions-equities, credits, derivative products, insurance contracts, portfolios, etc.-are commonly random variables defined on some state space . Capital letters X Y are usually used instead of x y to refer to those risky positions. A possible choice for is the vector space 8 A preorder is a binary relation on , which is reflexive and transitive. A binary relation is reflexive if x x for all x ∈ , and transitive if x y and y z implies x z. A total preorder is a preorder, which in addition is complete, that is, x y or y x for all x y ∈ . Note that a complete binary relation is reflexive. 9 A total preorder is separable if there exists a countable set ⊆ such that for any x y ∈ with x ≺ y there is z ∈ for which x z y. 10 The framework of a mixture space could have been considered as well, at least in the first section. However, up to two reasonable additional conditions (nontriviality, and a weak form of associativity), mixture spaces can be embedded as a convex subset of a vector space, see Mongin <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. 11 A vector preorder is the restriction to of a preorder defined on the vector space ⊃ such that x y implies x + z y + z for any z ∈ and x y for any ≥ 0. A vector preorder is specified by the convex cone = x ∈ x 0 , for which x y exactly when xy ∈ .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>=</head><p>P , 12 where P is a reference probability measure defined on a -algebra of possible scenarios . The diversification is expressed by the state-wise convex combination X + 1 -Y for P -almost all , and the canonical preorder is given by the relation "greater than P -almost surely."</p><p>• Lotteries. Historically, probability distributions, referred to as lotteries, play an important role in decision theory. Here also, the tradition sees the use of the notation instead of x y We will consider the set 1 c of lotteries with compact support on the real line. Here, a convex combination + 1 -can be interpreted as some additional randomization, because it corresponds to the sampling of either the lottery or depending on the outcome of a binary lottery with probability or 1 -. As a convex set, 1 c spans the vector space ca c of bounded signed measures with compact support. Different orders might be considered on 1 c such as the first or second stochastic order defined by if f d ≥ f d for all continuous nondecreasing, respectively, concave continuous nondecreasing functions f → . • Consumption patterns. They are particularly adequate to excerpt the intertemporal dimension in the perception of successive consumption of a commodity, in particular the substitution effects. To take into account gulps along continuity, these consumption patterns in time are modelled by nondecreasing right-continuous paths c 0 1 → 0 + , where the value c t represents the cumulative amount of consumption up to time t ∈ 0 1 . Diversification expressed by means of the time-wise convex combination c</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">1 t + 1 -c 2 t</formula><p>for all 0 ≤ t ≤ 1. The set of consumption patterns denoted by = 0 1 is a convex cone. A possible preorder is defined by c 1 c 2 exactly when c 1 -c 2 belongs to .</p><p>• Stochastic kernels. They can be seen as lotteries that are additionally subject to model uncertainty. These state dependant lotteries denoted by ˜ = ˜ dx unify somehow lotteries and random variables in one object and can be used to illustrate the interplay between model uncertainty and distributional uncertainty in the risk perception. 13 Mathematically, the set of stochastic kernels consists of all measurable mappings 14 ˜ → 1 c , where P is a probability space. Convex combinations are -wise randomizations between state dependant lotteries, ˜ dx + 1 -˜ dx . As for the preorder we consider the P -almost sure second stochastic order, that is, ˜ ˜ if the lottery ˜</p><p>• dominates in the second stochastic order the lottery ˜ • for P -almost all ∈ .</p><p>Remark 2. The notion of diversification strongly depends on the underlying setting. This can be seen in the difference between the settings of random variables and lotteries. Indeed, the randomization P X + 1 -P Y of lotteries P X and P Y corresponding to the laws of random variables X and Y under a probability measure P generally differs from the lottery P X+ 1-Y corresponding to the law of the state-wise convex combination X + 1 -Y . This has crucial consequences for the interpretation in terms of risk perception as illustrated in the following example. Suppose that a lender faces a choice between two similar but independent loans each with a default probability of 1%. Assume also that the risk perception of this lender is focused on the probability of loosing money. The lender estimates therefore a mere convex combination of half a loan and half the other as more risky because the probability of loosing money increases to almost 2%, even if the loss size is reduced. The perspective of its perception is however explicitly in a distributional sense rather than in terms of values. From this point of view, diversification is understood on the level of lotteries, where such a convex combination corresponds to a coin toss before choosing one loan or the other. By doing so, the probability of loosing money remains at 1%. Numerical representations of risk orders inherit the key properties of risk perception and thus are from now on called risk measures and generically denoted by . In Theorem 1 a correspondence between risk measures and risk orders will be given that justifies the following definition.</p><p>Definition 2 (Risk Measure). A mapping → -+ is called a risk measure if it is</p><p>• quasiconvex:</p><p>x + 1 -y ≤ max x y for all x y ∈ and ∈ 0 1 ;</p><p>• monotone: x ≤ y whenever x y. Example 1. The certainty equivalent of an expected loss can be considered on the level of lotteries,</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">= l -1 l -x dx ∈ 1 c<label>(6) 12</label></formula><p>P denotes the vector space of all essentially bounded random variables, where random variables are identified when they coincide P -almost surely. 13 They were first used in economic theory by Anscombe and Aumann <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> and further by Gilboa and Schmeidler <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> for their maximin expected utilities with multiple priors. See also Föllmer and Schied <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, Klibanoff et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, Maccheroni et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, and Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> among others. where l → is a continuous increasing loss function. Because the increasing function l -1 is clearly quasiaffine 15 it follows that is monotone with respect to the first stochastic order and</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">+ 1 - = l -1 l -x dx + 1 - l -x dx ≤ max</formula><p>for all ∈ 1 c and ∈ 0 1 and so is a risk measure. On the level of random variables, the certainty equivalent of an expected loss is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">ˆ X = l -1 E l -X X ∈<label>(7)</label></formula><p>Even though ˆ X = P X , the diversification on the level of random variables is different and the loss function l has to be additionally convex to ensure that ˆ is a risk measure; see Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> where a robust version of it with more than a loss function has also been studied. Explicit computation of the robust representation of this risk measure will be given in §4, Example 8. Before stating the relation between risk orders and risk measures, we introduce another concept crucial for the further understanding of this work. Given a risk measure , for any risk level m ∈ , we define the risk acceptance set of level m as the subset m ⊆ of those elements having a risk smaller than m, that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">m = x ∈ x ≤ m m ∈<label>(8)</label></formula><p>We call = m m∈ the risk acceptance family associated to . Here again, the risk acceptance family carries the specificities of the risk measure. In Theorem 1 we will state a one-to-one relation between risk measures and risk acceptance families that satisfy the following conditions.</p><p>Definition 3 (Risk Acceptance Family). An increasing 16 family = m m∈ of subsets m ⊆ is a risk acceptance family if it is</p><p>• convex: m is a convex subset of for all m ∈ ; • monotone: x ∈ m and y x implies y ∈ m ; • right continuous: m = n&gt;m n for all m ∈ . The risk acceptance family is not only a major instrument for the robust representation of risk measures in §3, it can also be used to describe further structural properties or to model specific economical features of risk (see <ref type="bibr">Example 6)</ref>.</p><p>The following theorem states the one-to-one correspondence between risk orders, risk measures, and risk acceptance families.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theorem 1. Any numerical representation</head><p>→ -+ of a risk order is a risk measure. Conversely, any risk measure → -+ defines a risk order through x y if and only if x ≤ y</p><p>Moreover, = and = h for some increasing transformation h. Furthermore, for any risk measure , the family given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">m = x ∈ x ≤ m m ∈ (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">)</formula><p>is a risk acceptance family. Conversely, for any risk acceptance family , the functional given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">x = inf m ∈ x ∈ m x ∈<label>(11)</label></formula><p>defines a risk measure. Moreover, = and = .</p><p>The proof is in Appendix C.1. The idea of expressing the numerical representation of a total preorder by means of an increasing family of acceptance sets as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> was recently used in other works: Cherny and Madan <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> characterize a class of performance measures built upon a specific family of acceptance sets 17 and Brown et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> represent a type of prospective preferences also by means of acceptance sets that are not necessarily convex. 15 Any nondecreasing function from to is automatically quasiaffine, a definition of which is given in Appendix A. 16 That is, m ⊆ n for any m ≤ n. 17 The risk acceptance family corresponds to the acceptance sets of a family of coherent monetary risk measures (see §2.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. Remark 3. Although the convexity and monotonicity of a risk acceptance family reflect the key properties of risk perception, the right continuity is needed to ensure the one-to-one correspondence. Indeed, in the proof of Theorem 1, it turns out that is a risk measure even if the risk acceptance family is not right continuous. Nevertheless, it plays a crucial role for the relation 18  = . Be aware that the right-continuity condition for the risk acceptance family is not of topological nature.</p><p>For notational convenience we mostly drop the reference indices and simply write , , instead of , , or , respectively. We now illustrate the previous theorem with the following two families of risk measures. Example 2. Introduced by Föllmer and Schied <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, the shortfall risk measure is of additive nature and given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">X = inf s ∈ E l -X -s ≤ c 0 X ∈<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where E l -X is the expected loss of the position X according to a lower semicontinuous convex loss function l → -+ increasing on its domain and such that l s 0 &lt; + for some s 0 &gt; 0. This risk measure accounts for the minimal amount of money, which added to the position X pulls its expected loss below a given threshold c 0 in the range of l 0 +</p><p>. By the strict monotonicity and the lower semicontinuity of the loss function l holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">m = X ∈ X ≤ m = X ∈ c 0 ≥ E l -X -m</formula><p>for any risk level m ∈ . Since X → E l -X -m is convex and monotone, we deduce that is a risk acceptance family and therefore, by means of Theorem 1, is a risk measure.</p><p>Example 3. First introduced by Aumann and Serrano <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> in the exponential case and extended to the logarithmic case by Foster and Hart <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, the economic index of riskiness, similar to the shortfall risk measure but of multiplicative nature, fits particularly well for returns. It can be generalized and interpreted as follows. We first define</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">X = sup &gt; 0 E l -X ≤ c 0</formula><p>which represents the maximal exposure to a position X ∈ provided that the expected loss remains below an acceptable level c 0 in the range of l 0 + . Here, l is a loss function as in Example 2, which in addition fulfills the growth condition 19 lim x→+ l x /x = + . The economic index of riskiness is then defined 20 as</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">X = 1 X X ∈ Given a risk level 21 m &gt; 0 holds m = X ∈ X ≥ 1/m = X ∈ c 0 ≥ E l -X/m</formula><p>Because of the convexity and the monotonicity of X → E l -X it follows that is convex and monotone and thus a risk acceptance family. Therefore, in view of Theorem 1, the economic index of riskiness is a risk measure. The loss functions in Aumann and Serrano <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and Foster and Hart <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> correspond to l s = e s -1 and l s = -ln 1 -s , respectively. A computation of the robust representation will be given in §4, Example 9. Remark 4. Theorem 1 ensures that as soon as of one of these objects-risk order, risk measure, or risk acceptance family-is given, the other two are simultaneously precised. The notion of quasiconvexity and monotonicity are therefore global features, because any numerical representation of a risk order shares these properties, and vice versa. In the following subsections, we will study additional properties of risk measures, such as convexity, affinity, or cash additivity among others. Unlike quasiconvexity and monotonicity, most of them do not hold for the entire class of numerical representations of the corresponding risk order and are in this sense no longer global. In the following, we call a risk order convex, affine, cash additive, etc., when there exists at least one numerical representation having this property. 18 Indeed, on = , consider the family m = -m + , which is monotone and convex but fails to be right continuous since m = -m + = n&gt;m -n + . Here, x = -x and m = -m + for all m ∈ , showing that = . 19 Because of the monotonicity and convexity of l this growth condition insures the intuitive idea that expected losses are inflated more than gains since for any X ∈ taking negative values on a set of positive probability, E l -X → + for → + . 20 With the usual conventions 1/0 = + and 1/+ = 0. 21 Clearly, for any m &lt; 0 holds m = , and 0 = + , which are both convex.</p><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. </p><formula xml:id="formula_16">• convex if x + 1 -y ≤</formula><p>x + 1 -y for all x y ∈ and ∈ 0 1 ;</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">• positive homogeneous if x =</formula><p>x for all x ∈ and &gt; 0;</p><p>• scaling invariant if x = x for all x ∈ and &gt; 0;</p><p>• affine if is real valued and x + 1 -y = x + 1 -y for all x y ∈ and ∈ 0 1 . The notions of positive homogeneity and scaling invariance require in addition that is a convex cone. In line with Remark 4, we call a risk order convex, positive homogeneous, etc. if it can be represented by a risk measure that has this property.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposition 1. (i)</head><p>A risk measure is convex if and only if the corresponding risk acceptance family is level convex, that is, m + 1 -m ⊆ m+ 1-m for all m m ∈ and ∈ 0 1 . (ii) A risk measure is positive homogeneous if and only if the corresponding risk acceptance family is positive homogeneous, that is, m = m for all m ∈ and &gt; 0. Moreover, any positive homogeneous risk order satisfies</p><p>x =</p><p>x for all x ∈ and &gt; 0. (iii) Any risk measure corresponding to a risk order , which satisfies x ∼ x for all &gt; 0, is scaling invariant. Moreover, is scaling invariant if and only if the corresponding risk acceptance family is scaling invariant, that is, m = m for all m ∈ and &gt; 0. (iv) A risk order admits an affine risk measure if and only if it fulfills the independence and Archimedean properties. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">22</ref> This affine risk measure is, up to increasing affine transformations, unique in the class of affine risk measures. <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>, for the others we refer to Appendix C.2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statement (iv) is a well-known result by von Neumann and Morgenstern</head><p>Remark 5. Even if convexity, positive homogeneity, or affinity are not global properties, the scaling invariance though is global because any increasing transformation of a scaling invariant risk measure is scaling invariant.</p><p>Example 4. The Sharpe ratio introduced by Sharpe <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref> is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">X =      - E X E X 2 -E X 2 if E X &gt; 0 0 else X ∈<label>(13)</label></formula><p>with convention that s/0 = -for s &lt; 0, is quasiconvex and scaling invariant. Even if it is not monotone for the relation "greater than P -almost surely," it is still a scaling invariant risk measure with respect to the trivial preorder. For a monotone alternative to the Sharpe ratio we refer to Cerny <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. A general study of scaling invariant risk measures can be found in Cherny and Madan <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p><p>In the spirit of expected utilities by Savage <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>, we define the expected loss of a random variable as</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">X = E Q l -X X ∈<label>(14)</label></formula><p>for some probability measure Q absolutely continuous with respect to P and a continuous loss function l → . It is a convex risk measure if l is nondecreasing and convex. The expected loss is not affine on the level of random variables, unless l is affine. However, because it is law invariant, it can also be considered on the level of probability distribution by the identification</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">Q X = ∈ 1 c through ˜ = l -x dx ∈ 1 c<label>(15)</label></formula><p>which is an affine risk measure and corresponds to a von Neumann and Morgenstern <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> representation. Note that a robust version of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">14</ref>) over more than one probability measure yields the representation of Gilboa and Schmeidler <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>.  2.2. Monetary risk orders. Especially for financial applications, it is meaningful to express risk in monetary units by means of a numéraire 0, which often is a risk free bank account = 1 + r for some interest rate r &gt; -1. Throughout this section, we assume that is a vector space.</p><p>Definition 5. A risk measure → -+ is cash additive if for any m ∈ holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">x + m = x -m</formula><p>An axiomatic approach to monetary risk measure has first been given by Artzner et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> in terms of coherent <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">23</ref> monetary risk measures. Föllmer and Schied <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> and Frittelli and Rosazza Gianin <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> generalized them to convex monetary risk measures, which by means of Proposition 2 correspond in our terminology to cash additive risk measures.</p><p>The cash additivity expresses that x is precisely the minimal amount of money that has to be reserved on the risk free bank account to pull the risk of the position x below the level<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">24</ref> 0. Here again, the cash additivity is not a global property and we call a risk order cash additive if it can be represented by at least one cash additive risk measure, see also Remark 4.</p><p>Theorem 2. A risk order is cash additive if and only if the following two conditions hold: (i) Certainty equivalent. for any x ∈ such that y ≺ x ≺ z for some y z ∈ there exists a unique m ∈ that satisfies x ∼ m , (ii) Translation indifference. x y implies x + m y + m for all m ∈ .</p><p>The proof is in Appendix C.3. Furthermore, cash additive risk measures share the property of convexity and a special shape of their risk acceptance family. Proposition 2. A risk measure is cash additive if and only if the related risk acceptance family satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">0 = m + m for all m ∈<label>(16)</label></formula><p>Furthermore, any cash additive risk measure is automatically convex.</p><p>The proof <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">25</ref> is in Appendix C.4. This special shape of the risk acceptance family has a concrete economic interpretation. In the theory of monetary risk measures, 0 is understood as the set of acceptable positions from a regulating agency's point of view. This agency enforces financial institutions with assets x in the risk class m to reserve a liquid amount of money m on a risk free bank account to ensure that x + m is acceptable in the sense that it belongs to 0 .</p><p>Example 5. We here list some examples of cash additive risk measures on . The celebrated mean variance risk measure introduced by Markowitz <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">X = -E X + 2 Var X X ∈<label>(17)</label></formula><p>is monotone with respect to the trivial preorder but not with respect to the preorder <ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">26</ref> "greater than P -almost surely." Given q ∈ 0 1 , the so-called average value at risk is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">AV @R q X = sup Q∈ q E Q -X X ∈ (<label>18</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">)</formula><p>where q is the set of probability measures Q absolutely continuous with respect to P such that dQ/dP ≤ 1/q. This risk measure is positive homogeneous. Another prominent example is the entropic risk measure given by Finally, an important class is the optimized certainty equivalent introduced and studied by Ben-Tal and Teboulle <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>, which is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">X = ln E exp -X X ∈<label>(</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">X = inf m∈ E l m -X -m X ∈<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where l → -+ is a lower semicontinuous convex nondecreasing loss function such that l 0 = 0 and 1 ∈ l 0 .</p><p>Recently, El Karoui and Ravanelli <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> pointed out that in the framework of monetary risk measures, the risk free bank account could also be subject to discounting uncertainty. In consequence, a higher amount of liquidity should be reserved today on the bank account to ensure that risky positions remain acceptable. For this purpose, they introduced the notion of cash subadditivity 27 for convex risk measures, which has been extended to quasiconvex risk measures in Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Definition 6. A risk measure on is cash subadditive if for any m &gt; 0 holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">x + m ≥ x -m</formula><p>Here again, it is possible to characterize cash subadditive risk measures by the properties of their related risk acceptance families. Proposition 3. A risk measure is cash subadditive if and only if the related risk acceptance family satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">n ⊆ n+m + m for all m &gt; 0 and n ∈ (<label>21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">)</formula><p>The proof is in Appendix C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> We finally illustrate with one example about numéraire uncertainty how monetary risk measures-not necessarily cash additive nor cash subadditive-can be defined by economically motivated risk acceptance families.</p><p>Example 6. For global acting financial institutions, it is reasonable that regulating agencies require the acceptability of risky positions with respect to a basket of currencies in reason of the different interest rate policies. The financial institutions face here some numéraire uncertainty to assess the risk. 28 Modelling this problem is particularly easy from the risk acceptance family point of view. Indeed, let 0 be the acceptance set given by the regulating institution and let ⊆ be a set of possible numéraires, for instance $, E, £, and ¥. Define</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">m = X X + m ∈ 0 for all ∈ = ∈ 0 -m m ∈</formula><p>Here, a position is of risk level m if this amount, invested in any of the currencies, pulls the risk of the position within the set of acceptable risky positions specified by the regulatory agency. Because is obviously a risk acceptance family, it defines a risk measure by means of Theorem 3.</p><p>3. Robust representation of risk orders. The goal of this section is to provide a dual representation of risk orders, which is the key to get a differentiated interpretation of risk perception depending on the underlying setup. To this end, we however need some topological structure. Hence, we assume that is a locally convex topological vector space 29 and denote by * its topological dual space endowed with the weak topology * . Unless explicitly precised, we denote x * y * the elements of the dual space * . We assume that the preorder is upper semicontinuous, that is, the cone = x ∈</p><p>x 0 is *closed. The bipolar theorem 30 states that x y exactly when x * xy ≥ 0 for all x * in the polar cone</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">= x * ∈ * x * x ≥ 0 for all x ∈<label>(22)</label></formula><p>which is * closed. By ˜ we denote those elements ∈ that are strictly positive with respect to , that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">˜ = ∈ x * &gt; 0 for all x * ∈ \ 0 (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">)</formula><p>27 Cash subadditive risk measures also appear naturally as the generators describing the one-step actualisation of dynamic cash additive risk measures for stochastic processes, (see Cheridito and Kupper <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, Acciaio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>). 28 Note that the question of the interest rate uncertainty is similar, because the regulator requires acceptability then with respect to a set of possible interest rates. 29 The study of as a convex subset of a topological vector space is postponed to §3.1. The preorder is called regular if there exists a strictly positive element, that is, ˜ = . In this case, for any ∈ ˜ holds = + , for the normalized polar set</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">= x * ∈ x * = 1 (24)</formula><p>Note that the trivial relation corresponds to the convex cone = 0 , which is not regular as ˜ = .</p><p>To illustrate the nature of these new elements, we briefly expose to what they concretely correspond in two of the settings introduced in §2.</p><p>• Random variables. The vector space of P -almost surely bounded random variables = admits the cone = + for the preorder "greater than P -almost surely." Depending on the considered topology we alternatively have the following:</p><p>1. For the • -norm, the dual space * = ba P is the set of bounded finitely additive signed measures on absolutely continuous with respect to P . The polar cone is then the set of finitely additive measures denoted by = ba + P . The preorder is regular since 1 ∈ ˜ , for which the normalized polar set 1 = 1 f P is the set of all finitely additive probability measures Q absolutely continuous with respect to P .</p><p>2. For the 1 -topology, the dual space is * = 1 . In this case, = 1 + . Here again, the preorder is regular and by means of the Radon-Nikodým theorem, 1 = 1 P is the set of all -additive probability measures in 1 f P .</p><p>• Lotteries. Let ca c be the vector space of bounded signed measures with compact support spanned by the lotteries 1 c . On ca c we consider the ca c C -topology, where C is the vector space of continuous functions f → . The dual pairing is given by f = f d . The first stochastic order corresponds to the cone</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">= ∈ ca c f d ≥ 0 for all f ∈</formula><p>where is the set of those f ∈ C that are nondecreasing. Notice that this order is not regular since ˜ = . Definition 7. A risk order is lower semicontinuous if x = y ∈ y x is closed for all x ∈ . The fact that separable lower semicontinuous risk orders admit lower semicontinuous risk measures is a consequence of the so-called gap theorem of Debreu <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref>. Proposition 4. A risk order is separable and lower semicontinuous if and only if there exists a corresponding lower semicontinuous risk measure . Furthermore, the class of lower semicontinuous risk measures of a lower semicontinuous risk order is stable under lower semicontinuous increasing transformation.</p><p>The proof is in Appendix C.11. An alternative proof for the first assertion can be found in Bosi and Mehta <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Note that any lower semicontinuous separable risk order can be represented by a risk measure that is not lower semicontinuous. Even though, the second assertion states that the class of lower semicontinuous risk measures is stable under lower semicontinuous increasing transformation. It can therefore be seen as a global characteristic in a topological sense.</p><p>Remark 6. The risk acceptance family of a lower semicontinuous risk measure is closed, that is, m is closed for all m ∈ . Conversely, the risk measure corresponding to a closed risk acceptance family is lower semicontinuous.</p><p>Aside from the numerous technicalities, the core idea of the proof leading to the robust representation of the subsequent Theorem 3 is insightful because the risk acceptance family plays a central role. To get an intuition of the objects in play and how they get involved, we informally sketch the key steps of the proof in the special case of random variables. To begin with, by way of relation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, we express the risk measure in terms of its risk acceptance family</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">X = inf m ∈ X ≤ m = inf m ∈ X ∈ m</formula><p>We now exploit the fact that each of these risk acceptance sets m has the polar representation</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">X ∈ m if and only if E Q -X ≤ min Q m for all probability measures Q where min Q m = sup X∈ m E Q -X</formula><p>is the so-called minimal penalty function. 31 Hence 31 This terminology was introduced in the theory of monetary risk measures (see Föllmer and Schied <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>).</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">X = inf m ∈ X ∈ m = inf m ∈ E Q -X ≤ min Q m for all Q</formula><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. Without duality gap in interchanging the supremum over Q with the infimum over m, we finally get the robust representation</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">X = sup Q inf m m ∈ E Q -X ≤ min Q m = sup Q R Q E Q -X</formula><p>where R is the left inverse of the nondecreasing function m → min Q m , that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">R Q s = inf m ∈ s ≤ min Q m</formula><p>Following this sketch of the proof, we define the minimal penalty function of a risk acceptance family by</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">min x * m = sup x∈ m x * -x x * ∈ and m ∈<label>(25)</label></formula><p>Notice that even if the risk acceptance family is right continuous, the penalty function m → min x * m is generally neither right nor left continuous. 32  Definition 8. A risk function is a mapping R × → -+ , which is nondecreasing and left continuous in the second argument. The set of risk functions is denoted by .</p><p>The left inverse of the minimal penalty function will be the cornerstone of the robust representation and is a specific risk function that belongs to the following class.</p><p>Definition 9. By max we denote the set of those risk functions R ∈ for which (i) R is jointly quasiconcave;</p><p>(ii) R x * s = R x * s/ for all x * ∈ , s ∈ and &gt; 0;</p><p>(iii) R has a uniform asymptotic minimum, that is, lim s→-R x * s = lim s→-R y * s for all x * , y * ∈ ;</p><p>(iv) its right-continuous version, R + x * s = inf s &gt;s R x * s , is upper semicontinuous in the first argument. Risk functions in max are referred to as maximal risk functions. In most examples, see §4, the function m → x * m is continuous and increasing, in which case the maximal risk function is in fact the true inverse of the minimal penalty function, that is, R x * • = -1 min x * • . After the preliminary definitions and notations, we present our robust representation results.</p><p>Theorem 3 (Robust Representation of Risk Orders). Any lower semicontinuous risk measure → -+ corresponding to a lower semicontinuous risk order has the robust representation</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x x ∈<label>(26)</label></formula><p>for a unique R ∈ max , which is the left inverse of the minimal penalty function min . Conversely, for any R ∈ , the function defined by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_43">26</ref>) is a lower semicontinuous risk measure.</p><p>The proof is in Appendix C.6.</p><p>The terminology "robust" in robust representation has been introduced in the theory of monetary risk measures. In the context of risk orders, the "loss" -x is tested under the evaluation x * by means of the operation x * -x . Because a risk perceiver is not sure which exact evaluation is adequate to compute the expected loss, he or she takes a precautionary estimation by considering all possible evaluations weighted according to their plausibility by a risk function R x * • . This precautionary estimation, core characteristic of risk perception, justifies henceforth the term robust for the representation <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>.</p><p>In the case where the preorder is regular, we obtain a finer robust representation. Here, in line with Definitions 8 and 9, the set of normalized risk functions with respect to ∈ ˜ consists of those mappings R × → -+ , which are nondecreasing and left continuous in the second argument. Moreover, max is the set of those R ∈ , for which R is jointly quasiconcave, R has a uniform asymptotic minimum on , and R + is upper semicontinuous in the first argument. 32 Indeed, consider = 0 1 with the Borel -algebra = 0 1 and the Lebesgue measure P = dx and define m = for m &lt; 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">m = X ∈ X1 m 1 ≥ 0 for 0 ≤ m ≤ 1 and m = for m &gt; 1.</formula><p>Obviously, is a closed risk acceptance family, and for x * = P holds min x * m = -for m &lt; 0, min x * m = 0 for m = 0 and min x * m = + for m &gt; 0, which is neither right nor left continuous.</p><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. </p><formula xml:id="formula_45">x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x x ∈<label>(27)</label></formula><p>for a unique R ∈ max , which is the left inverse of the minimal penalty function min .</p><p>Conversely, for any R ∈ , the function defined by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_45">27</ref>) is a lower semicontinuous risk measure.</p><p>The proof is in Appendix C.7.</p><p>The one-to-one relation between risk measures and their risk functions R ∈ max is crucial for the dual classification of risk orders and makes comparative statics meaningful. To this aim, Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> introduced the notion of a complete duality, in the sense that there exists a one-to-one relation between functions and their respective dual functions within a specified primal and dual class. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">33</ref> They give complete duality results for the class of monotone evenly <ref type="foot" target="#foot_7">34</ref> quasiconvex functions and for different subclasses of it including the upper semicontinuous monotone quasiconvex functions. In the spirit of those results, Theorem 4 states the complete duality result for the class of lower semicontinuous quasiconvex functions, which is not treated in Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</p><p>Remark 7. The technical assumption of lower semicontinuity is often a direct consequence of the monotonicity; see Namioka <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>, Borwein <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, Ruszczyński and Shapiro <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>, Cheridito and Li <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, Delbaen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> and Cheridito et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Furthermore, by means of Proposition 4, lower semicontinuous risk orders can be represented by lower semicontinuous risk measures; a similar statement for evenly quasiconvex risk orders is to our knowledge still open. Finally, for some topologies (Campion et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>) the lower semicontinuity of the risk order automatically ensures the separability; see § §4.1 and 4.2.</p><p>In contrast to Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, Theorem 3 holds for functions that are monotone with respect to any preorder including the trivial one that corresponds to = 0 and that are defined on locally convex topological vector spaces. The representation part of our proofs are in line with Penot and Volle [48, Proposition 3.6 and Theorem 3.8]. However, in Penot and Volle <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>, the robust representation is stated in terms of elements in * rather than or , and more important, uniqueness considerations and characterizations of the maximal risk function are not treated. For further references on quasiconvex duality theory, we refer to de Finetti <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, Greenberg and Pierskalla <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, Crouzeix <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and the references therein.</p><p>The denomination "maximal" risk function is justified by the following result.</p><p>Proposition 5. Suppose that a lower semicontinuous risk measure → -+ admits the robust representations x = sup</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">x * ∈ R x * x * -x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x x ∈<label>(28)</label></formula><p>for some risk functions R R with R ∈ max . Then, R is pointwise greater than R, that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">R x * s ≥ R x * s for all x * ∈ * and s ∈ (<label>29</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_48">)</formula><p>The proof is in Appendix C.8. Remark 8. Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> state a complete duality result between upper semicontinuous risk measures and risk functions that are jointly upper semicontinuous. The lower semicontinuous case is different and is stated in terms of an upper semicontinuity condition for the right-continuous version R + of the risk function R. Actually, the property (iv) in Definition 9 cannot be expressed in terms of a semicontinuity condition for the risk function R as illustrated in Appendix C.9. Furthermore, in Appendix C.9 it is shown that the regularity assumption on the preorder in Theorem 4 cannot be dropped.</p><p>In the following proposition we sum up the impact on the robust representation of additional properties of the risk measure as discussed in §2. Similar results have been established in Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> in the context of M-spaces. Proposition 6. A lower semicontinuous risk measure with corresponding R ∈ max is convex, positive homogeneous, or scaling invariant if and only if s → R x * s is, respectively, convex, positive homogeneous, or scaling invariant for all x * ∈ . If the preorder is -regular, a lower semicontinuous risk measure with corresponding R ∈ max is cash additive if and only if R x * s + m = R x * s + m for all x * ∈ and s, m ∈ , in which case R x * s = smin x * 0 . It is cash subadditive if and only if R x * sm ≥ R x * sm for all x * ∈ , s ∈ and m &gt; 0.</p><p>The proof, in Appendix C.10, relies on the properties of m → min x * m inherited from the risk acceptance family.</p><p>3.1. Robust representation of risk orders on convex sets. In Theorems 3 and 4, we assumed that the risk order is defined on a vector space. This is however not the case for many important settings. 35 To address this problem, we continuously extend the risk order to a vector space and then apply Theorem 3. Throughout this subsection we assume that is a convex subset of a locally convex topological vector space and that the preorder corresponds to the closed convex cone ⊆ . The main difficulty here beyond the continuous extension is to specify for which set of maximal risk functions the uniqueness result in the robust representation is guaranteed. Indeed, the following example illustrates the fact that max is in general too big to state a uniqueness result for risk orders on convex sets as in Theorem 3.</p><p>Example 7. Consider the risk measure x = 0 on the convex set = + in = with = = + . For any c ∈ 0 + , the risk measure c x = 0 for x ≥ 0 and x = c otherwise is an extension of on the real line. Direct inspection 36 yields for all x * ∈ + and s ∈ ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">R c x * s =      0 if s ≤ 0 c if s &gt; 0 and x * &gt; 0 + if s &gt; 0 and x * = 0</formula><p>Hence R c ∈ max for all c ∈ 0 + . On the other hand, since = c on + it follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">x = sup x * ≥0 R c x * -x * x x ∈ +</formula><p>for any c ∈ 0 + , showing that the uniqueness statement in max fails. Definition 10. A lower semicontinuous 37 risk order on is continuously extensible if</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">x + ∩ = x for all x ∈<label>(30)</label></formula><p>A risk order → -+ is continuously extensible if its risk acceptance family fulfills m + ∩ = m for all m ∈ (31)</p><p>Remark 9. Actually, this rather technical assumption automatically holds for many convex sets. For instance, if is open or compact, or if is a subset of as in the case of consumptions patterns, then any lower semicontinuous risk order and any lower semicontinuous risk measure on is continuously extensible. 38  Yet, a lower semicontinuous risk measure corresponding to a continuously extensible lower semicontinuous risk measure is not necessarily continuously extensible. However, an assertion in the spirit of Proposition 4 holds. Proposition 7. A lower semicontinuous risk order is separable and continuously extensible if and only if there exists a corresponding continuously extensible lower semicontinuous risk measure . Moreover, the class of continuously extensible risk measures is stable under lower semicontinuous increasing transformation.</p><p>The proof is in Appendix C.11. The set of risk functions for which the uniqueness statement holds involves a stability with respect to a closure operation. The max -closure of a function R × → -+ denoted by cl max R is the pointwise infimum of those functions in max that dominate R, that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">cl max R x * s = inf R x * s R ∈ max and R ≥ R</formula><p>In fact, this closure is itself an element of max as stated in the following proposition. 35 Lotteries or consumption patterns for instance. 36 Computing first the minimal penalty function and then taking the left inverse. 37 The considered topology on is the relative topology induced by the topology on . 38 Indeed, for open it follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">x + ∩ = x + ∩ ∩ = x ∩ = x . If is compact,</formula><p>x is also compact and thus</p><p>x + ∩ = x + ∩ = x . Finally, if ⊆ then x + ⊆ x and in turn x + ∩ = x ∩ = x . The same argumentation also holds for a lower semicontinous acceptance family .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. The proof is in Appendix C.12. By use of this closure operation, we now define the set of maximal risk functions on . Definition 11. By max we denote the set of those risk functions R ∈ max such that 39 R x * s = cl max sup</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">y * ∈ * R x * -y * s - y *<label>(32)</label></formula><p>where denotes the support function of the convex setgiven by</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">y * = sup y∈ y * -y y * ∈ *<label>(33)</label></formula><p>Remark 10. Depending on the considered set the definition of max sometimes simplifies. For instance for lotteries we prove in §4.2 that max 1 c = max . We can now state our main representation result for risk orders on convex sets.</p><p>Theorem 5. Let be a lower semicontinuous risk measure corresponding to a continuously extensible lower semicontinous risk order on . Then, has the robust representation</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x x ∈<label>(34)</label></formula><p>for a unique R ∈ max . Moreover, there exists a unique maximal lower semicontinuous risk measure ˆ on , which restricted to coincides with .</p><p>The proof is in Appendix C.13. Remark 11. To compute the risk function R ∈ max of a risk measure on , the strategy is to pick any extension ˜ of and compute its maximal risk function R ∈ max . Then, the risk function R ∈ max is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">R x * s = cl max sup y * ∈ * R x * -y * s - y *</formula><p>For instance, coming back to the Example 7, the maximal lower semicontinuous risk measure that extends is clearly + . Furthermore, + y * = 0 for y * ∈ + and + otherwise. Hence, a direct computation yields for any c ∈ 0 + , sup</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">y * ∈ R c x * -y * s -+ y * = 0 if s ≤ 0 + otherwise = R + x * s Since R + ∈ max , it follows cl max R + = R + and therefore R = R + .</formula><p>4. Illustrative settings. In the following subsections, we will illustrate how the robust representation in each particular setting introduced in §2 provides the key perspective for a context depending interpretation of risk perception.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Random variables.</head><p>In this subsection, we consider the vector space of random variables = with the preorder "≥ than P -almost surely," which corresponds to = + . If we endow with the •topology, the normalized polar set 1 = 1 f P consists of all finitely additive probability measures. However, probability measures that are not -additive are not desirable as they do not have a density and can at most be constructed implicitly by use of the axiom of choice. To work with the more tractable set of probability measures 1 = 1 P , we endow with the 1 topology. Because this weak topology is coarser than the norm topology, we need an extra condition called Fatou property, which ensures a risk order to be 1 -lower semicontinous.</p><p>Definition 12 (Fatou Property). A risk order has the Fatou property if and only if for any X Y ∈ and any • -bounded sequence X n converging P -almost surely to X holds X n Y for all n implies X Y (35) 39 By convention R x * • ≡ -for all x * ∈ and R • -≡ -.</p><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. By means of Campion et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> and under the assumption we take throughout this subsection that the -algebra is separable, 40 the Fatou property implies that the risk order is automatically separable. The following theorem specializes Theorem 4 in the present context. Theorem 6. Any risk order on that has the Fatou property can be represented by a 1 -lower semicontinuous risk measure → -+ , with the robust representation</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">X = sup Q∈ 1 P R Q E Q -X X ∈<label>(36)</label></formula><p>for a unique risk function R ∈ max 1 . The proof is in Appendix C.14. The robust representation <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref> shows that risk perception in the context of random variables can be interpreted in terms of model risk. Indeed, in face of model uncertainty, a prudent approach is adopted where different probability models for the estimation of the expected losses are taken into account, weighted according to their respective plausibility by means of the risk function R.</p><p>For the robust representation of the optimized certainty equivalent in Example 5 we refer to Ben-Tal and Teboulle <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. This example includes the average value at risk and the entropic risk measure also from Example 5. As for the robust representation of the shortfall risk measure in Example 3 we refer to Föllmer and Schied <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr">Theorem 4.106</ref>]. We next address the robust representation of the certainty equivalent of an expected loss; see Example 1.</p><p>Example 8. Given a proper lower semicontinuous convex nondecreasing loss function 41 l → -+ , the certainty equivalent of an expected loss is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">X = l -1 E l -X X ∈</formula><p>In the following, we assume for simplicity that l is differentiable on its domain. By use of (B4), it follows that for any</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">Q ∈ 1 P and m ∈ min Q m = sup X∈ E l -X ≤l + m E Q -X = sup X∈ E - dQ dP X - 1 l -X -l + m<label>(37)</label></formula><p>for some Lagrange multiplier = Q m &gt; 0. The first-order condition yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">- dQ dP + 1 l -X = 0</formula><p>The derivative l is nondecreasing. We denote by h its right inverse. Assume then that X = -h dQ/dP fulfills the previous equation. 42 Then, under integrability and positivity conditions, is determined through the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">E l h dQ dP = l + m (38)</formula><p>Plugging the optimizer X in <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_64">yields min Q m = E Q h dQ dP<label>(39)</label></formula><p>the left inverse of which finally delivers R. We subsequently list closed-form solutions for specific loss functions.</p><p>• Quadratic function. Let l s = s 2 /2 + s for s ≥ -1 and -1/2 otherwise for which E l -X corresponds to a monotone version of the mean-variance risk measure Markowitz <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">For m ≥ -1, since 1 ∈ m holds min Q m = -E Q 1 = -1.</formula><p>Otherwise, the first-order condition yields X = dQ/dP -1 and therefore</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">min Q m = 1 + m E dQ/dP 2 1/2 -1 Hence, R Q s = s + 1 dQ/dP 2 -1 Q ∈ 1 P</formula><p>if s &gt; -1 andotherwise. 40 A algebra is separable if it can be generated by a countable collection of sets. 41 In Example 1, l was increasing. Here, because l is nondecreasing, its left inverse l -1 is nondecreasing and lower semicontinuous (see Appendix B). 42 This is often the case, for instance if l is increasing.</p><p>• Exponential function. For l s = e s -1, corresponding to the entropic risk measure, it follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">R Q s = s -E dQ dP log dQ dP Q ∈ 1 P</formula><p>• Logarithm function. If l s = -ln -s for s &lt; 0 and l = + elsewhere, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">R Q s = s exp -E ln dQ dP Q ∈ 1 P • Power function. If l s = --s 1-/ 1 -</formula><p>for s ≤ 0 and l = + elsewhere for 0 &lt; &lt; 1, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">R Q s = sE dQ/dP -1 / / 1- Q ∈ 1 P</formula><p>As for the economic index of riskiness, we use the same technique.</p><p>Example 9. For the definition and notations, we refer to Example 3. The risk acceptance family is given for m &gt; 0 by m = X ∈ E l -X/m ≤ c 0 , and for m ≤ 0 by m = + . Applying the same technique as for the certainty equivalent yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">min Q m = sup X∈ E - dQ dP X - 1 l - X m -c 0 = E Q mh m dQ dP Q ∈ 1 P</formula><p>where h is a pseudo inverse of l and the Lagrange multiplier is given by E l h m dQ/dP = c 0 . In the case of Aumann and Serrano <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> where l s = e s and c 0 &gt; 1, holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">R Q s = s E Q ln c 0 dQ/dP Q ∈ 1 P</formula><p>In the case of Foster and Hart <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> where l s = -ln 1 -s and c 0 &gt; 0 holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">R Q s = s 1 -exp E ln dQ/dP -c 0 Q ∈ 1 P</formula><p>and because of Proposition 6, both are positive homogeneous.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Lotteries.</head><p>As for the risk perception in the setting of lotteries with compact support = 1 c we consider the induced ca c C topology, where ca c denotes the vector space of signed measures with compact support. Recall that the first stochastic order is determined by the polar cone</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">= f ∈ C f is nondecreasing</formula><p>Even though 1 c is not a compact subset of ca c , we obtain a robust representation from Theorem 5 with the remarkable facts that the separability of the risk order is a consequence of the lower semicontinuity and that max 1 c = max . Theorem 7. Any lower semicontinuous risk order on 1 c that is monotone with respect to the first stochastic order can be represented by a lower semicontinuous risk measure 1 c → -+ , which has the robust representation</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">= sup l∈ R l l -x dx ∈ 1 c (<label>40</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_75">)</formula><p>for a unique R ∈ max = max 1 c . The proof is in Appendix C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref>. A related representation on the level of simple lotteries has been studied independently by Cerreia-Vioglio <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. As a consequence of the monotonicity, we provide in Delbaen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> and Cheridito et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> automatic continuity results for affine and general risk orders, respectively, allowing to drop or weaken the lower semicontinuity assumption in Theorem 7.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref> the loss of a lottery is tested with respect to a nondecreasing continuous loss function l. However, the risk induced by the uncertainty about the reliability of this loss function yields a precautious approach by means of the risk function R. Hence, risk perception on the level of lotteries might be viewed as distributional risk.</p><p>Note that the certainty equivalent of the expected loss of a lottery introduced in Example 1 is already in its robust representation form. 43   43 Indeed for = l -1</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">0 l 0 -x dx , is R l t = l -1 0 t , if l = l 0 , and inf ∈ 1 c otherwise.</formula><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. Example 10. Following the prescriptions of Basel II, value at risk is the central instrument used by banking institutions to assess their exposure to risk in a monetary way. Regardless of repeated critics, starting with Artzner et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, that it might penalize diversification because it is not quasiconvex, this measure instrument remains astonishingly resilient in the practice. There are several arguments for the defense of the value at risk, 44  but the most recurrent one is that many persons think that it gives some indications about risk. It is this strong but erroneous belief we here want to study and try to explain.</p><p>The value at risk is defined for q ∈ 0 1 by</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">V @R q X = sup s ∈ P X + s ≤ 0 &gt; q X ∈ (<label>41</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_78">)</formula><p>This functional is cash additive and monotone but not quasiconvex. From its definition, V @R q depends only on the distribution of X and can therefore be viewed 45 on 1 c for I = , that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">V @R q = sup s ∈ --s &gt; q = -F -1 q ∈ 1 c (<label>42</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_80">)</formula><p>where F -1 is the right inverse of the nondecreasing function s → F s = -s . In fact, V @R q X = V @R q for = P X ∈ 1 c . On the level of probability distributions, V @R q is monotone with respect to the first stochastic order. Moreover, for any risk level m ∈ , it follows from relation (B4) that</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">m = ∈ 1 c V @R q ≤ m = ∈ 1 c F -1 q ≥ -m = ∈ 1 c q ≥ F - -m = ∈ 1 c q ≥ --m<label>(43)</label></formula><p>which is a convex set. Therefore, V @R q is a risk measure on 1 c . In Appendix C.16, we further show that V @R q is lower semicontinuous and provide the following robust representation</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">V @R q = sup l∈ l -1 l -x dx -ql + 1 -q<label>(44)</label></formula><p>From this viewpoint, the strong belief of the finance industry in the value at risk as a risk measure, is truly founded because it is indeed a risk measure on the level of probability distributions. Yet, it is a fundamental error to consider it as a reliable instrument to assess the risk of financial positions that are definitively random variables for which a scenario-wise diversification is needed. So, even if this instrument is in principle a sound one, it is fundamentally misused in the wrong environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Consumption patterns.</head><p>Consumption patterns of a commodity reveal another form of uncertainty, namely, the one driven by the perception of different future points in time at which this consumption occurs. The risk perception induced by this intertemporal dimension will be the subject of this subsection.</p><p>Recall that the commodity space = is the set of nondecreasing right-continuous functions c 0 1 → . In a stimulating discussion, Hindy et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> gave several reasons why the Orlicz topology induced by the Luxemburg norm • on the Orlicz heart 46  = ⊃ is economically and mathematically reasonable to address coherently both continuity and jumps issues for preferences over consumption patterns. As for the preorder we consider as the set of nondecreasing elements 47 in with polar cone</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">= f ∈ * 1 0 f s c s ds + f 1 c 1 ≥ 0 for all c ∈</formula><p>By use of integration by parts it follows that for any c ∈ and f ∈ * the linear pairing is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">f c = 1 0 f s c s ds + f 1 c 1 = 1 0- s dc s (<label>45</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_85">)</formula><p>44 For instance, restricted to Gaussian risky assets, the value at risk is a convex risk measure. 45 This has been done in Weber <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref> for the case of monetary risk measures considered on the level of probability distributions. 46 The space is a subspace of the Orlicz heart consisting of all measurable functions c 0 1 → such that 1 0 m c t dt + m c 1 &lt; + for all m &gt; 0, where 0 + → 0 + is a convex function with 0 = 0 and lim t→+ t /t = + . Equipped with the topology induced by the Luxemburg norm c = inf m &gt; 0 1 0 c t /m dt + c 1 /m ≤ 1 , the dual space * is the Orlicz space consisting of all measurable functions f 0 1 → with finite Luxemburg norm • , where is the convex conjugate of . 47 In which case ∩ = , and thus corresponds to the preorder introduced in §2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org.</p><p>where t = t f = 1 t f s ds + f 1 . We can therefore identify f ∈ * with the respective = f , for which the linear pairing modifies to 1 0-s dc s . Since 1 0-s dc s ≥ 0 for all c ∈ is equivalent to s ≥ 0, the polar cone can then be identified with</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">= = f f ∈ * ≥ 0<label>(46)</label></formula><p>Theorem 8. Any lower semicontinuous risk measure of a lower semicontinuous risk order on monotone with respect to = has the robust representation</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">c = sup ∈ R - 1 0- t dc t c ∈<label>(47)</label></formula><p>for a unique maximal risk function R ∈ max .</p><p>The proof is in Appendix C.17. Diversification on the level of consumption patterns typically avoids concentration effects of consumption at particular times. The interpretation excerpted by the robust representation is that risk orders in this context address a discounting estimation. The value 1 0-s dc s represents the discounted value of the consumption pattern c for the discounting factor that gives different weights to different points in time. The higher this discounted value the less risky the consumption pattern. The uncertainty arising from the choice of an adequate discounting factor is then addressed in a precautionary way by means of the risk function R and justifies here an interpretation of risk perception as a discounting risk. We illustrate this intertemporal perspective in risk perception with a class of risk measure inspired by Hindy et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">c = 1 0 l t - t+k 2 t t-k 1 t t s dc s dt c ∈<label>(48)</label></formula><p>for some parameter function satisfying t s = 0 whenever s ∈ 0 1 and that is jointly continuous on × 0 1 . The functions k 1 and k 2 are continuous and l 2 → is a jointly measurable function that is continuous in the first argument and lower semicontinuous nondecreasing and convex in the second argument. The terminology intertemporal risk measure means that risk estimation of a commodity pattern at time t is not the "instant" consumption dc t but a weighted average in the time around t. Proposition 9. The function given by (48) is a lower semicontinuous risk measure that is monotone with respect to = .</p><p>For the proof, see Appendix C.18.</p><p>Example 11. In the following we address the robust representation for the risk measure</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">c = 1 0 l - t 0- e -t-s dc s dt<label>(49)</label></formula><p>that is, t s = e -t-s and l → -+ is a lower semicontinuous convex function that is increasing and continuously differentiable on -0 . After computations involving a relaxation technique to the whole vector space given in Appendix C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref>, we obtain the following risk functions:</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">• l x = e x yields R s = exp s + ln 1 0 t dt 1 0 t dt - 1 0 ln t t dt / 1 0 t dt ; and • l x = -ln -x yields R s = -ln -s + 1 0 ln t dt</formula><p>, where ∈ with t ≥ 0 and 1 = 0, and otherwise holds R = -. Even if R represents also , the maximal risk function R corresponding to in the sense of Theorem 5 is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">R s = cl max sup ¯ ∈ R -¯ s<label>(50)</label></formula><p>since ¯ = 0 if ¯ ∈ and + otherwise.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Stochastic kernels.</head><p>Because of their intrinsic mixed nature between random variables and lotteries, stochastic kernels illustrate the interplay of risk perception between model risk and distributional risk. They typically corresponds to the setting of Anscombe and Aumann <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> used in Gilboa and Schmeidler <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, Klibanoff et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, Maccheroni et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, and Föllmer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. Recall that given a probability space <ref type="foot" target="#foot_8">48</ref>P , the set of stochastic kernels denoted by is the set of measurable functions </p><formula xml:id="formula_92">A convex function f → -+ is proper if f &gt; -and f x ∈ for some x ∈ . A concave function f → is proper if -f is proper.</formula><p>For a nondecreasing function f -+ → -+ , we denote by f -and f + the respective unique left-and right-continuous versions of f , that is,</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">f -s = sup t&lt;s f t and f + s = inf t&gt;s f t s ∈ (A1)</formula><p>which satisfy f -≤ f ≤ f + with convention that f --= -and f + + = + . Note that f -and f + only differ on a countable subset of .</p><p>If is a topological space, a function f → -+ is called lower semicontinuous if x ∈ f x ≤ is closed for all ∈ and upper semicontinuous if -f is lower semicontinuous. The Fenchel-Legendre conjugate f * of a function f is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">f * x * = sup x∈ x * x -f x x * ∈ * (A2)</formula><p>whereby * is the topological dual of and with the convention that sup = inf = -and sup = inf = .</p><p>The infimal convolution of convex functions f 1 f 2 → -+ is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">f 1 f 2 x = inf x 1 +x 2 =x f 1 x 1 + f 2 x 2 x ∈</formula><p>By the first part of Theorem 16.4 in Rockafella <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>, which carries over to the present context, holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">cl f 1 f 2 = f * 1 + f * 2 * (A3)</formula><p>Appendix B. Pseudo inverse. We here present the notion of the pseudo, left and right inverse of a nondecreasing function.</p><p>Definition 13. A function g -+ → -+ is a pseudo inverse of a nondecreasing function</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">f - → -+ if f -g t ≤ t ≤ f + g t t ∈ -+ (B1)</formula><p>The left inverse f -1 l and the right inverse f -1 r are defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">f -1 l t = sup s ∈ f s &lt; t = inf s ∈ f s ≥ t t ∈ -+ (B2) f -1 r t = sup s ∈ f s ≤ t = inf s ∈ f s &gt; t t ∈ -+ (B3)</formula><p>The definition of the pseudo inverse carries over to nondecreasing functions f defined on some interval I ⊆ -+ , by considering the extension also denoted by f given by f x = sup y∈I f y for x &gt; I and f x = inf y∈I f y for x &lt; I. The following proposition summarises known results on pseudo inverses; see also Penot and Volle <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> and Föllmer and Schied <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">Proposition 10. Given a nondecreasing function f -+ → -+ , any pseudo inverse g of f is nondecreasing, f -1 l = g -≤ g ≤ g + = f -1 r ,</formula><p>and all pseudo inverses of f differ at most on a countable subset of -+ . Furthermore, f is itself a pseudo inverse of any of its pseudo inverses.</p><p>If f is moreover left continuous, then g -1 l = f for any pseudo inverse g of f and</p><formula xml:id="formula_100">f s ≤ t if and only if s ≤ f -1 r t (B4)</formula><p>Symmetrically, if f is right continuous, then g -1 r = f for any pseudo inverse g of f and</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">f s ≥ t if and only if s ≥ f -1 l t (B5)</formula><p>Finally, if f is right continuous, then f is concave if and only if f -1 l is convex.</p><p>Proof. Consider a nondecreasing function f -+ → -+ and a pseudo inverse g of f . By definition, f -1 l ≤ g -≤ g ≤ g + ≤ f -1 r . Fix now a decreasing sequence t n t ∈ -+ . Then</p><formula xml:id="formula_102">s ∈ f s &gt; t = n∈ s ∈ f s &gt; t n</formula><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. and therefore f -1 r t n f -1 r t for any t &lt; + . Hence, since f -1 r + = + by definition, f -1 r is right continuous. The fact that g + = f -1 r is immediate as they only differ on the countable set of their respective discontinuities and both are right continuous. A similar argumentation yields f -1 l is left continuous and f -1 l = g -.</p><p>For any pseudo inverse g of f holds g t ≥ s whenever t &gt; f s and therefore g + f s ≥ s. Conversely, g t ≤ s whenever t &lt; f s and thus g -f s ≤ s, that is, f is a pseudo inverse of g. In particular, if f is left continuous, respectively, right continuous, then g -1 l = f , respectively, g -1 r = f . Further, the definition of f -1 l and f -1 r imply the implications "⇒" of relations (B4) and (B5). The reverse implications "⇐" follow from f -1 r -1 l = f in case that f is left continuous and</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">f -1 l -1 r = f if f is right continuous.</formula><p>Finally, if f is right continuous, from (B5) follows that the hypograph of f and the epigraph of f -1 l are related to each other by means of the relation: s t ∈ hypo f if and only if t s ∈ epi f -1 l . Hence, the last assertion follows.</p><p>Appendix C. Technical proofs.</p><p>C.1. Proof of Theorem 1. It is straightforward to check that is a risk order if and only if is a risk measure, that = , and that and coincide up to an increasing transformation. It remains to show the one-to-one relation between risk measures and risk acceptance families.</p><p>Step 1. Let be a risk measure with corresponding level sets</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">m = x ∈ x ≤ m m ∈</formula><p>Then, m ⊆ n for any m ≤ n that together with the monotonicity of implies the monotonicity of . Because level sets of quasiconvex functions are convex it follows that is convex. Obviously, m ⊆ n&gt;m n for all m ∈ , and conversely, if x ∈ n&gt;m n , then x ≤ n for all n &gt; m implying x ≤ m and therefore x ∈ m , showing the right continuity. And so, is a risk acceptance family.</p><p>Step 2. Let = m m∈ be a risk acceptance family and let be the function defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">x = inf m ∈ x ∈ m x ∈</formula><p>As for the monotonicity, consider x y and fix 52 m ∈ for which y ∈ m . The monotonicity of yields x ∈ m . Hence, m ≥</p><p>x and therefore y ≥ x . As for the quasiconvexity, let ∈ 0 1 , x, y ∈ with x ≥ y , and fix 53 m ∈ for which x ∈ m . The monotonicity implies that y ∈ m and by the convexity of m it follows x + 1 -y ∈ m . This implies that</p><p>x + 1 -y ≤ m and therefore</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">x + 1 -y ≤ x = max x y</formula><p>Hence, is a risk measure.</p><p>Step 3. Let be a risk measure. In view of the first and second step, is also a risk measure. If x ∈ is such that x = + , then it is unacceptable at any level of risk for , and therefore x = + . The same argumentation holds for those x ∈ satisfying x = -. If x ∈ , then x ∈</p><p>x , hence x ≤ x . On the other hand, x ∈ n for all n &lt; x , henceforth</p><p>x ≥ x and so = . Let be a risk acceptance family. Because of the first and second step, is also a risk acceptance family. If x ∈ m for some m ∈ , it follows</p><p>x ≤ m yielding x ∈ m . Conversely, x ∈ m implies x ≤ m, which in view of (11) yields x ∈ n for all n &gt; m. The right continuity of implies x ∈ n&gt;m n = m , and so = .</p><p>C.2. Proof of Proposition 1. (i) Suppose that is convex. Take ∈ 0 1 and some reals m, m . Any element of m + 1 -m can be written as x + 1 -y for x ∈ m and y ∈ m . The convexity implies</p><formula xml:id="formula_107">x + 1 -y ≤ x + 1 - y ≤ m + 1 -m 52</formula><p>The case where there is no such m is trivial as y = + . 53 Here again, the case where there is no such m is obvious.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. showing that, x + 1 -y ∈ m+ 1-m . Conversely, by Theorem 1, for m m ∈ such that x ∈ m and y ∈ m , it follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_108">x + 1 -y = inf n ∈ x + 1 -y ∈ n = inf n n ∈ n + 1 -n x + 1 -y ∈ n+ 1-n ≤ inf n n ∈ n + 1 -n x + 1 -y ∈ n + 1 - n ≤ m + 1 -m</formula><p>showing that x + 1 -y ≤ x + 1 -y . The cases x = + or y = + are obvious. (ii) Suppose that is positive homogeneous. Fix &gt; 0 and some m ∈ . Then, x ∈ m if and only if x ≤ m if and only if x/ ≤ m if and only if x ∈ m , that is, m = m . Conversely, Theorem 1 yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">x = inf m ∈ x ∈ m = inf m ∈ x ∈ m/ = inf m ∈ x ∈ m = x</formula><p>For the related risk order, since x = x , it follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_110">x = x = x = x = x</formula><p>(iii) It is straightforward that any risk measure corresponding to a risk order satisfying x ∼ x for any &gt; 0 is scaling invariant. As for the following assertions, the proof is analogous to the proof of (ii).</p><p>C.3. Proof of Proposition 2. The cash additivity of a risk measure corresponding to obviously implies the properties (i) and (ii).</p><p>Conversely, conditions (i) and (ii) implies that the mapping </p><formula xml:id="formula_111">x =      - if x</formula><formula xml:id="formula_112">= x ∈ x ≤ m = x ∈ x + m ≤ 0 = 0 -m</formula><p>and therefore fulfills the condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>. Conversely, let be risk acceptance family satisfying relation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>. The cash additivity for the related risk measure follows from Theorem 1 since</p><formula xml:id="formula_113">x + m = inf m ∈ x ∈ m = inf m ∈ x + m + m ∈ 0 = x -m</formula><p>for any x ∈ and m ∈ . As for the convexity, let be a cash additive risk measure. Proposition 2 implies that its risk acceptance family fulfills the relation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>. Hence, for any m m ∈ and ∈ 0 1 follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_114">m + 1 - m = 0 -m + 1 - 0 -1 -m = 0 -m + 1 -m = m+ 1-m</formula><p>And so, by Proposition 1, is convex.</p><p>C.5. Proof of Proposition 3. Let be a cash subadditive risk measure with corresponding risk acceptance family . For any m &gt; 0, n ∈ , and x + m ∈ n follows n ≥ x + m ≥ xm, showing that x ∈ m+n . Hence, nm ⊆ m+n .</p><p>Conversely, consider some risk acceptance family fulfilling the relation <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> and with corresponding risk measure .</p><p>Theorem 1 yields for any m &gt; 0 that</p><formula xml:id="formula_115">x + m = inf n ∈ x + m ∈ n ≥ inf n ∈ x ∈ n+m = x -m</formula><p>showing that is a cash subadditive risk measure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. We need two lemmata the first of which states a one-to-one relation between min and max . Lemma 1. The left inverse of any function ∈ min is in max , that is</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mathematics of Operations</head><formula xml:id="formula_116">-1 l x * s = sup m ∈ x * m &lt; s ∈ max (C1)</formula><p>The left inverse of any function R ∈ max is in min , that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_117">R -1 l x * m = sup s ∈ R x * s &lt; m ∈ min (C2)</formula><p>Moreover, -1 l -1 l = , as well as R -1 l -1 l = R for any ∈ min and R ∈ max .</p><p>Proof. Note that both minimal penalty functions and maximal risk functions are mappings from × to -+ , which are left continuous and nondecreasing in the second argument. In the following, is such a mapping from × to -+ . By Proposition 10, its left inverse denoted by R is again a left continuous nondecreasing function and in that case holds = R -1 l = -1 l -1 l , R = -1 l = R -1 l -1 l and R + = -1 r . Relation (B5) in Proposition 10 further implies that</p><formula xml:id="formula_118">R + x * s ≥ m if and only if s ≥ x * m (C3)</formula><p>for all m, s ∈ , and x * ∈ . We now show that = R -1 l is in min if and only if R = -1 l is in max .</p><p>• Equivalence between condition (a) for min and condition (i) for max . Firstly, since R is the left-continuous version of R + that itself is the right-continuous version of R holds by definition</p><formula xml:id="formula_119">x * s ∈ × R + x * s ≥ m = &gt;0 x * s ∈ × R x * s + ≥ m x * s ∈ × R x * s ≥ m = &gt;0 &gt;0 x * s ∈ × R + x * s -&gt; m -</formula><p>showing the equivalence between the joint quasiconcavity of R and the joint quasiconcavity of R + . Secondly, relation (C3) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_120">x * s ∈ × R + x * s ≥ m = x * s ∈ × s ≥ x * m = epi • m</formula><p>for any m ∈ . Finally, a function is convex if and only its epigraph is convex.</p><p>• Equivalence between condition (b) for min and condition (ii) for max . If is positive homogeneous in the first argument, then for any &gt; 0 holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_121">R x * s = sup m ∈ x * m &lt; s = sup m ∈ x * m &lt; s/ = R x * s/</formula><p>Conversely, under the assumption that R x * s = R x * s/ for all &gt; 0, it follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_122">x * m = sup s ∈ R x * s &lt; m = sup s/ ∈ R x * s/ &lt; m = x * m</formula><p>• Equivalence between condition (c) for min and condition (iii) for max . Define</p><formula xml:id="formula_123">C = x * m ∈ × x * m = - D = x * m ∈ × lim s←- R x * s ≥ m</formula><p>It is clear that if ∈ min , condition (c) for min is equivalent to C = × J for the interval J = -c 0 , where c 0 ∈ -+ . On the other hand, condition (iii) for max holds if and only if D = × J for J as</p><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org.</p><p>before. Indeed, D = × if and only if lim s→-R x * s = -for any x * ∈ . Further, D = × if and only if R ≡ + . Finally, D = × -c 0 for c 0 ∈ if and only if lim s→-R x * s = c 0 for all x * ∈ . It remains to show that C = D. Indeed, relation (C3) states that</p><formula xml:id="formula_124">C = x * m ∈ × x * m ≤ s for all s ∈ = x * m ∈ × m ≤ R + x * s for all s ∈ = x * m ∈ × m ≤ R x * s for all s ∈ = D</formula><p>• Equivalence between condition (d) for min and condition (iv) for max . Again by relation (C3) holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_125">x * ∈ R + x * s ≥ m = x * ∈ s ≥ x * m</formula><p>for any m, s ∈ . This states the equivalence between the lower semicontinuity of and the upper semicontinuity of R In this case, is given as the support function of -, that is, the minimal 55 penalty function</p><formula xml:id="formula_126">x * = min x * = sup x∈ x * -x x * ∈ (C5)</formula><p>If in addition is regular then for any fixed ∈ ˜ holds</p><p>x ∈ if and only if x * -x ≤ x * for all x * ∈ (C6)</p><p>and is unique in the set of all lower semicontinuous convex functions from to -+ such that if there exists x * ∈ with x * = -, then ≡ -.</p><p>Proof. Let min denote the support function ofgiven by relation (C5). By definition, min ∈ min 0 . We next show that min fulfills relation (C4). The cases = and = are obvious. If = , the implication</p><formula xml:id="formula_127">x ∈ implies x * -x ≤ sup y∈ x * -y = min x * for all x * ∈ (C7)</formula><p>is straightforward. Conversely, for any x ∈ \ , the hyperplane separation theorem yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_128">x * 0 -x &gt; sup y∈ x * 0 -y (C8)</formula><p>for some x * 0 ∈ * . By the monotonicity of holds x * 0 -x &gt; x * 0 -y + x * 0 -k for some y ∈ and all k ∈ . Hence, 0 ≥ x * 0 -k for all k ∈ , implying that x * 0 ∈ and therefore, the right-hand side of (C8) is equal to min x * 0 showing the reverse implication in (C4). As for the uniqueness, suppose there exist 1 2 ∈ min 0 that represent in the sense of (C4). In case that 1 is identically + or -, the same obviously holds for 2 , and vice versa. By definition of min 0 , it remains to show the case where both 1 and 2 are proper. Define ˜ i = i on and ˜ i = + on c that remains proper, convex, and lower semicontinuous. For the conjugates ˜ * i x = sup x * ∈ x * xi x * that are positive homogeneous follow ˜ * i x = 0 if and only if -x ∈ . Thus, ˜ * 1 = ˜ * 2 and the Fenchel-Moreau theorem yields ˜</p><formula xml:id="formula_129">1 = ˜ * 1 * = ˜ * 2 * = ˜ 2 , that is, 1 = 2 on</formula><p>. Finally, in case that ∈ ˜ = , it follows that x * &gt; 0 for any x * ∈ \ 0 so that x whereby min • m is the support function ofm as given by relation (C5). Combining (C9) and (C10) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_130">x = inf m ∈ x * -x ≤ min x * m for all x * ∈ = inf m ∈ x * -x ≤ - min x * m for all x * ∈ (C11)</formula><p>for the left-continuous version - min of min . The goal is to show that</p><formula xml:id="formula_131">x = sup x * ∈ inf m∈ m x * -x ≤ - min x * m (C12)</formula><p>To begin with, Equation (C11) implies</p><formula xml:id="formula_132">x ≥ sup x * ∈ inf m∈ m x * -x ≤ - min x * m</formula><p>As for the reverse inequality, suppose that x &gt; -, otherwise (C12) is trivial, and fix m 0 &lt; x . Define C = y ∈ y ≤ m 0 , which is * -closed, convex, and such that x ∈ C. By the hyperplane separation theorem, there exists x * 0 ∈ * \ 0 such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_133">x * 0 x &lt; inf y∈C x * 0 y (C13)</formula><p>By monotonicity of we have C = C + , hence (C13) yields x * 0 x &lt; x * 0 y + x * 0 k for all k ∈ and y ∈ C. It follows that 56 x * 0 ∈ \ 0 . Since m ⊆ C for all m ≤ m 0 , (C13) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_134">x * 0 -x -min x * 0 m ≥ x * 0 -x -sup y∈C x * 0 -y &gt; 0 (C14) Hence, since m → min x * 0 m is nondecreasing, m 0 ≤ sup x * ∈ inf m∈ m x * -x ≤ min x * m = sup x * ∈ inf m∈ m x * -x ≤ - min x * m (C15)</formula><p>Since the last relation holds for any m 0 &lt; x we derive</p><formula xml:id="formula_135">x ≤ sup x * ∈ inf m∈ m x * -x ≤ - min x * m and (C12) is established. Step 2. Since - min x * m = sup m &lt;m sup x∈ m x * -x = sup x∈ m- x * -x</formula><p>where m-= m &lt;m m is closed, a direct inspection shows that - min ∈ min . According to Lemma 1, the left inverse of - min , denoted by R is a maximal risk function, that is R ∈ max and therefore relation (C12) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_136">x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x x ∈ (C16)</formula><p>As for the uniqueness, according to Lemma 1 it is sufficient to show the uniqueness of - min in (C12) as min ∈ min . Consider 1 2 ∈ min satisfying</p><formula xml:id="formula_137">x = sup x * ∈ inf m∈ m x * -x ≤ i x * m x ∈</formula><p>56 In case that C = , x * 0 can arbitrarily be chosen in \ 0 .</p><p>Copyright: INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. </p><formula xml:id="formula_138">∈ x &lt; m = m &lt;m x ∈ sup x * ∈ inf n∈ n x * -x ≤ i x * n ≤ m = m &lt;m x ∈ inf n∈ n x * -x ≤ i x * n ≤ m for all x * ∈ = m &lt;m x ∈ x * -x ≤ i x * m + m -m /2 for all x * ∈ = m &lt;m x ∈ x * -x ≤ i x * m for all x * ∈ = m &lt;m m i (C17) for the * -closed convex sets m i = x x * -x ≤ i x * m for all x * ∈ . The uniqueness result in Lemma 2 yields i x * m = sup x∈ m i x * -x (C18)</formula><p>Thus, from relations (C17), (C18) and the left continuity of i x * • it follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_139">i x * m = sup m &lt;m i x * n = sup m &lt;m sup x∈ m i x * -x = sup m &lt;m m i x * -x = sup x x &lt;m x * -x</formula><p>and therefore 1 = 2 .</p><p>Step 3. Conversely, let x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x for a risk function R ∈ . Since s → R x * s is nondecreasing, it follows that is monotone. Further, s → R x * s is left continuous, nondecreasing and x → x * -x is linear and continuous for all x * ∈ . In view of relation (C3) it holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_140">x ∈ R x * x * -x ≤ m = x ∈ x * -x ≤ R -1 r x * m</formula><p>and therefore x → R x * x * -x is a lower semicontinuous quasiconvex function. This implies that the level sets</p><formula xml:id="formula_141">x ∈ x ≤ m = x ∈ sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x ≤ m = x * ∈ x ∈ R x * x * -x ≤ m</formula><p>are closed and convex for all m ∈ . Hence, is a lower semicontinuous risk measure.</p><p>C.7. Proof of Theorem 4. Let be a lower semicontinuous risk measure. By Theorem 3 there exists a unique R ∈ max whose restriction to × is in max and such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_142">x = sup x * ∈ &gt;0 R x * x * -x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x</formula><p>Because of the condition (ii) for max , there is a one-to-one relation between max and max , from which the uniqueness follows.</p><p>C.8. Proof of Proposition 5. Let R, R be two risk functions such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_143">x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x</formula><p>where R ∈ max . According to Theorem 3, R is the left inverse of min . Further, R x * x * -x ≤ m for all x * ∈ , m ∈ and x ∈ m . Hence, relation (B4) yields x * -x ≤ R -1 r x * m for all x * ∈ , m ∈ and x ∈ m . Because of Lemma 2, min is the smallest function having this property, that is, min x * m ≤ R -1 r x * m for all x * ∈ * and m ∈ . Since by Theorem 3 the maximal risk function R is the left inverse of min , it follows R x * s ≤ R x * s for all x * ∈ * and s ∈ .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. </p><p>+ , and = 1 1 in which case = p 1 -p p ∈ 0 1 . As for the first example, consider the risk function R p s = 1 s&gt;p , which is in max . However, R • 1/2 is not upper semicontinuous, since p ∈ 0 1 R p 1/2 ≥ 1/2 = 0 1/2 is not closed. In the second example, we show that maximal risk functions are in general not lower semicontinuous in the first argument. Indeed, within the setup of the previous example, we consider the maximal risk function R p s = 1 p≥1/2 for which R = R + , but R • s is for any s ∈ not lower semicontinuous.</p><p>Example 13 (Importance of the Regularity Assumption for Theorem 4). Indeed, let = , = 0 so that = * = and consider the lower semicontinuous quasiconvex function x = x 2 , which is monotone with respect to the nonregular preorder = 0 . However, there does not exist any ∈ \ 0 such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_145">x = sup x * ∈ R x * -x * • x for all x ∈ as = x * ∈</formula><p>x * = 1 reduces to the singleton 1/ and x = x 2 is different from any function x → R 1/ -x/ for some R ∈ , which by definition is either nondecreasing or nonincreasing depending on the sign of . C.10. Proof of Proposition 6. The proof is built on the respective properties of the acceptance family, which have been established in Propositions 1, 2, and 3.</p><p>In case that R is convex, positive homogeneous or scaling invariant in the second argument, it follows that is convex, positive homogeneous, or scaling invariant as the supremum of convex, positive homogeneous, or scaling invariant functions is convex, positive homogeneous, or scaling invariant, respectively.</p><p>Conversely, suppose that is convex. By Proposition 1, for any m, m ∈ , ∈ 0 1 and x * ∈ holds For the cash additive and cash subadditive case, the sufficiency is obvious. Conversely, if is cash additive, Proposition 2 implies min x * m = min x * 0 + m from which we deduce R x * s = smin x * 0 , and therefore R x * s + m = R x * s + m for all m, s ∈ and x * ∈ . If is cash subadditive, it follows from Proposition 2 that min x * n + m ≥ min x * n + m for all x * ∈ , n ∈ and m &gt; 0. Hence, for any x * ∈ , s ∈ and m &gt; 0 holds The sufficiency in both propositions is immediate. As for the necessity, the separability implies the existence of a risk measure . By Debreu's <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref> gap theorem, we can assume, up to a strictly increasing transformation, that Im c consists of intervals of either the form a b or a b for a, b ∈ . The lower semicontinuity and continuously extensible properties of imply the same properties for , respectively. Indeed, let be the corresponding risk acceptance family and m ∈ . Copyright: INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. </p><formula xml:id="formula_146">ˆ m = x ∈ ˆ x = h x ≤ m = x ∈ x ≤ h -1 r m = h -1 r m</formula><p>and so the lower semicontinuity of implies the lower semicontinuity of ˆ . Furthermore, the continuously extensible assumption on yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_147">ˆ m + ∩ = h -1 r m + ∩ = h -1 r m = ˆ m</formula><p>C.12. Proof of Proposition 8. Fix R × → -and define = R ∈ max R ≥ R . We have to show that the function R = inf R∈ R ∈ max . To this end, we first notice that R as an infimum of jointly quasiconcave functions is jointly quasiconcave. Secondly, for any x * ∈ , s ∈ and &gt; 0 holds x * s ∈ ×</p><formula xml:id="formula_148">R x * s = inf R∈ R x * s = inf</formula><p>• the closure in min of h denoted by cl min h is given by cl min h x * s = sup ˜ x * s ˜ ≤ h and ˜ ∈ min x * s ∈ ×</p><p>• the convex closure of g denoted by cl g * → -+ is either uniformly equal toif g x * =for some x * ∈ * or is the greatest lower semicontinuous convex function majorized by g; A similar argumentation as for the proof of Proposition 8 shows that for cl min h ∈ min . Proof. Fix ∈ min with cl -≤ ≤ . Since cl -∈ min and cl -= -= it follows cl -≤ ≤ cl -and thus = cl -, that is, cl min = cl -. As for the second equality, by Lemma 1 holds -1 l ≤ cl min -1 l ∈ max . Fix R ∈ max satisfying -1 l ≤ R ≤ cl min -1 l . Then, cl min ≤ R -1 l ≤ and since by Lemma 1 R -1 l ∈ min , we deduce that R -1 l = cl min , which in turn implies R = cl min -1 l . This shows that the cl max -closure of -1 l is cl min -1 l . Proof of Theorem 5. Given a continuously extensible lower semicontinuous risk measure with corresponding acceptance family , define the family ˆ by ˆ m = n&gt;m n + for m ∈ . By means of relation <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref>, it is straightforward to check that ˆ is the smallest closed acceptance family in , for which ˆ m ∩ = m for all m ∈ . Hence, the corresponding risk measure ˆ on is lower semicontinuous and coincides with on . Furthermore, since ˆ is the smallest closed risk acceptance family containing , it follows that ˆ is the unique maximal lower semicontinuous risk measure extension of on . According to Theorem 3, denote by R the unique element in max , such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_149">ˆ x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x x ∈</formula><p>57 Here, cl is the convex closure with respect to the first argument and • -is the left-continuous version in the second argument.</p><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. -closed and consequently 1 -closed. The Krein-Šmulian theorem then implies that Y is 1 -closed. Moreover, since 1 is separable by means of the separability of , it follows from Corollary 3.2 and its subsequent remark in Campion et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, that is separable. By Proposition 4 it can be represented by a 1 -lower semicontinuous risk measure → -+ . Finally, the robust representation (36) follows from Theorem 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>9</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp.1-35, © 2012 INFORMS    </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>15 Proposition 8 .</head><label>158</label><figDesc>Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS The max -closure of a function R × → -is itself an element of max .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS 23</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS C.6. Proof of Theorem 3. Throughout this subsection we assume the setup of §3. Definition 14. By min , we denote the set of minimal penalty functions, consisting of those mappings × → -+ , which are nondecreasing and left continuous in the second argument and such that (a) is convex in the first argument; (b) is positive homogeneous in the first argument; (c) if there exists x * ∈ such that x * m = -, then • m ≡ -; (d) is lower semicontinuous in the first argument.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>min x * m + 1 -m = sup x∈ m+ 1</head><label>11</label><figDesc>min x * m + 1min x * m Hence, m → + min x * m is concave. The function R x * • as the left inverse of + min x * • is therefore convex by Proposition 10. Analoguously, if is positive homogeneous or scaling invariant, it follows from Proposition 1 that min x * m = min x * m or min x * m = min x * m and thus R is positive homogeneous or scaling invariant in the second argument, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>R x * sm = sup n∈ n min x * n &lt; sm ≥ sup n∈ n min x * n + m &lt; s = R x * sm C.11. Proof of Propositions 4 and 7.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>If m ∈ Im or m in a gap a b ⊆ Im c , then m =x for x = m or m = a = x for x = a. In both cases, m is closed if is lower semicontinuous. For the same choice of x, the continuously extensible assumption on yields m + ∩ = x + ∩ = x = m .• If m is in a gap a b ⊆ Im c , the right continuity of implies the existence of a sequence of x l with x l b such that m = l∈ x l . Hence m is closed if is lower semicontinuous. For the same sequence x l , the continuously extensible assumption implies m + ∩ ⊆ x l + ∩ = x l for any l ∈ , and therefore m ⊆ m + ∩ ⊆ l∈ x l + ∩ = l∈ x l = m</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>R∈R</head><label></label><figDesc>x * s/ = R x * s/ Thirdly, R has a uniform asymptotic minimum as for any x * , y * ∈lim s→-R x * s = inf s∈ inf R∈ R x * s = inf R∈ inf s∈ R x * s = inf R∈ inf s∈ R y * s = lim s→-R y * sFinally, R+ is upper semicontinuous in the second argument as for any s, m ∈ , the setx * R+ x * s ≥ m = R∈ t&gt;s x * R x * t ≥ m = R∈ x * R+ x * s ≥ m is closed. C.<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref>. Proof of Theorem 5. For the proof, we use other notions of closures. For a function h × → -+ and a function g * → -+ , • recall that the closure in max of h denoted by cl max h is given by cl max h x * s = inf R x * s R ≥ h and R ∈ max</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Lemma 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Let × → -be nondecreasing in the second argument, then 57</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>=C. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp.1-35, © 2012 INFORMS    We next show that any lower semicontinuous risk measure ˜ x = sup x * ∈ R x * x * -x on with R ∈ max is a maximal extension of the lower semicontinuous risk measure on if and only if R ∈ max . Indeed, since ˜ m ∩ = m and ˆ m ⊆ ˜ m for all m ∈ , it follows˜ is a maximal extension ⇐⇒ ˜ = ˆ ⇐⇒ ˜ m Denoting ˜ min x * m = sup x∈ ˜ m x * -x for x * ∈ * , we deduce from (A3) that cl ˜ min x * m + x cl ˜ min + x * m + x *for all x * ∈ and m ∈ Thus, by the second step in the proof of Theorem 3 and Proposition 3 holds˜ = ˆ ⇐⇒ ˜ - min = cl ˜ min -+ = cl min ˜ min +Since R is uniquely determined as the left inverse of ˜ - min , Proposition 3 yields˜ = ˆ ⇐⇒ R = cl max ˜ min + -1 l on ×We are left to show that˜ min + -1 l x * s = sup y * ∈ * R x * -y * sy *for all x * ∈ and s ∈ For any x * ∈ and s ∈ holds˜ min + -1 l x * s = inf m ∈ s ≤ ˜ min x * m + x * = inf m ∈ s ≤ inf y * ∈ * ˜ min x * -y * m + y * = inf m ∈ s ≤ ˜ min x * -y * m + y * for all y * ∈ * = inf m ∈ s ≤ ˜ + min x * -y * m + y * for all y * ∈ * Finally, since ˜ + min x * -y * • + y * -1 l = R x * -y * • -y *, by use of relation (B5) follows˜ min + -1 l x * s = inf m ∈ R x * -y * s -Proof of Theorem 6.We first show that is 1 -lower semicontinuous. Indeed, the Fatou property and the dominated convergence theorem imply that Y ∩ B N is • 1 -closed for all Y ∈ and any ball B N = X X ≤ N of radius N &gt; 0. By convexity Y ∩ B N is 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS representation of the form</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS 2.1. Further structural properties. As mentioned in Remark 4, the properties of convexity, positive homogeneity, or affinity are no longer global and are therefore defined on the level of risk measures.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Definition 4. A risk measure</cell><cell>→ -+</cell><cell>is</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp.1-35, © 2012 INFORMS    </figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Theorem 4 (Robust Representation in the Regular Case). Let</cell><cell>be a regular preorder. Any lower</cell></row><row><cell>semicontinuous risk measure</cell><cell>→ -+</cell><cell cols="2">corresponding to a lower semicontinuous risk order has the</cell></row><row><cell>robust representation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp.1-35, © 2012 INFORMS    </figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp.1-35, © 2012 INFORMS    </figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS 21</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation 22 Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS Proof of Theorem 3. Step 1. Let be a lower semicontinuous risk measure. Theorem 1 yields</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Mathematics x = inf m ∈ x ∈ m</cell><cell>x ∈</cell><cell>(C9)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Since any m is</cell><cell cols="5">*  -closed, convex, and monotone, it follows from Lemma 2 that</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">x ∈ m if and only if x  *</cell><cell cols="2">-x ≤ min x  *  m for all x  *</cell><cell>∈</cell><cell>(C10)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>∈</cell><cell>.</cell></row><row><cell>Hence,</cell><cell>= +</cell><cell cols="2">and (C4) is equivalent to</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>x ∈ if and only if</cell><cell>x  *  x  *</cell><cell cols="2">-x ≤</cell><cell>x  *  x  *</cell><cell>for all x  *</cell><cell>∈ \ 0</cell></row></table><note><p><p>* / x * 54 That is y x with x ∈ implies y ∈ . 55 The minimality of the penalty function follows from the arguments given in Föllmer and Schied [29, Theorem 4.15].</p>Copyright:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation</figDesc><table><row><cell>Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS</cell><cell>27</cell></row><row><cell>for i = 1 2. For any m ∈ holds</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>x</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS C.9. Technical examples referring to Remark 8. Example 12 (Importance of Property (iv) in Definition 9). Let = 2 , =</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation Mathematics of Operations Research, Articles in Advance, pp. 1-35, © 2012 INFORMS 29 Let now ˆ = h for a continuously extensible lower semicontinuous risk measure → -and a lower semicontinuous increasing function h Im → . By relation (B4),</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="22" xml:id="foot_0"><p>A risk order satisfies the independence property if x ≺ y implies x + 1 -z ≺ y + 1 -z for all z ∈ and ∈ 0 1 and the Archimedian property if x ≺ z ≺ y implies the existence of ∈ 0 1 such that x + 1 -y ≺ z ≺ x + 1 -y.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="23" xml:id="foot_1"><p>A coherent risk measure is a positive homogeneous cash additive risk measure. By Proposition 2, is convex, hence, the positive homogeneity implies that is subadditive, that is, x + y ≤ x + y .</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="24" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Indeed, x + x = xx = 0 and by monotonicity x + m ≤ 0 for any m ≥ x .</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="25" xml:id="foot_3"><p>The automatic convexity is a well known result (see Frittelli and Rosazza Gianin<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, Cerreia-Vioglio et al.<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and the references therein). However, an argumentation relying on (16) is presented there. Furthermore, Cheridito and Kupper<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> showed that real-valued risk measure satisfying m = -m for all m ∈ are convex exactly when they are cash additive.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="26" xml:id="foot_4"><p>A monotone version with respect to the preorder greater than P -almost surely has been studied in Maccheroni et al.<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_5"><p>posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org.Drapeau and Kupper: Risk Preferences and Their Robust Representation</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="33" xml:id="foot_6"><p>For instance, the Fenchel-Moreau theorem states a complete duality between proper lower semicontinuous convex functions f and their proper lower semicontinuous convex conjugates f * .</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="34" xml:id="foot_7"><p>The level sets are evenly convex, that is, they are the intersection of a family of open half spaces.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="48" xml:id="foot_8"><p>In line with §4.1 we assume that the -algebra is separable.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Acknowledgments. The authors thank Philippe Artzner, Patrick Cheridito, Simone Cerreia-Vioglio, Freddy Delbaen, Damir Filipović, Hans Föllmer, Ulrich Horst, Fabio Maccheroni, Antonis Papapantoleon, and Irina Penner for helpful comments and fruitful discussions. Financial support from MATHEON project E.11 and the Berlin Mathematical School is gratefully acknowledged. Financial support from the DFG IRTG 1339 is gratefully acknowledged by the first author. Financial support from the Vienna Science and Technology Fund is gratefully acknowledged by the second author.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>˜</head><p>→ 1 c for which there exists 49 m &gt; 0 such that ˜ • -m m = 1 P -almost surely. As for the monotonicity, ˜ ˜ if ˜ dominates ˜ in the second stochastic order for P -almost all ∈ . The set of lotteries with compact support 1 c can be identified with the set of P -almost surely constant elements of . Further, the P -almost surely bounded random variables are canonically embedded into by means of the relation X → ˜ = X , where X is defined as the stochastic kernel equal to the Dirac measure at the point X , that is, ˜ = X for almost all ∈ . We henceforth say that a risk order on satisfies the Fatou property if for any • -bounded sequence X n of random variables converging P -almost surely to a bounded random variable X and any bounded random variable Y holds</p><p>The adequate condition that separates a risk order on in a model risk and a distributional risk component is given by</p><p>Theorem 9. Let be the risk order on such that (i) fulfills the Fatou property; (ii) s ≺ t for any two reals s, t with s &gt; t;</p><p>(iii) restricted to 1 c is 1 c C -lower semicontinuous and sensitive, that is c ≺ for some c ∈ implies c- for some &gt; 0</p><p>(iv) satisfies condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref>. Then, can be represented by a risk measure that factorizes into a model risk component and a distributional risk component, that is</p><p>where → is a 1 -lower semicontinuous risk measure and g 1 c → is a 1 c C -lower semicontinuous risk measure such that c = g c = -c for all c ∈ . Conversely, any risk order corresponding to a risk measure of the form (53) fulfills the conditions (i) to (iv).</p><p>For the proof, see Appendix C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref>. In contrast to the representations provided in Gilboa and Schmeidler <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, Klibanoff et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, Maccheroni et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, and Cerreia-Vioglio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> the risk order in Theorem 9 restricted to the set of lotteries 1 c is not necessarily affine.</p><p>Remark 12. By means of Theorem 6 and Theorem 7, any risk measure of the form (53) has the robust representation 50   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>˜ =</head><p>sup</p><p>where R and r are the maximal risk functions of and g, respectively.</p><p>Appendix A. Notations and basic concepts. Throughout, the extended real line -+ = ∪ -+ is considered with the canonical order and the convention + + -= + . The extended real line endowed with the metric d x y = arctan xy is a compact Polish space. 51 A function f → -+ , where ⊆ is a convex subset of a vector space , is</p><p>y for all x y ∈ and ∈ 0 1 , concave if -f is convex, and affine if f is concave and convex;</p><p>• quasiconvex if f x + 1 -y ≤ max f x f y for all x y ∈ and ∈ 0 1 , quasiconcave if -f is quasiconvex, and quasiaffine if f is quasiconvex and quasiconcave. 49 The constant m &gt; 0 depends on the choice of ˜ . 50 Because the risk measure g is monotone with respect to the second stochastic order, it is also monotone with respect to the first stochastic order. 51 Recall that a Polish space is a separable complete metrisable space. Let K n be an increasing sequence of compact intervals such that n K n = and denote by n , 1 K n , ca K n , C K n the respective restrictions of , 1 c , ca c , C to K n . Because of Corollary 3.2 and its subsequent remark in Campion et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, the risk order n is separable and consequently so is . By Proposition 4, the risk order can be represented by a lower semicontinuous risk measure 1 c → -+ . Denote by n the restriction of to 1 K n that is again a lower semicontinuous risk measure. Recall that ca K n is the dual space of C K n and 1 K n is ca K n C K n -compact in ca K n . The ca K n C K n -lower semicontinuous risk order n is therefore continuously extensible as well as n . Then, Theorem 5 yields a unique</p><p>Since n coincides with n on 1 K n for all n ≥ n, for the respective risk functions holds</p><p>We next show that and are continuously extensible. To this end, we define</p><p>for any ∈ 1 c . Because of the previous representation, it follows that and in turn are ca c C -lower semicontinuous and continuously extensible to ca c . In view of Theorem 5 there exists a unique R ∈ max</p><p>The claim then follows from Definition 11 and the proof is completed. </p><p>is a lower semicontinuous risk measure on 1 c . Because of Theorem 7, it admits then a robust representation. To compute the penalty function</p><p>we define t = q t + 1 -q -m , which is in m since F - t -m ≤ q for all t ∈ . Then for any loss function</p><p>Thus, for any l ∈ holds R l s = l -1 sql + 1 -q where l -1 is the left inverse of l.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Copyright:</head><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. </p><p>where y t = c t -t 0 e -t-s c s ds. In the line with the proof of Proposition 9 shows that ˜ is a lower semicontinous risk measure on that is an extension of that is however not maximal. Further, for any c ∈ the respective y given by</p><p>is in . Conversely, for any y ∈ the Volterra Equation (C21) of the second kind has the unique solution c t = y t + t 0 y s ds, which is in . By use of this one-to-one relation, c ∈ ˜ m exactly when 1 0 l -y t dt ≤ m and using <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref> the minimal penalty function ˜ min for ∈ can be computed as</p><p>where t = tt , since dc t = dy t + y t dt. Fix m &gt; inf l, since otherwise, for m ≤ inf l holds ˜ min m = -as m = .</p><p>• If 1 &gt; 0 then ˜ min m = + . Indeed, take some c ∈ ˜ m . By (C20) we have </p><p>We suppose now that is such that ≥ 0, 1 = 0 and m &gt; 0. For some Lagrange multiplier = m &gt; 0, define the function</p><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. </p><p>C.20. Proof of Theorem 9. The restriction of to 1 c is 1 c C -lower semicontinuous and monotone with respect to the first stochastic order. In view of Theorem 7 the restriction of to 1 c is separable and can be represented by a lower semicontinuous risk measure g 1 c → . The function h c = g c for c ∈ is decreasing and lower semicontinuous. Because of (ii) and (iii) holds Im g = Im h . Indeed, take some ∈ 1 c and suppose that g ∈ Im h . Consider the smallest t ∈ such that t , which exists because of the lower semicontinuity. From the sensitivity, ∼ t in contradiction to g ∈ Im h . This shows that up to an increasing lower semicontinuous transformation, we can suppose that Im g = and g c = -c. The lower semicontinuity implies moreover that → G ˜ = g ˜ is measurable. The condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref> and the monotonicity imply that for any k &gt; 0 such that the support of ˜ lies uniformly in -k k holds k = g -k ≥ G ˜ ≥ g k = -k, showing that G maps to . Moreover, the fact that 58 G X = -X for any X ∈ yields Im G = . We now define the binary relation G on by</p><p>To be well defined, we have to show that for any X ∈ , the stochastic kernels in G -1 -X are equivalent to each other. To do so, consider two stochastic kernels ˜ , ˜ ∈ such that G ˜ = G ˜ P -almost surely. Then g ˜ = g ˜ for P -almost all ∈ and so ˜ ∼ ˜ . In view of condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(51)</ref>, it follows that ˜ ∼ ˜ and therefore, for any X ∈ , the elements of G -1 -X are equivalent. Moreover, is transitive and complete, and therefore a total preorder. It is furthermore a risk order. Indeed, concerning the monotonicity, for X Y ∈ with X = -G ˜ ≥ -G ˜ = Y , the condition (51) implies ˜ ˜ and therefore X G Y . As for the quasiconvexity, consider some</p><p>Recall that for X ∈ , the notation X stands for the stochastic kernel X dx , which is a Dirac measure at X for all ∈ .</p><p>Copyright:</p><p>INFORMS holds copyright to this Articles in Advance version, which is made available to subscribers. The file may not be posted on any other website, including the author's site. Please send any questions regarding this policy to permissions@informs.org. for any nondecreasing concave function f . Since is a risk order, it follows that X+ 1-Y ˜ + 1 -• ˜ ˜ . Hence X + 1 -Y G Y . Finally, the risk order G satisfies the Fatou property. Indeed, let X n be a</p><p>• -bounded sequence in converging P -almost surely to some X ∈ . Because of condition (i) holds that X n Y for all n implies X Y . From the definition of G follows that X n G Y for all n implies X G Y , and therefore, by means of Theorem 6, the risk order G is a separable and 1 -lower semicontinuous. Let → -+ be a 1 -lower semicontinuous risk measure representing G . Then</p><p>is a risk measure corresponding to . Indeed, for ˜ ∈ holds ˜ ∼ -G ˜ , and therefore ˜ ˜ is equivalent to -G ˜ -G ˜ , which by definition is equivalent to -G ˜ G -G ˜ . Hence ˜ ˜ is equivalent to -G ˜ ≤ -G ˜ . Conversely, it is plain to check that any risk order corresponding to a risk measure of the form (53) fulfills the conditions (i) to (iv).</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk assessment for uncertain cash flows: Model ambiguity, discounting ambiguity, and the role of bubbles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Acciaio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Föllmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Penner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Finance Stochastics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="669" to="709" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Aliprantis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Border</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Infinite Dimensional Analysis: A Hitchhiker&apos;s Guide</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Heidelberg, New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A definition of subjective probability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Anscombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Aumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Math. Statist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coherent measures of risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Artzner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Delbaen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Heath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An economic index of riskiness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Aumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Serrano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Political Econom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="810" to="836" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expected utility, penalty functions and duality in stochastic nonlinear programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ben-Tal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Teboulle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1445" to="1466" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An old-new concept of convex risk measures: The optimized certainty equivalent</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ben-Tal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Teboulle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="476" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic continuity and openness of convex relations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Borwein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Amer. Math. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence of a semicontinuous or continuous utility function: A unified approach and an elementary proof</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Econom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="328" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aspirational preferences and their representation by risk measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Giorgi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://mansci.journal.informs.org/content/early/2012/06/15/mnsc.1120.1537" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-06-15">2012. June 15</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The existence of utility functions for weakly continuous preferences on a Banach space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Campion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Candeal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Indurain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Soc. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalised Sharpe ratios and asset pricing in incomplete markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cerny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. Finance Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Maxmin expected utility on a subjective state space: Convex preferences under risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cerreia-Vioglio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cerreia-Vioglio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Maccheroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marinacci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Montrucchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk measures: Rationality and diversification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cerreia-Vioglio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Maccheroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marinacci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Montrucchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="743" to="774" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uncertainty averse preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cerreia-Vioglio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Maccheroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marinacci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Montrucchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Econom. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1275" to="1330" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recursivity of indifference prices and translation-invariant preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cheridito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kupper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Financial Econom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Composition of time-consistent dynamic monetary risk measures in discrete time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cheridito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kupper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Internat. J. Theoret. Appl. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk measures on Orlicz hearts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cheridito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weak closedness of monotone sets of lotteries and robust representation of risk preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cheridito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Drapeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kupper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Actuarial Academy (EAA) Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Forthcoming</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New measures for performance evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cherny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Madan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Financial Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2571" to="2606" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conditions for convexity of quasiconvex functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-P</forename><surname>Crouzeix</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sulle stratificazioni convesse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>De Finetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annali di Matematica Pura e Applicata</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="1949">1949</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation of a preference ordering by a numerical function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Debreu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Decision Processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Coombs</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1954">1954</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="165" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuity Properties of Paretian utility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Debreu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Internat. Econom. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A von Neumann-Morgenstern representation result without weak continuity assumption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Delbaen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Drapeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kupper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Econom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cash sub-additive risk measures and interest rate ambiguity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>El Karoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ravanelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convex measures of risk and trading constraint</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Föllmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schied</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Finance Stochastics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="447" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Föllmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schied</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Stochastic finance. An introduction in discrete time</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Walter de Gruyter</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>de Gruyter Studies in Mathematics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust preferences and robust portfolio choice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Föllmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schied</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Numerical Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="87" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An operational measure of riskiness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Foster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Political Econom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="785" to="814" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Putting order in risk measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Frittelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rosazza</forename><surname>Gianin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Banking Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1473" to="1486" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maxmin expected utility with a non-unique prior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gilboa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schmeidler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Econom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="153" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quasiconjugate functions and surrogate duality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Pierskalla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cahiers du Centre d&apos;Etude de Recherche Operationelle</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="448" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Back to the future. Plenary Lecture at the First World Congress of the</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Heath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Bachelier Society</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On intertemporal preferences in continuous time: The case of certainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hindy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C-F</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kreps</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Econom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="440" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">General theory of employment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Keynes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quart. J. Econom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="1937">1937</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A smooth model of decision making under ambiguity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Klibanoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marinacci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mukerji</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1849" to="1892" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Knight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Risk, Uncertainty, and Profit</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Houghton Mifflin Company</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">&amp;</forename><surname>Schaffner</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Marx</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1921">1921</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modern society shocked by its risks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Luhmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Sciences Research Centre: Occasional Papers (Social Sciences Research Centre in association with the Dept. of Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Hong Kong, Hong Knog</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Luhmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Risk: A Sociological Theory</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Piscataway, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Transaction Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ambiguity aversion, robustness, and the variational representation of preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Maccheroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marinacci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rustichini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1447" to="1498" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Portfolio selection with monotone mean-variance preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Maccheroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marinacci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rustichini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taboga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="521" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Portfolio selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Markowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="1952">1952</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on mixture sets in decision theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mongin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Decision Econom. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Namioka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Partially Ordered Linear Topological Spaces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Princeton, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inversion of real-valued functions and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-P</forename><surname>Penot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Volle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Methods Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On quasi-convex duality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-P</forename><surname>Penot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Volle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="597" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Rockafella</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Convex Analysis</title>
		<title level="s">Princeton Mathematics Series</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimization of convex risk functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ruszczyński</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Savage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Foundations of Statistics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Mineola, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Dover Publications</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capital asset prices: A theory of market equilibrium under conditions of risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Sharpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Von Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Morgenstern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Theory of Games and Economics Behavior</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1947">1947</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distribution-invariant risk measures, information, and dynamic consistency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
