<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Nonblocking and Orphan-Free Message Logging Protocols</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lorenzo</forename><surname>Alvisi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bruce</forename><surname>Hoppe</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Keith</forename><surname>Marzullo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Cornell University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>14853</postCode>
									<settlement>Ithaca</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at San Diego</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>9500 Gilman Dr. 0114, La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92093-0114</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Nonblocking and Orphan-Free Message Logging Protocols</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">0D8C1AE0664B4BCA47FAC21667595B5F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T05:09+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Currently existing message logging protocols demonstrate a classic pessimistic vs. optimistic tradeoff. We show that the optimistic-pessimistic tradeoff is not inherent to the problem of message logging. We construct a message-logging protocol that has the positive features of both optimistic and pessimistic protocol: our protocol prevents orphans and allows simple failure recovery; however, it requires no blocking in failure-free runs. Furthermore, this protocol does not introduce any additional message overhead as compared to one implemented for a system in which messages may be lost but processes do not crash.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Message logging protocols are a common method of building a system that can tolerate process crash failures. These protocols require that each process periodically record its local state and log the messages it received after that state. When a process crashes, a new process is created, given the appropriate recorded local state, and then sent the logged messages in the order they were originally received.</p><p>Message logging protocols are not the only techniques for making systems robust against process crashes. For example, active replication <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> or passive replication <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> are commonly-used techniques for masking failures more severe than crash failures. However, message logging protocols are attractive in that they are considered an inexpensive technique: they introduce little or no process replication in failure free runs and the protocols are relatively simple. Another advantage of message logging protocols is that they are readily applied to any process communication structure, while both active and passive replication are typically applied in a client-server setting. Of course, one can use either active or passive replication to implement a message logging system.</p><p>The published message logging protocols exhibit a classic tradeoff in performance: there exist pessimistic protocols that introduce blocking in order to simplify recovery and optimistic protocols that introduce no blocking but may require computation to be undone upon recovery. In this paper, we show that the optimistic-pessimistic tradeoff is not necessary for message logging protocols. We derive a message logging policy that is weaker than that used by pessimistic protocols yet is strong enough to guarantee that computation need not be rolled back. This policy is based on the notion of logging a message when the effects of its delivery are visible to some process other than the process to which it was delivered. This logging policy can be implemented without introducing additional blocking. We then give a protocol that can tolerate non-concurrent failures and discuss its performance.</p><p>The paper proceeds as follows. Section 2 describes the system model commonly assumed for message logging protocols. Section 3 discusses message logging protocols and explains the current optimistic-pessimistic tradeoff. Section 4 defines what it means for a message to be relevant, derives logging and recovery rules for relevant messages, and presents a message logging protocol that is nonblocking but creates no orphans. Section 5 discusses the performance of an implementation our protocol, and Section 6 concludes the paper.</p><p>Due to space limitations, there are no proofs about the correctness of the protocols in this paper. The interested reader can find the proofs in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">System Model</head><p>We assume that processes communicate only by exchanging messages, and that a process never sends a message to itself. The system is asynchronous: there exists no bound on the relative speeds of processes, no bound on message transmission delays, and no global time source. Hence, the order in which a process receives messages is nondeterministic.</p><p>The execution of a system of n processes is represented by a run, which is an irreflexive partial ordering of the send events, receive events and delivery events ordered by potential causality <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Delivery events are local to a process and represent the delivery of a received message to the application. For any message m from process p to process q, q delivers m only if it has received m, and q delivers m no more than once.</p><p>We assume a fail-stop failure model for the processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. We assume channels to be FIFO, in that if process p sends m 1 and then m 2 to process q, then q will not receive m 2 before receiving m 1 . Furthermore, we as- sume that if p sends m to q, and p and q do not crash, then q will eventually receive m. 1   At any point in an execution, the state of a process is determined by its initial state and the sequence of messages that it has delivered. For any message m delivered by process p, its receive sequence number, denoted m:rsn, represents the order in which m was delivered: m:rsn = ìf m is the `th message delivered by p <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. We denote with p `] the state of process p after having delivered messages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">3 Issues in Message Logging</head><p>In message logging protocols, each process must record both the contents and receive sequence numbers of all the messages it has delivered in a location (called a message log) that will survive the failure of the process. This action is called logging. The process may also periodically create a checkpoint of its local state, thereby allowing its message log to be trimmed. For example, once process p knows that state p `] is checkpointed, all messages m such that m:rsn `can be removed from p's message log. Note that the periodic checkpointing of a process's state is only needed to bound the length of its message log (and hence the recovery time). For simplicity we ignore checkpointing in this paper.</p><p>Logging a message may take time, and so there is a natural design decision of whether or not a process should wait for the logging to complete before delivering the message to the application. For example, suppose that having delivered message m, process p sends message m 0 to process 1 These channel properties are typically provided by a transport protocol.</p><p>2 By state of a process we mean the value of its variables, the program counter, and so on. We do not consider the queue of messages that have been received but not delivered by a process to be part of its state.</p><p>q. If message m were not logged by the time p sent m 0 , then the crash of p may cause information about m to be lost. Then, when a new process p is initialized and replayed logged messages, p may follow an execution in which m 0 is not sent to q. Hence, process q would no longer be consistent with p once q delivers m 0 . Such a message m is called a lost message, message m 0 an orphan message and the state of process q an orphan state <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Protocols that can create orphan states are called optimistic because the likelihood of creating an orphan state is (hopefully) small.</p><p>A pessimistic protocol is one in which each process p never sends a message m 0 until it knows that all messages delivered before sending m 0 are logged. Pessimistic protocols will never create orphan states, and so the reconstruction of the state of a crashed process is very straightforward as compared to optimistic protocols, in which orphan states must be detected and rolled back. On the other hand, pessimistic protocols potentially block a process for each message it receives. This can slow down the throughput of the processes, even in an execution in which no process crashes.</p><p>Another design decision in message logging protocols is where each message is to be logged. An obvious choice is to log at the receiving process, since it is the receiving process that assigns the receive sequence number to an incoming message <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. Unfortunately, such a receiverbased protocol requires an implementation of stable storage that will survive the crash of the receiving process. Another choice, called sender-based logging, is to log each message m in the sender's volatile storage <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Doing so requires the receiver to tell the sender what receive sequence number was assigned to m. Furthermore, the receiver does not know that m is logged until it receives an extra acknowledgement from the sender indicating that the receive sequence number has been recorded. The receive sequence number can be piggybacked on the acknowledgement of message m, but the extra acknowledgement from the sender may require an additional message; and in pessimistic sender-based logging, the receiver still must block until it receives the final acknowledgement <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. A further problem with sender-based logging is that multiple concurrent failures may make a process unable to recover its previous state even when a pessimistic protocol is used. However, sender-based logging is, in some sense, optimal in the number of resources it uses: it requires no stable storage and an additional process is needed only when recovery of a crashed process begins.</p><p>These two design decisions-pessimistic vs. optimistic and receiver-based logging vs. sender-based logging-are independent. In particular, there exist pessimistic receiverbased logging protocols <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>, optimistic receiver-based logging protocols <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>, pessimistic sender-based log-ging protocols <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref> and optimistic sender-based logging protocols <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</p><p>All message protocols must address the problem of communication with the environment. For input, the data from the environment must be stored in a location that is accessible for the purpose of replay. For output, the process must be in a recoverable state before sending any message to the environment. This means that, in general, even optimistic message logging protocols may block before sending a message to the environment. Such issues are outside of the scope of this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Nonblocking, Orphan-Free Protocols</head><p>In this section, we first review how recovery can be done when there are no orphan states. We then develop a nonblocking protocol in which orphan states cannot occur by more carefully considering the design decision: by what point must a message be logged?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Recovery with no Orphans</head><p>Suppose that process q delivers a message m from process p. We define another message m 0 to depend on m if the delivery of m causally precedes the sending of m 0 .</p><p>Consider the execution of a distributed system and a set of local states 1 `1]; : : :; n `n], one for each process 1; : : :; n. We say that two states p `p] and q `q] are mutually consistent if all messages from p that have been delivered to q by q `q] have been sent by p `p], and all messages from q that have been delivered to p by p `p] have been sent by q `q]. The collection of local states is a consistent global state if all pairs of states are mutually consistent <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>;<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">3</ref> otherwise it is inconsistent. With message logging protocols, an inconsistent global state arises when a lost message occurs due to optimistic recovery.</p><p>A pessimistic message logging protocol is one in which a message m is always logged by the time any message m 0 that depends on m is sent. Recovery in pessimistic protocols is straightforward: the crashed process is reinitialized and replayed the logged messages in increasing receive sequence number order. Since the process is deterministic with respect to message delivery order, it will follow the same path of execution as before. Thus, in the act of recovering, it will send the same sequence of messages as before. Any duplicate message m sent during recovery is acknowledged and discarded if the destination has already received m.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">4</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Abstract Message Logging Protocol</head><p>A pessimistic protocol guarantees that a message m is logged before any message that depends on m is sent. However, it is not necessary that m be logged until a message that depends on m is delivered, because it is at this point that the effects of m will become visible to another process. Hence, we define a message m to be relevant when a process has delivered a message that depends on m.</p><p>The following protocol is based on the above observation. We call this an abstract message logging protocol because it specifies the logging of a message as merely including its information in a set. In this protocol, we assume that message acknowledgements are never delivered to the application: that is, they are only seen by the underlying transport protocol. Thus, an application-level send is nonblocking in that the application does not wait for an acknowledgement from the recipient. This assumption allows us not to log acknowledgements, since they carry no information as far as the application is concerned. Note that this assumption is not fundamental, in that if it does not hold, then acknowledgements can be logged and replayed in the same way the other messages are.</p><p>A message is logged by including attributes about the message in a set L. A message m has the following five attributes: m:source is the sender of m; m:dest is the destination of m; m:data is the data that the application m:source sends to m:dest; m:ssn is the send sequence number: m:ssn = `denotes that m is the `th message sent by m:source; m:rsn is the receive sequence number. Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, a message m is partially logged if the four attributes m:source; m:dest; m:data; m:ssn are defined in L, and m is fully logged if all five attributes are defined in L. Finally, L p is the subset of messages m 2 L such that m:dest = p.</p><p>The protocol is as follows. It qconsists of a logging policy and a recovery procedure:</p><p>Logging policy A message m is partially logged by the time it is sent and fully logged by the time it is relevant.</p><p>Recovery procedure To recover a crashed process p: after any messages that p sent before crashing are either received or dropped due to transient channel faults, p is restarted from its initial state. It is then sequentially sent the messages in L p in an order that is consistent with the receive sequence numbers of the fully logged messages and that cess state and then have acknowledgements logged in the same way as other messages. In this case, a process receiving a repeat message m would discard m without sending an acknowledgement because the message acknowledgement will be replayed. As is discussed in Section 4.2, the choice of implementation is not just a matter of efficiency-which implementation is correct depends on whether or not acknowledgements are visible to the application. is consistent with FIFO channels for the partially logged messages.</p><p>The abstract message logging protocol given above will recover the state of the application after the failure of a single process. However, recovery of the logged messages has not yet been addressed. In particular, if the information about a logged message m can be lost due to a process crash and recovery, then the protocol may only be able to tolerate a single failure in any run. If the following property holds, however, then the abstract message logging protcol can tolerate any sequence of (process crash; process recovery) pairs:</p><p>Stable log property: If a message m is partially logged and will eventually be received, then m is partially logged after any process p crashes and recovers. And, if m is fully logged and a process p crashes, then m is fully logged after p recovers.</p><p>Note that we allow partially logged messages that will never be received to become "unlogged". Such a message, however, is never received by any process and so can be lost without any effect.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Family-Based Logging</head><p>According to the abstract message logging protocol described in Section 4.2, a message m must be fully logged when it becomes relevant. Which process determines when a message becomes relevant? In order to answer this question, we introduce the following definitions: We say a process p is a parent of a process q, and q is a child of p, if q delivers a message sent by p. Note that p can simultaneously be a parent and a child of q.</p><p>Consider a message m from process p to process q. The relevance of m is not determined by q, nor in general by q's parent, p. Rather, m becomes relevant when some child of q delivers a message that depends on m. Thus, the children of q determine the moment when any message delivered by q must be fully logged, and so it is natural to assign the responsibility of logging m's receive sequence number to the children. To do so, q can piggyback m:rsn on every message q sends after delivering m, and the recipient of the piggybacked receive sequence number can log it. If m becomes relevant, then some child r must have delivered a message that depends on m, and so m:rsn is logged at r. Of course, q need not piggyback m:rsn on every subsequent message: once q receives an acknowledgement from r for any message that depends on m, then q knows that m:rsn is logged at r. Finally, the other attributes of m are already located at its sender p that is a parent of q, and so we assign to p the responsibility of partially logging m before m is sent. We call this logging strategy family-based logging.</p><p>Suppose that process q fails. The messages logged at q's parents and the receive sequence numbers logged at q's children must be recombined to recover q. Thus, q's children must log more than receive sequence numbers; there must be some means of matching receive sequence numbers to the corresponding messages. To do so, q can piggyback triplets of the form (m:source; m:ssn; m:rsn) where m is the message delivered by q. Each triplet (p; ssn; rsn) corresponds to a unique message partially logged at process p with send sequence number ssn; and so when q fails, the receive sequence numbers logged at q's children can be matched with the corresponding messages logged at q's parents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1">Data Structures</head><p>The protocol requires each process p to maintain the following data structures:</p><p>Send sequence number: SSN p is an integer, initially 0, used to uniquely identify and order each message sent by p.</p><p>Receive sequence number: RSN p is an integer, initially 0, used to uniquely identify and order each message delivered by p. Send log: SendLog p is a set, initially empty, of elements of the form e = (data; ssn; rsn; dest). This set represents the messages that have been sent by p. e 2 SendLog p if there exists a message m sent by p in state p e:rsn] such that m:data = e:data, m:ssn = e:ssn, and m:dest = e:dest. RSN log: RsnLog p is a set, initially empty, of elements of the form e = (parent; ssn; rsn; child). This set represents the messages that have been delivered by p. This set represents the relevant messages that have been delivered by parents of p. If e 2 ReceiveLog p , then there exists a message m delivered by process e:parent such that m:source = e:grandparent, m:ssn = e:ssn, m:rsn = e:rsn; and furthermore, there exists a message m 0 with m 0 :source = e:parent delivered by p such that m 0 depends on m. SSN table: SsnTable p is a vector of send sequence numbers whose entries are initialized to 0. SsnTable p q] records the highest send sequence number of any message from q delivered by p. Piggyback sequence number: PSN p is an integer, ini-tially 0. PSN p keeps the value of the highest receive sequence number such that the corresponding entry e 2 RsnLog p has e:child 6 = ?. Entries e 2 RsnLog p such that e:rsn &gt; PSN p might not be logged, and will be therefore piggybacked by p on the next outgoing message.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">m 1 = (d 1 ; 1; ;) m 2 = (d 2 ; 1; ;) p 1 p 2 p 3 p 4 p 5 m 3 = (d 3 ; 1; f#m 2 g) m 4 = (d 4 ; 2; f#m 1 ; #m 2 g) ack(1)</formula><p>m 5 = (d 5 ; 2; ;)</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">t 2 t 3 t 1 ack(2)</formula><p>#m i = (m i :source; m i :ssn; m i :rsn) </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">m 6 = (d 6 ; 3; f#m 5 g)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2">Example</head><p>As an illustration of how FBL's message logging protocol works in the absence of link failures, consider Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>. For the sake of clarity we have included only the acknowledgments for messages m 3 and m 4 . We assume that the acknowledgments for the remaining messages have not yet been received. Each message that carries data is a triple (data; ssn; piggyback) where data is the data of the message, ssn is the message's send sequence number and piggyback is the information that is piggybacked on the message.</p><p>We consider the execution of the protocol from the perspective of process p 3 . Notice that p 3 piggybacks on each outgoing message m i enough information to fully log all the partially logged messages on which m i depends. In particular, consider the situation at time t 1 : even though process p 3 has already piggybacked the information con- cerning m 2 on message m 3 , p 3 has not yet received an acknowledgment for m 3 , and so cannot assume m 2 is fully logged. Hence, m 4 contains the information necessary to fully log m 1 and m 2 . By time t 2 , however, p 3 has received the acknowledg- ments for both m 3 and m 4 , and therefore knows that m 1 is logged at p 4 and m 2 is logged at p 5 . It then piggybacks on m 6 only the information necessary to fully log m 5 .   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref> give the code for the family-based logging protocol. Due to lack of space, we rely on the example given above instead of giving a detailed explanation of the code. Briefly, Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> give the code for the send and deliver operations. The message attribute m.piggyback is the set of triples (m 0 :parent; m 0 :ssn; m 0 :rsn) for messages m 0 received by p but not yet fully logged.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SSNp SSNp</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> gives the part of the protocol that advances the piggyback sequence number when an acknowledgement is received. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> gives the protocol a process runs when recovering, and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref> gives the protocol a process executes when it is requested to send its logs to a recovering process.    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.3">Protocol</head><p>When p recovers, it uses this protocol to collect the send logs from its parents and the receive logs from its children in order to construct the logged messages in the data structure ReplayLog p , and it uses the RSN logs of its parents to reconstruct its receive log. 5 In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>, process q sends a sequence of messages to the recovering process p bracketed by the messages "q begin replay" and "q exit replay". The receives of these bracketing messages are not explicitly shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>, but instead are denoted implicitly by the predicates "m.source has begun replaying"</p><p>and "all processes have exited replay to p". 5 Obviously, this protocol can be simplified if p knows the identity of its parents and children.</p><p>q receives ''p crashed/recovering'' send ''q begin replay'' to p for all e 2 SendLogq st e:dest = p send (q; e:data; e:ssn) to p for all e 2 ReceiveLogq st e:parent = p send (q; e:grandparent; e:ssn;e:rsn) to p for all e 2 RsnLogq st ((e:child = p) _ (e:child = ?)) send (q; e:parent; e:ssn; e:rsn) to p send ''q exit replay'' to p </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Optimizations</head><p>In this section we discuss a number of techniques for reducing the cost of family-based logging. Our goal is to reduce the quantity of information piggybacked on each message, without adding too much complexity to the failure recovery protocol.</p><p>For example, consider the grandparent and ssn fields of the receive log. Together, these fields uniquely determine a single message recorded in the appropriate send log; but, since channels are FIFO, the grandparent and rsn fields can be used to uniquely determine a message. Suppose that process p delivers message m and then later fails. Note that if m:rsn has been logged, then m is relevant, and so every message delivered by p before m must also be relevant, hence fully logged. Thus, by using the grandparent and rsn fields from the receive logs of its children, the recovering p can compute the order in which its parents sent it relevant messages. If p also constructs the replayed messages from each of its parents in separate sequences, each ordered by send sequence number, then the ordered sequence of parents can be merged with the ordered sequences of messages so that all relevant messages are matched with their original receive sequence numbers.</p><p>Once the ssn field is eliminated from the receive log, the RSN log no longer needs an ssn field, and so ssn values need not be piggybacked (except for the single m:ssn associated with a message m itself).</p><p>Not only can we eliminate send sequence numbers from piggybacks, we can also eliminate most of the receive sequence numbers. Consider a single message m from p to q; m carries a sequence of entries from RsnLog p . If we constrain p to piggyback in receive sequence number order, then only the lowest rsn value attached to m need be piggybacked, and q can compute the other receive sequence numbers itself. Thus, p need piggyback only a sequence of parents, together with a single receive sequence number.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.1">Sender-Based Optimization</head><p>Suppose it is known that some process p has only a single child, q. In this special case, we can easily optimize the usual message logging protocol. Because of FIFO channels, p need never piggyback the same entry in RsnLog p to q more than once. The message logging protocol for such a process p can thus be modified as follows: Whenever p sends a message m to q in state p RSN p ], then p's piggyback sequence number, PSN p , can immediately be set to RSN p (without waiting for q to acknowledge m).</p><p>This optimization can be generalized to the case where p has more than one child. For any process p, no entry in RsnLog p need be piggybacked to any single destination more than once. To implement this, p must keep track of a different piggyback sequence number for each child of p. We store these in a new data structure: the PSN table. For any pair of processes p and q, let Q p be the set of entries of RsnLog p that have been piggybacked from p to q. Then define PsnTable p q] = maxfe:rsn : e 2 Q p g. If PSN p is maintained as before (based on acknowledgements), then whenever p sends a message m to q, p need only piggyback all e 2 RsnLog p such that e:rsn &gt; maxfP SN p ; PsnTable p q]g. After m has been sent, p must update PsnTable p q]to reflect the information piggybacked on m.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.2">Receiver-Based Optimization</head><p>Using the above optimizations, we have transformed the piggyback data structure from a sequence of the form f(p 1 ; ssn 1 ; rsn 1 ); : : :; (p k ; ssn k ; rsn k )g to a sequence of the form frsn 1 ; p 1 ; p 2 ; : : :; p k g, such that no information is piggybacked to a single child more than once. We now consider one method of further compressing the piggybacked sequence of parent id's.</p><p>Suppose it is known that some process p has only a single parent, q. In this case, we can again easily optimize the usual message logging protocol. Note that the send sequence numbers assigned by q define a total ordering of the messages delivered by p. Thus, p need not keep any RSN log at all. Should p fail, q's send log contains sufficient information to recover p. (Likewise, p does not need RSN p , PSN p , and PsnTable p ; however, p does need SsnTable p and ReceiveLog p in case q fails.) This optimization can be generalized to the case where p can have multiple parents, as we show below. The result is similar to the null logging technique described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</p><p>Process p logs receive sequence numbers in order to record the nondeterministic characteristics of a run. Since channels are FIFO, however, p need only log the order in which p interleaves messages from different parents.</p><p>If a message logging protocol records the interleaving of messages from different parents for a process p, then this information together with the send logs of p's parents is sufficient to recover p from failure.</p><p>Family-based logging can easily accommodate this general optimization. Each process p can maintain an interleave sequence number, or ISN p . ISN p is initially zero, and is incremented in state p `] if `= 1 or if the source of the `th message is different from the source of the (`? 1) th message.</p><p>The RSN log can then be modified to record interleave sequence numbers. An entry e 2 RsnLog p contains two new fields: Field e:isn equals the value of ISN p in state p e:rsn]. Field e:runlength equals the number of consecutive messages delivered by p from e:parent since state p e:rsn]. The message logging protocol can then be modified so that p adds a new entry to its RSN log only when p increments its interleave sequence number. Thus, e:isn serves to count RSN log entries just as e:rsn does in the unoptimized protocol. If p delivers a message but does not increment its interleave sequence number, then p has delivered a run of messages from the same parent, and p must increment the runlength field in the last entry of its RSN log. Together with e:rsn, e:runlength encodes all the receive sequence numbers corresponding to entry e 2 RsnLog p . Given these modifications, consider a message logging protocol in which PSN p and PsnTable p contain interleave sequence numbers rather than receive sequence numbers, but otherwise function as before. Whenever p delivers consecutive messages from a single parent, RsnLog p will stop growing, and p will piggyback nothing on its outgoing messages. Whenever p interleaves messages from different parents, p will record the interleaving in new entries of RsnLog p , and then piggyback the information in these new entries on outgoing messages as before. (Note that the sequence of parent id's actually piggybacked by p can also be compressed with run length encoding, but this optimization is independent of the changes to the message logging data structures described here.) Finally, we must strengthen our failure recovery protocol in order to guarantee correctness. Suppose process p fails. Note that p may have delivered many consecutive relevant messages from one parent before crashing. Only the first receive sequence number of this sequence has necessarily been piggybacked and recorded in a child's receive log.</p><p>However, if we require that p deliver replayed messages such that runs of consecutive messages from the same parent are maximized (subject to the receive sequence number ordering imposed by p's replay log) then failure recovery will return the system to a consistent state.</p><p>We have described in Section 4 an optimal message logging protocol, in the sense that it requires no extra messages and no extra processes in a failure-free run. However, this measure of optimality ignores the most interesting cost of family-based logging: the extra information that must be piggybacked on application messages. In this section we discuss theoretical bounds and empirical measurements of this cost. We also briefly discuss failure recovery performance. Our discussion concerns family-based logging as described in Section 4.3 with the additional optimization provided by the PSN table of Section 4.4.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Predicted Performance</head><p>For a message m from p to q, we will measure the quantity of piggybacked information by the number of RSN log entries contained in m. Unfortunately, for arbitrary m, we can only bound this number by the total number of messages delivered by p. However, let denote the average piggyback size on all messages sent during a run R of a set of processes P , in which no process crashes.</p><p>That is, equals the total number of piggybacked RSN log entries divided by the total number of send events. We can bound as follows: If R contains s send events, r receive events, d delivery events, and f transient channel failures, then f = s ? r.</p><p>Note that the total number of RSN log entries recorded by all p 2 P is at most d. Let jPj = n. Using the PSN table optimization, each entry can be piggybacked no more than n?1+f times; thus, the total number of piggybacked RSN log entries is at most d (n ? 1 + f). Dividing by the total number of send events, we obtain d (n?1+f )=(r +f ). Since d r and f 0, this bound simplifies to n?1+f.</p><p>This bound is achieved if each p2P runs the following application:</p><p>do forever for all q2P st q6 =p send message to q for i 1 to n ? 1 receive message</p><p>The second time the do-loop iterates, each process must piggyback n ? 1 RSN log entries on every outgoing message. Assuming no channel failures, the average piggyback size will quickly approach n ? 1 as the loop repeats.</p><p>This example illustrates the worst possible environment for family-based logging. We expect that many applications will not approach the n?1 + f worst case. The practical behavior of family-based logging depends largely on two factors. First, the frequency of acknowledgements has an obvious effect. Piggyback size will decrease if acknowledgements arrive promptly. Thus, a positive acknowledgement protocol is an ideal setting for family-based logging. Negative acknowledgement protocols may delay acknowledgements and increase piggyback size compared to positive acknowledgement schemes; however, the n ? 1 + f bound applies regardless of the underlying transport protocol.</p><p>Second, the application communication pattern strongly affects the performance of family-based logging. As our example shows, family-based logging suffers when each process has a large family of active parents and children. Note that in this case the set of parents and children will tend to intersect: each process will tend to send messages to and receive messages from some common set of processes. In such an environment, a negative acknowledgement protocol should be very effective, since extra acknowledgement packets will rarely be sent. Thus, in worst-case applications, family-based logging should actually perform better using a negative acknowledgement protocol.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Observed Performance</head><p>We have built a preliminary implementation of the message logging and failure recovery protocols described in Section 4.3, with the addition of the PSN table described in Section 4.4.1. In addition, we have developed a special application to measure the performance of family-based logging under a wide variety of conditions. This section describes our current implementation and presents some empirical results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1">Experimental Setup</head><p>We implemented family-based logging and have used it on a set of four Sun workstations-two SPARC2s and two IPXs-running Sun OS 4.1.1. Communications were implemented using UDP datagram sockets, layered over IP on a 10 Mbit/sec Ethernet; we used Sun LWP to manage program concurrency. Because the family-based logging protocol needs to receive the acknowledgements from the underlying data link layer protocol, we implemented a simple data link layer using a positive acknowledgement sliding window protocol; the data link layer can send 1024-byte messages between any pair of processes at the sustained rate of 2.5 milliseconds per message.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2">Application</head><p>We designed a unique application in order to test our implementation of family-based logging. The application is controlled by a master process. Based on user input, the master determines the number of additional processes to create and the characteristics of the communication among these processes. The master then writes a script for each process and sends each script to the appropriate process. Once each process has received its script, it executes the instructions contained in the script (e.g., "send to p", "receive") while monitoring message logging statistics.</p><p>There are two important properties of this application. First, it reduces application computational overhead to near zero. Writing, sending, and receiving scripts is completed before any performance data is collected. Each application event requires only a single array access and a test of the resulting value; the rest of the measured time is devoted to interprocess communication. Thus, we measure the message logging overhead as compared to virtually pure communication cost.</p><p>Second, our single application can model a wide range of application communication patterns in a controlled and repeatable manner. In addition to specifying the number of processes and the number and size of application messages, the user can control two parameters: the blast factor and the branch factor. The blast factor determines the relative frequency of sends and receives for each process. A process in a "blasty" run typically sends many messages before receiving any, and then receives many before sending again; in a non-blasty run it usually alternates between a single send and a single receive. The branch factor determines the relative number of parents and children for each process. A process in a "branchy" run typically sends messages to and receives messages from many different processes; in a non-branchy run it communicates with a small subset of processes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3">Results</head><p>We measured message logging overhead for two distinct application scenarios. The worst-case example of Section 5.1 can be tested with a script that is both highly blasty and maximally branchy. We call this scenario blast. To test family-based logging in a different setting, we set the blast factor to its minimum value, and kept the branch factor at its maximum value; a process in such a run typically alternates between sending one message and receiving one message, and communicates with all other processes equally often. We call this scenario spray.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref> we summarize our results. Both scenarios send and receive 5000 1024-byte messages system-wide (approximately 1250 at each process). Using the Sun system clock, we measured the total run-time for three different logging settings: first with no message logging, ("No Log") then with piggybacking only ("P'back only") (that is, the send log is not updated), and finally with full message logging ("Full Log"). The piggybacking figures do not truly isolate the cost of piggybacking, but do suggest the relative cost of piggybacking for different scenarios. For example, spray spends more time piggybacking less data than blast: spray almost always has to recompute a new piggyback for each send, while blast can re-use the same piggyback for each sequence of sends. On the other hand, blast needs, on average, to piggyback more information than spray on each message ("P'back Size"). Our message logging overhead of 25% ("Log Ovhd") is comparable to performance figures of pessimistic sender-based logging <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. It should be noted, however, that the measurements for sender-based logging refer to an application in which the protocol performs especially well, in that it does not have to block or send any extra messages. The application for family-based logging, on the other hand, was chosen to accentuate the overhead of message logging.</p><p>We also tested failure recovery by crashing a single process half-way through each scenario, ("Half-run Recovery") and at the end of each scenario ("Full-run recovery"). Recovery in blast is significantly slower than in spray: blast causes complete redundancy in receive logs, giving a recovering process extra work to do, whereas spray tends to piggyback each RSN log entry to only one or two children.</p><p>Real applications may be less branchy than spray or blast: however, we expect both the recovery time and the cost of piggybacking to be highest for maximally branchy applications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusions and Further Directions</head><p>In this paper, we developed a message logging protocol that introduces no additional blocking to the application and does not create orphan states. Furthermore, the protocol is very efficient in that it only sends the application messages (possibly resent due to link failures) and their acknowledgements. Thus, our protocol does not use any more messages in a failure-free run than a message delivery protocol for a system in which transient link failures can occur but processes do not crash. The protocol may make application messages arbitrarily larger, but from our observations the average amount of overhead is small.</p><p>The major limitation of this protocol is that it can only withstand a sequence of (process crash; process recovery) pairs. For example, if process p sends messages to process q and both p and q simultaneously crash, then orphan states may be created and q may find itself trying to reconstruct a message m 2 L q for which there exists only a receive sequence number. However, we are designing a protocol that can tolerate f 1 simultaneous crashes, implements the stable log property, and has the same efficiency as the protocol presented here. This generalized protocol is similar to the Manetho protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> with the exception that in our protocol f is a parameter and in Manetho f = n. We are trying to prove this protocol correct by extending the abstract message logging protocol described in Section 4.2.</p><p>We are also examining how the message logging protocol can be further optimized by using the semantics of the application. For example, this research was first motivated by discussions with a group at IBM FSC in the AAS project <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. In this system, processes are assumed to be usually functional and can recover by simply receiving new messages. This idea can be generalized to the existence of messages that a process p can receive in any order with respect to messages from other processes without changing the sequence of messages that p subsequently sends. If such optimizations are taken into account, then the amount of logged information can be further diminished.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>e 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>RsnLog p if there exists a message m delivered by p such that m:source = e:parent, m:ssn = e:ssn, and m:rsn = e:rsn. If ve:child 6 = ? then m:rsn is logged at e:child. Receive log: ReceiveLog p is a set, initially empty, of elements of the form e = (parent, grandparent, ssn, rsn).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Family-Based Logging</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Process p sends data to process q</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Process q delivers message m</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Let l 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>SendLogp st l:ssn = ssn if (l:rsn &gt; PSNp) PSNp l:rsn for all e 2 RsnLogp st ((e:child = ?) ^(e:rsn PSNp)) e:child l:dest</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Transport protocol informs process p of ack(ssn)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Failure recovery for faulty process p</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Non-faulty process q helping faulty process p recover</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This definition is different from that of<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> in that it is defined in terms of deliver events rather than receive events. Our usage is consistent with the literature on message-logging protocols.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Another possibility is to include the state of the transport in the pro-</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Acknowledgements This work originated through discussions with Fred B. Schneider and with Jon Dehn and Burnie Witt of IBM FSC. We would like to thank Robbert Van Rennesse for his help in understanding the intricacies (and pitfalls) of Sun LWP and socket-level communication.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This material is based upon work supported by Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DoD) under NASA Ames grant number NAG 2-593, a National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship, and by grants from IBM Glendale Programming Laboratory, IBM T. J. Watson Research Center, Siemens, and Xerox Webster Research Center. y Also supported by research fellowship number 203.12.191 of the Italian National Research Council (Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonblocking and orphan-free message logging protocols</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lorenzo</forename><surname>Alvisi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bruce</forename><surname>Hoppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Keith</forename><surname>Marzullo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>TR92-1317</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-10">October 1992</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Cornell University Department of Computer Science</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A message system supporting fault tolerance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anita</forename><surname>Borg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baumbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Glazer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Symposium on Operating Systems Principles</title>
		<meeting>the Symposium on Operating Systems Principles</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM SIGOPS</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983-10">October 1983</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="99" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Primary-backup protocols: Lower bounds and optimal implementations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Navin</forename><surname>Budhiraja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Keith</forename><surname>Marzullo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fred</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sam</forename><surname>Toueg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Third IFIP Conference on Dependable Computing for Critical Applications</title>
		<meeting>the Third IFIP Conference on Dependable Computing for Critical Applications</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-09">September 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed snapshots: determining global states of distributed systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamport</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Computer Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1985-02">February 1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fault-tolerance in the Advanced Automation System</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cristian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dancey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digest of Papers: 20th IEEE International Conference on Fault-Tolerant Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990-06">June 1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Manetho: Transparent rollback-recovery with low overhead, limited rollback and fast output commit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Elnozahy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zwaenepoel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="526" to="531" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-05">May 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Distributed System Fault Tolerance Using Message Logging and Checkpointing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>COMP TR89-101</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989-12">December 1989</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Rice University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Available as report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-11">November 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Personal communication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sender-based message logging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zwaenepoel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digest of Papers: 17 Annual International Symposium on Fault-Tolerant Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987-06">June 1987</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="19" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recovery in distributed systems using optimistic message logging and checkpointing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zwaenepoel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Algorithms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="491" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time, clocks, and the ordering of events in a distributed system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leslie</forename><surname>Lamport</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="558" to="565" />
			<date type="published" when="1978-07">July 1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Publishing: A reliable broadcast communication mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Presotto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Ninth Symposium on Operating System Principles</title>
		<meeting>the Ninth Symposium on Operating System Principles</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM SIGOPS</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983-10">October 1983</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="109" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Byzantine generals in action: Implementing fail-stop processors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fred</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Computer Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-05">May 1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implementing fault-tolerant services using the state machine approach: A tutorial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fred</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computing Surveys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="319" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-09">September 1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient distributed recovery using message logging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Sistla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Welch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Eighth Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing</title>
		<meeting>the Eighth Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM SIGACT/SIGOPS</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989-08">August 1989</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="238" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimistic recovery in distributed systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Strom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yemeni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Computer Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="1985-04">April 1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volatile logging in n-fault-tolerant distributed systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Strom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bacon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yemini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Eighteenth Annual International Symposium on Fault-Tolerant Computing</title>
		<meeting>the Eighteenth Annual International Symposium on Fault-Tolerant Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="49" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
