<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Audoly</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bellu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>D'angiò</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Saccomani</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cobelli</surname></persName>
							<email>cobelli@dei.unipd.it</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Structural Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cagliari</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>09100</postCode>
									<settlement>Cagliari</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cagliari</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>09100</postCode>
									<settlement>Cagliari</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electronics and Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Uni-versity of Padova</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>35131</postCode>
									<settlement>Padova</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electronics and Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Padova</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Via Gradenigo 6A</addrLine>
									<postCode>35131</postCode>
									<settlement>Padova</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B8FA8334B3753CAC49C312DDCB726AD4</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T05:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Global Identifiability of Nonlinear Models of Biological Systems</head><p>Stefania Audoly, Giuseppina Bellu, Leontina D'Angiò, Maria Pia Saccomani, and Claudio Cobelli*, Senior Member, IEEE Abstract-A prerequisite for well-posedness of parameter estimation of biological and physiological systems is a priori global identifiability, a property which concerns uniqueness of the solution for the unknown model parameters. Assessing a priori global identifiability is particularly difficult for nonlinear dynamic models. Various approaches have been proposed in the literature but no solution exists in the general case. In this paper, we present a new algorithm for testing global identifiability of nonlinear dynamic models, based on differential algebra. The characteristic set associated to the dynamic equations is calculated in an efficient way and computer algebra techniques are used to solve the resulting set of nonlinear algebraic equations. The algorithm is capable of handling many features arising in biological system models, including zero initial conditions and time-varying parameters. Examples of usage of the algorithm for analyzing a priori global identifiability of nonlinear models of biological and physiological systems are presented. Index Terms-A priori identifiability, compartmental models, differential algebra, Gröbner basis, model identification, parameter estimation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>T HE parameters characterizing the internal behavior of bio- logical and physiological systems are usually not directly accessible to measurement. Their measurement is usually approached indirectly as a parameter estimation problem. A dynamic model describing the internal structure of the system is formulated and an input-output (I/O) experiment is designed for model identification. A well-known prerequisite for well-posedness of parameter estimation is a priori global identifiability (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> and references therein). This property guarantees that, under ideal conditions of noise-free observations and error-free model structure, the unknown parameters of the postulated model can be uniquely estimated from the designed I/O experiment.</p><p>Several results on a priori global identifiability of linear models have been published (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> for a list of references). In particular, for a class of linear dynamic models widely used in biology and medicine, i.e., compartmental models, a powerful method has been recently automated in a software tool <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> which is capable to handle rather general structures and I/O configurations.</p><p>For nonlinear models very few results have been obtained and no standard algorithm exists for testing a priori global identifiability. Various approaches have been proposed, e.g., power series, differential algebra and similarity transformation methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. In particular, Pohjanpalo <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> proposed a method based on the analysis of the power series expansion of the output which gives rise to an algebraic system constituted by an infinite number of equations; this makes the identifiability analysis difficult in general, especially when the model is nonidentifiable. Vajda <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> has proposed a method, subsequently used by Chappel and Godfrey <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, based on the state isomorphism theorem, which has been successfully applied to some specific nonlinear structures. However, this method does not seem suitable for constructing an automatic procedure and can easily fail when the dimension of the nonlinear algebraic system is large. Ollivier <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and Ljung and Glad <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> have first proposed techniques of differential algebra to study this problem, in particular they introduced the concept of characteristic set of a differential ideal. Although differential algebra methods greatly improve a priori identifiability analysis of nonlinear models, the construction of an efficient algorithm remains a difficult task. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, it has been shown that the algorithm proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> is heavily limited by the high computational complexity and that, often, it cannot be applied to nonlinear systems of order greater than two or three. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, an algorithm which integrates the strategies proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> has been developed. More recently, a new differential algebra algorithm has been developed <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> which improves the efficiency of the previous ones and enlarges their applicability domain.</p><p>In this paper, we present a new algorithm to test a priori global identifiability of nonlinear models. The algorithm is based on differential algebra, i.e., on Ritt algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, and uses Buchberger algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> to solve the resulting set of nonlinear algebraic equations. Preliminary results on a less general version of the algorithm have been presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. After briefly reviewing some fundamentals and the available methods to study a priori identifiability of nonlinear models, we describe the new algorithm and its features. Finally, examples of usage of the algorithm for analyzing a priori global identifiability of some nonlinear biological and physiological models are presented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. SYSTEM MODELS AND A PRIORI IDENTIFIABILITY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. The System-Experiment Model</head><p>Many dynamic models of biological and physiological systems together with the I/O experiment designed for their identification can be described by a general nonlinear model of the following type <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(1) (2)</formula><p>where -dimension state variable vector; -dimension input vector of differentiable functions; the -dimension output; -dimension parameter vector; vectors of polynomial or rational functions in and . Equality constraints (linear or nonlinear) on on the following form:</p><p>(3) where is a vector of polynomial functions, may be also present.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. A Priori Identifiability</head><p>Given the system-experiment model, ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">2</ref>), a priori identifiability concerns with the uniqueness of the solution for under the ideal conditions of error-free model structure and noise-free data.</p><p>To state the a priori identifiability problem one considers the output , (2), as a function of time and of the observational parameter vector <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> which is known by the experiment. Thus, each I/O experiment will provide a particular value of . Further, for systems as that of (1)-( <ref type="formula">2</ref>), all the components of are algebraic functions of the basic parameters of the model (4)</p><p>In particular <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> where is that particular value of providing .</p><p>Consider the system-experiment model described by (1)-(2). Different definitions have been given in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Here, we adopt those recently given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>For the input class and the single parameter is a priori : globally (or uniquely) identifiable if and only if, for almost any the system <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> has the only one solution ; Locally (or nonuniquely) identifiable if and only if, for almost any , the system (6) has for more than one, but a finite number of solutions; nonidentifiable if and only if, for almost any , the system (6) has for an infinite number of solutions. The model is a priori globally (or uniquely) identifiable, if all its parameters are globally (or uniquely) identifiable; locally (or nonuniquely) identifiable, if all its parameters are identifiable-either uniquely or nonuniquely-with at least one parameter nonuniquely identifiable; nonidentifiable, if at least one of its parameters is nonidentifiable.</p><p>Thus, to study a priori global identifiability of , there is the need to solve the system of nonlinear algebraic equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> where are known. We will refer to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> as the exhaustive summary <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> of the model. If some equality constraints, (3), are present, these need to be added to algebraic equations to form the exhaustive summary.</p><p>Note that the a priori identifiability is a structural property, i.e., it holds almost everywhere in .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. THE METHOD</head><p>Here, the theoretical aspects on the newly proposed algorithm for studying a priori global identifiability of nonlinear models are described.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Some Fundamentals</head><p>For a formal description of the fundamentals of differential algebra, the reader is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Here, some definitions are briefly recalled.</p><p>Let be a vector of functions: the totality of polynomials in the variables and their derivatives with coefficients on a set is a differential polynomial ring and will be denoted can be a ring itself. Consider a set of differential polynomials belonging to . The totality of polynomials that can be formed by elements in by addition, multiplication by elements in and differentiation, is a differential ideal having the elements of as generators. A differential ideal is prime if implies that or . In order to handle differentials ideals, a ranking on the variables and their derivatives must be introduced, according to a system that satisfies the following relations: <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> were and are variables and is an arbitrary derivation.</p><p>The leader of a polynomial is the highest ranking derivative of that polynomial, in particular it can be a derivative of order zero.</p><p>The polynomial is said to be of lower rank than if or . A polynomial will be said reduced with respect to a polynomial if does not contain neither the leader of with equal or greater degree nor its derivatives.</p><p>If is not reduced with respect to it can be reduced by using the psudodivision according to the following: if contains the th-derivative (it can be ) of the leader of must be derived times so its leader becomes .</p><p>Hence, is substituted by the rest of the pseudodivision between and with respect to . The set of differential polynomials will be called a chain if either and is different from zero, or and for is of higher rank than and reduced with respect to .</p><p>The chain will be said of higher rank than the chain if, either there is a exceeding neither nor , such that and are of the same rank for and is higher than , or if and and are of the same rank for . Let be a finite or an infinite set of differential polynomials. It is possible to form chains with different polynomials in . Among all chains in , there are some which have lowest rank. Any such chain will be called characteristic set of . The characteristic set of a differential ideal has been introduced by <ref type="bibr">Ritt [13]</ref> who also proposed an algorithm to construct it. The peculiarity of the characteristic set is that it summarizes all the information contained in the differential ideal into a finite number of polynomials.</p><p>With these definitions at hand, we can now return to the system-experiment model of ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">2</ref>). The set of differential polynomials is, thus (9) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> Polynomials ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) are the generators of a differential ideal in a differential ring. The state space description ensures the primality of the ideal generated by ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) and, thus, the uniqueness of the characteristic set of this ideal <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. As a result, this characteristic set is a finite set of nonlinear differential equations which allows to construct the exhaustive summary of the model itself. This allows to overcome the difficulties of handling an infinite number of equations.</p><p>The problems now are as follows: 1) to construct, in an algorithmic way, the characteristic set starting from the model equations, 2) to solve the algebraic nonlinear equations ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) of the exhaustive summary. To solve the first problem, we have observed <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> that the computation complexity is strongly influenced by the choice of the differential ring and of the ranking of the variables of the differential polynomials. This has suggested to develop the new algorithm with a particular attention to the structure of the dynamic model equations and by defining a suitable order relation. Furthermore, since our interest is in biological and physiological system models, general structures and I/O configurations need to be considered, allowing in particular for time-varying parameters and zero (i.e., nongeneric) initial conditions. Finally, it would be desirable to test different I/O configurations on the same model without having to recalculate a new characteristic set. This is particularly useful when studying qualitative experiment design <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, e.g., the minimal I/O configuration for a priori global identifiability. All these issues are separately addressed in the next sections.</p><p>We tackle now the second problem. It can be solved by a computer algebra method, e.g., the Buchberger algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>This algorithm calculates the Gröbner basis, which is a set of polynomials with specific properties which make it a powerful tool for solving systems of nonlinear equations, like those of the exhaustive summary.</p><p>To solve <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, a symbolic point has to be chosen (see Section V, Example 1). When the system dimension increases, the use of a symbolic point affects the complexity of the Gröbner basis calculation, thus severely limiting the class of testable models. In order to simplify the calculations, a numerical random point can be used. This allows to significantly enlarge the class of testable models, while retaining mathematical rigor. In fact, since a priori identifiability is a structural property, i.e., it holds almost everywhere, the numerical point strategy gives the right result with probability one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Choice of Ring</head><p>The differential ideal can be considered in different rings depending on which elements are considered as coefficients and which as variables of their differential polynomials. This is a crucial step for the construction of the characteristic set, and has strong consequences on the number and complexity of the reductions required for its calculation. For example, Ljung and Glad <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> choose as differential ring in which all the states, inputs, outputs and unknown parameters are variables. Thus, they arrive at a characteristic set which is triangular in and immediately provides the identifiability results. In contrast, Ollivier <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> chooses the characteristic set of ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) in the ring , in which the variables are the states, inputs and outputs. In this way, once the characteristic set is obtained, the coefficients are polynomials in . With this choice we obtain as many differential polynomials as the outputs are, only in the and variables, i.e., belonging to and, thus, known. These allow to extract their coefficients, that is a number of known algebraic polynomials in , to construct the exhaustive summary of the model. This strategy gives rise to a very simplified reduction procedure, since the number of variables is significantly decreased. For this reason, the ring proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> was chosen.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Ranking of Variables</head><p>Two criteria dictate the choice of the ranking: reduction of the computation complexity and extraction of the maximum information from the characteristic set. We have already noted <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> that computational complexity and, thus, computer time, not only depends on state vector dimension and nonlinearity degree, but also on the ranking chosen for the variables of polynomials.</p><p>The two principal ranks are as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(11)<label>(12)</label></formula><p>Both ranking ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">12</ref>) define the inputs as the smallest components, followed by the outputs, and the state variables.</p><p>For example, if ranking ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>) is chosen, the characteristic set of polynomials ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) has the following form: <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> We will refer to the polynomials as input/output relations (I/O relations).</p><p>With ranking <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, the characteristic set is in triangular form, thus allowing to easily extract not only information coming from the I/O relations but also from the equations containing the state variables. This is particularly useful in various situations encountered in biosystem modeling since it allows to: 1) know the identifiable parameterization corresponding to different output equations without having to recalculate the characteristic set; 2) easily extract information on parameter identifiability from known initial conditions, if any (see Appendix, point 2); 3) identify time-varying parameters with unknown functional form (see Section III-D).</p><p>If the system is of high dimension, i.e., high number of both states and parameters, and of high nonlinearity degree, the calculation of the characteristic set can become too complex (see, e.g., Example 3 in Section V). In this case, the ranking ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">12</ref>) can be adopted to decrease the computational complexity.</p><p>In summary, the choice of the rank strongly affects either the strategy of reductions, and thus the efficiency of the algorithm itself, or the type of information contained in the characteristic set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Time-Varying Parameters</head><p>Handling time-varying parameters is often important in biological and physiological modeling. A rather general case arises when their functional form is known with one or more unknown parameters. It is assumed that <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> were and is a rational function. With the above hypothesis, one can handle classical timevarying situations like <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> where are known or unknown constant parameters. The strategy is to consider as a new state variable and to consider (14) as a state equation in the model.</p><p>If the functional form is known but <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> does not hold, a general method is not available. However, it is often possible to resort to some auxiliary variable (see Appendix, point 1a) and to express the derivatives of the time-varying parameter in state equation form analogously to the previous case.</p><p>If the functional form of is unknown, the problem is more difficult. However, if more than one output is available, the following strategy can be adopted. The ranking ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>) is chosen and is considered as the new unknown state of minimum rank. In this case, the first equation of the characteristic set, after the I/O relations, exhibits only the "state" variable. To make it identifiable the two following conditions must hold: 1) all the unknown constant parameters which appear in that equation are identifiable from the I/O relations, 2) the "state" is algebraically observable <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, i.e., it appears in the characteristic set with zero order (see Appendix, point 1b).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Generic Initial Conditions</head><p>The construction of the characteristic set ignores the initial conditions which are assumed to be generic. If initial conditions are known, this information can be exploited to complete the exhaustive summary, assuming the system has some states algebraically observable <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</p><p>In the case of generic initial conditions, the following strategy can be adopted. Once the characteristic set has been calculated and its coefficients are extracted by the I/O relations to construct the exhaustive summary, the remaining differential polynomials are calculated at the initial time, thus obtaining new polynomials in the unknown parameters of the model. These are symbolic polynomials having as known constant coefficients the differential polynomials in , , and with their derivatives at time zero. The related equations are added to the previously extracted ones to form the exhaustive summary, (7) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p><p>Conversely, the above polynomials allow us to calculate possible unknown initial conditions, only if the polynomials contain only those parameters which are identifiable from the I/O relations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. Nongeneric Initial Conditions</head><p>Often, biological and physiological models exhibit nongeneric initial conditions, e.g., a model of radiotracer kinetics is characterized by . In this case, it is possible that some differential polynomials (perhaps multiplying a parameter) may vanish identically for some nongeneric initial conditions, thus making some parameters disappear from the I/O relation (see Appendix, point 3). Hence, if some initial conditions are nongeneric, it is necessary to take into account these polynomials. To do so, a procedure inspired by one developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> for a completely different purpose is adopted. Further, we assume that the system is algebraically observable <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</p><p>We remark that since and are assumed generic, only differential polynomials containing and/or its derivatives can vanish at zero time. Before extracting the coefficients, we order the I/O relations with respect to each parameter , and verify for each , whether or not its coefficient, that is a differential polynomial , vanishes identically. To do so, we enlarge the set of the ideal generators with and calculate a new characteristic set with a ranking in which and its derivatives are the smallest variables.</p><p>Two situations can occur: 1) the new characteristic set exhibits an additional equation only in , its derivatives and parameters; in this case one returns to the previous characteristic set and examines a new parameter or 2) the new polynomial reduces to zero at least one of the I/O relations.</p><p>At this point, we verify that vanishing of is consistent with the initial conditions: if so the new characteristic set is adopted and a further parameter is examined; if not we return to the previous characteristic set and examine a new parameter.</p><p>Remark: If the ideal is enlarged with a new polynomial, the new ideal needs not be prime, hence the intersection of various characteristic sets has to be considered (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>). In this case, a factorization is requested and this poses difficulties for a complete automation of the algorithm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. Inputs</head><p>If the inputs are unknown differentiable functions, they can be dealt with by simply adopting the strategy outlined at the end of Section III-D for time-varying parameters. If the inputs are nondifferentiable functions, they cannot be dealt with in a differential algebra context.</p><p>It should be noted that in biomedical experiments often the input is a short injection of a quantity of unknown or known material, e.g., a radiotracer isotope, of duration much smaller than the system slowest time constant. These inputs can be safely modeled as impulses (Dirac functions) and their effect is just to drive the system (originally at rest) to a nonzero known or unknown initial condition. Hence, input functions can be completely eliminated from the picture. Since nonlinear operations on distributions are in general not defined, this strategy cannot be applied to nonlinear systems (this aspect has often been overlooked in the literature).</p><p>To avoid difficulties which are purely formal, in the following we assume that:</p><p>1) the input is a smooth function of time lasting a time interval negligible with respect to the slowest time constant of the system; 2) the response of the system to this input is arbitrarily close for to the response corresponding to a suitable nonzero initial state at time 0 and zero input function. The last property can actually be proven to hold under mild regularity conditions of the system, which are satisfied by ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">2</ref>).</p><p>Thus, the procedure presented in Section III-E for generic initial conditions can be applied.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. THE ALGORITHM</head><p>The starting point of the algorithm is the model equations which provide the differential polynomials. These are considered in the differential ring . The principal steps of the algorithm are as follows.</p><p>i) The standard ranking (see Section III-A, ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>)) is introduced first. Subsequently, it is possible to select the most suitable ranking by a careful analysis of the system characteristics (see Section III-C); ii) The leaders of each polynomial are found; iii) The polynomials are ordered following the increasing leaders. Each polynomial is compared with the previous ones and, if it is of equal or higher rank, is reduced with respect to them. This step is repeated until the chain of minimum rank is reached. This set of polynomials is the characteristic set in the differential polynomial ring . In particular, it contains as many polynomials free of with coefficients in as the model outputs are; iv) The common coefficients, if any, not containing variables are eliminated from each polynomial; v) If some polynomial do not contain a term free of parameters, such term is generated by dividing the polynomial for a suitable coefficient; vi) The coefficients belonging to the polynomial ring are extracted. These are the observational parameters of the model, , (see Section II-B); vii) If unknown initial conditions are present, the remaining polynomials of the characteristic set are calculated for and the obtained polynomials in are added to those calculated in step vi; viii) A random numerical point from the parameter space is chosen and equations are constructed which form the exhaustive summary of the model; ix) The Buchberger algorithm is applied to solve the equations and the number of solutions for each parameter is provided. The algorithm outlined above applies in the case of generic initial conditions.</p><p>In case of nongeneric initial conditions, after steps i-v which calculate the characteristic set, we introduce the following steps: a) for each parameter and I/O relation, considered as polynomial in , we calculate the coefficients; b) let be the coefficient of of degree and the list of such coefficients, we delete from differential polynomials not containing and/or its derivatives; c) for each in we enlarge the previous ideal with itself and apply steps i-v to calculate a new characteristic set. If at least one of the I/O relations vanishes and the new polynomial is consistent with the initial conditions, then a new ideal obtained by enlarging the previous one with is considered and the procedure restarts from step i until the all elements in are considered. In this case, the ideal needs not be prime, thus, we make a factorization (see Remark at the end of Section III-F). Finally, note that if the algorithm does not successfully terminate because the computation of the characteristic set is too complex, i.e., the procedure of extraction of coefficients or the Buchberger algorithm fails, the algorithm can be reapplied by using a different ranking between the variables.</p><p>The algorithm has been implemented in Reduce 3.5 and runs on any Pentium PC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CASE STUDIES</head><p>In order to illustrate the features of the method, we discuss below a priori identifiability of a number of biological and physiological nonlinear models. All the models have been implemented on a Pentium 3 with 550 MHz and the computing time is reported.</p><p>Example 1: Consider the nonlinear model discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. It is a two compartment model which describes the kinetics of a drug in the human body. The drug is injected into the blood (compartment 1) where it exchanges linearly with the tissues (compartment 2); the drug is irreversibly removed with a nonlinear saturative characteristic from compartment 1 and with a linear one from compartment 2. The I/O experiment takes place in compartment 1. The system-experiment model is <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> where drug masses in compartment 1 and 2, respectively; drug input; measured drug output; and constant rate parameters; and classical Michaelis-Menten parameters; and input and output parameters, respectively. The intial conditions are and . Now the question is: are all the unknown parameters globally identifiable from the designed I/O experiment?</p><p>In the notation previously introduced one has</p><p>The major steps of the algorithm are as follows:</p><p>• choice of the ranking of the input, output and state variables</p><p>• at this stage the reduction procedure starts and the characteristic set is calculated</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(19) (20)<label>(21)</label></formula><p>Note that only the differential polynomial <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> contains information on model identifiability, in fact it does not contain as variables neither nor its derivatives. This polynomial represents the I/O relation of the model. • the algebraic observability of the system is checked, see Section III-D. Since derivatives of unknown states do not appear in the characteristic set, we can state that the system is algebraically observable. • coefficients are extracted and evaluated at a numerical point randomly chosen in the parameter space . Each coefficient, in its polynomial form, is then set equal to its corresponding numerical value. The obtained equations, reported below, are the exhaustive summary of the model (see Section II-B)</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(22)</formula><p>• the Buchberger algorithm is applied and the Gröbner basis is (23)</p><p>It is easy to see that the system has an infinite number of solutions, thus, the model is a priori nonidentifiable. Note that if the input is assumed to be known, i.e., , the model becomes a priori globally identifiable.</p><p>The method assumes generic initial conditions, while the model of ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) has zero, i.e., nongeneric, initial conditions. Thus, following the theory presented in Section III-F, we need to verify if the differential polynomials multiplying unknown parameters vanish consistently with the initial conditions; if yes, we will enlarge the set of original equations by adding these polynomials one at a time and recalculate a new characteristic set. For sake of space, we do not report the complete calculation but only describe the results obtained for each parameter. Coefficient of is a relation in and all the unknown parameters, hence it cannot vanish at zero time because of the genericity of and the parameters. Coefficients of , the two coefficients of and the three coefficients of , , and added one at a time to the set of original equations give a characteristic set that exhibits a relation only in and the parameters; as already pointed out these polynomials cannot vanish. We conclude that none of the coefficients of parameters in the input/output relation of the differential system are zero, hence the result provided by the above method is correct. For more detail on the procedure and more extended calculations see point 3 in Appendix.</p><p>The computation time is 54 850 ms. Note that if a symbolic point is used the computation time increases till 154 990 ms.</p><p>Remark: As observed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, a priori identifiability of this model cannot be studied with the power series expansion method <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> because of computational complexity. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, Vajda et al. have solved this identifiability problem by using the method based on the state isomorphism theorem. In this light, it is also of interest to reconsider the two compartment model of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> with nonlinearity taking place in the second compartment. By comparing the computation time of a priori identifiability analysis of this model, 38 860 ms (149 930 ms with symbolic point), with that of Example 1, one can appreciate that they are similar. This shows that the method, in contrast with the series expansion method <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, is not "sensitive" to increased model complexity.</p><p>Example 2: This example deals with a model describing the control of insulin on glucose utilization in humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. The model is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. The experiment consists of an impulse input of glucose labeled with a tracer and of the measurement in plasma of glucose, labeled glucose and insulin concentrations. The measured insulin concentration acts as model input , while the model output is the measured tracer glucose concentration. The control by insulin on the glucose system is exerted by insulin in a remote compartment . The glucose system is described by two compartments which represent, respectively, glucose in rapidly and slowly equilibrating tissues which include the muscle tissues. Insulin control is exerted on glucose utilization in compartment 3 (insulin-dependent tissues) while glucose utilization in compartment 1 refers to insulin-independent tissues.</p><p>The system-experiment model is (24) where glucose masses in compartments 1 and 2 and the concentration of insulin in a remote compartment 3, respectively; plasma insulin concentration; known plasma glucose concentration; plasma tracer glucose concentration; volume of the accessible compartment; constant component of insulin-independent glucose uptake with accounting for the proportional component; constant rate parameters. The initial conditions are , and . The question is: are the unknown parameters a priori globally identifiable from the designed experiment?</p><p>The input, output and states are ordered as follows:</p><p>(25)</p><p>The algorithm calculates the characteristic set and verifies the algebraic observability of the system. Then, a numerical random point is chosen and the related 33 coefficients are calculated. For sake of brevity, we report below only the final Gröbner basis (26)</p><p>The model is nonidentifiable.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, the following physiological constraint was used to ensure a priori identifiability: <ref type="bibr">(27)</ref> where is the known pretest glucose concentration. If we add this constraint, in the polynomial form, together with the initial condition (28) which shows that the system is now a priori globally identifiable. The same result was obtained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> but the very laborious power series expansion method <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> was employed.</p><p>The computation time is 42 570 ms.</p><p>Example 3: Consider the model discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> where all fluxes are assumed linear except some leaving compartment 3. In particular, parameters , , and are assumed to be parametrically linearly controlled by the arrival compartment, i.e., and . The model equations are as shown in (30) at the bottom of the page. The input, output and states are ordered following ranking <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>.</p><p>The unknown vector parameter is (31)</p><p>One can calculate the characteristic set. Since derivatives of the state components do not appear, one can claim that the system is algebraically observable.</p><p>A numerical random point is chosen and the Gröbner basis which reveals the a priori global identifiability of the system is calculated.</p><p>The computation time is 509 480 ms.</p><p>Example 4: The model we discuss here has been proposed to study glucose metabolism in the brain from positron emission tomography (PET) [ F]-Fluoro-Deoxy-Glucose( F-FDG) data <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. The model is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>. It is a two compartment model with two time-varying parameters which account for brain tissue heterogeneity.</p><p>The system-experiment model is (36)</p><p>The unknown parameter vector is (37) One can calculate the characteristic set. The system is algebraically observable.</p><p>We choose a numerical random point , construct the exhaustive summary of the model and calculate the Gröbner basis (38)</p><p>Because can be uniquely calculated by the last equation of the characteristic set, we obtain as . The system is globally identifiable.</p><p>The computation time is 43 310 ms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSION</head><p>A priori identifiability is a necessary prerequisite for parameter estimation of nonlinear biological and physiological system models. In this paper, the a priori global identifiability problem was first introduced and then formal definitions were given. Checking a priori global identifiability, i.e., the uniqueness of the solution, is difficult since it requires solving a system of an infinite number of nonlinear algebraic equations which is increasing in both number of terms and nonlinearity degree with increasing model order. After a brief overview of the available methods, a new algorithm for attacking a priori identifiability of nonlinear models has been presented. The algorithm automatically tests a priori identifiability of nonlinear models of general structure with a general I/O experimental configuration. It resorts to differential algebra concepts, in particular it is based on the characteristic set of the ideal generated by the polynomials defining the model, and on computer algebra methods, in particular the Buchberger algorithm. This new algorithm increases the efficiency of the previous ones and allows one to successfully deal with models characterized by time-varying parameters, generic or nongeneric initial conditions, which are features often present in biosystem modeling. The algorithm has been shown to successfully analyze a priori identifiability of several complex biological and physiological system models.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. A nonlinear two compartment model of drug kinetics in the body. The I/O experiment configuration is also shown (the large arrow denotes the input and the dashed line ending with a bullet the output).</figDesc><graphic coords="6,91.38,62.28,147.60,99.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. A nonlinear model of glucose utilization in the body and its control by insulin.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,90.42,62.28,146.40,159.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. A nonlinear four compartment model.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,63.24,62.28,203.76,201.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. A time-varying parameter model of glucose metabolism in the brain.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,337.20,62.28,181.92,88.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FDG plasma concentration which acts as known input of the model; and [ F]FDG and [ F]-Fluoro-Deoxy-Glucose-6-Phosphate concentrations in the brain tissue; output and states are ordered as follows:</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the Cagliari University Research Project. Asterisk indicates corresponding author.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head><p>A. Time-Varying Parameters 1) If the functional form of , is known, but <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> does not hold, we express the derivative of the time-varying parameter in terms of other new states by constructing a sequence that has still the form of state equations. For example we consider the sinusoidal form (A. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1)</ref> where and are known or unknown constant parameters. We put</p><p>where is the model order and add the equations <ref type="bibr">(A.3)</ref> to those of the model. 2) If the functional form of the time-varying parameter is unknown, one can also try to identify it provided one has a sufficient number of outputs. For example consider the following system-experiment model (A.4) were is the unknown parameter vector and is the initial condition vector which is assumed to be known.</p><p>We adopt ranking <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> where is considered as the state of minimum rank. The characteristic set with respect to the above ranking is (A. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5)</ref> One can see that the state is not algebraically observable (see Section III-D) while it is. Further, parameter is identifiable from the first equation of (A.5), hence can be identified from the second equation of (A.5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Known Generic Initial Conditions</head><p>Let us consider the following nonidentifiable nonlinear dynamic system: (A.6) where unknown vector; input; initial condition vector which is assumed to be unknown. The variable ranking is</p><p>The characteristic set is calculated</p><p>The numerical random point <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref> is chosen and the exhaustive summary is extracted by the characteristic set (A.9) This polynomial is not sufficient to identify parameters.</p><p>Suppose now that the initial conditions are known. We add to the exhaustive summary the polynomials obtained with the procedure described in Section III-E. In particular, we obtain the following polynomials:</p><p>where are the known values, at zero time, of , respectively. Now, the Gröbner basis of polynomials (A.9) and (A.10) is calculated</p><p>The basis shows that the system is globally identifiable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Nongeneric Initial Conditions</head><p>Let the equations of a dynamic system be the following:</p><p>where the same notation of the previous system, (A.6), is used. The characteristic set is calculated</p><p>Following Section IV we construct the list of the differential polynomials that are coefficients of parameters. From , we extract , i.e., the coefficient of order one</p><p>We add to polynomials of (A.13) and calculate a new characteristic set</p><p>Note that is a zero of the ideal generated by (A.12), in fact annihilates the I/O relation, i.e., the first equation of (A.13). Further, we verify that is consistent with the zero initial conditions, hence, we adopt the characteristic set of (A.15) and extract , i.e., the coefficient of order 1. Since , we add polynomial to the set of (A.15) and calculate a new characteristic set. This contains, as equation of minimum rank, which is not consistent with a generic input; hence, it has to be rejected. Thus, the characteristic set of the model under study, (A.12), is that of (A.15). By analyzing the equations of this set, we conclude that the model is nonidentifiable, in particular only is globally identifiable. Note that if , the third equation of (A.15) is not consistent with the initial value, hence the set of (A.15) has to be rejected. In this case, the characteristic set of (A.14) has to be reconsidered and a coefficient of a different parameter has to be examined. Dr. Cobelli is presently Chairman of the Italian Biomedical Engineering Group of the National Research Council and has been <ref type="bibr">Chairman (1990</ref><ref type="bibr">Chairman ( -1993</ref><ref type="bibr">Chairman ( &amp; 1993</ref><ref type="bibr">Chairman ( -1996) )</ref>  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global identifiability of linear compartmental models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Audoly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>D'angiò</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Saccomani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cobelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Biomed. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-01">Jan. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">System identifiability based on the power series expansion of the solution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pohjanpalo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global approaches to identifiability testing for linear and nonlinear state space models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lecourtier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Comput. Simulat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="472" to="482" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cobelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Finkelstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Mathematical Modeling of Metabolic and Endocrine Systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similarity transformation approach to identifiability analysis of nonlinear compartmental models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vajda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Godfrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rabitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural identifiability of the parameters of a nonlinear batch reactor model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chappel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Godfrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On global identifiability for arbitrary model parameterizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ljung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Glad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="276" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jacquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Compartmental Analysis in Biology and Medicine</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ann Arbor, MI</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>BioMedware</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural identifiability of models characterizing saturable binding: Comparison of pseudo-steady-state and non pseudo-steady-state models formulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chappel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Le problème de l&apos;identifiabilité structurelle globale: étude théorique, méthodes effectives et bornes de complexité</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ollivier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>École Polytéchnique</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Thèse de Doctorat en Science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural identifiability of nonlinear systems: Algorithms based on differential ideals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>D'angio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">'</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Audoly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bellu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Saccomani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cobelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SYSID&apos;94 10th IFAC Symp. System Identification</title>
		<meeting>SYSID&apos;94 10th IFAC Symp. System Identification</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global identifiability of nonlinear model parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Saccomani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Audoly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bellu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>D'angio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">'</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cobelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SYSID&apos;97 11th IFAC Symp. System Identification</title>
		<meeting>SYSID&apos;97 11th IFAC Symp. System Identification</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="224" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Differential Algebra</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ritt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1950">1950</date>
			<publisher>Amer. Math. Soc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Providence, RI</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An algorithmical criterion for the solvability of algebraic system of equation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Buchberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aequationes Mathematicae</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Numerical parameter identifiability and estimability: Integrating identifiability, estimability, and optimal sampling design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jacquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Greif</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gröbner bases and differential algebra</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Carra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ferro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">356</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin, Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Qualitative experiment design in physiological system identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Saccomani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cobelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Contr. Syst. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An algebraic approach to linear and nonlinear control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fliess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Glad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Essays on Control: Perspectives in the Theory and Its Applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, Ma</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Birkhaüser</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="267" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hepatic glucose production during the labeled IVGTT: Estimation by the convolution with a new minimal model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Caumo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cobelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">264</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>E829-E841</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Identifiability of State Space Models</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model of kinetic behavior of deoxyglucose in heterogeneous tissues in brain: A reinterpretation of the significance of parameters fitted to homogeneous tissue models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sokoloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cereb. Blood Flow Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
