<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Subband Coding of Images Using Vector Quantization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Westerink</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">7th Benelux Information Theory Symposium</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<postCode>1986</postCode>
									<settlement>Noordwijkerhout, May</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">7th Benelux Information Theory Symposium</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<postCode>1986</postCode>
									<settlement>Noordwijkerhout, May</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dick</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Boekee</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">7th Benelux Information Theory Symposium</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<postCode>1986</postCode>
									<settlement>Noordwijkerhout, May</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Information Theory Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Delft University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2600 GA</postCode>
									<settlement>Delft</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>SENIOR MEMBER, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Biemond</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">7th Benelux Information Theory Symposium</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<postCode>1986</postCode>
									<settlement>Noordwijkerhout, May</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>AND</roleName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Woods</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">7th Benelux Information Theory Symposium</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<postCode>1986</postCode>
									<settlement>Noordwijkerhout, May</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Subband Coding of Images Using Vector Quantization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">01388A210DB970F7C14DCB93034B51DF</idno>
					<note type="submission">received November 12, 1986; revised June 15, 1987.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T15:05+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Subband coding has proven to be a powerful technique for medium bandwidth source encoding of speech. Recently, some promising results have been reported on the extension of this concept to the source coding of images. In this paper, a new two-dimensional subband coding technique is presented which is also applied to images. A frequency band decomposition of the image is carried out by means of 2-D separable quadrature mirror filters, which split the image spectrum into 16 equal rate subbands. These 16 parallel subband signals are regarded as a 16-dimensional vector source and coded as such using vector quantization. In the asymptotic case of high bit rates, a theoretical analysis yields a lower bound to the gain that is attainable by choosing this approach over scalar quantization of each subband with an optimal bit allocation. It is shown that vector quantization in this scheme has several advantages over coding the subbands separately. Experimental results are given and comparisons are made between the new technique presented here and some other coding techniques. This new subband coding scheme has a performance which is comparable to other more complex coding techniques.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION INCE its introduction by</head> <ref type="bibr">Crochiere et al. [l]</ref> <p>in 1976, S subband coding (SBC) has proven to be a powerful technique for medium rate speech coding. The basic idea of SBC is to split up the frequency band of the signal and then to downsample and code each subband separately using a coder and bitrate closely matched to the statistics of that particular band. Often PCM of DPCM coders are used to code the subbands [l], [2] where the bit rate of each subband coder is determined by a bit allocation which distributes coding errors among the subbands [3]-[SI. By varying this bit assignment a noise spectrum shaping can be achieved which exploits the subjective noise perception of the human ear. This indeed is one of the advantages of subband coding. Recently, other SBC schemes for speech have been presented, in which vector quantization (VQ) is used to encode the subbands <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>- <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>.</p><p>The extension to multidimensional subband filtering was made by Vetterli [ 101, who considered the problem of splitting a multidimensional signal into subbands, but no coding results were presented in that paper. The first image coding results, together with an approximate theoretical analysis, were presented by <ref type="bibr">Woods and O'Neil [ l l ]</ref> , <ref type="bibr">[12]</ref> who used both DPCM and adaptive DPCM to encode the individual subbands. Some initial results on SBC with vector quantization were then presented by Westerink et al. [13]. SBC applied to ..................................................... video conference signals was realized by V. <ref type="bibr">Brandt [14]</ref>, using temporal DPCM with conditional replenishment.</p><p>In this paper, we present a form of SBC that makes use of VQ by exploiting the dependencies between the subbands. In this approach, we form vectors that consist of samples coming from each subband. First, Section I1 summarizes the extension of subband filters to two dimensions in the case of separable filters. The new subband coding scheme is next presented in Section 111. Further, Section IV deals with a mathematical analysis of the coding gain that can be achieved with SBC using VQ. Experimental results are given in Section V for images which are outside the training set, and a comparison is made to other coding techniques. Finally, in Section VI conclusions are drawn.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.">SUBBAND FILTERING</head><p>In the subband coding scheme presented in this paper, the image frequency band is split into 16 equally sized subbands, following <ref type="bibr">Woods and O'Neil [ I l l ,</ref><ref type="bibr">[12]</ref>. This is done hierarchically. First, the signal is partitioned into the four bands shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, using four separable 2-D digital filters. Each of these four subbands is then demodulated to baseband by a (2 x 2) downsampling. The four resulting signals are then full band at a lower sampling rate. For the 16-band system, this process is repeated by further splitting each subband into four smaller subbands. The resulting 16 subbands are full band at a sampling rate which is a factor four smaller than the original in each dimension.</p><p>After encoding, transmission and decoding the image must be reconstructed from the decoded subbands. For that purpose the subbands are upsampled by a factor (2 x 2) and suitably bandpass filtered to eliminate the aliased copies of the signal spectrum which result due to upsampling. The original signal is then reconstructed by adding each of the four upsampled and filtered subbands. For the 16-band system this process is repeated in the tree-like fashion as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p><p>When the ideal filter characteristics of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> are approximated with FIR filters, the downsampling in the splitting stage will cause aliasing errors that are not removed during reconstruction. Both in speech and in images this effect is found to be unacceptable [3], [15] and needs to be removed.</p><p>For that purpose the quadrature mirror filter (QMF) technique was introduced in 1-D subband filtering by <ref type="bibr">Esteban and Galand [16]</ref> and was later extended to the multidimensional case by Vetterli [ 101. Vetterli also shows that as a special case of the general rn-D technique it is possible to consider separable quadrature mirror filters that reduce the filter problem again to one dimension.</p><p>In the case of 1-D subband filtering, a 1-D filter pair ho(n) and h l ( n ) is chosen for splitting a signal into two subbands. Then their corresponding transfer functions are Ho(w) and H I (0) which are low-pass and high-pass, respectively. The QMF approach now consists of defining the 1-D reconstruction filters Fo( w ) and Fl ( w ) according to <ref type="bibr">[16]</ref> F &amp; J ) = 2 (l ) k H k ( W ) k=O, 1.</p><p>(1) By choosing the 1-D filters this way it follows that for perfect reconstruction the QMF pair ho(n) and h , ( n ) must satisfy <ref type="bibr">[16]</ref> ho(n)=ho(L-1-n) 0 5 n s L / 2 -1,</p><p>( 2 4</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">M I = ( -l)"ho(n) (2b)</formula><p>Unfortunately, the filter requirement in (2c) cannot be exactly met for filter lengths other than L = 2 or for L approaching infinity. However, it can be very closely approximated for modest values of L and can be obtained with the aid of an optimization procedure [ 171.</p><p>Perfect reconstruction is possible by partly leaving the QMF approach. By dropping the coefficient symmetry condition of (2a) and by choosing reconstruction filters Fk(o) that are different from those in (I), <ref type="bibr">Smith and Barnwell [18]</ref> showed that it is possible to design filters for perfect reconstruction of a 1-D input signal. Actual filter coefficients are presented in a more recent paper <ref type="bibr">[19]</ref>. By analogy with Vetterli's construction [lo], these Smith-Barnwell filters can be used to design 2-D separable filters which will result in perfect reconstruction of a 2-D input signal. <ref type="bibr">Galand and Nussbaumer [20]</ref> proposed an extension of the original method from [lt?], allowing a slight overall ripple in the reconstructed signal and present filter coefficients for 16-and 20-tap filters.</p><p>In this paper, we follow the line of work by Woods and  O'Neil [ l l ] , [12] and also allow a small ripple in the reconstructed signal (s 0.025 dB) by using 2-D separable QMF's. For the four band partitioning as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>  In our coding simulations, we used the filter coefficients of the 1-D 32-tap QMF designated as 3 2 0 in <ref type="bibr">[17]</ref>.</p><p>111. SUBBAND CODING SCHEME Subband coding of speech was partially motivated by the idea that the individual subbands could be coded more efficiently than the full band signals thus yielding an overall bit rate reduction with the same amount of distortion. The subbands are coded separately where the bit rate per subband has to be determined by some sort of bit allocation procedure, optimizing a chosen error criterion. In the most simple form, each subband is coded using a scalar quantizer (SQ) matched to the statistics of that band with a certain preassigned bit rate. More complex coding systems for speech may incorporate adaptive PCM [l], DPCM, or adaptive DPCM <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>. Both DPCM and adaptive DPCM have also been applied to images [ 1 11, [ 121. All of these subband coding schemes make use of only the within-band dependencies and a variable bit allocation possibility between the bands.</p><p>The output of the QMF bank consists of 16 signals all of which are sampled at the same rate. It is therefore natural to consider corresponding samples as vectors in a 16-dimensional space and to then encode this vector source as such using a vector quantizer. The advantages of designing the system in this fashion are several. There is no bit allocation procedure needed, while noise shaping can still be achieved by choosing a suitable distortion measure for the VQ. Furthermore, both the linear dependencies (correlations) and the nonlinear dependencies (being all other statistical dependencies [2 13) between the subbands are exploited, and as is well known, a VQ has a better sphere-packing capability than an SQ, which partitions space into multidimensional rectangular blocks. These properties can directly be derived from the various processes at work in a VQ as described by <ref type="bibr">Makhoul et al. 1211.</ref> It is also possible to incorporate the same predictive and adaptive techniques as are used in SQ schemes in this vectorbased subband coding concept, but in this paper, we will only consider the described elementary vector-SBC system to minimize coder complexity. The total subband coder system as outlined above is shown schematically in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. ASYMFTOTIC CODING GAIN</head><p>To show the importance of taking this approach, in this section we will calculate the coding gain that is obtained when applying VQ to the subband signals as described in the previous section, instead of taking a set of scalar quantizers to quantize each subband separately. The coding gain GVQ is defined as the ratio between the distortion in the case of scalar quantizers for each subband to the distortion in the case of a single vector quantizer. This quantity can be expressed as</p><p>where k is the vector dimension (in our case the number of subbands) and R is the total bit rate in bits per vector. In the case of SQ, the distortion of each subband is computed for an optimal bit assignment to each quantizer.</p><p>In 1966, Algazi 1221 derived an expression for the distortion-rate function for a probability density function (pdf) optimized scalar quantizer, denoted here by DkQ(R) (where R is in bits per sample because the vector dimension is one). However, in that paper he assumed a small distortion, or equivalently, a large bit rate R. The resulting SQ performance is therefore called asymptotic and is a function of the pdf p ( x ) and the rth power difference distortion measure d, which is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">D(X)=Ix-q(X))', r l l (<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">)</formula><p>where q ( x ) is the quantization of x. Then the asymptotic distortion-rate function is given by <ref type="bibr">[22]</ref> Experimental results [3] for some special cases for p ( x ) point out that the approximation of (7) is accurate to within a few percent for values of R = 7 bits per sample or larger. Unfortunately, no useful expressions have been found that are also applicable for lower bit rates. A similar result can be derived for VQ and therefore in the following only the asymptotic case of large values for R is considered. Taking (7) as a starting point, the problem of finding the optimal bit assignment R; for the scalar quantizer of subband i is posed as minimizing the total resulting distortion D t Q ( R ) with a certain total bit rate R. The total distortion is here defined as the mean of the subband distortions. Noise shaping, which would imply weighting of the distortions, is not considered because it has no real contribution to the actual problem. The problem can thus be formulated as As mentioned above a similar asymptotic approximation as in the scalar case is known for a vector quantizer. <ref type="bibr">Zador [23]</ref> gives an expression for the distortion-rate function of a VQ in the asymptotic case where the bit rate R is high. The kdimensional rth power difference distortion measure that is used is defined as and is consistent with the distortion measure used in the scalar case, which follows from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">6</ref>) and (Sa). The distortion-rate function is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(r+ k)/k Dk,,(R)=A(k, r)2-(r/k)R [ ) [ p ( ~) ] ~/ ( ' + ~)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>dx]</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I</head><p>The constant A ( k , r) is a function of the vector dimension k and of r and represents how well cells can be packed in kdimensional space. However, the problem is that A ( k , r) is known explicitly only for a very few cases. For values of k other than k = 1, only A(2, 2) is known exactly. Fortunately, useful upper and lower bounds are available for A( k , r) that are fairly tight <ref type="bibr">[24]</ref>. The density function p ( x ) is the kdimensional joint pdf of the vector process x. Unfortunately, very little is known of multidimensional pdfs and the possibility to measure them. Therefore, to be able to compare (1 1) to the scalar case of (9) for some specific pdfs, the vector elements (the subbands) are here assumed to be independent, yielding a pessimistic approximation of D $ Q ( R ) . Then the joint pdf p ( x ) is separable and can be written as and the VQ performance of (1 1) will simplify to</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(13)</head><p>As a result, the gain as defined in (5) can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(r+ I ) / k</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>[p;(x;)] I) dx;</head><p>[ p ; (x;)] k / ( r + k, dx;</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(r+ k)/k 1 2-' GVQ =</formula><p>Note that GVQ does not depend on the bit rate R. Again, it must be stated here that this result applies only when the number of bits assigned per subband R; are greater than zero and, in fact, large.</p><p>For three special cases, GVQ has been evaluated and the results are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref>. It can be seen that in all three cases, the gain GVQ is independent of the variances of the pdfs. This implies that a VQ implicitly establishes an optimal distribution of bits between the subbands.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>, the curves of GvQ are plotted as a function of the vector dimension k for the three cases considered in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref>. As a distortion measure the mean squared error (r = 2) is used. For A ( k , 2) the upper bounds from <ref type="bibr">[24]</ref> are taken, again to get an indication of the minimum gain GVQ that is attainable. These values for A ( k , 2) are also responsible for the nonsrnoothness of the curves. As Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> shows, even in the case of independent vector elements VQ, has a gain over SQ.</p><p>Measurements point out that the distribution of the image subbands can be approximated quite well with a Laplacian pdf which in our case of 16 subbands yields a minimum gain of  almost 4. It can reasonably by expected that the asymptotic gain will be higher because the subbands are definitely not independent and because upper bounds on A(k, 2) are used to calculate GvQ .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GAUSS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>v. SIMULATIONS AND RESULTS</head><p>Coding simulations were carried out using the subband coding system of Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. The quadrature mirror filter banks for splitting the image into 16 subbands and for reconstructing the image were implemented using the 2-D separable filters as described in Section 11. These 2-D QMF's were realized as a circular convolution by means of the 2-D fast Fourier transform (FFT). The 1-D QMF that is used to construct the 2-D QMF's is the 32-tap filter designated as 3 2 0 in [16]. This filter has a transition bandwidth of 0.043 radians and an overall passband ripple of 0.025 dB. The stopband rejection varies from 38 to 48 dB.</p><p>The vector quantizer is a full search vector quantizer based on the well-known mean squared error (MSE) distortion measure; no noise shaping is applied. The codebooks that are searched by the VQ have been generated using the LBG algorithm, due to Linde, Buzo, and Gray 1251. The algorithm uses a training set and an initial guess of the codebook to arrive iteratively at a (locally) optimal codebook. The initial guess for generating a codebook of rate R is obtained using the "splitting" technique <ref type="bibr">[25]</ref>, in which a codebook of rate R -1 is split into a double-sized codebook of rate R. Splitting is done by the addition and subtraction of a splitting vector to each vector in the codebook. By taking the centroid of the entire training set as the codebook of rate R = 0, all codebooks up to a certain desired rate can be generated by repetitive use of splitting followed by the LBG algorithm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(d</head><p>For the coding simulations, all codebooks were generated for rates R = 0 up to R = 12, using a training set consisting of five different images. All images used for the experiments are of size 256 x 256 pixels and have 8-bit gray levels. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref> shows the coding results for the "lady with hat" image ("LENA"). LENA was not included within the set of five images which was used to generate the codebooks so that Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref> shows results of coding outside the training set. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>(a) is the original 256 X 256 image with 8 bits per pixel. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5(b)</ref> shows the result of coding at 0.50 bits per pixel for which a codebook of rate R = 8 was used. Using a codebook of rate R = 10 yields the coding result as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5(c</ref>) which is at 0.63 bits per pixel. Clearly, both in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5(b</ref>) and (c), the coding degradations can be seen in the vicinity of edges and in high-frequency areas (such as the feather). These coding errors, however, appear not to be annoying to the human observer, being a very advantageous property of subband coding.  To evaluate the coder performance numerically, the signalto-noise ratio (SNR) between the original image x ( m , n) and the processed image 9 ( m , n) has been calculated where the SNR is defined as Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref> shows the SNR values of the coding simulation results for the image LENA where all codebooks up to a rate of R = 12 are used. To compare the coder performance, the performances of some other image coding techniques applied to LENA are also shown in discrete cosine transform (DCT) coding technique (f) 1271. All dashed line plots are taken from [ 151 and [26]. As can be seen the coder performance of our SBC using VQ is comparable to these other coding techniques in the bit rate region between 0.50 and 0.70 bits per pixel. The SBC using adaptive DCPM, however, still outperforms all techniques but has the highest complexity.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref> the SNR values for coding LENA at 0.63 bits per pixel are shown as a function of the number of training images. For coding inside the training set, curve a) shows a decreasing performance at increasing training set size. This is not surprising, since the codebooks then become more general. Curve b), which is for coding outside the training set, however, shows that adding images to the training set of two Finally, in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9</ref> experimental results are shown on the coding gain Gvo of SBC using VQ over SBC using SQ. As is to be expected the coding gain starts off at 1 .O for R = 0 bits per vector, since all subbands are then coded with just their mean value (being zero) by both coding methods. As the bit rate becomes larger the coding gain increases, no doubt towards an asymptotic value for high bit rates. This final value will depend on the type of image, the training set, and the set of quantizers used. The estimated value in Section IV of 4.0 in this case seems to be too optimistic for the low-bit rates subband coders are working on.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>In this paper, we have described a new subband coding scheme for images which has several advantageous properties. These follow directly from the way SBC and VQ are incorporated into the system. First, by splitting the image into subbands it is possible to include noise shaping between the subbands. However, in contrast to coding each subband separately as is usually employed, no bit allocation procedure is necessary, while noise shaping is performed by the vector quantizer once an appropriate distortion measure has been chosen.</p><p>In general, SBC has good subjective properties. Blocking effects which are quite annoying to a human observer may appear when an image is coded by using spatial VQ or by using block transform coding, such as DCT-coding. This type of distortion does not occur in the new SBC technique because the vector quantizer is designed across the subbands.</p><p>The complexity of the filtering part in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> is comparable to transform coders when pseudo-QMF's are used for splitting and reconstruction [ 101. Coder complexity, however, is relatively low, at least when the codebook that has to be searched is not too large (R s 12). Although a vector quantizer consumes much CPU time in coding simulations (especially in training), VQ is a suitable technique for hardware implementation and can therefore be very well used as a basis for more complex subband coders that incorporate predictive and adaptive techniques as well as vector quantization. An example of such an extension can be found in [28].</p><p>The choice of vectors as described in this paper is one of many possible choices. Another form of doing VQ might be by partitioning each subband into blocks and to code the subbands separately using a vector quantizer. Unfortunately, this approach will increase the coder complexity enormously. These, and other subband coding techniques are presently subject of investigation, both experimentally and theoretically.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head><p>The problem of finding an optimal bit assignment for each subband scalar quantizer is formulated in Section IV as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">1 k k subject to R = R;. (<label>16b</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">)</formula><p>i= I</p><p>This minimization problem can be solved by using Lagrange multipliers. The equation to solve using this technique is (17</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">)</formula><p>where X is a Lagrange multiplier. Setting, for convenience, (r+ 1)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>[ p ; ( ~; ) ] l ' ( ~+ l ) dx;</head><p>, ( e l ) (18) 1 and using ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) then ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) can be written as Taking the partial derivative with respect to R; yields The Lagrange multiplier is next calculated by substituting (2 1) into the constraint of the minimization problem, (16b), yielding Substituting X into (21) results in an expression for the optimal bit assignment R; to the scalar quantizer of subband i</p><p>This expression can be used to evaluate the optimal bit allocation for the scalar quantizers if the pdf's of the subbands are known. By combining ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>) with (7), (16a) and ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>) finally</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Initial four-band partitioning of the image frequency spectrum.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Hierarchical 16-band decomposition, coding, and reconstruction scheme.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Subband coding scheme.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>function of r, k, R and of the p d f s p i ( x i ) of the subbands.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Asymptotic gain G,, of VQ over SQ as a function of the vector dimension k: (a) Gaussian pdf, (b) Laplacian pdf, (c) uniform pdf.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. SBC with VQ results on the "lady with hat" image: (a) original, (b) 0.50 bits per pixel, and (c) 0.63 bits per pixel.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>number of bits for: (a) SBC + VQ outside the training set, (b) SBC + SQ, (c) SBC + adaptive DPCM, (d) spatial VQ imide the training set, (e) spatial differential VQ imide the training set, (f) adaptive DCT, and (g) SBC + DPCM.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>FigFig. 6 .Fig. 6</head><label>66</label><figDesc>Fig. 7.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig.7shows the SNR values of the coding simulation results for the image LENA where all codebooks up to a rate of R = 12 are used. To compare the coder performance, the performances of some other image coding techniques applied to LENA are also shown in Fig.7. Considered were the following four methods: subband coding using adaptive DPCM (c) [ll], [12], spatial VQ (d) and differential VQ (e) both inside a single image training set consisting ofLENA [26], and an adaptive</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Experimental coding gain G , , of SBC + VQ over SBC + SQ for (a) "FACE" and (b) "LENA."</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>rewriting, gives an expression for R; in terms of X cui@, r)(r In 2)2-' R;=-log2 r Xk(r+l)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE I ASYMPTOTIC LOWER BOUND TO THE GAIN OF VQ OVER SQ OF EACH SUBBAND FOR THREE pdf S</head><label>I</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>the desired distortion-rate function D &amp; ( R ) is obtained 1281</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="bibr">, Cambridge, MA, in 1965</ref><ref type="bibr">, 1967</ref><ref type="bibr">, and 1970, respectively.</ref> <p>Since 1976 he has been with the ECSE Department at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, NY, where he is currently Professor. He has authored or coauthored over 40 papers on estimation, signal processing, and coding of images and other multidimensional data. He has coauthored one text in the area of probability, random processes, and estimation. During the academic year <ref type="bibr">1985-1986, he</ref>  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital coding of speech in sub-bands</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Crochiere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Webber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Flanagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bel/ Syst. Tech. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1085" />
			<date type="published" when="1976-10">Oct. 1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital signal processor: Sub-band coding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Crochiere</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bel/ Syst. Tech. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1633" to="1653" />
			<date type="published" when="1981-09">Sept. 1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jayant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Noll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Digital Coding of Waveforms</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Considerations on quantization and dynamic bitallocation in sub-band coders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ramstadt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ZCASSP &apos;86</title>
		<meeting>ZCASSP &apos;86<address><addrLine>Tokyo, Japan, A. Segall</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976-03">Mar. 1976</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="169" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Bit allocation and encoding for vector sources</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fully vector quantized subband coding with adaptive codebook allocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gersho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ramstadt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Versvik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICASSP</title>
		<meeting>ICASSP<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984-03-10">Mar. 1984, paper 10.7</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vector quantizers for sub-band coded waveforms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Abut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Luse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICASSP</title>
		<meeting>ICASSP<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>paper 10</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sub-band coding with vector quantization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Versvik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Guren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICASSP</title>
		<meeting>ICASSP<address><addrLine>Tokyo, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3099" to="3102" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low rate speech coding using vector quantization and sub-band coding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Abut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ergezinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICASSP</title>
		<meeting>ICASSP<address><addrLine>Tokyo, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="452" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-dimensional sub-band coding: Some theory and algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vetterli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sig. Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-04">Apr. 1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sub-band coding of images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Woods</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>O'neil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICASSP</title>
		<meeting>ICASSP<address><addrLine>Tokyo, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986-04">Apr. 1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sub-band coding of images using vector quantization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Westerink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Woods</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Boekee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">th Benelux Inform. Theory Symp</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Noordwijkerhout, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986-10">Oct. 1986. 1986</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1278" to="1288" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sub-band coding of images</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sub-band coding of videoconference signals using quadrature mirror filters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Brandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IASTED Conf. Appl. Signal Processing Dig. Filtering</title>
		<meeting>IASTED Conf. Appl. Signal essing Dig. Filtering<address><addrLine>Pans, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985-06">June 1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sub-band coding of images with adaptive bit allocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>O'neil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ECSE Dep., R.P.I</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985-04">Apr. 1985</date>
			<pubPlace>Troy, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">M.S. thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Applications of quadrature mirror filters to split band voice coding systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Esteban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Galand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ZCASSP</title>
		<meeting>ZCASSP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977-05">May 1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A filter family designed for use in quadrature mirror filter banks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ZCASSP</title>
		<meeting>ZCASSP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980-04">Apr. 1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="294" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A procedure for designing exact reconstruction filter banks for tree structured subband coders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J T</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Barnwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Iii</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICASSP</title>
		<meeting>ICASSP<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="28" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exact reconstruction techniques for tree structured subband coders</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Acoust., Speech, Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">434441</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986-06">June 1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quadrature mirror filters with perfect reconstruction and reduced computational complexity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Galand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nussbaumer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICASSP</title>
		<meeting>ICASSP<address><addrLine>Tampa, FL</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985-04">Apr. 1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="525" to="528" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vector quantization in speech coding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Makhoul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Roucos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1551" to="1588" />
			<date type="published" when="1985-11">Nov. 1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Useful approximations to optimum quantization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Algazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic quantization error of continuous signals and the quantization dimension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zador</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ZEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="149" />
			<date type="published" when="1982-03">Mar. 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A lower bound on the average error of vector quantizers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Conway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Sloane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>It-Y. Linde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Buzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ZEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="1980-01">Jan. 1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>IEEE Trans. Commun.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image compression using non-adaptive spatial vector quantization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 16th Asimolar Conf</title>
		<meeting>16th Asimolar Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982-11">Nov. 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive coding of monochrome and color images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="1977-11">Nov. 1977. 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
