<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Error Exponents, and Code Constructions</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2007-12-25">25 Dec 2007</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Student Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Ying</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<email>yingw@qualcomm.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Pierre</forename><surname>Moulin</surname></persName>
							<email>moulin@ifp.uiuc.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Perfectly Secure Steganography: Capacity</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and is now with Qualcomm Flarion Technologies</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>08807</postCode>
									<settlement>Bridgewater</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Coordinate Science Lab and Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Beckman Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>61801</postCode>
									<settlement>Urbana</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Error Exponents, and Code Constructions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2007-12-25">25 Dec 2007</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">24E38FDFAEC5D5383FA5C9869C08C5AF</idno>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:cs/0702161v3[cs.IT]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T13:14+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Steganography</term>
					<term>watermarking</term>
					<term>secret communication</term>
					<term>timing channels</term>
					<term>capacity</term>
					<term>reliability function</term>
					<term>error exponents</term>
					<term>binning codes</term>
					<term>randomized codes</term>
					<term>universal codes</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>An analysis of steganographic systems subject to the following perfect undetectability condition is presented in this paper. Following embedding of the message into the covertext, the resulting stegotext is required to have exactly the same probability distribution as the covertext. Then no statistical test can reliably detect the presence of the hidden message. We refer to such steganographic schemes as perfectly secure. A few such schemes have been proposed in recent literature, but they have vanishing rate. We prove that communication performance can potentially be vastly improved; specifically, our basic setup assumes independently and identically distributed (i.i.d.) covertext, and we construct perfectly secure steganographic codes from public watermarking codes using binning methods and randomized permutations of the code. The permutation is a secret key shared between encoder and decoder. We derive (positive) capacity and random-coding exponents for perfectly-secure steganographic systems. The error exponents provide estimates of the code length required to achieve a target low error probability.</p><p>In some applications, steganographic communication may be disrupted by an active warden, modelled here by a compound discrete memoryless channel. The transmitter and warden are subject to distortion constraints. We address the potential loss in communication performance due to the perfect-security requirement. This loss is the same as the loss obtained under a weaker order-1 steganographic requirement that would just require matching of first-order marginals of the covertext and stegotext distributions. Furthermore, no loss occurs if the covertext distribution is uniform and the distortion metric is cyclically symmetric; steganographic capacity is then achieved by randomized linear codes. Our framework may also be useful for developing computationally secure steganographic systems that have near-optimal communication performance.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Information embedding refers to the embedding of data within a cover object (also referred to as covertext) such as image, video, audio, graphics, text, or packet transmission times <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Applications include copyright protection, database annotation, transaction tracking, traitor tracing, timing channels, and multiuser communications.</p><p>These applications often impose the requirement that embedding only slightly perturbs the covertext. The name watermarking has been widely used to describe information embedding techniques that are perceptually transparent, i.e., the marked object (after embedding) is perceptually similar to the cover object.</p><p>In some applications, the presence of the embedded information should be kept secret (see applications below).</p><p>Then perceptual transparency is not sufficient, because statistical analysis could reveal the presence of hidden information. The problem of embedding information that is hard to detect is called steganography, and the marked object is called stegotext <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Steganography differs from cryptography in that the presence of the message needs to remain secret, rather than the value of the message. The dual problem to steganography is steganalysis, that is, detection of hidden information within a stegotext.</p><p>A classical model for steganography is Simmons' prisoner problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Alice and Bob are locked up in different cells but are allowed to communicate under the vigilant eye of Willie, the prison warden. If Willie detects the presence of hidden information in the transmitted data, he terminates their communication and subjects them to a punishment. Willie is a passive warden if he merely observes and analyzes the transmitted data. He is an active warden if he introduces noise to make Alice and Bob's task more difficult.</p><p>In the information age, there are several application scenarios for steganography.</p><p>1) Steganography may be used to communicate over public networks such as the Internet. One may embed bits into inconspicuous files that are routinely sent over such networks: images, video, audio files, etc. Users of such technology may include intelligence and military personnel, people that are subject to censorship, and more generally, people who have a need for privacy.</p><p>2) Steganography may also be used to communicate over private networks. For instance, confidential documents within a commercial or governmental organization could be marked with identifiers that are hard to detect.</p><p>The purpose is to trace unauthorized use of a document to a particular person who received a copy of this document. The recipient of the marked documents should not be aware of the presence of these identifiers.</p><p>3) Timing channels can be used to leak out information about computers. A pirate could modify the timing of packets sent by the computer, encoding data that reside on that computer. The pirate wishes to make this information leakage undetectable to avoid arousing suspicion. To disrupt potential information leakage, the network could jam packet timings -hence the network plays the role of an active warden.</p><p>The channel over which the stegotext is transmitted could be noiseless or noisy, corresponding to the case of a passive and an active warden, respectively. Moreover, the steganographer's ability to choose the covertext is often limited if not altogether nonexistent. In the private-network application above, the covertext is generated by a content provider, not by the steganographer (i.e., the authority responsible for document security). Similarly in the timing-channel application, the covertext is generated by the computer, not by the pirate.</p><p>In view of these applications, the four basic attributes of a steganographic code are: 1) detectability: quantifying Willie's ability to detect the presence of hidden information;</p><p>2) transparency (fidelity): closeness of covertext and stegotext under an appropriate distortion (fidelity) metric;</p><p>3) payload: the number of bits embedded in the covertext; and 4) robustness: quantifying decoding reliability in presence of channel noise (i.e., when Willie is an active warden).</p><p>If Alice had complete freedom for choosing the covertext, the transparency requirement would be immaterial. A covertext would not even be needed: it would suffice for Alice to generate objects that follow a prescribed covertext distribution. This model has two shortcomings: (a) as mentioned above, in some applications Alice has little or no control over the choice of the covertext; (b) even if she has, covertexts have complicated distributions, and generating a size-M steganographic code by sampling the covertext distribution would be highly impractical for large M .</p><p>Information theory is a natural framework for studying steganography and steganalysis. Assuming a statistical model is available for covertexts, the only truly secure strategy from the steganographer's point of view is to ensure that the probability distributions of the covertext and stegotext are identical. This strong notion of security was proposed by Cachin <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and is the steganographic counterpart of Shannon's notion of perfect security in cryptography. We refer to steganography that satisfies this strong property as perfectly secure.</p><p>If Alice is allowed to select the covertext and Willie is passive, Alice may use the following perfectly secure steganographic code <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Alice and Bob agree on a hash function, and the value of the hashed stegotext is the message to be transmitted. Alice searches a database of covertexts until she finds one that matches the desired hash value. This approach is perfectly secure irrespective of the distribution of the covertext. The disadvantages are that the search is computationally infeasible for large message sets (communication rate is extremely low), and the underlying communication model is limited, as discussed above.</p><p>Cachin also proposed two less stringent requirements for steganographic codes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. One is ǫ-secure steganographic codes, where the Kullback-Leibler divergence between the covertext and stegotext probability distributions is smaller than ǫ (perfect security requires ǫ = 0). For random processes he redefined perfectly secure steganography by requiring that the above Kullback-Leibler divergence, normalized by the length N of the covertext sequence, tends to zero as N → ∞. Unfortunately this does not preclude the possibility that Kullback-Leibler divergence remains bounded away from zero, even grows to infinity (at a rate slower than N ) as N → ∞. If such is the case, Willie's error probability tends to zero asymptotically, and therefore the perfect-security terminology is misleading.</p><p>While Cachin focused on security and not on communication performance in terms of payload, robustness and fidelity, Kullback-Leibler divergence has become a popular metric for assessing the security of practical steganographic schemes subject to transparency, payload, and robustness requirements <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. Other metrics are studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</p><p>The tradeoffs between detectability, fidelity, payload, and robustness can be studied in an information-theoretic framework. The basic mathematical model for steganography is communications with side information at the encoder <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. Moulin and O'Sullivan studied a general information-theoretic framework for information hiding and indicated its applicability to steganography [27, Section VII.C]. However, they did not study perfectly secure steganography and did not derive expressions for steganographic capacity. Galand and Kabatiansky <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> constructed steganographic binary codes, but the code rate vanishes as log N N . Fridrich et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> proposed positive-rate "wet paper" codes, which permit a change from the original cover distribution to a new stegodistribution. However they did not analyze the fundamental tradeoffs between payload, robustness, and detectability.</p><p>The goal of this paper is therefore to study the information-theoretic limits of perfectly undetectable steganography.</p><p>As a first step towards this problem, we assume that covertext samples are independently and identically distributed (i.i.d.) over a finite alphabet. In practice the i.i.d. model could be applied to transform coefficients or to blocks of coefficients. While this is just a simplifying approximation to actual statistics, it allows us to derive tangible mathematical results and to understand the effects of the perfect security constraint on transparency, payload, and robustness. Our first result is a connection between public watermarking codes <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> and perfectly secure steganographic codes. Given any public watermarking code that preserves the first-order statistics of the covertext (this property will be referred to as order-1 security), we show that a perfectly secure steganographic code with the same error probability can be constructed using randomization over the set of all permutations of {1, 2, • • • , N }. We use this construction to derive capacity and random-coding exponent formulas for perfectly secure steganography.</p><p>The codes that achieve capacity and random-coding exponents are stacked-binning schemes as proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> for general problems of channel coding with side information. The random-coding exponent yields an asymptotic upper bound on achievable error probability and therefore serves as an estimate of the code length required to achieve a target low error probability. A stacked-binning code consists of a stack of variable-size codeword arrays indexed by the type of the covertext sequence, and the corresponding decoder is a maximum penalized mutual information (MPMI) decoder. The analysis is based on the method of types <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>.</p><p>Due to the added perfect-security constraint, capacity and random-coding exponent for steganography cannot exceed those of the corresponding public watermarking problem. Nevertheless, we have identified a class of problems where the covertext probability mass function (PMF) is uniform and the distortion function is symmetric, with the property that the perfect undetectability constraint does not cause any capacity loss. One special example in the general class is the case of Bernoulli( <ref type="formula">1</ref>2 ) covertexts with the Hamming distortion metric <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. For the binary-Hamming case, the perfect security condition has no effect on both the capacity and random-coding error exponent.</p><p>Steganographic capacity is achieved by randomized nested linear codes. This paper is organized as follows. Section II describes the notation, and Section III the problem statement.</p><p>Section IV shows how perfectly secure steganographic codes can be constructed from codes with the much weaker order-1 security. Section V presents our main theorems on capacity and random-coding error exponent. Section VI discusses the role of secret keys in steganographic codes. Simplified results for the no-attack case are stated in Section VII. A class of steganography problems for which perfect security comes at no cost is studied in Section VIII.</p><p>As an example of this class, the binary-Hamming problem is studied in Section IX. The paper concludes with a discussion in Section X.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. NOTATION</head><p>We use uppercase letters for random variables, lowercase letters for their individual values, and boldface letters for sequences. The PMF of a random variable X ∈ X is denoted by p X = {p X (x), x ∈ X }. The entropy of a random variable X is denoted by H(X), and the mutual information between two random variables X and Y is denoted by I(X; Y ) = H(X) -H(X|Y ). Should the dependency on the underlying PMFs be explicit, we use the PMFs as subscripts, e.g., H pX (X) and I pX ,p Y |X (X; Y ). The Kullback-Leibler divergence between two PMFs p and q is denoted by D(p||q); the conditional Kullback-Leibler divergence of p Y |X and q Y |X given p X is denoted by</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">D(p Y |X ||q Y |X |p X ) = D(p Y |X p X ||q Y |X p X ).</formula><p>Let p x denote the empirical PMF on X induced by a sequence x ∈ X N . Then p x is called the type of x. The type class T x associated with p x is the set of all sequences of type p x . Likewise, we define the joint type p xy of a pair of sequences (x, y) ∈ X N × Y N and the type class T xy associated with p xy . The conditional type p y|x of a pair of sequences (x, y) is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">pxy (x,y) px(x)</formula><p>for all x ∈ X such that p x (x) &gt; 0. The conditional type class T y|x given x is the set of all sequences ỹ such that (x, ỹ) ∈ T xy . We denote by H(x) the empirical entropy for</p><p>x, i.e., the entropy of the empirical PMF p x . Similarly, we denote by I(x; y) the empirical mutual information for the joint PMF p xy . The above notation for types is adopted from Csiszár and Körner <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>.</p><p>We let U(Ω) denote the uniform PMF over a finite set Ω. We let P X and P N X represent the set of all PMFs and all empirical PMFs, respectively, on the alphabet X . Likewise, P Y |X and P N Y |X denote the set of all conditional PMFs and all empirical conditional PMFs on the alphabet Y. We use E to denote mathematical expectation. N log aN bN ≥ 0, respectively. We define |t| + max(t, 0), exp 2 (t) 2 t , and the binary entropy function</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">h(t) -t log t -(1 -t) log(1 -t), t ∈ [0, 1].</formula><p>We use ln x to denote the natural logarithm of x, and the logarithm log x is in base 2 if not specified otherwise.</p><p>The notation 1 {A} is the indicator function of the event A: to transmit the message M to the decoder reliably. The covertext and stegotext are required to be close according to some distortion metric. The distortion model is motivated by the fact that stegotext and covertext represent physical signals (such as images, text, etc.) which can be modified to some extent without affecting perceptual quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">1 {A} =    1 A is true; 0 else.</formula><p>The strength of the transparency constraint is controlled by a distortion parameter.</p><p>A steganalyzer observes X and tests whether X is drawn i.i.d. from p S . If not, Willie, the steganalyzer terminates the transmission, and obviously the decoder is unable to retrieve M . If X is deemed innocuous, Willy may simply forward it to the decoder. In this case, Willie is a passive warden. To be on the safe side for preventing reliable transmission of hidden messages, Willie may want to pass X through some attack channel p Y|X (y|x), thereby producing a corrupted text Y. In this case, Willie is an active warden, and the corrupted text and the stegotext are also required to be close according to some distortion metric. The alphabets S, X and Y for S, X and Y , respectively, are assumed to be identical.</p><p>The decoder does not know p Y|X selected by the steganalyzer and does not have access to the original covertext S. The decoder produces an estimate M = φ N (Y) ∈ M of the transmitted message. We assume that the encoder/decoder pair (f N , φ N ) is randomized, i.e., the choice of (f N , φ N ) is a function of a random variable known only to the encoder and decoder but not to the steganalyzer. We can think of this random variable as a secret key as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. Note that in generic information-hiding games, this secret key provides some protection against adversaries with arbitrary memory and unlimited computational resources [4, Section X]. In steganography, the secret key plays a fundamental role in ensuring perfect undetectability: the covertext and the stegotext have the same PMF when the secret key is carefully designed. The randomized code will be denoted by (F N , Φ N ) with a joint distribution p(f N , φ N ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Steganographic Codes</head><formula xml:id="formula_4">A distortion function is any nonnegative function d : S × S → R + ∪ {0}. This definition is extended to length-N vectors using d N (s, x) = 1 N N i=1 d(s i , x i ). Let D max = max s,x d(s, x).</formula><p>We assume without loss of generality that d(s, x) ≥ 0, with equality if s = x. Definition 1: A length-N perfectly secure steganographic code with maximum distortion D 1 is a triple (M, F N , Φ N ), where • M is the message set of cardinality |M|;</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">• (F N , Φ N ) has a joint distribution p(f N , φ N ); • f N : S N × M → S N maps covertext s and message m to stegotext x = f N (s, m). The mapping is subject to the maximum distortion constraint d N (s, f N (s, m)) ≤ D 1 almost surely (1)</formula><p>and the perfect undetectability constraint</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">p X = p S ;<label>(2)</label></formula><p>• φ N : S N → M maps the received sequence y to a decoded message m = φ N (y).</p><p>The above definition is similar to the definitions for a length-N data-embedding or watermarking code in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, with the additional steganographic constraint of (2) which requires perfect matching of N -dimensional distributions. Also observe that the distortion constraint is inactive if D 1 ≥ D max , i.e., the covertext S available to Alice plays no role. Given p S , define the set of conditional PMFs p X|S such that the marginals of p S p X|S are equal (p X = p S ) and the expected distortion between S and X does not exceed D 1 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">Q Steg 1 (p S , D 1 ) p X|S : s,x p X|S (x|s) p S (s) d(s, x) ≤ D 1 , p X (x) = s p X|S (x|s) p S (s) = p S (x), ∀x ∈ S .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Also recall that in Def. 1, randomization of (F N , Φ N ) is realized via a cryptographic key shared by encoder and decoder.</p><p>Next, we define CCC and RM codes which will be used to construct perfectly secure steganographic codes.</p><p>Definition 2: (CCC Code). A length-N code with conditionally constant composition, order-1 steganographic property, and maximum distortion D 1 is a quadruple (M, Λ, F N , Φ N ), where Λ is a mapping from</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">P [N ] S to P [N ] X|S . The transmitted sequence x = f N (s, m) has conditional type p x|s = Λ(p s ). Moreover, Λ(p s ) ∈ Q Steg 1 (p s , D 1 ).</formula><p>Observe that such a code matches the first-order empirical marginal PMF of the covertext, but not necessarily higher-order empirical marginals. Hence such a code generally does not satisfy the perfect-undetectability property.</p><p>Definition 3: (RM Code). A length-N randomly modulated code is the randomized code defined via permutations of a prototype (f N , φ N ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">x = f π N (s, m) π -1 f N (πs, m)<label>(4)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">φ π N (y) φ N (πy),<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where π is drawn uniformly from the set Π of all N ! permutations and is not revealed to Willie. The sequence πx is obtained by applying π to the elements of x.</p><p>Definition 4: Given alphabets S and U, a steganographic channel p XU|S (x, u|s) subject to distortion D 1 is a conditional PMF whose conditional marginal p X|S belongs to</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">Q Steg 1 (p S , D 1 ) of (3). We denote by Q Steg (L, p S , D 1 )</formula><p>the set of steganographic channels subject to distortion D 1 when the alphabet U has cardinality L.</p><p>If the channel p XU|S satisfies the distortion constraint D 1 but not necessarily the steganographic constraint p X = p S , p XU|S is simply a covert channel in the sense of <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. We shall denote by Q(L, p S , D 1 ) the set of all such covert channels. Clearly, Q Steg (L, p S , D 1 ) ⊆ Q(L, p S , D 1 ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Attack Channels</head><p>A passive warden simply produces Y = X. An active warden passes X through a discrete memoryless channel (DMC), producing a degraded sequence Y.</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">Definition 5: A discrete memoryless attack channel p Y |X is feasible if the expected distortion between X and Y is at most D 2 : x,y p X (x) p Y |X (y|x) d(x, y) ≤ D 2 . (<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">)</formula><p>Then the joint conditional PMF is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">p Y|X (y|x) = N i=1 p Y |X (y i |x i ).</formula><p>We denote by</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">A(p X , D 2 ) = p Y |X ∈ P Y |X : x,y p X (x) p Y |X (y|x) d(x, y) ≤ D 2</formula><p>the set of all such feasible DMCs. This set is a compound DMC family.</p><p>As an alternative to Def. 5, one may consider attack channels that have arbitrary memory but are subject to an almost sure distortion constraint <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. In this case, the set of feasible attack channels is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">A ′ (p x , D 2 ) = p Y|X ∈ P N Y |X : P r d N (y, x) ≤ D 2 = 1 .</formula><p>There are three reasons why only memoryless channels are considered in this paper. First, it is shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> that for watermarking problems, both DMCs with expected distortion and arbitrary memory attack channels with almost sure distortion result in the same capacity formula, and the former allows a smaller random-coding error exponent when D 2 is the same. Thus, in terms of minimizing the random-coding exponent, selecting p Y |X from the compound DMC class A(p X , D 2 ) is a better strategy for the warden than selecting</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">p Y|X from A ′ (p x , D 2 ).</formula><p>Second, the assumption of memorylessness simplifies the presentation of main ideas. Finally, note that the proofs for the compound DMC provide the basis for the proofs in the case of channels with arbitrary memory <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Steganographic Capacity and Reliability Function</head><p>The probability of error for a randomized code (F N , Φ N ) under a channel p Y |X is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">P e,N (F N , Φ N , p Y |X ) = P r( M = M ),<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where the average is over all possible covertexts S, messages M , and codes (F N , Φ N ).</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">Definition 6: A rate R is achievable if there exists a randomized code (F N , Φ N ) such that |M| ≥ 2 N R and sup p Y |X P e,N (F N , Φ N , p Y |X ) → 0 as N → ∞. (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">)</formula><p>Definition 7: The steganographic capacity C Steg (D 1 , D 2 ) is the supremum of all achievable rates.</p><p>Definition 8: The steganographic reliability function E Steg (R) is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">E Steg (R) = lim inf N →∞ - 1 N log inf FN ,ΦN sup p Y |X P e,N (F N , Φ N , p Y |X ) .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>IV. FROM ORDER-1 TO PERFECTLY SECURE STEGANOGRAPHIC CODES Codes with conditionally constant composition (Def. 2) and randomly modulated codes (Def. 3) play a central role in our code constructions and coding theorems. The following proposition suggests a general construction for perfectly secure steganographic codes: first select some deterministic prototype f N with the CCC and order-1 steganographic properties and maximum distortion D 1 (Def. 2), second construct a RM code from that prototype.</p><p>In Section V we show that this strategy is an optimal one. The proof of the proposition appears in the appendix.</p><p>Proposition 1: Let (M, F N , Φ N ) be a RM code whose prototype (f N , φ N ) has conditionally constant composition, order-1 security, and maximum distortion D 1 . Then (M, F N , Φ N ) is a perfectly secure steganographic code with maximum distortion D 1 and same error probability as the prototype (f N , φ N ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. STEGANOGRAPHIC CAPACITY AND RANDOM CODING ERROR EXPONENT</head><p>The steganographic codes in our achievability proofs are randomly-modulated binning codes with conditionally constant composition. The existence of a good deterministic prototype is established using a random coding argument. An arbitrarily large integer L is selected, defining an alphabet U = {1, 2, • • • , L} for the auxiliary random variable U in the binning construction. Given the covertext s and the message m, the encoder selects an appropriate sequence u in the binning code and then generates the stegotext randomly according to the uniform distribution over an optimized type class T x|u,s . Proofs of the theorem and propositions in this section appear in Appendices II-VI.</p><p>The following difference between two mutual informations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |XUS ) I(U ; Y ) -I(U ; S)<label>(10)</label></formula><p>plays a fundamental role in the analysis.</p><p>Theorem 1: Under Def. 1 for steganographic codes and Def. 5 for the compound attack channel, steganographic capacity is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">C Steg (D 1 , D 2 ) = lim L→∞ C Steg L (D 1 , D 2 ),<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">C Steg L (D 1 , D 2 ) max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X )<label>(12)</label></formula><p>and (U, S) → X → Y forms a Markov chain.</p><p>The proof of Theorem 1 is given in two parts. The converse part is proved in Appendix II. The direct part is a corollary of a stronger result stated in Proposition 2 below, which provides a lower bound on the achievable error exponent (hence an upper bound on the average probability of error) and is proved in Appendix III.</p><p>Proposition 2: Under Def. 1 for steganographic codes and Def. 5 for the compound attack channel, the following random-coding error exponent is achievable:</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">E Steg r (R) = lim L→∞ E Steg r,L (R),<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">E Steg r,L (R) min pS ∈PS max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L, pS,D1) min pY |XU S ∈P Y |XU S min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2)<label>(14)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">D(p S p XU|S pY |XUS ||p S p XU|S p Y |X ) + J L (p S , p XU|S , pY |XUS ) -R + .</formula><p>Moreover,</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">E Steg r (R) = 0 if and only if R ≥ C Steg .</formula><p>Remark 1: The capacity and error exponent formulas in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">11</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">14</ref>) coincide with those for public watermarking <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, the only difference being that here the maximization over p XU|S is subject to a steganographic constraint. Clearly</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">E Steg r,L (R) ≤ E P ubW M r,L (R) and C Steg ≤ C P ubW M .</formula><p>Remark 2: Proposition 2 is proved using a random binning technique. First we establish the existence of a deterministic prototype CCC code with order-1 steganographic property, maximum distortion D 1 , and error exponent</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">E Steg (R).</formula><p>The decoder is an MPMI decoder. The main steps in this part of the proof are similar to those in the proof of Theorem 3.2 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, with the additional order-1 steganographic constraint on the encoder. The second part of the proof is an application of Proposition 1: random modulation of the CCC prototype code yields a perfectly-secure steganographic code with maximum distortion D 1 and error exponent E Steg (R).</p><p>Remark 3. As mentioned earlier, the covertext plays no role in the special case D 1 ≥ D max , and so Alice can generate X independently of S. The capacity formula <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> becomes simply</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">C Steg = min p Y |S ∈A(pS ,D2) I(S; Y ),</formula><p>and the random-coding exponent is</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">E Steg r (R) = min pS min pY |S ∈P Y |S min p Y |S ∈A(pS ,D2) D(p Y |S pS p Y |S p S ) + |I pS pY |S (S; Y ) -R| + .</formula><p>The binning codes are degenerate in this case; the expressions for capacity and random-coding exponents reduce to classical formulas for compound DMCs without side information <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> and are achieved using constant-composition codes. Further specializing this result to the case of a passive warden (D 2 = 0, hence p Y |X = 1 {Y =X} ), we obtain The operation of the deterministic prototype code is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The codebook C consists of a stack of codeword arrays indexed by the possible covertext sequence types. Given an input s, the encoder evaluates its type p s and selects the corresponding codeword array </p><formula xml:id="formula_33">C Steg = H(S)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">C(p s ) = {u(l, m, p s ), 1 ≤ l ≤ 2 N ρ(ps) , 1 ≤ m ≤ |M|},<label>(15)</label></formula><p>By letting ρ(p s ) = I(u; s) + ǫ, where T us T * US (p s ) is an optimized joint type and ǫ is an arbitrarily small positive number, an optimal balance between the probability of encoding error and the probability of decoding error is achieved. The former vanishes double-exponentially while the latter vanishes at a rate given by the random coding error exponent in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>. The above MPMI decoder can be thought of as an empirical generalized maximum a posterior (MAP) decoder [33, Section 3.1].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. SECRET KEY</head><p>In standard information-hiding problems with a compound DMC attack channel, deterministic codes are enough to achieve capacity; random coding is used as a method of proof to establish the existence of a deterministic code without actually specifying the code <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. In our steganography problem, a randomized code is used to satisfy the perfect-undetectability condition of (2). Without the secret key, a deterministic code generally could not satisfy the perfect-undetectability condition. Also note that a randomized code is generally needed if the attacks have arbitrary memory <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. For example, in watermarking games, knowing a deterministic code the adversary would decode and remove the message; deterministic codes are vulnerable to this kind of "surgical attack" <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p><p>For randomized codes, the secret key shared between encoder and decoder is the source of common randomness.</p><p>For RM codes, the secret key specifies the value of the permutation π. The entropy rate of the secret key is</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">H RM K = 1 N log 2 N ! &lt; log 2 N.<label>(17)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. PASSIVE WARDEN</head><p>A passive warden introduces no degradation to the stegotext; in this case, D 2 = 0 and Y = X, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">p Y |X = 1 {Y =X} .<label>(18)</label></formula><p>This results in simplified expressions for the perfectly secure steganographic capacity in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> and the random-coding error exponent in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>, see Propositions 3 and 4 below. The proofs of these propositions appear in Appendices IV and V, respectively.</p><p>Proposition 3: For the passive-warden case (D 2 = 0), the maximization in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">12</ref>) is achieved by U = X and</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">C Steg (D 1 , 0) = max p X|S ∈Q Steg 1 (pS ,D1) H(X|S). (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">)</formula><p>Remark. Since H(X|S) = H(X) -I(S; X) = H(S) -I(S; X), we have </p><formula xml:id="formula_40">C Steg (D 1 , 0) = H(S) - min p X|S ∈Q Steg (pS ,D1) I(S; X).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I(S; X)</head><p>where the inequality holds because</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">p X|S ∈ Q Steg 1 (p S , D 1 ) implies E d(S, X) ≤ D 1 . Hence C Steg (D 1 , 0) ≤ H(S) -R S (D 1 )<label>(20)</label></formula><p>and the capacity-achieving codes for the passive-warden case are analogous to rate-distortion codes. Equality holds in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> if the distribution that achieves the rate-distortion bound satisfies the steganographic property p X = p S .</p><p>Proposition 4: For the passive-warden case (D 2 = 0), the random-coding exponent is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">E Steg r (R) = min pS ∈PS max p X|S ∈Q Steg 1 ( pS,D1) D(p S ||p S ) + H pS ,p X|S (X|S) -R + .<label>(21)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VIII. PENALTY FOR PERFECT SECURITY</head><p>The capacity expressions for public watermarking in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> and for steganography in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> take the same form, except that here the maximization of p XU|S is subject to the steganographic constraint. Consequently, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">C Steg ≤ C P ubW M<label>(22)</label></formula><p>and similarly</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">E Steg r (R) ≤ E P ubW M r (R).<label>(23)</label></formula><p>For some special cases, it is possible that the optimal covert channel for public watermarking automatically satisfies the perfect security condition, and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_43">22</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_44">23</ref>) hold with equality. Proposition 5 below states sufficient conditions on the covertext PMF p S and the distortion function d(•, •) that ensure the perfect security constraint causes no penalty in communication performance.</p><p>We consider S = Z q = {0, 1, 2, • • • , q -1}, which is a group under addition modulo q. We shall use the notation k k mod q. The covertext S is uniformly distributed over Z q , i.e., p S = U(S).</p><p>The associated distortion function d : S × S → R + ∪ {0} satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">d(i, i) = 0 and d(i, j) = d(0, j -i),</formula><p>If we write {d(i, j)} q-1 i, j=0 in a matrix form, the distortion matrix is cyclic-Toeplitz.</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">Definition 9: Let V {0, 1, • • • , L-1}, p S = U(S), and U {0, 1, 2, • • • , qL-1}. Given any covert channel p XV |S ∈ Q(L, p S , D 1 )</formula><p>, where v ∈ V, we define an associated covert channel p XU|S ∈ P XU|S , where U ∈ U, by</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">p XU|S x, qv + i s = 1 q p XV |S x -i, v s -i , ∀ v ∈ V, ∀ i, s, x ∈ S.<label>(24)</label></formula><p>For any stochastic matrix p XV |S ∈ Q(L, p S , D 1 ), by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>, the new channel p XU|S contains all of its q cyclically shifted versions (with respect to X and S) and these shifted versions are equally likely. Since the distortion function is cyclic, it is easy to verify that</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">E pS ,p XU |S [d(S, X)] = E pS ,p XV |S [d(S, X)] ≤ D 1 .</formula><p>Moreover, the marginal PMF pX induced by p S = U(S) and p XU|S is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">pX (x) = 1 q q-1 i=0 p X (x -i) = 1 q ≡ p S (x), ∀ x ∈ S,<label>(25)</label></formula><p>where p X is the marginal PMF induced by p S = U(S) and p XV |S ∈ Q(L, p S , D 1 ). That is,</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">p XU|S ∈ Q Steg (qL, p S , D 1 ).</formula><p>Definition 10: The class Q Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 ) is the set of all such p XU|S defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>. Clearly, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">Q Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 ) ⊂ Q Steg (qL, p S , D 1 ) ⊂ Q(qL, p S , D 1 ). (<label>26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">)</formula><p>Definition 11: The class of cyclic attack channels subject to distortion D 2 is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">A cyc (D 2 ) p Y |X ∈ P Y |X : p Y |X (y|x) = p Y |X (y -x | 0 ), ∀ x, y ∈ S,<label>and</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">1 q q-1 y=0 p Y |X (y|0) d(y, 0) ≤ D 2 . (<label>27</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_55">)</formula><p>Any stochastic matrix p Y |X ∈ A cyc (D 2 ) is cyclic-Toeplitz. Also note that for any p X ∈ P X ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">A cyc (D 2 ) ⊂ A(p X , D 2 ). (<label>28</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_57">)</formula><p>Proposition 5: For the above q-ary information-hiding problem, the capacities for both the perfectly secure steganography game and the public watermarking game are the same. That is, the perfect security constraint in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> does not cause any capacity loss. Moreover, there is no loss of optimality in restricting the maximization in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> to Q Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 ) and the minimization to A cyc (D 2 ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">C P ubW M (D 1 , D 2 ) = C Steg (D 1 , D 2 ) = lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg cyc (qL,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈Acyc(D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ). (<label>29</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">)</formula><p>The proof is given in Appendix VI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IX. EXAMPLE: BINARY-HAMMING CASE</head><p>We illustrate the above results through the following example, where S = {0, 1}, and the covertext is Bernoulli( 1 2 ) sequence, i.e.,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P r[S</head><formula xml:id="formula_60">= 1] = P r[S = 0] = 1 2 .</formula><p>The Hamming distortion metric is used: d(x, y) = 1 {x =y} .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Capacity</head><p>The capacity in the public watermarking game setting is given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">C =          D1 dD 2 [h(d D2 ) -h(D 2 )], if 0 ≤ D 1 ≤ d D2 ; h(D 1 ) -h(D 2 ), if d D2 ≤ D 1 ≤ 1/2; 1 -h(D 2 ), if D 1 &gt; 1/2,<label>(30)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">d D2 = 1 -2 -h(D2) . When D 2 = 0, C =    h(D 1 ) if 0 ≤ D 1 ≤ 1/2; 1 if D 1 ≥ 1/2.<label>(31)</label></formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the above two capacity functions. Active warden:</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">D 2 =0.2 h(D 1 )-h(D 2 )</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>: Capacity for a perfectly secure steganography game when the covertext S is a Bernoulli( <ref type="formula">1</ref>2 ) sequence.</p><p>The optimal attack channel is a binary symmetric channel (BSC) with crossover probability</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">D 2 . If d D2 ≤ D 1 ≤ 1/2,</formula><p>the optimal covert channel is also a binary symmetric channel: BSC(D 1 ) (i.e., |U| = 2, U = X, and p XU|S = p X|S ); otherwise, the capacity is achieved by time sharing: no embedding on a fraction of 1 -D1 dD 2</p><p>samples and embedding with the optimal covert channel BSC(d D2 ) on the rest of samples. Since the covertext S is a Bernoulli( 1 2 ) sequence, the output of the above optimal BSC(p) covert channel is also Bernoulli( <ref type="formula">1</ref>2 ). That is, the optimal covert channel for the public watermarking game satisfies p X = p S , and the perfect security constraint does not cause any loss in capacity, as stated by Proposition 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Random-Coding Exponent</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, we numerically computed the random-coding exponent for public watermarking in the case of D 1 = 0.4, D 2 = 0.2, and |U| = 2 as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>. We found that the optimal covert channel is still a BSC(D 1 ) (p XU|S = p X|S ) with the time sharing strategy. It implies that at least for the case of |U| = 2, p X = p S and the perfect security constraint causes no loss in random-coding exponent either.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Randomized Nested Linear Codes-A Capacity-Achieving Code Construction</head><p>For information-embedding problems with a fixed attack channel BSC(D 2 ), deterministic nested binary linear codes were proposed to achieve capacity, where C 1 , a good source code with Hamming distance D 1 , is nested in C 2 , a good channel code over BSC(D 2 ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. When is equal to the capacity in the regime D 1 ≥ d D2 . In the regime D 1 &lt; d D2 , the time-sharing strategy of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_61">30</ref>) is applied. These nested linear codes apply to both public watermarking and steganography because BSC(D 2 ) is the optimal discrete memoryless attack channel. The stegotext codewords are elements of C 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">|C 2 | . = 2 N [1-h(D2)] and |C 1 | . = 2 N [1-h(D1)] , the asymptotic code rate R = lim N →∞ 1 N log 2 |C 2 | |C 1 | = h(D 1 ) -h(D 2 )</formula><p>In the passive-warden case (D 2 = 0), we simply let C 2 = F N 2 , and perfect security is achieved even without a secret key. In the active-warden case, C 2 is a subgroup of F N 2 , and randomization via the secret key plays an essential role in achieving perfect security. The strategy described below makes the transmitted stegotext uniformly distributed over F N 2 . The resulting code is a randomized nested binary linear code. Partition the whole space F N 2 into a disjoint union of C 2 and its cosets:</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">F N 2 = c∈Ω2 C 2 ⊕ c,<label>(32)</label></formula><p>where C 2 ⊕ c is a coset of C 2 , the element c ∈ Ω 2 is a coset leader, and the set Ω 2 contains all coset leaders. We have</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">|Ω 2 | = 2 N |C 2 | . = 2 N h(D2) . (<label>33</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_68">)</formula><p>Let the secret key K be uniformly distributed over Ω 2 . For any k ∈ Ω 2 , the encoder output is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">x = f k N (m, s) = f 0 N (m, s ⊕ k) ⊕ k, (<label>34</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_70">)</formula><p>where f 0 N (•, •) is the deterministic encoder used for the information-embedding or watermarking problem. The decoding function is</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">m = φ k N (y) = φ 0 N (y ⊕ k),<label>(35)</label></formula><p>where φ 0 N (•) is the decoder associated with f 0 N (•). Since the output of the deterministic encoder is uniformly distributed over C 2 and the secret key K is uniformly distributed over Ω 2 , the coset decomposition property <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref> ensures that the randomized encoder output of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_69">34</ref>) is uniformly distributed over F N 2 . Hence perfect security is achieved. By <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> the entropy rate of the secret key is h(D 2 ), unlike the log 2 N growth required for general RM codes in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>X. CONCLUSION</head><p>A strict definition of perfect security has been adopted in this paper, implying that even a warden with unlimited computational resources is unable to reliably detect the presence of a hidden message. We have studied the Shannontheoretic limits of communication performance under this perfect-security requirement and studied the structure of codes that asymptotically achieve those limits. The main results are summarized below.</p><p>• Perfectly secure steganography is closely related to the public watermarking problem of <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. Positive capacity and random-coding exponents are achieved using stacked-binning codes and an MPMI decoder.</p><p>• Randomized codes are generally needed to achieve perfect security. The common randomness is provided by a secret key shared between the encoder and decoder. For i.i.d. covertexts, Proposition 1 shows that perfectly secure steganographic codes can be constructed using randomized permutations of a prototype CCC watermarking code that merely has an order-1 security property, i.e., the prototype code matches the first-order marginals of the covertext and stegotext, but not the full N -dimensional statistics.</p><p>• The cost of perfect security in terms of communication performance is the same as the cost of order-1 security.</p><p>However, if the covertext distribution is uniform and the distortion metric is cyclically symmetric, the security constraint does not cause any loss of performance.</p><p>Computational Security. This paper has focused on the interplay between communication performance and information-theoretic security, where security is achieved using a private key that is uniformly distributed over a group G sub . A more practical setup would involve a public-key system, in which a reduced set of representers of G sub is selected, each corresponding to a value of the key. Assume that the uniform distribution over this reduced set is computationally indistinguishable (in a sense to be precisely defined) from the uniform distribution over G sub . The resulting steganographic code is no longer perfectly secure but inherits the computational security of the key generation mechanism. Thus the framework analyzed in this paper can form the basis for constructing computationally secure steganographic codes that have near-optimal communication performance.</p><p>Extensions. Our basic framework can also be used to analyze complex problems involving covertexts with Markov dependencies and covertexts defined over continuous alphabets <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40,</ref><ref type="bibr">Sec. X]</ref>. While such extensions are technically challenging, we hope that the mathematical structure of optimal codes identified in this paper under simplifying assumptions will shed some light on the development of practical codes with high communication performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX I PROOF OF PROP 1</head><p>First we verify the perfect security condition. For RM codes (Def. 3), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">p X|π,S,M (x|π, s, m) = 1 {πx=fN (πs,m)} .</formula><p>Also note that for any x, z ∈ T s , there exists a permutation π 0 such that x = π 0 z. Hence the value of the sum π 1 {πx=z} is independent of z (conditioned on z ∈ T s ), and so</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">π 1 {πx=z} = 1 |T s | z∈Ts π 1 {πx=z} = 1 |T s | π 1 = N ! |T s | . (<label>36</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_74">)</formula><p>Hence for any type class T s we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">p X|Ts (x|T s ) = 1 N ! π 1 |M| m∈M 1 |T s | s ′ ∈Ts p X|π,S,M (x|π, s ′ , m) = 1 N ! π 1 |M| m∈M 1 |T s | s ′ ∈Ts 1 {πx=fN (πs ′ ,m)} (a) = 1 N ! π 1 |M| m∈M 1 |T s | s ′′ ∈Ts 1 {πx=fN (s ′′ ,m)} = 1 |M| m∈M 1 |T s | s ′′ ∈Ts 1 N ! π 1 {πx=fN (s ′′ ,m)} (b) = 1 |M| m∈M 1 |T s | s ′′ ∈Ts 1 |T s | 1 {x∈Ts} = 1 |T s | 1 {x∈Ts} ,<label>(37)</label></formula><p>where in (a) we have made the change of variables s ′′ = πs ′ , and in (b) we have used <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref> with z = f N (s ′′ , m).</p><p>From (37) we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">p X (x) = Ts p S (T s ) p X|Ts (x|T s ) = Ts p S (T s ) 1 |T s | 1 {x∈Ts} = p S (x), ∀x ∈ S N ,</formula><p>hence the perfect security condition (2) is satisfied. Now verifying the maximum-distortion constraint (1), for every π we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">d N (s, f π N (s, m)) (a) = d N (s, π -1 f N (πs, m)) (b) = d N (πs, f N (πs, m)) (c) ≤ D 1</formula><p>where (a) uses the definition of f π N in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">4</ref>), (b) holds because the distortion measure is additive, and (c) holds because of our initial assumption on the prototype f N . Therefore (1) holds.</p><p>Finally, let us evaluate the error probability for the RM code. Since the covertext source and the attack channel are memoryless, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">p N S (s) = p N S (πs) and p N Y |X (y|x) = p N Y |X (πy|πx)<label>(38)</label></formula><p>for any permutation π. The error probability for the prototype code takes the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">P e,N (f N , φ N , p Y |X ) = 1 |M| m∈M s∈S N p N S (s) x∈S N 1 {x=fN (s,m)} y∈S N p N Y |X (y|x) 1 {φN (y) =m} .</formula><p>For the prototype code modulated with permutation π, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">P e,N (f π N , φ π N , p Y |X ) = 1 |M| m∈M s∈S N p N S (s) x∈S N 1 {πx=fN (πs,m)} y∈S N p N Y |X (y|x) 1 {φN (πy) =m} (a) = 1 |M| m∈M s∈S N p N S (πs) x∈S N 1 {πx=fN (πs,m)} y∈S N p N Y |X (πy|πx) 1 {φN (πy) =m} (b) = 1 |M| m∈M π -1 s ′ ∈S N p N S (s ′ ) π -1 x ′ ∈S N 1 {x ′ =fN (s ′ ,m)} π -1 y ′ ∈S N p N Y |X (y ′ |x ′ ) 1 {φN (y ′ ) =m} (c) = 1 |M| m∈M s ′ ∈S N p N S (s ′ ) x ′ ∈S N 1 {x ′ =fN (s ′ ,m)} y ′ ∈S N p N Y |X (y ′ |x ′ ) 1 {φN (y ′ ) =m} = P e,N (f N , φ N , p Y |X ),<label>(39)</label></formula><p>where (a) holds because of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_78">38</ref>), (b) is obtained using the change in variables s ′ = πs, x ′ = πx, y ′ = πy, and (c) holds because the three sums run over all elements (s ′ , x ′ , y ′ ) of S N × S N × S N , and so the order of summation is inconsequential. Since (39) holds for every permutation π, the error probability for the RM code is equal to</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">P e,N (F N , Φ N , p Y |X ) = 1 N ! π P e,N (f π N , φ π N , p Y |X ) = P e,N (f N , φ N , p Y |X ).</formula><p>This completes the proof.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX II CONVERSE PROOF OF THEOREM 1</head><p>The converse is an extension of the proof in [33, <ref type="bibr">Section 7]</ref>. Our upper bound on achievable rates is derived by</p><p>• replacing the perfect-security constraint with a weaker order-1 security constraint on the encoder:</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">p x = p s ∀ m, s, x = f N (s, m)<label>(40)</label></formula><p>(matching the types of input s and output x = f N (s, m) of the encoder f N ),</p><p>• replacing the almost-sure distortion constraint with an expected distortion constraint on the encoder:</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">1 |M| s∈S N p N S (s) d N (s, f N (s, m)),<label>(41)</label></formula><p>• and providing the decoder with knowledge of the attack channel p Y |X .</p><p>Clearly any upper bound we derive under these assumptions is an upper bound on capacity as well.</p><p>For any rate-R code</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">(f N , φ N ) and DMC p Y |X ∈ A(p X , D 2 ), we have N R = H(M ) = H(M |Y) + I(M ; Y) ≤ 1 + P e (f N , φ N , p N Y |X ) N R + I(M ; Y),</formula><p>where the inequality is due to Fano's inequality. In order for P e not to be bounded away from 0, rate R needs to</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">satisfy N R -1 ≤ min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) I(M ; Y).<label>(42)</label></formula><p>The joint PMF of (M, S, X, Y) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">p MSXY|fN = p M p N S p N Y |X 1 {X=fN (S,M)} .<label>(43)</label></formula><p>Owing to (43), for any 1 ≤ i ≤ N , (M, S, {Y j } j =i ) → X i → Y i forms a Markov chain and so does</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">(W i , S i ) → X i → Y i ,<label>(44)</label></formula><p>where the random variable W i is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">W i = (M, S i+1 , • • • , S N , Y 1 , • • • , Y i-1 ).<label>(45)</label></formula><p>Using the same set of inequalities as in [26, <ref type="bibr">Lemma 4]</ref>, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">I(M ; Y) ≤ N i=1 [I(W i ; Y i ) -I(W i ; S i )].<label>(46)</label></formula><p>We define a time sharing random variable T , which is uniformly distributed over {1, • • • , N } and independent of all other random variables, and define the quadruple of random variables (W, S, X, Y ) as (W T , S T , X T , Y T ).</p><p>With this definition, the order-1 security constraint (40) becomes p X = p S , and the expected distortion constraint</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">(41) becomes s,x p S (s)p X|S (x|s) d(s, x) ≤ D 1 . Therefore p X|S ∈ Q Steg 1 (p S , D 1 ).</formula><p>By (45), the random variable W is defined over an alphabet of cardinality </p><formula xml:id="formula_91">exp 2 {N [R + log |S| ]}. Moreover (W, S) → X → Y</formula><p>where U = (W, T ) is defined over an alphabet of cardinality</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">L(N ) = N exp 2 {N [R + log |S| ]},<label>(48)</label></formula><p>and the last inequality is due to</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">I(T ; Y ) ≥ 0 and I(T ; S) = 0 (since T is independent of S). Since p X|S ∈ Q Steg 1 (p S , D 1 ), we have p XU|S ∈ Q Steg (L(N ), p S , D 1 ).</formula><p>Recall that J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) I(U ; Y ) -I(U ; S) when |U| = L, and that</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">C Steg L max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ).</formula><p>Following the same arguments as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, the sequence C Steg </p><p>This proves the converse part of Theorem 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX III PROOF OF PROPOSITION 2</head><p>We have</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">E Steg r,L (R) ≤ E P ubW M r,L (R).</formula><p>Recall from [33, Lemma 3.1] that the sequence E P ubW M r,L (R) is nondecreasing and converges to a finite limit</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">E P ubW M r (R) as L → ∞.</formula><p>Using the same arguments as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr">Lemma 3.1]</ref>, it follows that the sequence E Steg r,L (R) is nondecreasing and converges to a finite limit E Steg r (R) as L → ∞. Hence for any ǫ &gt; 0 and R, there exists</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">L(ǫ) such that E Steg r,L (R) ≥ E Steg r (R) -ǫ, ∀ L ≥ L(ǫ).</formula><p>We next prove that for any L, a sequence of deterministic codes (f N , φ N ) with order-1 steganographic security exist with the property that</p><formula xml:id="formula_100">lim N →∞ - 1 N log max p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) P e (f N , φ N , p Y |X ) = E Steg r,L (R).</formula><p>To prove the existence of such a code, we construct a random ensemble C of binning codes (f N , φ N ) with auxiliary alphabet U {1, 2, • • • , L} and show that the error probability averaged over C vanishes at rate E Steg r,L (R) as N goes to infinity. The proof is based on that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr">Theorem 3.2]</ref> with special treatment on the encoder construction for perfect security. </p><p>The decoder then outputs the column index m that corresponds to û. If there exist maximizers with more than one column index, the decoder declares an error.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Error Probability Analysis</head><p>The probability of error is given by P e,N max Following the steps in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr">Section 5]</ref>, the encoding error vanishes double-exponentially and only the decoding error contributes to P e,N on the exponential scale: </p><formula xml:id="formula_102">P e,N ≤</formula><formula xml:id="formula_103">) -R + .<label>(53)</label></formula><p>Clearly, E Steg r,L (R) ≥ 0, with equality if and only if the following conditions are met:</p><p>• the minimizing PMF pS is equal to p S ;</p><p>• the minimizing conditional PMF pY |XUS is equal to p Y |X ; and Coosing U = X yields the lower bound</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">• R ≥ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) = C Steg L . Therefore, E Steg r,L<label>(</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_105">C Steg (D 1 , 0) ≥ max p X|S ∈Q Steg 1 (pS ,D1) I(X; X) -I(X; S) = max p X|S ∈Q Steg 1 (pS ,D1) H(X|S).<label>(54)</label></formula><p>On the other hand, From (56), we obtain The maximum on the left side is achieved by U = X. Combining (58) and (59) proves the proposition.</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) = I(U ; X) -I(U ; S) ≤ I(U ; X|S) (55) = H(X|S) -H(X|U, S) ≤ H(X|S).<label>(56</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_107">C Steg (D 1 , 0) = lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L,</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX VI PROOF OF PROPOSITION 5</head><p>We prove Proposition 5 in two parts. We first establish that the right-hand side of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_58">29</ref>) is an upper bound on the public watermarking capacity C P ubW M . Then we prove that the right-hand side of (29) is at the same time a lower bound on the perfectly secure steganographic capacity C Steg .</p><p>We start with the following lemma on the properties of p XU|S ∈ Q Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 ), which are used throughout this proof.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_108">i) p S|U s qv + i = p S|V s -i v , ∀ i, s ∈ S and ∀ v ∈ V; (ii) p X|U x qv + i = p X|V x -i v , ∀ i, x ∈ S and ∀ v ∈ V; (iii) p U (qv + i) = 1 q p V (v), ∀ i ∈ S, v ∈ V</formula><p>, where p U (resp. p V ) is the marginal PMF of U (resp. V ) induced from p XU|S (resp. p XV |S ) and p S = U(S); and</p><p>(iv) pX = U(S), where pX is the marginal PMF of X induced from p XU|S and p S = U(S).</p><p>It is straightforward to verify Lemma 1(i)-(iv) from <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Upper Bound</head><p>For the capacity of the public watermarking game,</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">C P ubW M (D 1 , D 2 ) = lim L→∞ max p XV |S ∈Q(L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XV |S , p Y |X ) ≤ lim L→∞ max p XV |S ∈Q(L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈Acyc(D2) J L (p S , p XV |S , p Y |X ),<label>(60)</label></formula><p>since A cyc (D 2 ) ⊂ A(p X , D 2 ) by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_56">28</ref>).</p><p>Given any p XV |S ∈ Q(L, p S , D 1 ) and its associated p XU|S ∈ Q Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 ), we first verify that</p><formula xml:id="formula_110">I(S; U ) = I(S; V ).<label>(61)</label></formula><p>From p S = U(S) and p XV |S , we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_111">H(S|V ) = - L-1 v=0 p V (v) q-1 s=0 p S|V (s|v) log p S|V (s|v).<label>(62)</label></formula><p>From p S = U(S) and p XU|S , we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_112">H(S|U ) = - L-1 v=0 q-1 i=0 q-1 s=0 p U (qv + i) p S|U (s|qv + i) log p S|U (s|qv + i) = - L-1 v=0 q-1 i=0 q-1 s=0 1 q p V (v) p S|V s -i v) log p S|V s -i v) (63) = 1 q q-1 i=0 H(S|V ) = H(S|V ),<label>(64)</label></formula><p>where ( <ref type="formula">63</ref>) is obtained by using Lemma 1(i) and (iii). Since I(S; U ) = H(S) -H(S|U ) and I(S; V ) = H(S) - </p><formula xml:id="formula_113">H(S|V ),<label>(</label></formula><p>Therefore, (60) and (67) yield </p><formula xml:id="formula_115">C Steg (D 1 , D 2 ) ≤ C P ubW M (D 1 , D 2 ) ≤ lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg cyc (qL,pS<label>,</label></formula><p>Given p Y |X ∈ A(p X , D 2 ), we define q conditional PMFs:</p><formula xml:id="formula_117">p m Y |X (y|x) = p Y |X (y -m|x -m), ∀ x, y ∈ S, 0 ≤ m &lt; q. (<label>72</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_118">)</formula><p>Since the distortion matrix {d(i, j)} q-1 i, j=0 is cyclic, it is easy to verify that all the q conditional PMFs p m Y |X ∈ A(p X , D 2 ). </p><formula xml:id="formula_119">1 q p V (v) p Y |V (y -i|v) (89) = 1 q q-1 j=0 p Y (j -i) = 1 q ,<label>(90)</label></formula><p>where (89) follows from Lemma 1(iii) and (88). The conditional entropy of Y given U is</p><formula xml:id="formula_120">H(Y |U ) = - L-1 v=0 q-1 i=0 p U (qv + i) q-1 y=0 p Y |U (y|qv + i) log p Y |U (y|qv + i) = - L-1 v=0 q-1 i=0 1 q p V (v) q-1 y=0 p Y |V (y -i|v) log p Y |V (y -i|v) (91) = 1 q q-1 j=0 H(Y |V ) = H(Y |V ),<label>(92)</label></formula><p>where (91) follows from Lemma 1(iii) and (88), and (92) follows from (86).</p><p>Since pY (y) = 1 q for any y ∈ S as shown in (90), we have </p><formula xml:id="formula_121">H pY (Y ) ≥ H pY (Y ),<label>(93)</label></formula><p>Hence, Lemma 2 is proved.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>1 N 1 N</head><label>11</label><figDesc>The shorthands a N . = b N , a N ≤ b N , and a N ≥ b N are used to denote asymptotic equalities and inequalities in the exponential scale for lim N →∞ log aN bN = 0, lim sup N →∞ log aN bN ≤ 0, and lim inf N →∞ 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Finally, we adoptFig. 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1: Communication-theoretic view of perfectly secure steganography.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>in which the codewords are drawn from an optimized type class T u T * U (p s ). Each array C(p s ) has |M| columns and 2 N ρ(ps) rows, where ρ(p s ) is a function of the corresponding covertext type p s and is termed the depth parameter of the array. Given y, the decoder seeks a codeword in C = ps C(p s ) that maximizes the penalized empirical mutual information and outputs its column index as the estimated message: m = arg max m max l,ps [I(u(l, m, p s ); y) -ρ(p s )] .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>For the problem of 1 (</head><label>1</label><figDesc>encoding a source S subject to distortion D 1 , the minimum rate for representing the source is given by the rate-distortion function R S (D 1 ) = min p X|S : E d(S,X)≤D1 I(S; X) ≤ min p X|S ∈Q Steg pS ,D1)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig.4: Random-coding exponent for perfectly secure steganography game when the covertext S is a Bernoulli(12 ) sequence, D 1 = 0.4, D 2 = 0.2, and |U| = 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>forms a Markov chain. Combining (42) and (46), we further derive R ≤ 1 N min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) W i ; Y i ) -I(W i ; S i )] = min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) [I(W ; Y |T ) -I(W ; S|T )] = min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) [I(W, T ; Y ) -I(W, T ; S) -I(T ; Y ) + I(T ; S)] ≤ min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) [I(U ; Y ) -I(U ; S)] ,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>L</head><label></label><figDesc>is nondecreasing and converges to a finite limitC Steg lim L→∞ C Steg L = lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ).Therefore, continuing with (47), R is bounded by R ≤ min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) [I(U ; Y ) -I(U ; S)] = min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L(N ) (p X , p XU|S , p Y |X ) ≤ sup L max p U X|S ∈Q Steg (L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) = lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) = C Steg .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Assume that R &lt; C Steg L -ǫ. For any covertext type p s and conditional type p xu|s , define the function E L,N (R, p s , p xu|s ) min p y|xus min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) D(p s p xu|s p y|xus ||p S p xu|s p Y |X ) +|I(u; y) -I(u; s) -ǫ -R| + . (50) Define Q Steg (N, L, p s , D 1 ) as the set of conditional types p x|us that also belong to the set Q Steg (L, p s , D 1 ) of feasible steganographic channels. If p x|us ∈ Q Steg (N, L, p s , D 1 ) then (1) p x = p s , i.e., the stegotext sequence has the same type as the covertext sequence and the order-1 security condition is satisfied; (2) d N (x, s) ≤ D 1 , i.e., distortion is no greater than D 1 for any choice of s and m. The set Q Steg (N, L, p s , D 1 ) includes p x|us = 1 {x=s} and is therefore nonempty. Now denote by p x|us the maximizer of (50) over the set Q Steg (N, L, p s , D 1 ). As a result of this optimization, we may associate • to any covertext type p s , a type class T * U (p s ) T u and a mutual information I * US (p s ) I(u; s); • to any covertext sequence s, a conditional type class T * U|S (s) T u|s ; • to any sequences s and u ∈ T * US (p s ), a conditional type class T * X|US (u, s) T x|us . A random codebook C is the union of codeword arrays C(p s ) indexed by the covertext sequence type p s . Let ρ(p s ) I * US (p s ) + ǫ. The codeword array C(p s ) is obtained by drawing 2 N (R+ρ(ps)) random vectors independently and uniformly from the corresponding type class T * U (p s ), and arranging them in an array with 2 N ρ(ps) rows and 2 N R columns indexed by messages. A. Encoder f N Given a codebook C, a covertext sequence s, and a message m, the encoder finds in C(p s ) an l such that u(l, m) ∈ T * U|S (s). If more than one such l exists, pick one of them randomly (with uniform distribution). Let u = u(l, m). If no such l is available, the encoder declares an error and draws u from the uniform distribution over the conditional type class T * U|S (s). Then x is drawn from the uniform distribution over the conditional type class T * X|US (u, s). Recalling the discussion below (50), f N satisfies both the order-1 steganographic security constraint and the maximum distortion constraint. B. Decoder φ N Given y and the same codebook C used by the encoder, the decoder first seeks a covertext type p s and û ∈ C(p s ) that maximizes the penalized mutual information criterion max ps max u∈C(ps) [I(u; y) -ρ(p s )].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>p</head><label></label><figDesc>Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) P r(M = M ) = max p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) P e (f N , φ N , p Y |X ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>R) &gt; 0 and the error probability vanishes for any R &lt; C Steg L (D 1 , D 2 ). This implies that the capacity is lower-bounded by lim L→∞ C Steg L (D 1 , D 2 ). D. Perfect Security Having established the achievability of E Steg r,L (R) and C Steg L for a deterministic code (f N , φ N ) with order-1 security and maximum distortion D 1 , we invoke Proposition 1 to claim that the randomly modulated code with prototype (f N , φ N ) achieves the same error probability (hence error exponent) and distortion as the prototype. APPENDIX IV PROOF OF PROPOSITION 3 By (18), J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) is reduced to J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) = I(U ; X) -I(U ; S).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>)</head><label></label><figDesc>Note that (55) follows from the chain rule of mutual information I(U ; XS) = I(U ; X) + I(U ; S|X) = I(U ; S) + I(U ; X|S) and I(U ; S|X) ≥ 0. Choosing U = X achieves equality in both (55) and (56).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Lemma 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Any p XU|S ∈ Q Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 ) generated by<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> from its corresponding p XV |S ∈ Q(L, p S , D 1 ) has the following properties:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>C</head><label></label><figDesc>D1) min p Y |X ∈Acyc(D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ). (68) B. Lower Bound Using the same argument at the end of Appendix II for the sequence {C Steg L (D 1 , D 2 )}, we can argue that the sequence {C P ubW M L (D 1 , D 2 )} is also nondecreasing and bounded by log |S|. Therefore, {C P ubW M L (D 1 , D 2 )} andany of its subsequences converge to the same limit. That isC P ubW M (D 1 , D 2 ) = lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q(L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) = lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q(qL,pS ,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ). Steg (D 1 , D 2 ) = limL→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) = lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (qL,pS ,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ). Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 ) ⊂ Q Steg (qL, p S , D 1 ) ⊂ Q(qL, p S , D 1 ). Thus, we have C P ubW M (D 1 , D 2 ) ≥ C Steg (D 1 , D 2 ) ≥ lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg cyc (qL,pS ,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>1 x=0p- 1 x=0pppppq q- 1 m=0J= 1 x=0p- 1 x=0pp 1 x=0p- 1 x=0pp</head><label>1111111</label><figDesc>The conditional PMF p m Y |U induced by p XU|S , p m Y |X ∈ Q Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 ) × A(p X , D 2 ) is given byp m Y |U (y|qv + i) = q-X|U (x|qv + i)p m Y |X (y|x) = qX|U (x|qv + i)p Y |X (y -m|x -m) X|V (x -i|v)p Y |X (y -m|x -m) X|U (x -m|qv + i -m)p Y |X (y -m|x -m) (75) = p Y |U (y -m|qv + i -m), ∀ y, i ∈ S, v ∈ V,(76)where (73) follows from the definition (72), and both (74) and (75) follow by applying Lemma 1(ii). We also obtain the marginal PMF of Y asp m Y (y) = U (qv + i)p m Y |U (y|qv + i) U (qv + i -m)p Y |U (y -m|qv + i -m) (77) = p Y (y -m), ∀ y ∈ S,(78)where (77) follows from Lemma 1(iii) and (76).From (76) and (78), we obtainI pS ,p XU |S ,p Y |X (Y ; U ) = I pS ,p XU |S ,p m Y |X (Y ; U )(79)and henceJ L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) = J L (p S , p XU|S , p m Y |X ),(80)for 0 ≤ m &lt; q. Y |X . It is easy to check that pY |X ∈ A cyc (D 2 ). Also, J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) = 1 L (p S , p XU|S , p m Y |X ) (81) ≥ J L p S , p XU|S , J L (p S , p XU|S , pY |X ),(82)where the inequality comes from the fact that for fixed p S and p XU|S ,J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) is convex in p Y |X [27, Proposition 4.1(iii)]. Therefore, from (82) we haveC P ubW M (D 1 , D 2 ) ≥ C Steg (D1 , D 2 ) ≥ lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg cyc (qL,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) ≥ lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg cyc (qL,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈Acyc(D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ).(83)Combining the upper bound inequality in (68) and the lower bound inequality in (83), we prove the claimC P ubW M (D 1 , D 2 ) = C Steg (D 1 , D 2 ) = lim L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg cyc (qL,pS,D1) min p Y |X ∈Acyc(D2) J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ),(84)which means that the perfectly secure steganographic constraint does not cause any capacity loss.APPENDIX VII PROOF OF LEMMA 2For the pairp XV |S , p Y |X ∈ Q(L, p S , D 1 ) × A cyc (D 2 ), the conditional PMF of Y given V is p Y |V (y|v) = q-X|V (x|v) p Y |X (y|x) = qX|V (x|v) p Y |X (y -x| 0), ∀ y ∈ S, v ∈ V,(85)where (85) follows from<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> in Definition 11 forp Y |X ∈ A cyc (D 2 ). The conditional entropy of Y given V is H(Y |V ) = -Y |V (y|v) log p Y |V (y|v).(86)For the associated pairp XU|S , p Y |X ∈ Q Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 ) × A cyc (D 2 ), the conditional PMF of Y given U is p Y |U (y|qv + i) = q-X|U (x|qv + i)p Y |X (y|x) = qX|V x -i v p Y |X y -i -(x -i) 0 (87) = p Y |V (y -i|v), ∀ y, i ∈ S, v ∈ V,(88)where to obtain (87) we have used Lemma 1(ii) and<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> in Definition 11 for p Y |X ∈ A cyc (D 2 ); and (88) follows from (85). The marginal PMF of Y is given by pY (y) = U (qv + i) p Y |U (y|qv + i)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where pY and p Y are the marginal PMF of Y for p S , p XU|S , p Y |X and p S , p XV |S , p Y |X , respectively. Therefore, from (92) and (93), we obtainI(Y ; U ) = H pY (Y ) -H(Y |U ) (94) ≥ H pY (Y ) -H(Y |V )(95)= I(Y ; V ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. 2: A binning scheme with a stack of variable-size codeword arrays indexed by the covertext sequence type.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>. . . .</cell><cell>. . . .</cell><cell>. . . . .</cell><cell>C s (p )</cell><cell>Covertext sequence type p s</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>N ( ) ρ p s</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">C (p ) s</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>NR</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p>and E Steg r (R) is given by (21), see Section VII.</p>Fig</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>exp 2 -N min S p XU|S pY |XUS ||p S p XU|S p Y |X ) + J L (p S , p XU|S , pY |XUS</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="5">As N → ∞, by [33, Lemma 2.2], the above error exponent converges to</cell></row><row><cell>E Steg r,L (R) = min pS ∈PS</cell><cell>max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L, pS,D1)</cell><cell cols="3">min pY |XU S ∈P Y |XU S</cell><cell>min p Y |X ∈A(pX ,D2)</cell></row><row><cell>D(p</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">ps</cell><cell>max p xu|s</cell><cell>E L,N (R, p s , p xu|s ) .</cell><cell>(52)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>pS,D1)J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) Since p Y |X = 1 {Y =X} , the term D(p S p XU|S pY |XUS ||p S p XU|S p Y |X ) in (14) is infinite if pY |XUS = p Y |X .</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">≤ lim L→∞</cell><cell>max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L,pS,D1)</cell><cell>H(X|S)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>=</cell><cell cols="2">max p X|S ∈Q Steg (pS ,D1)</cell><cell>H(X|S).</cell><cell>(57)</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Combining (54) and (57) yields (19) and proves the proposition.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>APPENDIX V</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">PROOF OF PROPOSITION 4</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">respectively. This yields</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E Steg r</cell><cell>(R) = min pS ∈PS</cell><cell cols="2">D(p S ||p S ) + lim</cell><cell>(58)</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Similarly to the steps in the proof of Proposition 3, we derive that</cell></row><row><cell>∀ L ≥ 2 :</cell><cell>max</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p><p>Hence, the minimizing pY |XUS in (</p>14</p>) is given by</p>p * Y |XUS = p Y |X = 1 {Y =X} .</p>Consequently, the two terms of the cost function of (</p>14</p>) are reduced to</p>D(p S p XU|S p * Y |XUS ||p S p XU|S p Y |X ) = D(p S ||p S )</p>and</p>J L (p S , p XU|S , p * Y |XUS ) -R + = J L (p S ,</p>p XU|S , p Y |X ) -R + , L→∞ max p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L, pS,D1) |J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) -R| + . p XU |S ∈Q Steg (L, pS,D1) |J L (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ) -R| + = max p X|S ∈Q Steg 1 (pS ,D1) |H pS ,p X|S (X|S) -R| + . (59)</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>61) follows from (64).For the pairp XV |S , p Y |X ∈ Q(L, p S , D 1 )×A cyc (D 2 ) and its associated pair p XU|S , p Y |X ∈ Q Steg cyc (qL, p S , D 1 )× A cyc (D 2 ), we have the following lemma that is proved in Appendix VII.I pS ,p XV |S ,p Y |X (Y ; V ) ≤ I pS ,p XU |S ,p Y |X (Y ; U ). J L (p S , p XV |S , p Y |X )J qL (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ).</figDesc><table><row><cell>which yields</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>lim L→∞</cell><cell>max p XV |S ∈Q(L,pS,D1)</cell><cell cols="2">min p Y |X ∈Acyc(D2)</cell></row><row><cell>≤ lim L→∞</cell><cell cols="2">max p XU |S ∈Q Steg cyc (qL,pS,D1)</cell><cell>min p Y |X ∈Acyc(D2)</cell></row><row><cell>Lemma 2:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(65)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(66)</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p>From (61), Lemma 2, and the definition of J L in</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref></p>, we obtain</p>J L (p S , p XV |S , p Y |X ) ≤ J qL (p S , p XU|S , p Y |X ),</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>February 16, 2007. Revised September<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref> 2007   DRAFT</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported by NSF under grants CCR 02-08809 and CCR 03-25924, and presented in part at the 40th Conference on Information Sciences and Systems (CISS), Princeton, NJ, March 2004. Ying Wang was with the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A survey of steganographic techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Katzenbeisser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Information Hiding, S. Katzenbeisser and F. Petitcolas</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Artech House</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="78" />
			<pubPlace>Norwood, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Hiding: Steganography and Watermarking-Attacks and Countermeasures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Duric</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jajodia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Digital</forename><surname>Watermarking</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Morgan-Kaufmann</publisher>
			<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data-hiding codes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Köetter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-12">Dec. 2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2083" to="2126" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An information-theoretic and game-theoretic study of timing channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Giles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hajek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2455" to="2477" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-09">Sep. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the limits of steganography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A P</forename><surname>Petitcolas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Select. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="474" to="481" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-05">May 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring steganography: Seeing the unseen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jajodia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-02">Feb. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hide and seek: An introduction to steganography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Provos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Honeyman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Security and Privacy Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-06">May-June 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The prisoner&apos;s problem and the subliminal channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Simmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. CRYPTO&apos;83</title>
		<meeting>CRYPTO&apos;83</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="67" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An information-theoretic model for steganography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cachin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information and Computation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">192</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-07">Jul. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steganalysis of block-DCT steganography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Workshop on Statistical Signal Processing</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Workshop on Statistical Signal essing<address><addrLine>St. Louis, MO</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-09">Sep. 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="342" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steganalysis of block-structured stegotext</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the SPIE, Security, Steganography, and Watermarking of Multimedia Contents VI</title>
		<meeting>of the SPIE, Security, Steganography, and Watermarking of Multimedia Contents VI<address><addrLine>San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-01">Jan. 2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="477" to="488" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of hiding in the least significant bit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Dabeer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Madhow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Manjunath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3046" to="3058" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-10">Oct. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A stochastic QIM algorithm for robust, undetectable image watermarking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Briassouli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int. Conf. on Image Processing</title>
		<meeting>Int. Conf. on Image essing<address><addrLine>Singapore</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-10">Oct. 2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1173" to="1176" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimized feature extraction for learning-based image steganalysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Forensics and Security</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-03">Mar. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steganalysis for Markov cover data with applications to images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Madhow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Manjunath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Forensics and Security</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-06">Jun. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Provably secure steganography: Achieving zero K-L divergence using statistical restoration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Solanki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Madhow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Manjunath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. on Image Processing</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. on Image essing<address><addrLine>Atlanta, GA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-10">Oct. 2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="128" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determining achievable rates for secure zero divergence steganography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Solanki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Manjunath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Madhow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. on Image Processing</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. on Image essing<address><addrLine>Atlanta, GA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-10">Oct. 2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="124" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steganalysis of additive noise modelable information hiding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Harmsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pearlman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the SPIE, Security, Steganography, and Watermarking of Multimedia Contents VI</title>
		<meeting>of the SPIE, Security, Steganography, and Watermarking of Multimedia Contents VI<address><addrLine>San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-01">Jan. 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="142" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steganalysis using higher-order image statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lyu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Farid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Forensics and Security</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-03">Mar. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New blind steganalysis and its implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goljan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fridrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Holotyak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the SPIE, Security, Steganography, and Watermarking of Multimedia Contents VI</title>
		<meeting>of the SPIE, Security, Steganography, and Watermarking of Multimedia Contents VI<address><addrLine>San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-01">Jan. 2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting hidden messages using higher-order statistical models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Farid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. on Image Processing</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. on Image essing<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-09">Sep. 2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="905" to="908" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting LSB steganography in color and gray-scale images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fridrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goljan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Multimedia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-10">Oct. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Practical steganalysis of digital images-state of the art</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fridrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goljan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Proc. of SPIE Photonics West</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4675</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-01">Jan. 2002</date>
			<pubPlace>San Jose, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of LSB steganography via sample pair analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dumitrescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1995" to="2007" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-07">Jul. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coding for channel with random parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Gel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pinsker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prob. of Control and Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information-theoretic analysis of information hiding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>O'sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="563" to="593" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-03">Mar. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steganography via covering codes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Galand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kabatiansky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int. Sym. on Inform. Theory</title>
		<meeting>Int. Sym. on Inform. Theory<address><addrLine>Yokohama, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-07">Jul. 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">192</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Writing on wet paper</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fridrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goljan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lisonek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Soukal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3923" to="3935" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-10">Oct. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wet paper codes with improved embedding efficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fridrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goljan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Soukal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Forensics and Security</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-03">Mar. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the error exponent and capacity games of private watermarking systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Somekh-Baruch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Merhav</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="562" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-03">Mar. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the capacity game of public watermarking systems</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-03">Mar. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capacity and random-coding exponents for channel coding with side information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://arxiv.org/abs/cs.IT/0410003" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1326" to="1347" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-04">Apr. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Theory: Coding Theory for Discrete Memoryless Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Csiszár</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Körner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The method of types</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Csiszár</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2505" to="2523" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-10">Oct. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New results on steganographic capacity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Conf. on Inform. Science and Systems</title>
		<meeting>Conf. on Inform. Science and Systems<address><addrLine>Princeton, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-03">Mar. 2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="813" to="818" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reliable communication under channel uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lapidoth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Narayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2148" to="2177" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-10">Oct. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nested linear/lattice codes for structured multiterminal binning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zamir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shamai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Erez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1250" to="1276" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-06">Jun. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The duality between information embedding and source coding with side information and some applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Barron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1159" to="1180" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-05">May 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Perfectly secure steganography: Capacity, error exponents, and code constructions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://arxiv.org/abs/cs.IT/0702161" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-02">Feb. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
