<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic Models Inspired by Hybridization Theory for Short Oligonucleotide Arrays</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zhijin</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rafael</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>615 North Wolfe Street Baltimore</addrLine>
									<postCode>21205</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>615 North Wolfe Street Baltimore</addrLine>
									<postCode>21205</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<address>
									<addrLine>9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 16 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 16 1 1 1 1 1 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 16 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 16 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 16 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 12 9 9 9 9 99 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 16</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic Models Inspired by Hybridization Theory for Short Oligonucleotide Arrays</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">137CA52248CD60168A718653607E0BD2</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T07:56+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>J.3 [Life and medical sciences]: Biology and genetics Affymetrix probe-level data</term>
					<term>background adjustment</term>
					<term>microarrays</term>
					<term>physical models</term>
					<term>stochastic models</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>High density oligonucleotide expression arrays are a widely used tool for the measurement of gene expression on a large scale. Affymetrix GeneChip arrays appear to dominate this market. These arrays use short oligonucleotides to probe for genes in an RNA sample. Due to optical noise, nonspecific hybridization, probe-specific effects, and measurement error, ad-hoc measures of expression, that summarize probe intensities, can lead to imprecise and inaccurate results. Various researchers have demonstrated that expression measures based on simple statistical models can provide great improvements over the ad-hoc procedure offered by Affymetrix. Recently, physical models based on molecular hybridization theory, have been proposed as useful tools for prediction of, for example, non-specific hybridization. These physical models show great potential in terms of improving existing expression measures. In this paper we suggest that the system producing the measured intensities is too complex to be fully described with these relatively simple physical models and we propose empirically motivated stochastic models that compliment the above mentioned molecular hybridization theory to provide a comprehensive description of the data. We discuss how the proposed model can be used to obtain improved measures of expression useful for the data analysts.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In the Affymetrix system, a fair amount of further preprocessing and data reduction occur following the image processing step to obtain measures of gene expression. Background adjustments, normalization, and summarization of the probe level data are three typical steps. The model proposed in this paper is especially useful for the background adjustment step, thus we will focus our discussion on this aspect. However, in Section 6 we briefly discuss how it can be useful for normalization and summarization as well.</p><p>Affymetrix GeneChip arrays use short oligonucleotides (of length 25 bases) to probe for genes in an RNA sample. Each gene will be represented by 11-20 pairs of oligonucleotide probes. The first component of these pairs is referred to as a perfect match (PM) probe and is designed to be specific to transcripts from the intended gene. However, non-specific hybridization and optical noise are unavoidable. Therefore, the observed intensities need to be adjusted to give accurate measurements of specific hybridization. Affymetrix's approach to adjusting is to pair each perfect match probe with a mismatch (MM) probe, that is designed by changing the middle (13th) base, with the intention of measuring only optical background noise and non-specific hybridization (NSB). The default adjustment, provided as part of the Affymetrix system, is based on the difference between perfect match and mismatch probe intensities (P M -M M ).</p><p>A final step in the pre-processing of these arrays is to combine the 11-20 probe pair intensities, after background adjustment and normalization, for a given gene to define a measure of expression that represents the amount of the corresponding mRNA species. Affymetrix's default algorithm, MAS 5.0, is based on a robust average of log(P M -M M * ) values (M M * denotes that some tweaking is performed to avoid logs of non-positives). Various researchers have developed alternative algorithms, motivated by statistical models, that outperform the default algorithm in many applications. For example, Li and Wong <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref> notice a strong probe effect in both P M and P M -M M and describe it via a simple multiplicative model. By analyzing various arrays at once they are able to estimate probe effects and use this to improve outliers detection. Li and Wong also propose a non-linear normalization procedure that improves precision of the default re-scaling approach. Irizarry et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> demonstrate that the log(P M -M M * ) transformation results in gene expression estimates with exaggerated variance. As a practical solution, they propose a global background adjustment step that ignores the M M intensities. This approach sacrifices some accuracy for large gains in precision. After the global background adjustment, arrays are quantile normalized <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref> and a log-scale expression effect plus probe effect model is fitted robustly to define the robust multiarray analysis (RMA) expression measure. Irizarry et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref> and Cope et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref> demonstrate that RMA outperforms MAS 5.0 and the Li and Wong procedure in various practical tasks. RMA has been implemented in the Bioconductor project (http://www.bioconductor.org) affy package <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>, Iobion's Genetraffic (http://www.iobion.com), and Insightful's S+ArrayAnalyzer (http://www.insightful.com) and has become a popular alternative to the default algorithm provided by Affymetrix. Various other similar algorithms have been proposed <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24]</ref>. In Section 6 we will argue that the model described in this paper can be used to improve the accuracy of these methods, without much sacrifice in precision.</p><p>A simple version of our model can be written as P M = O + N + S with P M the measured intensity of a particu-lar PM probe, O representing optical background noise for this probe, N representing NSB and S represents observed specific signal. Similar models have been proposed by, for example, Hekstra et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref> and Zhang, Miles and Aldape <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref>. A deterministic model that motivates Affymetrix's approach to background adjustment would be M M = O + N which would imply that P M -M M = S. However, in Section 2 we demonstrate that a stochastic model is more appropriate. In this case, P M = O (P M ) + N (P M ) + S and M M = O (M M ) + N (M M ) where O (P M ) + N (P M ) and O (M M ) + N (M M ) have similar expectations but are not perfectly correlated. In this case the difference log</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(P M -M M * ) is approximately unbiased, since E[P M -M M ] ≈ S, but may have a large variance var[log(P M -M M * )].</formula><p>In Section 2 we demonstrate that the O + N component of the P M and M M are not perfectly correlated, thus var[log(P M )] &lt;&lt; var[log(P M -M M * )]. In part this explains why PM-only measures, such as RMA, are more precise than measures based on P M -M M , such as MAS 5.0. Irizarry et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> empirically show that for low intensity probes the variance of the difference log(P M -M M * ) can be considerably larger than that of log(P M ). Furthermore, in general, M M &gt; P M for roughly 40% of all probes and this is problematic because we know S is strictly positive. These facts have led some researchers to consider P M -only measures. However, because O and N are strictly positive, not correcting for optical noise and NSB can lead to biased </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(P M ) 1 + N (P M ) 1 + kµ1)/(O (P M ) 2 + N (P M ) 2 + kµ2).</formula><p>Thus, as the kµ1 and kµ2 become smaller, as compared to the the strictly positive mean of the background components O and N , the estimated fold change converges to 1. This results in attenuated fold change estimates. RMA performs a global background adjustment that improves accuracy over non-background adjusted methods. However, as we will discuss later, different probes have different propensities to NSB which implies RMA does not fully account for NSB. In this paper we develop a model that predicts the behavior of optical noise, NSB, and specific binding very well. We use hybridization theory from molecular biology together along with data from carefully designed experiments to motivate the model. We also propose a model for the distribution of the specific signal S intensities within an array. This model can be used to improve existing expression measures and provides theoretical explanations for various facts observed in practice, for example: 1) M M &gt; P M for a considerable amount of probes, 2) log(P M -M M * ) has much larger variance than log(P M ) when S is small, and 3) log(P M -M M * ) is more accurate than log(P M ) when S is small.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">EMPIRICALLY MOTIVATED STOCHASTIC MODELS</head><p>In this Section we use publicly available data and data from our own experiments to motivate some of the components of our stochastic models. The first of these data sets is the Affymetrix spike-in experiments. These experiments are described in detail, for example, by Irizarry et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> and Cope et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>. For this experiment, human cRNA fragments matching 16 probe-sets on one of the Affymetrix human chips were added to a hybridization mixture at concentrations ranging from 0 to 1024 picoMolar in a design similar to a Latin square. Apart from the spiked-in probesets, the same RNA mixture was hybridized to 59 arrays. Because we know the spike-in concentrations, it is possible to identify statistical features of the data for which the expected outcome is known in advance. The second data come from what we call the empty chip experiment. For this experiment, sample RNA control from human embryonic kidney derived cells was not labeled, but hybridized following the Affymetrix protocol. Because the RNA was not labeled, the observed intensities for this hybridization will represent optical noise in the presence of biological sample. Finally, the third data come from what we call the NSB experiment. For this experiment, yeast control RNA was hybridized to an array probing for human genes. This hybridization will represent the full component of the noise, NSB and optical noise. These two experiments are described in more detail in Wu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Optical noise</head><p>Data from the empty chip experiment (not-shown) appear to follow a normal distribution with mean of roughly 30 and standard deviation (SD) of roughly 2. This motivates modeling the first component of our model, the optical noise component, as normally distributed.</p><p>By using a log-scale transformation before analyzing microarray data, a great number of investigators have, implicitly or explicitly, proposed a multiplicative measurement error model <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20]</ref> for microarray data. A slightly more complicated additive background multiplicative measurement error model has been proposed by, for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6,</ref><ref type="bibr">8]</ref>. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref> we see observed P M log (base 2) intensities from the spike-in data plotted against their nominal log (base 2) concentration. The solid line shows the median value for each concentration. Notice that this line looks very Figure <ref type="figure">2a</ref> shows SD of probe intensities, computed across 28 replicate arrays, plotted against the respective average intensity. Figure <ref type="figure">2b</ref> shows the same plot for log intensities. The mean-variance dependence that is removed by applying a log transformation is a strong argument for a multiplicative error model. We therefore propose using an additive background multiplicative measurement error model.</p><p>Because the standard deviation of the optical noise is so small, as compared, for example, to the range of intensities, we will assume it is constant and correct for it by simply subtracting the minimum probe intensity (and adding 1 to avoid logs of 0). In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref> we see the median intensities for each nominal concentration, as in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, for the P M and the P M adjusted for optical noise (along with other adjustments described later). We expect the curves in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref> to be lines with slope 1, since every time the nominal concentration doubles observed concentration should double. We fit a line to the curve in this Figure and the slope for the P M intensities is 0.51. For the adjusted P M we have a slope of 0.59. The background adjustment slightly improves accuracy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Non-specific binding</head><p>Molecular hybridization theory predicts that short oligonucleotides will hybridize to non-complementary transcripts.</p><p>Our data from the NSB experiment support this. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5a</ref> demonstrate a log-scale scatter plot of optical noise adjusted P M s versus optical noise adjusted M M s. This plot demonstrates intensities due to NSB are larger (by orders of magnitude) than those obtained just from optical noise. Because in this data there is no specific signal, if in fact the M M are an exact measure of the NSB captured by the P M then the predictive power of the M M should be 1 and this plot should have no scatter. However, as expected, we do see scatter. The relative predictive power or R 2 for this scatter plot is 0.71. Although not perfect, the large R 2 suggest that there is information on NSB to be extracted from the M M . Notice also that Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5a</ref> seems to suggest that after adjustment for optical noise the NSB component of the P M, M M pairs appear to follow a bivariate normal distribution.</p><p>To see that NSB is an additive effect more than it is a multiplicative effect, we adjusted the P M by subtracting and by dividing the M M . The resulting median intensity of P M -M M is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>. The estimated slope is 0.90 which is a good improvement over the non-adjusted P M . The P M/M M adjustment is very inaccurate (not shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>). The slope is only about 0.14. This suggest that NSB is an additive effect more than it is a multiplicative effect.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref> we show a smooth curve demonstrating the over-all log-scale SD, across 28 replicate arrays, as a function of average log intensity, for the different adjustments. Notice that the P M -M M adjustment is very noisy, especially at the low end. The loss of precision is quite significant; the median SD grows from 0.20 for non-adjusted P M , to 0.36  for optical noise adjusted P M , to 0.91 for P M -M M . The loss in accuracy of ignoring the M M is not as drastic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Specific Signal</head><p>Li and Wong <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref> demonstrate that, even after subtracting M M , there is a strong probe effect. Notice in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> that the range of probe intensities measuring the same nominal amount of RNA cover various orders of magnitude. In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> we use color and numbers to denote the same probes. The probes that have, on average bigger effects, are shown in yellowish colors, those with lower values in blue colors. The fact that the blue are always at the bottom, the yellow at the top demonstrate the strong and consistent probe effects. The fact that Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> is a log-scale plot, suggests that their exists a multiplicative probe effect as well as the measurement error.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> better illustrate the size of the probe effects compared to the differential expression effect sizes. This Figure shows probe intensity on the y-axis (logged) against probe number on the x-axis (ordered by proximity to the 5' end of the target transcript), for one probeset. The two lines represent the intensities read on two arrays where this particular probe-set was spiked-in at 4 and 8 picoMolar respectively. This plot clearly shows that probe effects are huge compared to array effects. Other probe-sets behave similarly (data not shown).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">PHYSICAL MODELS</head><p>Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref> propose a stacking energy, positionaldependent-nearest-neighbor (PDNN) model for RNA/DNA duplex formed on microarrays. Their energy model takes into account the sequence of nearest-neighbors (adjacent two bases) and the position of these nucleotide pairs. It has been suggested that the effect of nearest-neighbor nucleotide pairs is the most important factor in determining RNA/DNA duplex stability. Zhang et al. add a positional weight factor to reflect the different contributions from different parts of the probe.</p><p>The energies for gene-specific binding (signal specific probe effect) and NSB of the j-th probe in i-th probe-set is thus calculated as, Eij =  <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref> then proceed to describe the P M intensity of the j-th probe in i-th probe-set as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">P Mij = Si/{1 + exp(Eij)} + N * /{1 + exp(E * ij )} + O,</formula><p>where Si is the number of expressed mRNA molecules of gene i, and Si/{1 + exp(Eij)} is the contribution from gene specific binding. N * is population of RNA molecules contributing to NSB for the entire array, and N * /{1+exp(E * ij )} is the contribution to intensity of j-th probe in i-th probeset. The weights (ω k s) are estimated empirically (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref> for more details).</p><p>Naef and Magnasco <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref> propose a simpler model to describe the probe effect, that considers only the sequence composition of the probes. Affinity of a probe is described as the sum of position-dependent base affinities:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Affinity = 25 k=1 j∈{A,T,G,C} µ j,k 1 b k =j with µ j,k = 3 l=0 β j,l k l</formula><p>where j is the base letter index, k = 1, . . . , 25 indicates the position along the probe, b k represents the base at position k as before, 1 b k =j is an indicator function, and µ j,k represents the effect of having base j in position k. Naef and Magnasco <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref> make the model more parsimonious by assuming that the µ j,k follow a polynomial of degree 3 as a function of position k. Their model is fitted to many arrays at once to obtain an affinity value for each sequence. We adapt this model to describe non-specific binding by fitting the model to our NSB experiment data and by modeling the µ j,k as spline functions with 5 degrees of freedom. Notice that this model does not take into accout the interactions between nearest neighbors. Naef and Magnasco <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref> demonstrate the these interactions for add much predictive power for specific signal probe effects. We find the same is true when predicting NSB. Notice also this model predicts that for certain probes the hybridization strength of the M M ill be stronger than the P M which implies P M -M M is only an approximately unbiased estimate of S.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5b</ref> and 5c we plot the optical noise adjusted log 2 (P M )s from the NSB data set against Naef and Magnasco's affinities and Zhang's PDNN log 2 (N * ) -log 2 (1 + exp(E * ij )). Notice that Naef and Magnasco's affinities predict the NSB almost as well as the M M . The R 2 is 0.62. Zhang's PDNN also does relatively well with an R 2 of 0.28. However, notice that the slope of the PDNN model scatter plot is not 1.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> demonstrates that these physical models can not predict NSB perfectly. However, they motivate a simple stochastic model. In Section 4 we propose a model that describes the NSB contribution as log-normal distributed with log-scale mean proportional to Naef and Magnasco's affinities. The two parameters describing this relationship is estimated from the data and not predicted using physical models. The model works similarly when using Zhang's -log 2 (1 + exp(E * ij )) as the affinity measure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Specific Signal</head><p>Irizarry et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref> postulate a log-scale additive model for the specific signal component of the probe level data: log(Sij) = si + αj + ij , i = 1, . . . , I, and j = 1, . . . .J Here si represents log scale expression (the quantity of interest), αj represents the probe effect, and ij is the multiplicative measurement error. This model fits very well in practice and if one has enough arrays the probe effects αj can be efficiently estimated <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref>. As described above, Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref> and Naef and Magnasco <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref> describe physical models useful for predicting αj from the probe sequence. For example, we could add the further assumption that alphaj = Affinity j β. However, as described in section 6, it is also useful to describe the within array distribution of the si. This distribution will vary somewhat among RNA sources, and varies greatly among chip designs and other processing and hybridization factors. In this section we describe a parametric distribution useful for describing the empirical distribution of si.</p><p>Wu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref> notice that for a wide variety of arrays (including arrays hybridized to samples of various type from humans, mice, and rats) the distribution of the specific signal for probe intensities can be well approximated with a power-law distribution. Observed intensities contain components of both the background noise and the signal. However, for higher intensities, where background has little effect, we observe that log frequency versus log rank plots fall on a line with slope near 1, as predicted by a power law, specifically by Zipf's Law <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>. This distribution has also been observed empirically in SAGE data <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref>.</p><p>Wu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref> demonstrate that a log-exponential distribution (a special case of Zipf's law) appropriately predicts the signal. If this assumption holds then we can write:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Pr(si &lt; s) = 1 -exp(s/α), α ≈ 1.</formula><p>Although we do not expect this assumption to hold true for all hybridization, we do find it useful in many instances.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">UNIFIED PHYSICAL/STOCHASTIC MODEL</head><p>The described physical models perform relatively well at predicting NSB and, as will become apparent, the distribution of the specific signal. However, the predictions are not perfect and are complimented well with stochastic versions. The system producing intensities is very complicated and we argue that one can use physical models to approximate the process relatively well, but the lack-of-fit is best described with a stochastic model.</p><p>Our model for the P M intensity contains NSB and specific signal components that on the probe sequence composition as described by the physical models. The model can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">P Mj = Oj + Nj + Sj where Oj ∼ Normal(bo, σ 2 o ), log(Nj) ∼ Normal(bN (Aj), σ<label>2</label></formula><p>N ), and log(Sj) = s+Ajβ+ j . Here bN (Aj) is a smooth function of Aj, and s ∼ Exponential(1). We assume independence across probes. For the M M we assume the same model except for the lack of the Sj:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">M Mj = Oj + Nj.</formula><p>Furthermore, we assume that the P M and M M log(Nj) have a correlation of 0.7 (what we observe in the NSB experiment).</p><p>Notice that this model is defined by only few parameters and that we have over 200,000 probe intensities to fit them. One can use maximum likelihood estimation to do this. However, writing down the likelihood for this model is complicated as it involved a convolution of 3 densities. We have developed some ad-hoc procedures to estimate the parameters that yield very good fits.</p><p>To estimate the parameters for the background model, we notice that σ 2 o &lt;&lt; σ 2 N , thus we can assume that optical noise is approximately constant (σo ≈ 0) which implies that bo is approximately equal to the minimum observed intensity. Our estimate is thus bo = min{minj P Mj, minj M Mj} -1 (we subtract 1 to avoid nonpositive adjusted values). We then construct the intensities adjusted for optical noise: P M j = P Mj -bo, M M j = M Mj -bo on an array. If we assume that the M M s do not measure specific signal, then Pr(P Mj &lt; M Mj) ≈ Pr{P M j &lt; bN (Aj)}. Because bN (Aj) is assumed to be a smooth function of Aj, we can estimate bN (Aj) by considering a neighborhood, {P M k , k ∈ Λj}, with k ∈ Λj if A k is "close" to Aj, define the quantile q = Pr(P Mj &lt; M Mj) ≈ 1 #{Λj} k∈Λ 1P M k &lt;M M k , and then define the estimate bN (Aj) as the q-th quantile of the log(P M k ), k ∈ Λ k probe intensity empirical distribution. Because we know that the N (Aj) is an increasing function we force it to be monotonic using the pool-adjacent-violators (PAV) algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1]</ref>. σ 2 N can be estimated using the negative residuals P M k -bN (Aj) (the positive residuals will contain part of the signal Sj). Finally, the β parameter can be estimated by simply regressing the P M j on Aj. We estimate the N (Aj) for the M Mj similarly but because we assume the M Mj do not detect signal we use q = 0.5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">RESULTS</head><p>We fitted the model as described in the previous Section. The model fits extremely well. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6a</ref> shows kernel density estimates of the P M intensities for one of the spike-in arrays along with the predicted distribution from the model. Notice that this model has less than 10 parameters (the smooth function fit uses about 4 degrees of freedom) and 200,000 data points so over-fitting is not a concern. Furthermore, the model is based on molecular hybridization theory. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6b</ref> shows a quantile-quantile plot that confirms the good fit.</p><p>In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3c</ref> and 3d we present the results shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref> and 3b but instead of real data we use data simulated from our model. Notice the similarity between the real and simulated results. Our model predicts that, for low intensity probes, log(P M -M M * ) is a low precision transformation and that log(P M ) is a low accuracy transformation. This suggests that our proposed model can be used for simulations related to statistical procedures based on Affymetrix data. For example, one could use it decide among different test statistics (Wilcoxon, t-test, SAM, etc...) Finally, we point out that under this model, as fitted to this array, predicts the probability of a M M &gt; P M to be 0.40 which is exactly what we see empirically. Thus having many M M &gt; P M is not necessarily a bad thing. It is just a consequence of the noisy character of the system and the differenct in affinities for different sequences. Both these issues can be dealt with statistically.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">DISCUSSION</head><p>We have presented a stochastic model motivated by molecular hybridization theory that fits Affymetrix GeneChip probe level data very well. Apart from giving a theoretical explanation for various facts observed in practice, this model can also be used to improve expression measures. For example, once we have fitted the model, we could correct for optical noise and NSB by computing the expectation of S given that we have observed a P M and M M . An approach such as this has been used by Wu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref> with very encouraging results. Wu et al. describe an expression measure algorithm similar to RMA but using a model such as the one described here to adjust for background. Their expression measure is about as precise as RMA but more accurate. In fact, it is more accurate than MAS 5.0. Notice that this model can also be used for normalization and summarization. The fact that we have a prior distribution for the specific signal component suggest that one could use the log-exponential as the reference distribution used in quantile normalization. Furthermore, by incorporating information about probe-sets in the model (i.e. which probes represent which genes) one could directly obtain MLE estimates of expression measures from the model. One aspect that is not described by our model is the existence of outliers probes. This is subject of future work.</p><p>Finally, we point out that the described model motivates a P M -only expression measure that can be as accurate as those that use M M (such as MAS 5.0). In Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>  This adjustment has similar precision to P M -M M but slightly better accuracy. Notice this adjustment does not depend on M Mj, except for that fact that we used to them to obtain the quantile q used to estimate bN (Aj). Although there is complimentary information in the M M and in the affinities, P M -only measures are attractive for various reasons, for example: 1) We can have twice as many probes on the chips and 2) the M M seems to detect signal as demonstrated by Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>. Using our model one could obtain roughly the same accuracy without the need for M M probes.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref> demonstrates that the gains in accuracy presented by the use of our model is not only a global result. The figure demonstrates that for almost all probes accuracy is improved by subtracting out the optical and NSB effects.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Signal detection by PM and MM probes in the Latin-square spike-in experiment. a). log 2 (P M ) intensities of spike-in genes plotted against concentration. Number indicate the order of each probe within probesets, each number is associated with a color for probesets. The line shows median log 2 (P M ) for each concentration. The dashed lines is the same median but for each probe-set. b). Same as a) but for MM intensities.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :(P M ) 1 +N 2 +</head><label>212</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Standard deviation of probe intensity in original scale (a) and log scale (b) plotted a</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Global accuracy and precision of various background adjustments. a) Log median adjusted intensity plotted against log concentration. b) Standard deviation of log adjusted intensity plotted against log concentration. Adjusted intensities resulting in negative values are ignored. c) As a) but with simulated data. d) as b) but with simulated data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Probe log (base 2) intensities for the same probe set on two arrays spiked in at 4 and 8 pico-Molar respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>24 k=1ω</head><label>24</label><figDesc>k (b k , b k+1 ) b k , b k+1 ), respectively, where ω k , ω * k are weights, (b k , b k+1 ), * (b k , b k+1 ) are nearest-neighbor stacking energies, and b k is the base (A, T, G, or C) at position k. Zhang et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Intensity prediction ability comparison. a) Optical noise adjusted log 2 (P M ) intensity plotted against optical noise adjusted log 2 (M M ) intensity. b) Optical noise adjusted log 2 (P M ) against Naef 's predicted affinity. c) Optical noise adjusted log 2 (P M ) against PDNN predicted non-specific binding.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Simulation result. a). Kernel density estimates of simulated PM intensity and PM intensity from Latin-square spike-in experiment. b). Quantile quantile plot of PM intensity from Latin-square spike-in experiment against simulated PM intensity.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Boxplots show distribution of probespecific fitted observed versus nominal log-scale slopes for different background adjustments. The scatterlots compare these slope for PM-MM, RMA, and the procedure described in this paper. Each point represents a probe.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>we show the global accuracy of the background adjustment defined by P Mj -Ê[Oj +Nj] ≡ P Mj -bo -exp bN (Aj)</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_0"><p>3 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_1"><p>3 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>3 3 3 3 3 3 3 3 3 3 3 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank Ben Bolstad, Felix Naef, Terry Speed, Li Zhang, and the reviewers for helpful comments and ideas that motivated and improved this extended abstract. We would also like to thank Forrest Spencer and Francisco Martinez-Murillo who helped us design and ran the experiments for us. Finally we would like to thank the R and Bioconductor developers for providing great software, specifically Robert Gentleman and Wolfgang Huber for developing the software to deal with sequence information.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>References</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The isotonic regression problem and its dual</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Barlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brunk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="140" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Denoising of data from serial analysis of gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Blades</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Parmigiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>page To appear.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of normalization methods for high density oligonucleotide array data based on bias and variance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bolstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Astrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Speed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic statistical linear modeling approach to oligonucleotide array experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wolfinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A benchmark for affymetrix genechip expression measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jaffee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Speed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/ri-rizarr/papers/index.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data transformations for cDNA microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Churchill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistical Applications in Genetics and Molecular Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical methods for identifying differentially expressed genes in replicated cDNA microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dudoit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Callow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Speed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistica Sinica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A variance-stabilizing transformation for gene-expression microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Durbin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hardin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hawkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rocke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. 1):S105-S110</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Absolute mRNA concentrations from sequence-specific calibration of oligonucleotide array</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hekstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Taussig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magnasco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1962" to="1968" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical analysis of high density oligonucleotide arrays: a SAFER approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Holder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Raubertas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Pikounis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Svetnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Soper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ASA Annual Meeting</title>
		<meeting>the ASA Annual Meeting<address><addrLine>Atlanta, GA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variance stabilization applied to microarray data calibration and to the quantification of differential expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Heydebreck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sultmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Poustka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vingron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploration, normalization, and summaries of high density oligonucleotide array probe level data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C B</forename><surname>Hobbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Beaxer-Barclay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Antonellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Scherf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Speed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="264" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An R package for analyses of affymetrix oligonucleotide arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gautier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cope</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Analysis of Gene Expression Data: Methods and Software</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Parmigiani</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Garrett</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zeger</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Summaries of affymetrix genechip probe level data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bolstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Collin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hobbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Speed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of variance for gene expression microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Churchill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="819" to="837" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based analysis of oligonucleotide arrays: Expression index computation and outlier detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the National Academy of Science U S A</title>
		<meeting>the National Academy of Science U S A</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="36" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">From features to expression: High density oligonucleotide array analysis revisited</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Patil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Magnasco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solving the riddle of the bright mismatches: labeling and effective binding in oligonucleotide arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Magnasco</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review E</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11906</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On differential variability of expression ratios: improving statistical inference about gene expression changes from microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Newton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kendziorski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Richmond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Blattner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">52</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing gene significance from cDNA microarray expression data via mixed models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wolfinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wolfinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hamadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bushel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Afshari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Paules</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="625" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new non-linear normalization method for reducing variability in DNA microarray experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Workman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jarmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Berka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gautier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Saxild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brunak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Knudsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model based background adjustment for oligonucleotide expression arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gentleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.bepress.com/jhubiostat/paper1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Dept. of Biostatistics Working Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Johns Hopkins University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model of molecular interactions on short oligonucleotide microarrays: implications for probe design and data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Aldape</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Biotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="818" to="821" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new algorithm for analysis of oligonucleotide arrays: application to expression profiling in mouse brain regions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ravindranathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Bio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">317</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Behaviour and the principle of least effort</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zipf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1949">1949</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
