<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">In-Network Caching Effect on Optimal Energy Consumption in Content-Centric Networking</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nakjung</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Alcatel-Lucent</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Bell-Labs</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">South Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kyle</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Alcatel-Lucent</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Bell-Labs</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Holmdel</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kilper</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Alcatel-Lucent</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Bell-Labs</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Holmdel</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Atkinson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Alcatel-Lucent</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Bell-Labs</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Holmdel</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">In-Network Caching Effect on Optimal Energy Consumption in Content-Centric Networking</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">538D54714EF21A35586CBDCF3B5DEA53</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T09:15+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In content-centric networking (CCN), the innetwork caching feature provides several attractive advantages such as low dissemination latency and network transport load reduction. Thus, CCN requires less transport energy but additional energy to provide a caching capability at every content router. In this paper, we investigate the minimum energy consumption that CCN can achieve with optimal cache locations by considering different caching hardware technologies, number of downloads per hour, and content popularity. We first set up an energy consumption model for CCN and then formulate linear and nonlinear programming problems to minimize total energy consumption of CCN. Also, a genetic algorithm (GA) approach is proposed to find energy-efficient cache locations. Using reported energy efficiency of computational hardware and network equipment, we show CCN yield greater energy savings for very popular content and small-sized catalog, compared to conventional CDN. Our results also indicate that two aspects of the memory technology, energy-proportional caching and sufficient memory capacity, are critical to the overall energy efficiency gain of CCN.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Recently, content-centric networking (CCN) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> has begun to attract much attention as a promising Future Internet architecture, adapting the network architecture to current network usage patterns, i.e., data dissemination. This novel networking paradigm can be characterized by two major features: routingby-name and in-network caching. Routing-by-name enables a content, not the host, to become a first-class citizen of the network, so a single content can be retrieved from multiple locations inherently. In-network caching contributes to low dissemination latency and network load reduction. At the protocol level, data delivery in CCN is driven by the consumers of data using an Interest packet. A user requests a content by broadcasting its interest to the network and then any content router hearing the interest and having data that satisfies it can respond with a Data packet. Data is retrieved only in the response to an interest so a single Interest packet corresponds to a single Data packet in each link.</p><p>In terms of energy efficiency, CCN potentially results in less transport energy by effectively reducing the distances to content and eliminating duplicated transmissions <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. However, CCN incurs additional energy consumption in providing a caching capability at every content router. Various different kinds of memory technologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> can realize in-network caching, each with differing power efficiency (watt/bit) and size. Generally, however, there is an inverse relationship between the transport energy and the in-network caching energy.</p><p>In this paper, we investigate the minimum energy consumption that CCN can achieve with optimal cache locations depending on the caching hardware technology and the content download rate, which can eventually give a target number for implementations and some guidance for designing practical distributed caching algorithms. For this purpose, the minimum energy consumption of CCN is formulated and analyzed by integer linear programming (ILP), nonlinear programming (NLP), and a heuristic method. In our work, we focus only on energy efficiency regarding to data delivery and storage, that is, we do not consider energy consumption caused by other computations, e.g., name lookup and security.</p><p>The energy benefit of CCN has been studied previously in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> [4] <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, the CCN architecture and its energy efficiency are evaluated via trace-based simulations. The authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> investigated the feasibility of deploying CCN in edge and core networks from both the cost and energy perspective. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, we provided a preliminary assessment of the relative energy benefit of CCN in comparison with other content delivery architectures. This paper represents a more extensive and in-depth treatment, with the emphasis on studying the impact of different memory technologies on the overall energy efficiency.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. In Section II, we describe network, content popularity, and energy models. In Section III, we provide mathematical formulations and a heuristic to minimize the total energy consumption. In Section IV, we evaluate the impact of different caching hardware technologies and traffic intensity on (near-)optimal energy consumption of CCN.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. MODELS FOR ANALYSIS</head><p>In this section, we briefly describe network, content popularity, and energy models (some of which were presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>) to keep this paper self-contained.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Network Model</head><p>A CCN network consists of N content routers and, in a steady state, n (≤ N ) copies of a content element are cached at n content routers. As a result, N -n content routers have to access content via one or more hops. Thus, the average hop distance to the content, H c ≥ 0, is an important measure of the cache location efficiency. The exact form of H c depends on both a network topology and a cache location algorithm. We use a hypothetical continental US backbone network US64<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> to represent the topological characteristics of commercial networks. For this irregular and asymmetric network, we take a semi-analytical approach in deriving H c as a power-law function of n. We first numerically compute the average hop distance to a content element by using a genetic algorithm approach to find (near-)optimal cache locations for n copies of a content. The process is repeated for every 1 ≤ n ≤ N . Then, we fit the computed data to the function</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">H c (n) = A (N/n) α , with α &gt; 0.</formula><p>For US64, H c can be estimated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">0.36(N/n) 0.6 [6] 2 .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Content Popularity Model</head><p>We assume that a content provider has a content catalog of size F , ranked from one (the most popular) to F (the least popular) based on its popularity. By letting the total number of requests in a given time duration t be R, the number of requests to the content of popularity k, R k , follows a Zipflike distribution as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">R k = R k -β F k=1 k -β = R a 0 k -β , (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">)</formula><p>where a 0 is a constant to normalize the request rate. A large value for β indicates a catalog that contains relatively small set of very popular contents. Typically, values of β range between 0.5 and 1.0 <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Energy Consumption Model of CCN</head><p>We assume an ideal case in which content routers carry out the tasks of content servers <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. In this case, the content servers holding the original contents are infrequently accessed so we do not consider their energy consumption. The total energy consumed by CCN, E CCN tot , consists of two major parts: the caching energy E ca and the transport energy E tr .</p><p>1) Caching Energy, E ca : We use an energy-proportional model. Assuming that the size of content element k is B k , if n k copies of element k are cached for a duration of t, the energy consumed by caching n k B k bits is given by  where w ca is the power efficiency of caching. The value of w ca strongly depends on the caching hardware technology. In this paper, we consider high-speed solid state disk (SSD), dynamic random access memory (DRAM), reduced latency DRAM (RLDRAM), static random access memory (SRAM), and ternary content-addressable memory (TCAM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. The energy efficiency and maximum size values for these technologies are listed in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>. Note that for the scenarios considered in this paper, the size of memory used for content indexing is much smaller compared to that used in caching content <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Hence the associated energy consumption is not considered here.</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">E ca k (n k ) = n k w ca B k t,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>2) Transport Energy, E tr : Although parallel transmission to retrieve a single content is possible according to a policy set at the strategy layer, to simplify our energy efficiency models with optimal cache locations we assume that a user acquires any one content from a single content router. Further, we assume each content router sends a content request to the closest content router with an original content or its copy. Those assumptions are reasonable because we are interested in an optimal case in terms of energy efficiency.</p><p>The transport energy includes the energy consumption in core and edge networks. We assume that for a duration of t, the k th -most popular content (of size B k ) is downloaded R k times. To clarify discussion, we summarize the notations and values for key energy efficiency parameters of transport equipments in Table <ref type="table">II</ref>.</p><p>Similar to the models used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, the core transport energy E tr,c k is expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">E tr,c k (H c ) = 4B k (1 + η)R k [(p r d + p roadm d )(H c + 1) +p wdm d H c ],<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where η is the signaling overhead, e.g., Interest packets. In CCN <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, η is defined by bin b pkt where b in and b pkt denote the size of an Interest packet and a Data packet, respectively. In our analysis, b in = 40 and b pkt = 1500 bytes give η ≈ 0.03. Also, a factor of four is to account for redundancy and cooling <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, for simplicity neglecting differences in overhead used for different equipments. Since the network topology follows the power-law scaling as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">H c (n k ) = A(N/n k ) α , we have E tr,c k (n k ) = 4B k R k (1 + η)[(p r d + p roadm d )(A(N/n k ) α +1) + p wdm d A(N/n k ) α ].<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Similar to the models used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, E e tr has the following form. Note that E e tr can be regarded as a constant because it does not depend on n.</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">E tr,e k = 4B k R k (1 + η)[3p e d + p g d + 2p pe d ]<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Thus the transport energy E tr k is the sum of E tr,c k and E tr,e k .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) Comparison to conventional CDN:</head><p>A conventional content distribution network (CDN) delivers content by employing a server (holding original content) as well as storage facilities distributed in the network (holding a copy of the content). Thus, the total energy consumption E CDN tot can be calculated by adding the server energy E sr , the storage energy E st , and the transport energy E tr . E sr is given as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">E sr = B k R k p s d .<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Similar to Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">2</ref>), the energy for storing content element k (denoted as E st k ) is given as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">E st k (n k ) = n k w st B k t, (<label>7</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">)</formula><p>where w st is the power efficiency of storage. We assume that a CDN is normally based on high-speed SSD for storage, so we set the value w st to 6.25 × 10 -12 (watt/bit) for the reference CDN case. The model of the transport energy for a CDN is exactly the same as that of a CCN (c.f., Eqs. (3-5)).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. PROBLEM FORMULATIONS AND SOLUTIONS</head><p>In this section, we first provide ILP and NLP formulations that minimize the total energy consumption of CCN. Then, we propose a genetic algorithm (GA) approach to find (near-)optimal cache locations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Integer Linear Programming (ILP) Formulation</head><p>To begin, we define the following quantities that can be pre-computed by combining knowledge of the given topology, traffic, and energy efficiency of network equipments.</p><p>• N , the number of content routers in CCN;</p><p>• i and j, index of a content router, with i, j = 1, ..., N ; • d ij hop distance between content router i and j; • S j , the maximum cache size at content router j; • F , the catalog size;</p><p>• k, index of a catalog element, with k = 1, ..., F ; • B k , the size of element k; • R ik , the download rate of element k at content router i;</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">• a ijk ≡ R i,k B k [(d ij + 1)(p r d + p roadm d ) + d ij p wdm d</formula><p>], the energy for transporting the k th content element from j to i; • b k ≡ w ca tB k , k th content storage energy for duration t.</p><p>We introduce the following variables:</p><p>• x ijk : x ijk takes the value of 1 if content router i downloads a copy of element k from content router j, and 0 otherwise. • y jk : y jk takes the value of 1 if content router j caches a copy of element k, and 0 otherwise.</p><p>Then, the formulation is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">min x,y : F k=1 N i=1 N j=1 a ijk x ijk + F k=1 N j=1 b k y jk s.t. : N j x ijk = 1, ∀(i, k), x ijk ≤ y jk , ∀(i, j, k), F k=1 B k y jk ≤ S j , ∀j, x ijk ∈ {0, 1}, y jk ∈ {0, 1}.<label>(8)</label></formula><p>In this ILP, the objective function consists of two terms for the transport and caching energy, respectively. The first constraint N j x ijk = 1 specifies that each content router i downloads element k from only one content router (no parallel downloading of an element from multiple content routers). The second constraint x ijk ≤ y jk specifies that content router i can download element k from content router j only when that content element is located there. Finally, the third constraint F k=1 B k y jk ≤ j specifies that the size of the elements located on content router j should not exceed the maximum cache size of the content router. We note that the number of variables and constraints of the ILP formulation grows approximately as N 2 F . How to efficiently solve this ILP for the network and catalog sizes that we are interested in (i.e., N =64 and F =1000) is left for future research. Instead, in the next two subsections we examine different aspects of the problem by providing a NLP formulation that can be solved analytically and a GA approach, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Nonlinear Programming (NLP) Formulation</head><p>In this section, we focus on the optimal caching capacity allocated for each content element, but not the optimal cache location. We assume that each content router has the same maximum cache size of S (S j =S) and each content element has the same size B (B k =B). We denote n k as the number of copies for element k. For simplicity, we remove the integer constraint of n k . The caching capacity constrained optimiza-tion problem can be formulated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">min n k F k=1 E CCN k (n k ) = F k=1 (E tr k (n k ) + E ca k (n k )) s.t.: 1 ≤ n k ≤ N, n k ∈ R, F k=1 n k ≤ N S B .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Note that the constraint F k=1 n k ≤ NS/B indicates that the total size of cached content should not exceed the total cache capacity. Since each content element needs to be cached at least once to be served by CCN, the total cache capacity satisfies NS ≥ F B.</p><p>The optimal n k , denoted as n * k can be derived as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">n * k = max[1, min[n • k * , n k , N]],<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where n • k * and n k are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">n • k * = 4AR k (p r d + p roadm d + p wdm d ) tw ca 1 α+1 N α α+1 (11) n * k = R 1 1+α k k R 1 1+α k NS B . (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_16">)</formula><p>Finally, the optimal total energy consumption is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">E * tot = F k=1 E CCN k (n * k ).<label>(13)</label></formula><p>The derivation follows the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker optimality condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, thus is omitted here for brevity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. GA Approach</head><p>In the last section we focused on cache sizing for each content without regard to cache locations in the network. Here, a genetic algorithm (GA) approach is used to provide solutions for energy-efficient cache locations. A GA is an example of so-called evolutionary computing approaches to random search inspired by a biological analog of repeated natural selection and mutation among a population of individuals over multiple generations <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. In our case, an individual represents a candidate solution for content cache locations in the network. Specifically, we let s k = {s k1 s k2 ...s kN } be the binary string representing the cache locations for content k, where s ki = 1 if a copy of content k is located at content router i and s ki = 0 if it is not. The first generation of the GA is an initial population of M (M is an even number) such individuals, each of which is the string representation of random cache locations. Starting with the first generation, the population evolution proceeds as follows. First, the survival fitness value of each individual is evaluated. For our purposes here the fitness value is the transport and caching energy consumption for content k, denoted E fit k , and is calculated as follows: where c ik = min</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">E fit k = N i=1 c ik + N i=1 s ik b k ,<label>(14)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">{j|s j,k =1}</formula><p>a ijk . The remaining steps of the proposed GA follow standard procedures of GA <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, in which M candidate solutions evolve toward solutions with lower energy use via iterative operations such as cross-cover and mutation. Hence, the detailed description is omitted here for brevity. Note that the GA runs for each content element separately and the cache size is not enforced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. NUMERICAL RESULTS</head><p>In this section, we evaluate the impact of the caching power efficiency and the maximum cache size on the optimal total energy per bit, based on the formulations and heuristic in Section III. We also study a tradeoff between the transport delay requirement and the total energy consumption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Impact of Caching Power Efficiency on Optimal Total Energy per Bit</head><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, we plot the optimal total energy per bit of CCN as a function of the power efficiency of different caching hardware technologies, for different catalog sizes and download rates. The results are obtained by numerical evaluation of Eqs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr">(13)</ref>. Note that here we are interested in energy efficiency of different caching hardware technologies, thus we do not enforce the maximum cache size in the calculation. In this case, we can simplify Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> as</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">n * k = max[1, min[n • k * , N</formula><p>]] and substitute it into Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_17">13</ref>) for optimal energy calculations. In addition, the following parameters are used: R = 10 5 , F = [10, 100, 1000], R = [10 4 , 10 5 , 10 6 ], and β = 0.8.</p><p>We observe that the optimal total energy per bit increases as energy consumption of the caching hardware increases. From the perspective of energy efficiency, high-speed SSD is the best option while TCAM incurs the highest energy cost. Compared to high-speed SSD, TCAM increases the total energy per bit by almost two orders of magnitude in the case of F =1000. This can be explained by the following: when the caching power per bit is low, many copies of a content element can be cached in the network without significantly increasing the total caching power consumption. As a result, the average number of hops to contents and accordingly the associated transport energy to download the content is reduced. In comparison, when the caching power per bit is high, only a few copies of a content element can be cached in the network. As a result, the average number of hops to content and the corresponding transport energy to download the contents increases. It is also noted that the small catalog size provides lower optimal total energy per bit. This is due to the fact that at least one copy of each content element needs to be cached in the network so that CCN can serve the content. Thus, a larger-sized catalog by default can incur much higher caching energy consumption than that of a smaller-sized catalog. This is especially the case for TCAM, for which an order of magnitude increase in the catalog size generates an order of magnitude increase in the optimal total energy per bit. In Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, we also compare the energy efficiency of CCN to that of conventional CDNs. As mentioned in Section II-C3, conventional CDN uses hard disks for storage. Also, the energy consumption of servers needs to be taken into consideration. We observe that CCN gains more energy benefit as the download rate increases. This is due to the fact that the caching energy can be amortized by the increased number of downloads, thus the per bit energy consumption decreases. Compared to CDN, CCN using high-speed SD or DRAM provides an energy benefit for serving a small-sized catalog, e.g., F =10, with a high download rate, e.g., R=10 6 , for all cases. We also note that CCN that uses TCAM as the caching hardware technology provides little energy benefit, even for a small-sized catalog.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Impact of Maximum Cache Size on Optimal Total Energy per Bit</head><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, we plot the distribution of the number of copies that each content router caches in the optimal energy consumption state. The results are given by the GA, with 128 candidate solutions and the number of iterations set to 1000. The following parameters are used: R = [10 4 , 4 × 10 4 , 10 6 ], F =10, and β=0.8. With the given R and β, we first run the GA  to determine (near-)optimal cache locations for each content element (in a catalog of F =10), and then we count all copies cached at each content router. Note that cache size limit is not enforced. In case of R=10 4 , more than a half of content routers do not cache any copies; about a third of content routers cache only one copy. In case of R=10 6 , most of content routers cache all the catalog. As the download rate increases, the number of copies cached in the network also increases. To better understand the distribution, in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>, we also plot the number of cached copies n * k depending on content element's popularity. Since the network topology US64 has 64 nodes, in the extreme case that a content is cached at every node, the maximum number of cached copies is 64. The plot shows as the download rate increases, the number of cached copies increases across different popularity to the extent that every content router caches almost the whole catalog (as shown in the right subplot of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>).</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>, we plot the normalized optimal total energy per bit as a function of the maximum cache size. We first solve Eqs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr">(13)</ref> with different values of S and then normalize the results to the optimal case obtained by solving Eqs. (10-13) with S → ∞. The following parameters are used: R=10 5 , F = [10, 100, 1000], and β=0.8. DRAM is used for caching, with w ca = 2.5 × 10 -9 (watt/bit). The total energy first decreases and then reaches to a plateau as the maximum cache size increases. Thus, S/B needs to be larger than some threshold to achieve the optimal energy efficiency. This threshold increases with higher F .</p><p>The results plotted in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>show the growing importance of improving two aspects in the current memory technology: the maximum cache size and energy-proportional caching. Increasing the memory size limit allows more innetwork caching to serve large-sized catalogs or reduce transport energy should the popularity and download rate of content increase. Energy-proportionality <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> enables the efficient use of caching resources. At a given moment of the network operation the number of content cached at each content router could be quite different depending on the the location of content routers and the total number of downloads. Moreover, the size of cached content at each router is likely to change over time. With current memory technology, a fixed power is consumed regardless of the actual usage. In contrast, energyproportional caching improves total efficiency of a CCN by reducing the energy use incurred by the under-utilization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Impact of Transport Delay Requirement on Total Energy per Bit</head><p>To understand the impact of transport delay requirements on the total energy per bit, we plot in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref> the total energy per bit, consisting of the caching energy and the transport energy in CCN. For clarity, we only consider the download of a single content element. Hence, the following parameters are used: F = 1, R=10 3 , and β = 0.8. We also normalized the results to the optimal total energy per bit. We note that if H c is larger than the (energy-optimal) average hop distance, the transport energy dominates the caching energy so reducing the average hop distance by increasing the number of caches is beneficial in terms of both energy and delay. However, across the optimal point, there should be a tradeoff between energy and delay. That is, if H c has to be kept at lower values to satisfy the given transport delay requirement, the total energy per bit is likely to increase sharply. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>, for H c =2, there is a 20% increase in the total energy per bit; for H c =1, there is a 175% increase in the total energy per bit. Thus, we should distribute caches carefully by considering the tradeoff between energy and delay because shorter transport delay requirements could increase the energy overhead rapidly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we formulated the minimum energy consumption with optimal cache locations as integer linear and nonlinear programming problems with the proposed energy consumption model of CCN. In addition, a genetic algorithm approach is proposed to find (near-)optimal cache locations. Our numerical results indicate that energy-proportional caching with sufficient caching capacity is required for realizing green CCN. Also, when distributing caches, careful consideration should be given to tradeoffs between energy and delay because the transport delay requirement can result in a sharp increase in energy consumption. In future work, we aim to understand strategies to best approach these optimal conditions and the impact of different implementation constraints. The final goal would be to design a practical in-network caching protocol for designing green CCN.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. A hypothetical United States backbone network US64 with N =64.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 . 8 .</head><label>28</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The optimal total energy per bit of CCN as a function of power efficiency (Watt/bit) of different caching hardware technologies. The following parameters are used: R = [10 4 , 10 5 , 10 6 ], F = [10, 100, 1000], and β = 0.8. For comparison, the energy per bit of CDN is also plotted.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. The distribution of the number of copies that each content router caches in the optimal energy consumption state. The following parameters are used: R = [10 4 , 4 × 10 5 , 10 6 ], F = 10, and β = 0.8.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. The number of cached copies depending on contents' popularity. The following parameters are used: R = [10 4 , 4 × 10 5 , 10 6 ], F = 10, and β = 0.8.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. The optimal total energy per bit as a function of the maximum cache size. The following parameters are used: R = 10 5 , F = [10, 100, 1000], and β = 0.8. DRAM is used for caching, with wca = 2.5 × 10 -9 (watt/bit).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig.6. The total energy per bit normalized to the optimal case, consisting of the caching energy and the transport energy in CCN. The following parameters are used: F = 1, R = 10 3 , and β = 0.8.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>This network topology is derived from the prototypical Continental United States (CONUS) topology used in the DARPA CORONET program<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>This model tends to overestimate the actual Hc when n → N . For example, H c (N ) = 0.36 &gt; Hc(N ) = 0.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>This work was supported by Seoul R&amp;BD Program (WR080951) funded by Seoul Metropolitan Government.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Networking named content</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Jacobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Thornton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Plass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Briggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Braynard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM International Conference on emerging Networking EXperiments and Technologies (CoNEXT)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Rome, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-12">December 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward Energy-Efficient Content Dissemination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Rimac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kilper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hilt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Network</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-03">March 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Greening the Internet with Nano Data Centers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Valancius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM International Conference on emerging Networking EXperiments and Technologies (CoNEXT)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Rome, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-12">December 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Reality Check for Content Centric Networking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Perino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Varvello</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM SIGCOMM Information Centric Networking (ICN) Workshop</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-08">August 2011</date>
			<pubPlace>Toronto, Canada</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power Trends in Communication Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kilper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal on Selected Topics in Quantum Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="284" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-04">March/April 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Energy Efficiency of Content Delivery Architectures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Atkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kilper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gulsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE ICC Green Communications (GreenComm) Workshop</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Kyoto, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-06">June 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Architectures for Energy-Efficient IPTV Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baliga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ayre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Optical Fiber Communication Conference (OFC)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Diego, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-03">March 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dynamic</forename><surname>Multi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">-</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.darpa.mil/sto/programs/coronet/index.html" />
		<title level="m">Terabit Core Optical Networks: Architectures, Protocols, Control and Management (CORONET)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Watching Television over an IP Network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crowcroft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Amatriain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Vouliagmeni, Greece</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-10">October 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonlinear Programming, 2nd Edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bertsekas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<pubPlace>Athena Scientific, Belmont, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Glodberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Genetic Algorithms in Search, Optimization, and Machine Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley Professional</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Case for Energy-Proportional Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Barroso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Holzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
