<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Perfect Elimination and Chordal Bipartite Graphs* M a r t i n Charles Golumbic</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Clinton</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Goss</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">COURANT INSTITUTE OF MATMMATICAL SCIENCES NEW YORK UNlVERSlN</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Perfect Elimination and Chordal Bipartite Graphs* M a r t i n Charles Golumbic</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">ED42F10B0F1AFE1AFC34498B8FB0F191</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T05:03+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We define two types of bipartite graphs, chordal bipartite graphs and perfect elimination bipartite graphs, and prove theorems analogous to those of Dirac and Rose for chordal graphs (rigid circuit graphs, triangulated graphs). Our results are applicable to Gaussian elimination on sparse matrices where a sequence of pivots preserving zeros is sought. Our work removes the constraint imposed by Haskins and Rose that pivots must be along the main diagonal.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>When performing Gaussian elimination on a sparse matrix, an arbitrary choice of pivots may result in filling in some zero entries with nonzeros. One may ask, when does there exist a sequence of pivots which induces no fill-in? The combinatorial notion of preservation of sparseness is important for the storage requirements in computer implementation.</p><p>Rose [9] gives a beautiful. solution to this problem for a nonsingular n X n matrix M under the restriction that I. All pivots are chosen along the main diagonal. 11. M is symmetric.</p><p>Haskins and Rose <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> treat the same problem with only restriction I, and Kleitman [S] settles some questions left open by Haskins and Rose. A discussion on the complexity of algorithms which calculate minimal and minimum fill-in in this case can be found in [6,7, l o ] . Golumbic <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[ 3 ]</ref> solves the problem under only restriction 11. In this paper we shall consider the general situation (without either constraint) by studying an elimination procedure on bipartite graphs.</p><p>An undirected graph (V, E ) consists of an irreflexive symmetric binary relation E over a finite set V of vertices. The members of E are called edges and can be thought of as pairs of distinct vertices. We denote the set of all vertices adjacent to the vertex v by Adj(v). Two edges are adjacent if they share a common vertex. Edges ab and cd are disjoint if the vertices a, b, c, d are all different and c, d d Adj ( a ) U A d j ( b ) . Thus, disjoint edges are nonadjacent but the converse is not true.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The subset A c V of a graph (V, E ) induces the subgraph (A, E [ A ] )</head><p>where </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">E [ A ] = {xy E E I x, y E A).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">PERFECT ELIMINATION BIPARTITE GRAPHS</head><p>A bipartite graph is an undirected graph whose vertices can be partitioned into disjoint sets X and Y such that every edge has one vertex in X and the other in Y. <ref type="bibr">A</ref>   <ref type="formula">2</ref>) are satisfied and a purrid scheme if only (1) is satisfied (see Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</p><p>Theorem 1. If e is a simplicial edge of a perfect elimination bipartite graph E, then E-[el is also a perfect elimination bipartite graph.</p><p>Proof. We wish to show that if G = ( X , Y, E) has a scheme [el, . . . , en], then there exists a scheme beginning with e. Let e = xy and ei =xiyi with x, x,, . . . , X,EX and y, yl,. . . , y n € Y, and let Ei = E-[el,. . . , ei-,].</p><p>Case 1. x =xi and y = yi for some i. From Remark 1, it follows that [e, e l , . . . , ei-l, ei+l,. . . , en] is a scheme.</p><p>Case 2 . x =xi and y = yi for some i # j . We may assume that i &lt; j by interchanging X and Y if necessary, hence [e, el,. . . , ei-J is a partial scheme.</p><p>Consider an edge xhyh for some i &lt; h &lt; j. Suppose there exists an m &gt; h such that xmyh and Xhyi are in E. We would then have the following implications:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">xiyi simplicial in Ei implies XhYj E E, xhyh simplicial in Eh implies xmyj E E, xiyi simplicial in E implies xmyi E E.</formula><p>This shows that cr=[e, el,. . . , ei-l, ei+l,. . . , ei-l] is a partial scheme.</p><p>Similarly, the following argument shows that e'=xjyi is in E and is Theorem 1 suggests an algorithm for recognizing perfect elimination bipartite graphs and producing a scheme. We repeatedly find a simplicial edge of a bipartite graph and delete it (thus also removing all edges adjacent to it). If we succeed in eliminating all edges, then the bipartite graph was perfect elimination, otherwise it was not. Clearly such a procedure can be implemented to run in polynomial time.</p><p>We can now comment upon the application mentioned in the opening paragraph. The bipartite graph B ( M ) of an n X n matrix M has vertices xl,. . . , x, and yl,. . . , yn, corresponding to the rows and columns, respectively, where xi is adjacent to yi if and only if m i i f O .</p><p>The reader can easily verify that using an entry mii as the pivot for row or column reduction will cause no fill-in if and only if xry, is a simplicial edge of B(M). Therefore, a nonsingular matrix M has a sequence of pivots preserving zeros if and only if B ( M ) is a perfect elimination bipartite graph assuming that no accidental zeros are created by arithmetic coincidence during the process. Additionai background on this and related problems can be found in the survey articles <ref type="bibr">[ 2 , 8 , 111</ref> and in their references. Our argument actually proves a stronger resuit, namely that if G has no induced copy of 2K2, then each nonisolated vertex z is the end point of some simpli.cia1 edge of G.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">CHORDAL BIPARTITE GRAPHS</head><p>Inspired by the results of Dirac <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref> and Rose <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, we shall define a notion of chordality for bipartite graphs and present theorems analogous to their results.</p><p>A minimal edge separator S for disjoint edges ab and cd is a minimal subset of the vertices whose removal from the graph separates ab and cd into distinct connected components. Clearly, every vertex of S is adjacent to some vertex in each of the connected components containing ab and cd.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A bipartite graph ( X , Y , E ) is chordal if every cycle of length strictly</head><p>greater than four has a chord.  REMARK 2. Unlike the results of [l, 91, the converse to this theorem is false (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). In fact, counter examples can be constructed having vertices of arbitrarily large degree.</p><p>Proof (Theorem 4). Let G = (X, Y, E ) be a chordal bipartite graph with at least two edges. Since an induced subgraph of G is also chordal Proof. If G possesses a chordless cycle C of length greater than four, then C would be an induced subgraph which is not perfect elimination. Cqnversely, if G is chordal bipartite, then so is every induced subgraph Let G = ( X , Y, E ) be a bipartite graph and let G = ( X , Y, E) denote its bipartite complement, that is, for all x E X and y E Y</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">xy E E x y &amp; E.</formula><p>For example, e6 = 3K2 and c8 = C, (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</p><p>Theorem 6. The graphs G and 6 are both chordal bipartite if and only if G contains no induced subgraph isomorphic to C,, 3K2 or C,.</p><p>Proof. This follows directly from the preceding example and the observation that if G contains no C,, then G contains no C, for n110. I A strengthened version of Theorem 2 can now be stated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corollary 7.</head><p>If a bipartite graph G contains no induced 2K2, then G and G are both chordal bipartite which further implies that G and G are both perfect elimination bipartite.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">CONCLUSION</head><p>Being perfect elimination bipartite does not seem to tell us much about the structure of a graph. Indeed, let G be any bipartite graph with vertices u,, u2,. . . , u,; add new vertices w l , w 2 , . . . , w, and connect ui with wi for each i = 1, . . . , n. This augmented graph is a perfect elimination bipartite graph and completely masks the structure of G. Only when the hereditary condition was added in Corollary 5 could a graph theoretic characterization be given.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>For</head><label></label><figDesc>example, if ab and cd are disjoint edges, then G[{a, b, c, d)]=22K2. Deleting an edge xy from a graph (V, E ) will mean the removal of all edges adjacent with xy, denoted by If u = [el, . . . , ek] is a sequence of pairwise nonadjacent edges to be deleted, then E -cr = E -[el, . . . , ek] is defined recursively E -u = ( E -e J -[ e , , . . . , ek].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Theorem 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>edges, then it is a perfect elimination bipartite graph. assume that \El &gt; 2. of subsets of X If a bipartite graph G = (X, Y, E) has no pair of disjoint Proof. It suffices to show that G has a simplicial edge. We may Suppose G has no simplicial edge. We shall construct an infinite chain x0cx1c * * * c X , c . . . which will contradict the finiteness of X . Assume we are given subsets and such that x i y j € E e i &lt; j for all 0 5 i, j l k and x i z c E forall O s i ~k . (An arbitrary edge xoz will start the induction when k = 0.) Since xkz is not simplicial, there exist vertices x and y ( Z z ) such that x k y , xz E E but xy&amp; E. Hence, y &amp; Y k . Moreover, for all 0 5 i &lt; k the edges xiyi+l and x k y are not disjoint, implying x i y € E . But xy&amp;E, so x&amp;Xk. Therefore, by renaming x = x k t l and y = y k + 1 and setting X k C l = x k u { x k + , } and Yk+1= Y k U { Y k + l } , we are ready for the next iteration of our construction. This algorithm goes on indefinitely, But X and Y are finite, hence contradiction. Thus, G must have a simplicia1 edge, and the theorem is proved. I</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Theorem 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>A bipartite graph ( X , Y, E ) is chordal if and only if every minimal edge separator induces a complete bipartite subgraph.Proof. ( e ) Suppose there exists a chordless cycle C =[v,, u 2 , . . . , vk, v,] of even length k r 6 . Consider the set S of all vertices adjacent to at least one of u2, ug, us, and ?&amp; but not including these four vertices. Certainly S separates u2u3 and and S n C = {u,, u,, u7} (if k = 6, then u, = v,). Let S'c S be a minimal edge separator for u2u3 and t)506. Thus, O,E S' and either u1 E S' or u7 E S' implying by hypothesis that C has a chord due to the opposite parity of the subscripts, contradiction.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>( 3 )Theorem 4 .</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Let S be a minimal edge separator and let G [ A ] = (A, E [ A ] ) and G [ B ] = (B, E[B]) be connected components of the graph after removing S. Suppose x, Y E S , X E X , and Y E Y. Since G [ A ] and G [ B ] are connected, there exist minimum length paths [x, uo, a,, . . . , y ] and [ y , b,, b,, . . . , x] with ai E A and bi E B. Since these paths are of odd length 2 3 , they join to give a cycle of length greater than four. This cycle must have a chord xy since by construction no other pair may be adjacent. I Every chordal bipartite graph is a perfect elimination bipartite graph.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIGURE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>FIGURE 2. A perfect elimination bipartite graph which is not chordal.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIGURE 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>bipartite graph (X, Y, E ) is complete if xy E E for every x E X and y E Y. An edge xy is called simplicia1 if Adj ( x ) U Adj ( y )</head><label></label><figDesc>The simpliciality of an edge is retained as an inherited property of an induced subgraph.</figDesc><table><row><cell>FIGURE 1. A</cell><cell>perfect</cell><cell>elimination</cell><cell>bipartite</cell><cell>graph</cell><cell>with</cell><cell>scheme</cell></row><row><cell>[</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">induces a complete bipartite subgraph.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>REMARK 1.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>XIYl, XZYZ. X3Y3, X4Y41.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>if there exists a sequence of pairwise nonadjacent edges [el,. . . , en] such</cell></row><row><cell>that (1) ei is a simplicial edge of</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>E -[el,. . . , ei-l] for each i, and (2) E-[el,</head><label></label><figDesc>. . . , en] is empty. We call [el,. . . , en] a scheme if (1) and (</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>*This research was supported in part by NSF Grants DCR-75-09218 and HES-75-19875.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On rigid circuit graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dirac</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Abh. Math. Sem. Uniu. Hamburg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Solution of linear systems of equations: Direct methods for finite element problems. Sparse matrix techniques. Lecture Notes in Math</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">572</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="101" />
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on perfect Gaussian elimination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Golumbic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Anal. Appl</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a characterization of perfect elimination digraphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Haskins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Comp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on perfect elimination digraphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kleitman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Comp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimal triangulation of a graph and optimal pivoting order in a sparse matrix</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ohtsuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Cheung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fujisawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Anal. A p p l</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="622" to="633" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fast algorithm for finding an optimal ordering for vertex elimination on a graph</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ohtsuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAMJ. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solution of linear systems of equations: Direct methods (general)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">572</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sparse matrix techniques</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Triangulated graphs and the elimination process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Anal. A p p l</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="597" to="609" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithmic aspects of vertex elimination on graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Tarjan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lueker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Comp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="283" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Graph theory and Gaussian elimination. Sparse Matrix Computations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Tarjan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="22" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
