<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Trajectory Generation for the N-Trailer Problem Using Goursat Normal Form</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, ZEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Dawn</forename><surname>Tiibury</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, ZEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, ZEEE</roleName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shankar Sastsy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tilbury</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Michigan</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>48109-2125</postCode>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Electronics Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mechanical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">California Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91 125</postCode>
									<settlement>Pasadena</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Trajectory Generation for the N-Trailer Problem Using Goursat Normal Form</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8C214163AC593FEA09832D77125EA3BC</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T10:05+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this paper, we develop the machinery of exterior differenllai forms, more particularly the Gourset normal form for a Ffaffian system, tor solving nonsoloMwic motion p h d n g probkms, &amp;.e., motion planning for systems with lloniatcgrable velocity constraints. We use tbis technique to solve the problem of rbxing a mobile robot WMI R trailers. We present an algorithm for finding a family of ~W I S ~-~~O M whicb will convert the system of rolling constraints on the wheels of the robot with n traiten into the GoaFapt canonical form. .nRo of these transformations are studied in detail. The G o m t normal form for exterior diffemtial systems is dual to the so-called chained-form for vector fields that bas been studied previously. Consequently, we are able to give the state feedback law aad change o€ e00rdinaW to -vert the N-trai4r system id0 chained form. Tllree metbods for for chained-form systems using shrosoidg and polynomiPls aa inputs are presented.</p><p>the N-trailer system into Gonrsat form, use this to lind the cboinedform coordinates, plan a path for the corresponding cimkd-form system, and then transform the resalting traje.ctory back into the original coordinates. Simulations and h.ames of mode animations of the N-tnder system for parallel parking and backing into a loading dock using this strategy are included.</p><p>The motion prpnnhag strategy Is therefore to</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>N the past few years, there has been a great deal of interest I in the generation of motion planning algorithms for robots with nonholonomic or nonintegrable velocity constraints in cluttered environments. These constraints on the instantaneous velocities arise from the kinematics of the drive "isms of the carts. This work has been a departure froa the traditional robot motion planning (see, for example, [81, [19], [22]) which concentrated on understanding the complexity of the computational effort associated with planning trajectories for robots (with no constraints on their instantaneous velocities) which would avoid both fixed and moving obstacle. the motion plans arising from these more traditional methods often required sideways motion of robot carts with wheels and,</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>as was pointed out by Laumond, most mobile robots ate not on castors <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[23]</ref>, [MI.</p><p>In this paper, we consider and solve the motion planning problem for a system consisting of a car-like mobile robot pulling n trailers. This system has been an important canonical example for the work on nonholonomic motion planning ever since it was posed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[25]</ref> and [33]. The nonholonomic constraints for this system arise from constraining each pair of wheels to roll without slipping. Strictly speaking, if an axle has a differential that keeps the pair of wheels rolling without slipping, then each wheel turns a Merent amount ia acc&amp;ce with a simple geometric relationship called the Alexandw-Maddocks condition [l]. In our work we will neglect this and model the wheels on an axle as being parallel.</p><p>The system of a car with n trailers has been viewed as a canonical example because each trailer adds one dimension to the state space of the system (representing its angle with respect to the inertial frame) and one nonholonomic constraint.</p><p>Regardless of the number of trailers attached, the general system always has two degrees of freedom, corresponding to the driving and steering directions of the front car. It has been shown that every point in the state space is reachable, i.e., that the system is completely controllable <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[25]</ref>. The question that is answered in this paper is one of constructive controllability; explicit open-loop controls for steering the car with n trailers from an initial to a final position are given. We first give a btief description of some of the previous work on this problem. A more detailed review of the general nonholonomic motion planning problem can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[34]</ref> or in a recent collection of papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[27]</ref>. A more detailed description of the N-trailer problem and its variations can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[25]</ref>. A tutorial introduction to nonholonomic motion planning is given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[32]</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Barraquand</ref> and Latombe [3] proposed a planner for cars with trailers in a cluttered environment, with an attempt at finding one with a minimal number of backups. The main drawback to their approach was that it required a discretization of the state space followed by an exhaustive search of all possible directions the robot could go at each point. Consequently, the method became computationally infeasible for a large n u b e r of trailers. The method world well, however, in a very cluttered environment since the presence of many obstacles drastically reduced the number of search directions.</p><p>Related to this work is that of Divelbiss and Wen [Ill, who have explored a computational approach to the N-trailer problem. They also discretize the system and use gradient descent in the (discretized) input space to generate a feasible path. Convergence projmties of their method are currently under investigation, but the algorithm has demmstrated good performance in simulation. They are also able to incorporate obstacles into the p b l e m formulation, using potential field methods. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[35]</ref> proved an interesting result on the mini" length feasible paths for a robot of the Hilare type with bounded turning radius. They showed that the optimal length path belonged to a family of paths that consisted of segments of straight lines and arcs of circles. It seems doubtful that such a method could be generalized easily to a car with n trailers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reeds and Shepp</head><p>A paper by Murray and Sastry <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[34]</ref> studied motion planning for nonholonomic systems and focused attention on a specific class of systems in so-called "chained form" This class of systems was inspired by some early work of Brockett [4] on optimal control of "canonical systems." In <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[34]</ref>, sufficient conditions were given for converting systems into chitined form along with an algorithm (using sinusoids at integrally related frequencies) for steering chained-form systems. The theory was used to transform the fiont-wheeldrive car, a car with one trailer, and a hopping robot into chained form, and to find feasible trajectories for these systems using the sinusoidal steering algorithm. The car with two trailers, however, did not fit the sufficient conditions and was left an open problem. Recently Sqjrdalen [39] showed that the system of the car with n trailers could be put into chaipexl form using the coordinates of the nth trailer (rather than ttme of the cab) for parameterizing the configuration space of the system. Necessary and sufficient conditions for converting systems into chained form are given in [31]; there is no general procedure known, however, for finding the coordinate transformation into chained form.</p><p>Femandes et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[12]</ref> used numerical methods for solving constrained optimal control problems associated with nonholonomic motion planning problems, using a perturbation (of the cost functional) to make the singular optimal controI problem regular. In another work [ 131, they also suggested the use of input sinusoids (as basis functions) in a Ritz approximation algorithm for steering nonholonomic systems. Sinusoids were also used in a method proposed by Suss" and Liu [40] (see also [MI). Their method was completely general in that it applied to any controllable nonholonomic system and used asymptotically high frequency, high magnitude sinusoids to achieve convergence. This method was applied to the system of Hilare with two trailers in 1421, but the paths generated were highly oscillatory and impractical, owing to their use of high magnitude and frequency sinusoids.</p><p>Several other methods have been proposed which used piecewise constant inputs [aO], <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[21]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[30]</ref>. AU of these worked best in the cases where the control Lie algebra is nilpotat.</p><p>Their extension to systems whose control Lie algebra is not nilpotent is not fully satisfactory, requiring a large number of steps to come close to the goal point. Very recently, it was pointed out that the N-trailer system is diffexentially flat ([14],</p><p>[15]), and thus motion planning can be done using Fdnet series [36], [37].</p><p>Our current paper is somewhat different in style from most of the previous work. Instead of focusing on the directions in which the system is allowed to move, namely the two vector fields which correspond to the two degrees of f r d o m of the system, we have defined the system from the constraints on its velocity. That is, instead of looking at the control system</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">5 = gl(x)Ul -f 92(x)U2</formula><p>and the distribution spanned by the input vector fields A = (91, g2}, we consider the exterior differential system d o gonal to this distribution, namely I = A I = { a1 , ---, a"}. In the context of motion planning, this is a very natural framework since each ai is a one-form defined on the co&amp;guration space and represents the constraint that the wheels on the ith axle must roll without slipping.</p><p>This codistribution I generates a Pfaffian system (of codimension two); such exterior differential systems and their properties were first studied by PfaE in the early 1800's. There and are reviewed in Section 11 of this paper. The normal form for P f a f h systems of codimension two that was proposed by Goursat is in fact the dual of chained canonical form as defined above. The conditions for converting a system into Goursat form are straightforward to check, but the main advantage of using the Goursat form is that there exists an algorithm for findtng the necessary c c " t e transformation. No such general algorithm exists for converting systems to chained form. As in the work of Sgrdalen, the ealculatians for the Goursat normal form for the n-trailer problem are simplified quite considerably by using the coordinates of the last trailer instead of those of the cab to parameterize the configuration space of the multitrailer system. Exterior differential forms to describe linear velocity constraints have been also been used in some of the mechanics literature; see, for example (21, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[45]</ref>,</p><p>and <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[47]</ref>.</p><p>After the review of exterior Merentid systems in Section 11, we examine the Pfaffian system associated with a mobile robot towing n traiIers. We show in Section ID that this system can be converted into Goursat nonnal form or equivakntly chained form. Section lV is devoted to presenting methods for steering systems in chained form. Three different methods are presented, using as inputs sinusoids, piecewise constant inputs (as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[30]</ref>), and polynomials. Finally, we apply some of these steering methods to the N-trailer example and display the results in Section V. Mathematica code for computing the coordinate transformations and control inputs used in this paper, as well as complete movie animations of some of the trajectories, can be found in E431 or obtained from the first a u k .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. A RFiyiEw OF EXTERIOR DIFFERENTlAL SYSTEMS</head><p>Here we give a very brief review of the tools available from the study of exterior differential systems and show how to apply these tools to the problem of finding a feedback transformation which converts a system into chained form. We concentrate on the computations that must be performed and refer the interested reader to the much more detailed description of these tools in the monograph by Bryant et al.</p><p>[61.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Exterior Algebra</head><p>Let V be a vector space over R, which we also refer to using the notation A'. We define a new vector space A2 by defining the wedge product as a skew-symmetric bilinear map which satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(aiai + a2a2) A fl =ai(ai A P) + a 2 ( ~2 A P) a A a = O ~r A p = -@/\a. (1) That is, A is a bilinear, associative, distributive, noncommu- tative product mapping A' x A' --f A2. If {gi} is a basis for A l , then {oi A u j , 1 5 i &lt; j 5 n} is a basis for A2. It follows that the dimension of A2 is (") 2. An element of A2 is called a two vector.</formula><p>In a similar way, we d e h e a p-vector 8 E AP by taking the wedge product between p one-vectors and using the rules a1 A A f f p changes sign if any two ai are interchanged.</p><p>AP consists of all pth order exterior products and has a basis given by {oh, A A (Th,} where {q} is a basis for A' and the hi's are ordered. AP is a vector space of dimension (3.</p><p>In particular, dimAn = 1 and dimAk = 0 if k &gt; n. For completeness, we defifie the set of zero-vectors as Ao = R.</p><p>The wedge product is a very powerful tool which can be used to great advantage in calculations. We will make frequent use of the following fact. Just as in the case of polynomials, it is often desirable to speak of a vector of mixed order (or unknown order). Using the wedge product, we can define an algebra over the set of p vectors. Let A = Ao @ 11' @ -. -@An and define multiplication between two elements of A using the wedge product. The wedge product is a bilinear, associative, distributive, skew product which maps A' x As + Ar+* andhence Ax A + A.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposition I: The vectors</head><p>We say an element E A is homogeneous of order p if f AP; i.e., it is a p-vector. An element [ of A is nonhomogeneous if it has components of different orders.</p><p>If V is a vectur space of dimension n, its dual, V*, is also a vector space of dimension n. The exterior product over V* can be used to form the vector space W ( V ) := AP(V*). An element a E W is called a p-form.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Difemtiul Forms</head><p>Given a manifold M of dimension n, the tangent space of A4 at a jbint x is a vector space of dimension n, denoted TxM. The vector space AP(T!M) consists of all p-vectors constructed from tangent vectors in T,M. By attaching the vector space AP(T,M) to each point x E M , we get a bundle structure on M , which we write as A*(M). Similarly, the bundle W ( M ) is defined by using the dual space T:M. We call a smooth section of this bundle, w E W ( M ) , an exterior differential p-form on M .</p><p>Relative to a local coordinate chart, we describe the tangent and cotangent bundles by choosing a local basis where A p-form w on M can be represented in this basis as 3) d2 = 0. These rules are extremely useful in computations. We have the following lemma, which relates the exterior derivative of a one-form to the Lie bracket between two vector fields.</p><p>-2:</p><p>Let w E O'(M), and let X and Y be smooth vector 'fields on M. Then We will be primarily interested in the special case of exterior differential systems which are generated by a set of nonholonomic constraints or one-forms and we focus on that case here.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">d w ( X , Y) = X w ( Y ) -Y w ( X ) -w ( ( X , Y ] ) .</formula><p>A Pfaffian system is an exterior differential system which is generated by a set of linearly independent one-forms. Zet I be a codistribution spanned by a set of linearly independent one-forms {ai}, i = 1, a a e , s. The ideal generated by I is</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Z = { I } = {CT E R : C T A ~' * * -A ~ = 0).</formula><p>For an ideal generated by a set of one-forms, each element in the ideal has the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">S &lt; = A j=1</formula><p>for some e j E R. The exterior differential system generated by I must be closed under differentiation, thus it contains Z, dZ. In this paper, we will mainly be concerned with the codistribution of one-forms I which generates the exterior differential system.</p><p>It is possible to rephrase Frobenius's Theorem in a concise way using ideals. Let Z be the ideal generated by {a', a -. , as} and write dz for the set consisting of the exterior derivative of all elements of Z. We say that Z is integrable if there exist functions hl, --, h, such that Z is also generated by {dhl, , dh,}. The Frobenius theorem asserts that the following set of relationships hold</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Z is integrable U dZ c Z U d a i A a' A a -. A as = 0 U dai = S 6; A aj j=1</formula><p>for some e;, j = 1, .-., s da' 0 mod2.</p><p>(3)</p><p>The last relationship in (3) uses the notion of congruence.</p><p>Given tovo forms w , [ E R, we write w z [modZ if there exists an exterior form q E Z such that w = &lt; + q. If I is a codistribution (and hence not an id&amp;), then we write w z tmodI if theze exist exterior forms a E I and 9 E SI such that w = ( + q A a. It follows that if I is the generator set for an ideal 2, then wmodZ = wmodI. In the case that Z is generakd by one-forms {ai}, we will often make use of the relatiomhip I wmodZ E 0 e w = ei A ai for some oi E R.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. The Derived Flag</head><p>, w"} be a smooth codistribution on M. The exterior derivative induces a mapping 6 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">I 3 Let I = span{wl,</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>fi2(M)lI</head><p>6 : X H dXmodI E R2(M).</p><p>The mapping 6 is a linear mapping over G"(M)</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">6 ( f a + gP) =df A a + f d a + dg A P + gdPmodI = f da + g domod I</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>=fh(&amp;) +!Jh(P).</head><p>It follows that the kemel of S is a codistribution on M (i.e., at each point p E M , the kemel of 6 is a linear subspace of T,*M). We call this subspace I(1), the 6rst derived system of I</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">I(1) = ker6 = {A E I : dXmodI E 0).</formula><p>I(1) contains the one-forms in I which are integrable mod I. We can represent I(1) using a set of one-forms, but it is important to note that the basis for I(1) may not be a simple subset of the basis for I. Linear combinations of basis elements (over the ring of smooth functions on M) must be searched to find a basis for the derived system.</p><p>Since I(') is itself a codistribution on M, we can continue this construction and generate a nested sequence of codistributions (4)</p><p>If the dimension of each I ( i ) is constant, then this construction terminates for some finite integer N. In this case, we call (4) the derived flag of I and N the deiived length.</p><p>The derived flag describes the integrability properties of the A proof can also .be found in 1321.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theorem G h o w ' s Theorem:</head><p>Let I = {a1, . . , a ' } rep resent a set of constraints and assume that the derived flag of the system exists. Then, there exists a path x ( t ) between any two points satiswig $(x)k = 0 far all i if and only if there exists an N such that I(N) = (0).</p><p>In control theory, Chow's theorem is usually stated by asking that the involutive closure of the distribution I* span the tangent space at each point x E M. The connection between the Lie algebra formulation of Chow's theorem and the exterior differential system formulation is made with the following lemma.</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Lemmu 5.-If I = A l then I(l) = (A + [A, A])l.</formula><p>This lemma allows us to compute the derived flag for a system given the distribution A = Il. Define the nested set</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">of distributions Eo C E1 c c EN as Eo = A Ei = Ei-1 + p i -1 , Ei-11.</formula><p>This sequence terminates if the dimension of each Ei is constant, and it follows from Lemma 5 that I(i) = E:. Remurk I : When doing computations with exterior Merential systems, it is convenient to choose a basis of one-forms whose structure matches that of the derived flag. We say that a basis {ai} is adapted to the derived flag if where si is a strictly decreasing sequence of integers. In other words, an adapted basis is one in which the derived systems are calculated by dropping elements from the end of the basis. An adapted basis can be calculated by computing the derived flag and then choosing the basis elements starting with a basis for and proceeding backwards.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. p f f f s Problem and Engel's Theorem</head><p>The simplest type of normal form for a nonholonomic system involves finding a normal form for a single constraint.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>T h e o r e m b ~a f s P m b l e m :</head><p>Suppose a is a one-form which satisfies (da)'+l A a = 0, (da)' A a # 0. Then there exist coordinates such that The proof uses a number of tools that are beyond the scope of this paper. In the T = 1 case, the proof d u c e s to proving that there exist two functions f l and fi which satisfy</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">d a A a A d f 1 = O # O (5) and a A dfi A df2 = O d f i A df2 #o.</formula><p>Given f1 and f 2 , a can be scaled such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">= df2 + gdf1 =: hi+ 2 2 d23.</formula><p>The HafF theorem guarantees that these equations have a solution (it need not be unique).</p><p>In the case of a single nonintegrable constraint in Et3, Pfaff's theorem is always satisfied for</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">T =1. If o is not integrable then d a A a # 0 but ( d ~) ~ A Q = 0 by a dimension</formula><p>count. Therefore, we can apply Theorem 6 (with a relabeling of coordinates) to conclude that a = &amp;3 -52 8 1 .</p><p>A basis for the right null space of this constraint is then given by </p><formula xml:id="formula_14">= d s 4 -6 4 1 -1 -1 a -a -2 -1 -;a 2 + X a l = d J 3 -&lt; 2 &amp; ,</formula><p>where X is chosen such that (7) becomes an equality.</p><p>Case 2 (b # 0): ~n this case we can scale o2 so that D e m g (2 = -a/b gives the normal form</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">- a ' = 4 4 -( 3 e 1 -2 --&amp;I -J 2 d 6 -</formula><p>It turns out that this normal form is diffeomorphic to Goursat form via the following change of coordinates</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">771 = 53 m = -J2 * = 5' = d774 -773 dql 773 = 4 1 774 = 54 -c l &amp; &amp;' = -Z2 = d773 -772dq1.</formula><p>Hence the transformed basis is in Engel's normal form. 0</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. Goursat Normal Form</head><p>We now turn to the more general case of n-2 constraints on an n-dimensional manifold M. Let I be a codistribution on M whose derived flag satisfies dimI(;) = ni -2.</p><p>Theorem 8-Goursat Normal Fonn: Let U be an open subset of lRn and I = {a', . . . , a"} be a collection of s = n-2 smooth, linearly independent one-forms defined on U. If there exists a one-form A # Omodl such that dai r\rmodcyl, . . . , ai i = 1, . . . , -1 da" #OmodI then there exists a set of coordinates . $ such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">I = {&amp;n -Cn-1 d t l , ' * 7 dC3 -'$2 &amp;1}.</formula><p>A few comments on the statement of this theorem are in order. The conditions of the theorem require the existence of a special basis {ai} and a special one-form A. A quick calculation shows that the basis {ai} is adapted to the derived flag of the system and hence if we start with an adapted basis, the real requirement is the existence of a one-form A which satisfies the congruences. Determining ?r can involve a further scaling of the adapted basis which preserves the adapted structure (see Section III-B for an example). For most examples, T can be determined by a combination of physical insight and guessing.</p><p>A complete proof of this theorem can be found in <ref type="bibr">[6]</ref>. It can be summarized in the following algorithm for converting a system into Goursat form (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[16]</ref> for the feedback linearization version of this algorithm on which this is based).</p><p>-, w " } with s = n-2, the following steps are requird It follows from the congruences that a' and a2 satisfy dal A a1 A a2 = 0 and hence the proof of Engel's theorem can be used to find coordinates such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">a1 = dCn -Cn-1 dC1 = d&amp;-1 - d&amp;.</formula><p>This may involve finding a new basis which preserves the adapted structure, as well as a change of coordinates, to convert between the two normal forms in the proof of Engel's theorem.</p><p>The remaining coordinates are detemhed by simple differentiation. Given we determine ti-1 by algebraically solving the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">,p-i+l = -a!&amp; -Ji-ld&amp;modal,</formula><p>The proof of Goursat's theorem is to essentially show that this equation always has a solution.</p><p>form can always be written as a control system in chained form-by choosing a which forms a basis for the distribution annihilated by I. Thus, we can formulate the problem of finding a basis for the constraints which is in Goursat form as the probleni of finding a feedback transformation to convert a system to chained form. The Goursat congruences are somewhat unsatisfying since they require the existence of a oneform ?r. Necessary and sufficient conditions for the existencc of such a ?r, and hence for converting a set of constraints into Goursat normal form, were presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[31]</ref>. We summarize the main result here.</p><p>, w " } be a codistribution on R" and write A = IL for the distribution which spans the null space of the codistribution. We define two nested sets of distributions Let I = span {d, .</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">Eo = A Fo = A E1 = Eo + [Eo, Eo] E2 = E1 + [El, El] Fl = Fo + [Fo, F O I F2 = Fl + [Fl, FOI<label>(9)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">Ei+l = E ; + [E;, E;] F;+l = Fi + [F;, Fo].</formula><p>Under the assumption that each distribution is constant rank, the two sequences have finite length (possibly different). The filtration { F;} is the one which usually appears in the context of nonlinear controllability and feedback linearization.</p><p>In particular, F; consists of all brackets up to order i. The distribution E; also contains all brackets of order i, but may contain additional Lie products of higher order. This is due to the recursive construction of E;, as opposed to the iterative construction of Fi. The filtration E, is precisely the sequence of distributions which is perpendicular to the derived flag of I = A l .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>" e m 9 [31]: Given a two-dimensional distribution</head><p>A = IL such that dim E; = dimF; = i + 2 i = 0, . . e , n -2 there exists a basis {a', e , a"} for I which is in Goursat</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">normal form.</formula><p>This theorem allows us to completely characterize the set of systems which are equivalent to a system in chained (or Gousat) form in the case that the relative growth vector of the system is c = (2, 1, * . . , 1). It will be shown in the following section that the N-trailer system satisfies the conditions of Theorem 9, and hence it can be converted to chained form.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>m. THE MOTION P L A N " G PROBLEM FOR THE N-TRAILER SYSTEM</head><p>In this section, we define the F'faffian system (or equivalently, the set of one-forms which represent the velocity constraints) for the N-trailer problem and calculate its derived flag. We then show how the system can be converted into either Goursat normal form (Mowing Theorem 8 aad Algorithm 1)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. Converting Systems to Chained Form</head><p>Chained form is dual to the Goursat normal form presented above. "hat is, a system with constmints in cioursat normal A / * or its dual, chained form. Although the calculations in this section assume a particular configuration of the mobile robot and M e r system, we will show that our model is general enough to encompass not only the specific choice we have made but also a front-wheel-drive car pulling traders and the luggage trains found in airports.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. The System of Roiling Constraints and Its Derived Flag</head><p>Consider a mobile robot such as Hilare' with n trailers attached, as in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>. Each trailer is attached to the body in front of it by a rigid bar, and the wheels of each body are constrained to roll without slipping. The trailers are assumed to be identical, but to have possibly different link lengths Li. A set of variables for defining the configuration of the system is the z, y coordinates of a point on each axle, say the midpoint, denoted by (2%) y;), together with the angle of each pair of wheels, which we call 8; and measure with respect to the horizontal.</p><p>The connections between the bodies give rise to the following constraints</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">2; =2;-1 -L i C O S 8; y; =y;-1 -Lisin 8;. (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">) i = 1, 2,</formula><p>, n for the general case with n trailers. These constraints are holonomic and will reduce the dimension of the configuration space, since the positions (z;, yt) for i 2 1 can be expressed in terms of 2 0 , yo, 80, . . , 8i. By symmetry, (z~, y;) for i &lt; n can also be expressed in terms of $, , y , , B, , ..., Bi. For our purposes it is useful to use as configuration space variables the z, y coordinates of a point on the nth trailer and the n f l hitch angles:</p><p>z , , y , , e, , . . ) 60 because the calculations that follow are vastly simplified? We will refer to the state space or configuration space as $ = ($, ,</p><p>. * , el, 8 0 ) . We have assumed that the bodies are connected between the midpoints of the two sets of rear wheels; it should be noted that if the trailers are hitched behind the rear axle, the equations will not simplify as shown here.</p><p>The wheels of the robot and trailers are constrained to roll without slipping; this implies that the velocity of each body in the direction perpendicular to its wheels must be zero. We model each pair of rear wheels as a single wheel at the midpoint of the axle and state the nonslipping conditions in terms of coordinates, beginning with the nth trailer Equation (11) models the fact that the velocity perpendicular to the wheels is zero. In the language of one-forms we write this as <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(12)</ref> a' (z,, y , , e ,, * , eo) = sin 8, b n -COS 8 , dyne I To write the other rolling constraints, we define vi to be the velocity of the ith trailer. The direction of motion of the (i + 1)st trailer and consequently the direction of wi+1, if its wheels are rolling without slipping, is along the direction of the hitch joining the (i + 1)st body to the ith body. Since the bodies are linked together by rigid rods, it follows that the projection of w; onto the line of the hitch is equal to q + l . Thus, we have that Also, we have that the velocity of the nth trailer w, is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">wn(z) = COS 8,xn + sin (14)</formula><p>In the sequel we will need to use w, as a one-form (i.e., we will need to use w, dt) and we denote this by abuse of notation as (15)</p><p>'U&amp;) = COS 8, dx, + sin 8, dy,.</p><p>We may now recursively write down the rolling without slipping constraints for all the trailers. The velocity of each trailer has a component due to +e velocity w;+1 of the previous trailer and a component L;+l&amp;+l due to the rotation of the hitch. The relative geometry of this situation is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">2</ref>. The component of wi+l in the direction perpendicular to the.whee1 base is wi+l sin (8; -8i+l) and the component of Li+18i+l in this direction is Li+lBi+l COS (ei -8i+l). If the itb trailer rolls without slipping then we must have <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(16)</ref> Dividing through <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(16)</ref> by COS(^^+^ -8;) yields the form constraint for n-1 2 i 2 0, which we write as ~P + l -~( z ) i = 0, where has the expression, in coordinates,</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">0 = Li+18i+l COS (8i+l -4) -w ~+ ~ sin -8;).</formula><formula xml:id="formula_28">(z) = Li+l -tan (8i+l -8i)vi+l. (<label>17</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">)</formula><p>an+l-i</p><p>Note that we have used the one-form version of w;+1 in (17) and that there will be a singuhty in the constraint when &amp;+I -0, = f r / 2 , or one of the trailers is jack-lnifed.</p><p>The forms a ' ( x ) , a 2 ( x ) , a . . , an+'(x) represent the constraints that the wheels of the nth, (nl)st, . --, m t h trailer (i.e., the cab), respectively, roll without slipping. They are given by the formulas (17) with the recursion relations (13). Thus, the Pfaffian system for the N-trailer problem is generated by I = span{a', a2, e . . , an+'}.</p><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">)<label>18</label></formula><p>The following theorem gives the derived flag associated with this Pfaffian system. Theorem IO-Derived Flag for the N-Trailer Pfaffian System: Consider the Pfaffian system of the N-trailer system (18</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">)</formula><p>with the one-forms ai defined by Proofi The proof is by recursion starting from the bottom of the flag of (19). Indeed for the first step, we compute da' do' = cos 8, den A dxn + sin 8, de, A dy, = -21, A de,.</p><p>From (15) it follows that dal # 0 mod a ' . This establishes the last two steps of the derived flag above. For the preceding step, we note that the form a2 is given by a2 = L, de,tan (8, -8n-l)v,. This yields that de, is proportional to U, mod a2. Consequently, we have that da' = -U, A de, is equal to 0 mod 0 2 . This establishes that</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I(,-') =span {a', a 2 ) I(") = span {a' } (0). (20) I("+') =</head><p>For the ith step of the recursion proof, we assume that we have shown that</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I(") = span { a'} I("+') = (0).</head><p>We need to show that dai = 0 mod a l , . . . , ai-', ai. To verify this it is useful to have the following preliminary lemma.</p><p>Lemma 11: For the one-forms vi we have that it follows that dv,-l 5 dvn se^ (0, -On-') + se^ (8, -en-')</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">dvn-i Omoda', a2, e . . ,<label>(22</label></formula><p>* tan (6, -On-1)wn A (de, -d&amp;-1).</p><p>The first term is zero mod a1 since dv, 0 mod a ' . The second term is zero mod a2 since w, is proportional to de, mod a2, and the third term is zero mod a3 since Vn is proportional to On-' mod a3. n u s , we have that</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>dw,-'</head><p>Omoda', a2, a3.</p><p>proceeding recursively, we have that dw,-i Omoda', a2, e . . , ai+'</p><p>which completes the proof of the lemma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>U</head><p>We will also need to make use of the relation</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">den-i+2 = vn moda'<label>(23)</label></formula><p>which follows directly from the definition of the a ' in (17) and the linear dependence of the one-forms U;, given in (1 3).</p><p>Continuing with the proof of the theorem, we now begin the calculation for</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">dai = -sec2 -en--r+l)(den--i+2 - ' A vn-i+2 -tan ( ~i + 2 -L -i + i ) dwn-i+2-</formula><p>This expression has three terms. By (22), we have that dv,-;+2 e 0 mod a', ..., ai. Also by the pportionahty of the dei to v, (23) and the linear dependence of the wi's (13), we have that dOn-i+2 A v,-i+2 =-0 mod ai and d8,-i+l A vn-i+2 0 mod ai-'. Thus, we have that da$ = 0 mod a ' , a2, e -+, ai which implies that the derived flag has</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>U</head><p>We note that the I("+') = (0) implies that the N-trailer the form 1(n-i+1) = {a', -. , ai}), as stated.</p><p>system is completely controllable (by Chow's Theorem).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Conversion to Goursat Normal Form</head><p>In the preceding subsection, we have shown that the basis of constraints a ' , . . -, an+' defined in (12) and (17) is adapted to its derived flag in the sense of (19). It remains to check whether the ai satisfy the Goursat congruences and if they do, to find a transformation that puts them into the Goursat canonical form. morem 124oursat Congruences for the N-Trailer System: Consider the PfafEan system associated with the Ntrailer system (18) with the one-forms ai defined by (12) and (17). There exists a change of basis of the one-forms ai to Z$ which preserves the adapted structure, and a one-form ?r such that the Goursat congruences are satisfied</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">4 d$ E-$+' ATmodE', . .. , i = 1, . . . , n d~"+'#OmodI.</formula><p>The one-form which satisfies these congruences is given by T = cos 8, dx, + sin 8, dy, = wnr and is equivalent to the velocity form of the nth trailer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proofi</head><p>The outline for the proof is first to determine a suitable one-form T from the first Goursat congruence, d a l E -a2 AT. Then we construct the new basis elements Z$ one at a time such that they satisfy the rest of the congruexes. For this example, we find that these new basis elements are multiples of the original basis elements, and since the original basis is adapted to the derived flag, the new basis is also We determine T by completing the basis of {a', -. , an+'} adapted.</p><p>with COS 8, dxn + sin 8 , dy, an+2 = = de*.</p><p>Note that then set T = Alan+2 + X2an+3 and solve for XI , A2 using dal= -a2 A Tmoda'.</p><p>= w,, the velocity form of the last trailer. We</p><p>Calculating the exterior derivative of a '</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">d d = COS 8 , de, A dxn + sin 0, de, A dyn = de, A w, (<label>24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">)</formula><p>and then examining a2 A T a2 A T = (L, de,tan ( e, -@ , -1 ) w , )</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">A (Xlv, + A2 d8o)</formula><p>we see that if we choose A1 = 1, A2 = 0, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">a2 A T = L,d&amp; A w, = L , d a l .</formula><p>We note here that we could have chosen A1 = -1/Ln, but instead we will define a new basis element Z2 = -(1/Ln)a2.</p><p>Then the one-form T = w, will satisfy</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>'</head><p>Since the new basis we are defining is merely a scaled version of the original basis, mod-ing out by oi or 7$ is equivalent. IU general, we assume that $ bas been defined as e seci-' (end2 -e,-l) . sec2 (dn-i+3 -e n -i + 2 ) ~ i . We now continue this procedure to find the rest of the From the above analysis, we know transformed basis. 'paking the exterior derivative of Z2 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Using</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>L n L -1 will result in the congruence</head><formula xml:id="formula_40">dE2 -$ A Rmoda1,E2.</formula><p>which is nonzero. 0</p><p>Now that we have shown that the one-forms ai do satisfy the Goursat congruences, we can follow the steps of the algorithm of Section 11 to find the coordinate transformation that will result in Goursat normal form. Following Algorithm 1, in step 2 we look for possibly nonunique functions f1, f2 which satisfy (3, namely Since a1 = sin 8, dx, -COS 4 , dy, and dal =cos 0 , dx, Aden -sin 0 , dynA de,, it follows that dcvl Aal = -dxn Ady, A de,. Thus f1 may be chosen to be any function of x,, y , , On exclusively. We now proceed to explain two merent solutions of (5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TrMonnarion I-Cmrdinates of the nth IRaikr:</head><p>In a choice motivated by sprrdalen [39], we chocrse f 1 = 2,. Then, the second equation of (5) becomes COS On dxn A dyn A df2 = 0 with the proviso that df1 Adf2 # 0. A nonunique choice of f 2 is</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">f 2 = 3/n.</formula><p>For the change of coordinates, we have This has the physical interpretation of being the origin of the reference frame when viewed from a coordinate frame attached to the nth trailer. It satisfies the first of the equations of (5) simply by virtue of the fact that it is a function of x n , gn, On It may be verified that a choice of f 2 (nonunique-we got it by guess work!) given by zn+3 := f 2 = x n sin enyn COS Onenrl satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">A dfi A df2 = 0.</formula><p>The remaining coordinates 82, . , zn+2 corresponding to this transformation may be obtained from the same procedure as in the previous solution. The details are tedious.3 ~n the next subsection, we discuss yet another technique for obtaining the coordinates for the Goursat normal form.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Conversion to Chained Form</head><p>In the previous section, we described a method for converting the N-trailer exterior differential system into Goursat normal form. Recalling from Section 11 that the dual of Goursat normal form is chained form, we now show how a similar procedm can be used to transform the nonholonomic control system corresponding to the N-trailer system into chained canonical form.</p><p>We note that an exterior differential system on Rn of codimension two, given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">I = { a l ( z ) , . . . , # -2 ( x ) }</formula><p>is dual to a two-input nonholonomic control system where the vector fields g j ( x ) span a two-dimensional distribution A which is annihilated by the one-fom ai a i ( . ) *Si(") = 0.</p><p>When we transform an exterior differential system into Goursat normal form, we only perform a coordinate transformation z = f (z). There is no input per se to a formal exterior differentid system, although we can speak of the two degrees of freedom of the system, given by the distribution A = IL. <ref type="bibr">'</ref>  where the vi are as specified in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(13)</ref>. A basis for the distribution A which is annihilated by these one-forms {a', -, an+'} is given by 1 cos e , sin 8, The proof of this proposition requires that the constraints ai be written out in coordinates ( z , , y , , On, e e , eo), and then it can be checked that the two given vector fields, g 1 and g 2 , are in the null space of this set of constraints. The details can be found in 1431.</p><p>Although there are many different choices of 9 1 , 9 2 which will span A, the two which we have picked are natural in the sense that when the nonholonomic control system is written as This is merely an input transformation, and will not change any of the properties of the chained-form system.</p><p>We will now derive the coordinate transformations and changes of input required to put the system into chained form, as was discussed in Section II-G. Recall that a system in chained canonical form is defined to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">tl =GI i 2 =Ti2 23 =z2%1</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2, = . z m _ 1 t 1 .</head><p>We note that,the functions q ( t ) and zm(t) will completely define all the state variables of a chained-form system. These functions are referred to by Flies et al. as flat outputs <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[14]</ref> and €151, since the other m-2 states and the two inputs can be determined from the equations Consequently, a coordinate transformation into chained form is completely defined by the first and last coordinates of the chain, zl and z, , as functions of the original coordinates 2, along with (28). (The fact that such a transform exists follows fmm our having verified the Goursat congruences for the ai in the previous subsection.) It does need to be checked that the transformation which results from (28) is a valid diffeomorphism. In general, there are many possible transformations into chained form; two are presented here. These two are exactly the same as those discussed in the previous subsection in the context of the Goursat normal form. If the input vector fields for a general system satisfy the sufficient conditions of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[34]</ref>, then the techniques given in that paper could be used to find the transformation into chained form. If the system does not satisfy those conditions but satisfies the necessary and sufficient conditions of Theorem 9, then a transformation to chained form exists. It can be found by checking the Goursat conditions and solving F'faff's problem, as in Section III-B, or by guessing. We show here how to find the chained-form coordinates once the Goursat form is known.</p><p>Transfmtion I-Coordinates of the nth Trailer: This transformation was originally proposed by Sgrdalen <ref type="bibr">[39]</ref>, and was also used in the previous section</p><p>The corresponding input transformation is</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">- U 1 = i 1 =COS Onv,</formula><p>=cos(O0 -0,) c0s(e1 -e2) . . cos(On-l -On) cos 8,vo.</p><p>The other input ~2 = i 2 is a quite complicated function of z, 210, w for the general case with n trailers; however, it is easily verified that &amp; 2 / a w # 0, implying that the input transformation E = b(z)u is nonsingular. The remaining coordinates z = f(z) are defined using (28).</p><p>It should be noted that this coordinate transformation is only defined locally. Since its definition requires a divisian by Til, if any of the factors in El are zero, the transformation is undefined for that particular configuration. For example, if 0 , = 7r/2, Corresponding to the last trailer being at right-angles with the coordinate frame, this coordinate transformation is no longer valid. In addition, if the ith trailer is jack-knifed, that is to say, for some 1 5 i 5 n, 8, -8i-1 = f7r/2, the coordinate transfomaation is also singular. the Last Trailer: Another coordinate transformation, which also has some singularities but will allow the trailer to be at any orientation with respect to the coordinate frame, was also detailed in the previous section; we define it here as z1 =zn cos 8, + yn sin 8, zn+3 = x, sin Ony,, cos 8, -Onzl.</p><p>The input transformation and the rest of the coordinates follow from (28).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Other Trailer Configurations</head><p>Thus far, we have concentrated our attention on the example of the Hilare mobile robot pulling a chain of trailers. In this section we describe how this model is equivalent (under a coordinate transformation and state feedback) not only to the more familiar system of a front-wheel-drive car pulling trailers, but also to the luggage trains commonly found in airports.</p><p>The model of the front-wheel-drive car is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">3</ref>. In comparison with the Hilare model, we have added another axle to the front body of the chain, and a variable 4 representing the angle of the front wheels with respect to the car. The length of the wheelbase of the lead car is defined to be LO.</p><p>The equivalence between the two models is most easily seen by looking at the form constraints. Each constraint corresponds to one axle rolling without slipping. Hilare with n trailers has n+l axles; the car with n trailers has n+2 axles, and its H&amp;an system is therefore equivalent to that of Hilare pulling n+l trailers.</p><p>O f course, the states and inputs that we define for the car system are slightly different. By convention, we define the angle of the front axle relative to the car instead of relative to the coordinate frame. This angle 4 is merely 60 -01 on the Hilare system. The velocity input is the same, assumed to be the linear velocity of the first body (we can define it at either the front or rear axle depending on whether our car is front-wheel-drive or rear-wheel drive), but the rotational input is usually taken as w' = 4, the steering wheel velocity.</p><p>Since in the-Hilare case we can control the velocity of the first body w = Bo, state feedback can be used to reconcile these differences. As mentioned after Proposition 13, there are many choices of vector fields orthogonal to a given H&amp;an system with each choice having a different physical meaning.</p><p>The luggage carts used at most airports are also equivalent to the Hilare model. Each trailer on the luggage cart train has two sets of wheels; the front axle can spin freely about its center but the back axle is constrained to be aligned with the trailer (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">4</ref>). Here again we have defined the angles of the front wheels with respect to each trailer, but looking at the form constraints it is easily seen that the cab with n luggage trailers is equivalent to a front-wheel-drive car with 2n one-axle trailers. Again, a coordinate transformation is needed, since in the model of the luggage carts we define the angle of the front wheels of the trailers relative to the trailer instead of relative to the coordinate frame.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. STEERJNG CHAINED FORM SYSTEMS</head><p>Now that we have seen how to transform an N-trailer system into chained form, we examine various methods for steering chained-form systems (27). We assume an m-state system and note that Hilare with n trailers has n+3 states, a car with n trailers has n+4 states, and a car with n luggage trailers has 2n+4 states.</p><p>The problem that we address in this section is: Given a system in chained form with an initial state zo and a goal state zf, find some control inputs ul(t), u2(t) which will steer the system from zo to zf after some time T. The application of these results to the problem of steering the mobile robot with multiple trailers is covered in the next section.</p><p>We present three methods to steer the chained-form system: 1) Sinusoidal inputs.</p><p>2) Piecewise constant inputs.</p><p>3) Polynomial inputs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Sinusoidal Inputs</head><p>The first steering method that we consider uses sinusoidal inputs. Steering chained-form systems with sinusoids was originally proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[34]</ref>. The method that we have developed here is different from the original algorithm in that it steers all the states in one step, instead of one state at a time.</p><p>Given an m-state chained-form system, it is easily seen that the first two states, z1 and 2 2 , can be steered from their initial to their final positions using constant inputs over any time period T. Of course, the states 23, --e , z, will drift as a consequence of this.</p><p>By direct integration, it may be verified that a Combination of out of phase sinusoids applied to the inputs, The states 24,</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">ul(t) = Q</formula><p>, z, will drift in some fashion. Now, consider inputs with u2 having k times the frequency of u1, namely ul(t) = cy sin w t ug(t) = p COS If these inputs are applied over one period T = 27r/w, it may be verified directly by integration that The intuition behind this steering scheme lies in the different levels of Lie brackets. If we consider the input vector fields 91, g2 for the chained-form system, we note that [91, gz] = [0 0 1 0 0IT, precisely in the z3 direction. Motion in this first level Lie bracket is generated by cycling between the two input vector fields in a continuous manner described by the out-of-phase sinusoids. To get motion in the second level Lie bracket, [gl, [gl, 9211 = [0 0 0 1 0 . -. 0IT or equivalently the z4 direction, the input 212 completes two cycles for one cycle on ul. More generally, motion in the ad:lg2 = [0 e . -1 e 0IT or the zk+2 direction is achieved by using k times the frequency of u1 on 212.</p><p>The steering algorithm in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[34]</ref> is step by step: It first steers z1, 2 2 to their final positions using constant inputs, disregarding the other states. Then it steers z3 to its desired final position using sinusoids; zl, z2 will return to their final values. Now z4 can be steered, and similarly on down the chain, until all states are at their final positions. This is a simple algorithm that is easy to implement, but can be timeconsuming when there are many states to be steered.</p><p>We propose instead an "all-at-once" sinusoids method, combining all the frequencies on u2 together in one step and maps them to values in the state space (zf , e , z i ) . We d e h e &amp;o(Q, bo, -, bm-2) to be the value of z(T) when the chained-form system <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(27)</ref> is integrated starting at the initial condition zo and applying the inputs (29) over the time period [0, TI. We choose a1 # 0. We will show that #J=O is a local difFeomorphism by looking at its directional derivatives, and demonstrating that the Jacobian of &amp;O is nonsingular.</p><p>Let { e i } z l be the standard basis for Ht" and let E be small. the directional derivative of 4 in the e k direction is given by where These m directional derivatives are seen to be linearly independent; implying that the Jacobian of dZo is nonsingular, 0 and that #J=O is a l d diffeomorphism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark2:</head><p>We have dealt with the overparameterization of the input (m+l parameters: ao, al, bo, ..-, bm-2 and m states) by initially choosing a value for a1 and then solving the m equations for the remaining m input parameters. We note here that by choosing a fixed value for al, we are requiring ul to go through one period. Since u1 roughly corresponds to the driving input in a mobile robot system, paths planned using the sinusoidal method generally have one back-up or speed reversal, corresponding to the zerocrossing of 211. Parallel-parking type maneuvers seem particularly wellsuited to sinusoidal trajectdries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Piecewise Constant Inputs</head><p>The second method we investigate for steering chainedform systems uses piecewise constant inputs. This method was originally proposed by Monaco and Normand-Cyrot <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[30]</ref> and was inspired by multirate digital control. It is most easily understood in the context of nonholonomic motion planning simply as piecewise constant inputs.</p><p>Consider holding the inputs u1 and u2 constant over some small time period [0,8)</p><p>The chained-form state equations can then be integrated, and evaluated at time 8 to yield z l ( q = Zl(0) + u1,18 z2(8) = z2(0) + u 2 , J z2 z3(8) = z3(0) + z2(0)w, 18 + 211,1u2,1 7</p><p>We can now consider another pair of constant inputs on the time interval @, 28)</p><p>Integration of the state equations gives us ~( 2 5 ) as a function of z(a), q 2 , u2,2. Using .(a) from (30), we get an expression for ~( 2 8 ) in terms of z(o), u1,1, UI, 2, u2,1, u2,2. This procedure of piecewise integration and substitution can be repeated as many times as necessary.</p><p>For path planning, we choose to keep u1 at a constant value over the entire trajectory. We therefore iterate <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(30)</ref> m-1 times so as to have exactly m parameters for which to solve: 211, U ~J , -, ~2 , ~-1 .</p><p>The total time needed for steering is 6 = ( m -1)8. Although S can be chosen arbitrarily, a smaller time S will result in larger inputs U to achieve the same path.</p><p>The m equations which result from setting z(0) = zo and z(6) = zf are polynomial (of order m-2) in u1 but are linear in u2,1, . . , u2, m--l. Since u1 is easily determined from the remaining m -1 linear equations can be solved €or u2 quite easily. This is one of the reasons that we propose keeping u1 constant over the entire trajectory; if u1 varied, we would need to sdve high-order polynomial equations in the ui,k parameters.</p><p>It should be noted that if zf = zy, or the initial and final states agree in the 6rst coordinate, this method as stated so far will fail to yield a solution. From looking at the chainedform equations, it is obvious that if ~1 = 0, only the second state z2 can move; all other states must remain stationary. In practice, this case is dealt with by planning two paths, the first of which takes the initial condition to an intermediate state, the second of which joins the intermediate state with the goal position. The concatenation of these two paths is a valid trajectory between the start and goal. Our algorithm chooses the intermediate point zm halfway between the initial and final points in all coordinates except the first, which we choose to be offset from the starting position by a constant amount</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">~2 = (zf -z,O)/2, k = 2, * * . , m z;" = zy + const.</formula><p>The constant offset can be adjusted to fit the situation.</p><p>The procedure detailed in the previous paragraph is used when a parallel-parking trajectory is desired for the mobile robot with trailers, since the z1 direction in chained form corresponds to "sideways" in the original coordinates. We have found it practical to choose the constant offset at approximately twice the length of the entire robot and trailer system. A smaller offset will result in tighter tums and more lateral motion. If there are obstacles in the field, this constant offset gives a parameter that can be adjusted in an effort to avoid collisions.</p><p>Another reason for choosing u1 to be constant over the entire trajectory is that in the mobile robot and trailer system, this input is roughly equivalent to the driving velocity. Because of the coordinate transformation that maps u1 to the actual velocity VO, the actual velocity of the robot will not be constant, but in most cases it will not cross zero and change sign. This means that the robot will not have to execute backing-up maneuvers to achieve its final goal position.</p><p>The main drawback of the piecewise constant inputs is the discontinuity of u2. The models used in this paper are purely kinematic using as inputs the driving and steering velocities. In a real robot system, the inputs are not velocities but accelerations, or torques. When a path satisfying the velocity constraints is found, the input velocities need to be differentiated to find the corresponding accelerations. Of their very nature, the piecewise constant trajectories are not Merentiable at the switching points.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Polynomial Inputs is to use polynomial inputs</head><p>Yet another possibility for steering systems in chained form Tbis approach bas the advantage of a constant input on ul with the iadded advantage of the differentiability of U Z .</p><p>'Fhe time needed to steer the system from zo to zf is determined by the change desired in the first coordinate T = zfzf.</p><p>Once T has been found, the state (27) can be integrated using the initial condition z(0) = zo where the matrix entries Mi, j (T) have the form It may be shown that this matrix is nonsingular for T # 0. athough if zf -&lt; o the solution gives a negative time period, this situation is easily remedied by choosing u1 = -1.</p><p>As in the case of steering with piecewise constant inputs, this method will yield no solution when zfzf = 0. We follow the same procedure outlined in Section IV-B to deal with this case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Other Choices</head><p>Because of the simple form of the chained-form system, many different classes of input functions other than the three described above could be used to steer systems in this form.</p><p>The chief requirement is that there should be at least as many parameters in the input functions as there are states. For rnultitrailer systems, a desirable characteristic of the input functions is that u1 have few or no zero-crossings since these will correspond to fewer backups. In fact, the number of backups needed to complete a maneuver may be taken as a measure of complexity of an input class. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. SIMULATIONS AND OBSERVATIONS</head><p>We now have an extensive toolbox from which to choose for steering an N-trailer system. With two different coordinate transformations into chained form and at least three different methods for steering the system once it is in chained form, we can try to pick the best combination of coordinate transformation and input type for each start and goal point. There is as yet no formal way to define when one path is "better" than another, but as we mentioned earlier, we tend to think of desirable paths as those that have few backups and do not stray too far from the vicinity of the start and goal One of the things that must be considered is coordinate singularities. Although we have shown that all three methods proposed here will find a path between any start and goal points in the chained-form coordinates, there is no guarantee that this path, when transformed back into the actual coordinates, will avoid the transformation singularities. This must be checked for each desired path. If a singularity does result, another steering method might yield a valid path, or perhqs an intermediate point will need to be chosen, and the path planned in two or more steps.</p><p>In Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">5</ref> and<ref type="figure">6</ref>, we show two different paths for a frontwheel-drive car with two trailers. We have chosen the wheelbase of the car to be L1 = 0.5 units, and each trailer to have a length of LZ = L3 = 2 units. Each path was generated using points. techniques described in this paper: first, transforming the start and goal points into the chained-form coordinates; second, steering the chained-fom system using one of the methods from Section IV; and finally, transforming the trajectory back into the original coordinates.</p><p>The trajectory shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> represents the truck backing into a loading dock. The initial condition is position is (0, O,n/2, 7r/2, 7r/2, 7r/2). Coordinate transformation 2 is used, since the first coordinate transformation is singular at the goal position. In the figure, we have presented the trajectory of the front of the car ($0, yo) instead of the back of the second trailer (23, 9 3 ) to amplify the difference between the two steering methods; the trajectories of the second trailer are virtually identical.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> we again have chosen to present the path taken by the front car; this figure shows a parallel-parking maneuver.</p><p>Here we have used two different coordinate transformations with the same steering method. The trajectories in the chainedform coordinates are identical; however, a difference can be seen in the physical coordinates. Once again, the trajectory traced by the rear of the second trailer is very similar in both cases. Some scenes from a movie animation of this trajectory are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">7</ref>; in the movie we present the coordinates derived from transformation 1.</p><p>With the sinusoidal steering method, there is one parameter that can be adjusted independently of the start and goal positions; this is the magnitude of the sinusoid on the first input, or a1 in the terminology of Section IV-A. In constructing this movie, we examined several different values of al; a larger value of a1 will correspond to the car driving out farther before it starts backing into the space. We were able to choose a value for this parameter so that the car and trailer system did not hit any of the obstacles along its path. Although our planning method does not explicitly take obstacles into account, we wanted to show that the generated paths are "nice" in some sense and may avoid obstacles in many cases. We are hopeful that the techniques described in this paper for constructing feasible paths can be integrated with an obstacle-avoidance package to solve the complete path planning problem.</p><p>(z3, y3, e3, e2, el, eo) = (io, 10, 0, 0, 0, 0) and the final </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. S ~~~Y ~F U T U R E W O R K</head><p>In this paper we applied the machinery of exterior differential systems to the N-trailer problem. We showed that the multitdler system could be put into Gwrsat normal form, and that this is the dual to chained form. We solved the motion planning problem for the mobile robot pulling n trailers by converting the kinematic constraints into Goursat form, using this to convert the kinematic equations into chained-form, steering the chained-form system from an initial to a final position, then converting the trajectory back into the original coordinates. Three different methods for steering chained-form systems were proposed.</p><p>The work done in this paper has several natural avenues of continuation:</p><p>1) The generation of trajectories for the N-trailer system in an environment cluttered with obstacles. This line of work has been started in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[29]</ref> where the authors considered the motion of a single Hilare-like robot in a cluttered environment. Another approach for a Hilare-like robot was defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[26]</ref>. Other methods for obstacle avoidance which use optimization-based approaches may be found in [ 1 11 and [ 121.</p><p>2) The stabilization of open-loop trajectories. The trajectories generated by our method need to be stabilized, perhaps using a technique such as that outlined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[46]</ref>. There has also been considerable interest in stabilizing nonholonomic systems not to trajectories but to points. Although from Brockett's necessary condition [5], it follows that such stabilizing control laws cannot be both CO and time-invariant, methods using either discontinuous or time-varying feedback have been suggested in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[28]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[41]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4)</head><p>Generalized Goursat type canonical forms for exterior differential systems for higher codimension systems are discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[16]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[31]</ref> and were useful in transforming a fire truck system to chained form. The fire truck has three inputs: driving and steering in the front and another steering wheel at the tiller [7] (multiinput chained-form systems are also discussed in [34]). This work is as yet far from complete since there is a very large number of different possibilities for the normal form in this instance. Since this paper was written, a complete discussion of the application of the extended Goursat normal form to a multisteering n-trailer system has been completed; see <ref type="bibr">[MI.</ref> There are several examples of nonholonomic systems whose constraints fail to meet the conditions of the Goursat normal form, for example, the system modeling a circular finger tip rolling on a planar face <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[34]</ref>. The problem of steering such systems remains an open one. ACKNOWLEDGMENT</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>exists a large body of work on Pfa€€'s problem in the literatwe (see [6] for a historical overview). The formulation of the N-M e r problem as an exterior differential system allows us to draw on classical results by Goursat, Engel, Cartan, and others on classification and canonical forms. Most of the relevant results in this area are presented in abbreviated fashion in [6]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>il&lt;...&lt;i, Let R(M) be the algebra of exterior Merentid forms on M. The exterior derivative on R(M) is the unique map d : s2' + a' +' which satisfies the follawing properties: 1) ~f f E ~O ( M ) = C"(M) Wn df = af/azi dx; (or the usual gradient, relative to a local coordinate chart). 2) If8 E Or, n E R" then d ( 8 A a ) = d8Aa+(-1)'8Ada.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>' 1 b-</head><label>1</label><figDesc>which is the chained form for two input vector fields in R3 and will be discussed further in Section II-G.Engel's theorem applies to the case of two nonintegrable constraints in WP. Theorem 7-Engel's Theorem: Let I be a two-dimensional codistribution on R4 with dimI(') = 1 and dimI(2) = 0. Then there exist local coordinates such that (6) I = ( 4 4t 3 417 d53t 2 2 1 ) . P m $ Choose a basis I = {a1, a2} which is adapted to the derivedqag. It follows that d a l A a l # 0 and (da1)2Aa1 = 0 (by dimension count). Hence we can use Pfaff's theorem to To determine 6 2 , we use the structure of a2. Since a1 E I(1), we have doll A a ' A a2 = 0. But dal = -&amp;3 A d&amp; and hence a E adJ3 + bd&amp; modal. Since a2 # 0, it follows that we can not have both a and b = 0. We split the proof into two cases. Case I (a # 0): Since a2 is only determined mod cy1, we are free to scale a2 by any n o m function. Hence (7) and choosing &amp; = -b/a yields a basis for the codistribution which is in Engel's normal form. Notice that the basis is a transformed version of the original basis, namely find ~00rdinate~ Such that = &amp;4 -E; 41. U a2 G e 3 +a 8 1 mod</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Algorithm I :</head><label>:</label><figDesc>Given a codistribution I = { w l , --Construct a basis I = { a 1 , e e a , a"} which is adapted to the derived flag. Check the Goursat congruences to ensure they are satisfied for some A.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. The mobile robot Hilare with n trailers.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>TheFig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Showing the definitions of the angles and velocities of the ith trailer.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>( 12 )</head><label>12</label><figDesc>and (17). The one-forms ai are adapted to the derived flag in the following sense I(') =span{a', a2, --a , an, an+'} I(') =span{a', cy2, . . e , an)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>- 4 i</head><label>4</label><figDesc>sec2(8,-i+2d,-i+i) den-i+iAw,moda',E2, . . e , a x -Z$+l A w, modal, z2, -. . , a .sec3 (en-i+3en-i+2)All that remains now is to demonstrate that $ 0 mod I. da' = -Z2 A T .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>- t a</head><label>a</label><figDesc>(e, -en-l) dw,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>21 = f l ( z ) = x n zn+3 = f i ( x ) = 3/n-The one-form a1 = 0 may be written by dividing through by cos on as a1 = dyntan On dxn = d ~n + 3 -3n+2 d z l so that zn+2 = tan On. By the proof of Engel's theorem, we now need to find a, b so that a2 adzn+2 + b d z l mod a1 m o d d . But a2 = L n de,tan (On -On-1)vn. Hence, we have that E a sec2 &amp;dO, + b d x n -tan (On -On-+d z l . Now, we define b tan(&amp; -On-1) COS On -&amp;+l:= -a -Ln The remaining coordinates are found by solving the equations ai = dZn-i+4zn-i+3 d z l modal, , ai-' for i 2 2. The details are not particularly insighthd and are omitted here. Transformation 2-Coordinates of the Origin Seenfrom the Last Trailer: Yet another choice for fi corresponds to writing the coordinates of the origin as seen from the last trailer. This is reminiscent of a transformation used by Samson [38] in a different context, and is given by f l ( X ) = x n COS On + yn sin On.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Proposition 13 :</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Iheprocedure for transforming a nonholonomic control system such as<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(25)</ref> into chained form requires both a coordinate transformation and state feedback. Although for the most general case, a state feedback is given by= U ( . ) + b(z)ufor drift-free nonholonomic systems it is easily seen that a($) = 0. (If this were not the case, the state feedback would add a drift term to a drift-* system and could not result in a chained form.) The purpose of the state feedback ti = Q(z)u is therefore to transform the basis of the distribution A into chained form in the new coordinate system a g2(z) = -. a22 3Readers interested in the details of the transformation may obtain it f " the first author. Consider an N-trailer system with n+l rolling constraints at = 0 a ' ( . ) = sin e , &amp;rncos e , dyn = o (2) = Li+l dei+ltan (8i+l -&amp;)vi+l = 0 an+l-i i = 0, * * e , n -1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>=</head><label></label><figDesc>gl(z)ul + 92(.).2 the input functions have the physical meanings u 1 = e, is the linear velocity of the nth trailer, and u2 = w is the rotational velocity of the lead car. From a practical point of view, we have control only on the velocity vo of the lead car given in t e ~ Of by uo = sec (do -0, ) sec (el -e2) sec e,)v,.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. The front-wheel-drive car with n trailers. This model is similar to that of Hilare with trailers (see Fig. 1) with an extra axle added to the first body in the chain.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. A car pulling n luggage carts. Each trailer has two axles; the front axle is free to spin about its midpoint but the rear axle is constrained to be aligned with the body of the trailer.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>sin w t up(t) = p COS wt over one period T = 27r/w, will cause a motion in the 23 variable as follows z l ( q = Z l ( 0 ) Z 2 ( 5 9 = z2(0) IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON AUTOMATIC C€"ROL, VOL. 40, NO. 5, MAY 1995</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Z l ( t ) = Z l ( 0 ) + t . . Evaluating the foregoing at time T and setting z(T) = zf yields a total of m-1 equations &amp;e in the m-1 variables CO, * a 7 &amp;-2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Backing a car with two trailers into a loading dock. We show hqre trajectories found by two different steering methods for the same initial and final conditions. The solid line corresponds to the piecewise constant inputs and the dashed line to the polynomial inputs. The I, y trace of the front of the car is shown, since the trajectory of the rear trailer is virtually identical in the two cases. Both trajectories use the second coordinate transformation.Tlre input 00 is the dotted line in both graphs. Clips from a movie simulation of this trajectory con be seen in Fig.8.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>0Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Scenes from a movie animation, showing the front-wheel-drive car with two trailers (a six-state system) parallel-parking in the pmence of obstacles. Sinusoidal inputs were used for steering, and the magnitude of the periodic part of the driving input (a1 in the terminology of section IV) was adjusted so that the obstacles were avoided. The first coordinate transformation was used.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. These am scenes from a movie animation, showing the front-wheel-drive car with two trailers backing into a loading dock. Piecewise constant inputs were used to steer the chained-form system.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>V I , -e , up E Ai .are lioearly dependent</head><label></label><figDesc>if and only if v1 A .</figDesc><table /><note><p>A up = 0.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>n j=k+1 for some set of one-forms 8; E W ( M ) . Pm08 Tbe proof follows from application of Lemma 2 and Frobenius' theorem for vector fields. Let X, Y be two vector fields in A. Then [ X , Y ] E A ~W ~( [ X , Y ] ) = O i = k + l , . . -, n since the w's annihilate A. Now applying Lemma 2 we have [X, Y ] E A +=+ -dwi(X, Y ) + X w i ( Y ) -Y w i ( X ) = 0 u ~w ' ( x , Y ) = o i = ~c + l , . . . , n .</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">It follows that dwi must have the form in (2) since dw annihilates all vectors X, Y E A and {wk+l, . e , o n } form</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">a basis for the space of oneaforms which annihilate A.</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">C. pfaffian Exterior Differential System</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Formally, an exterior differential system is given by an ideal</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Z c a ( M ) that is closed under exterior differentiation. Recall</cell></row><row><cell>that an ideal Z satisfies</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>a E Z , p E R ( M )</cell><cell>a A p E Z .</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>This lemma gives the following version of Frobenius's</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>theorem.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Theorem 3-Frobeniw Theorem: Let A be a C"O distribu-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>tion of dimension k on M , an n-dimensional manifold. A is</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>involutive if and only if there exist n -k linearly independent</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>one-forms wk+', , wn which vanish on A and satisfy</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>a1 sin w t U 2 =bo + bl cos ut + b2 COS 2wt</head><label></label><figDesc>+ * * + bm-2 cos (m -2)wt.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(29)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">It is no longer as simple to choose appropriate values for the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">parameters (ao, a l , bo,</cell><cell>, b,-2) because of the drift that we</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">were able to ignore when we considered each state individu-</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">a y . It is still possible to integrate the chained-form equations sequentially, however, finding z1 ( t ) , z 2 ( t ) , z3 (t) , e . , z, ( t )</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">which result from the inputs (29) above. The state z ( t ) is</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">a function of the initial condition zo as well as the input</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">parameters ao, a l , bo, a . . , b m -2 . If we evaluate z ( T ) , with</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">T = 27r/w, all the sinusoidal functions will evaluate to</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">either zero or one. By setting z(T) = zf we get a set</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">of m polynomial equations in the (m+l) input parameters</cell></row><row><cell>(ao, a l , bo,</cell><cell cols="2">, bm-2). The following proposition guarantees</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">the existence of solutions to these equations at least locally</cell></row><row><cell>around zo.</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>u1 = a0 +</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Proposition 14 :</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Consider an m-state chained-form system with initial and h a l states zo, zf. If Izo -zfl &lt; S small, then there exist input paramem (ao, a</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>l , bo, e . e , bm-2) such that the inputs</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>u1 = @ + a 1 s i n w t</cell></row><row><cell>212 =bo + bl COS w t + b2 COS 2wt ' + * * * + b,-2 COS (m -2)wt</cell></row><row><cell>will steer the system from zo to zf in time T = 27r/w.</cell></row><row><cell>P m f i Consider the map</cell></row><row><cell>which takes values in the parameter space (ao, bo, -* , bm-2)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>as before &amp; o ( E ~z ) = zo + [O ET O ( E ) o(e)IT.</head><label></label><figDesc>Set al # 0, Now consider the input parameterized by Eel</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>I</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">u1 = E + a1 sin w t 212 2 0.</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Integrating the chained-form equations aud evaluating it at</cell></row><row><cell>time T will give</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">beo(Eel) = zo + [ET o O ( E ) e -. o ( E ) ] ~</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">where O ( E ) represents terms that are of linear and higher order</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">in E . Now consider the input parameterized by ~e 2</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">211 = a1 sin w t</cell><cell>212 = E .</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">We integrate and evaluate at T In this case it may be verified that O ( E ) terms are linear in E.</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">In general, for an input parameterized by Eek</cell></row><row><cell>u1 = a1 sin w t</cell><cell cols="2">212 = E cos(k -2)wt</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The work was supported in part by NSF Grant IRI-9014490 and a grant f" the Powell Foundation. D. Tilbury would also like to acknowledge an N &amp; T Ph.D. Fellowship for financial support of this work.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">They are also indebted to 0. S0rdalen for furnishing us with his transformation of the Ntrailer system into chained-form coordinates. D. Tiibury and S. Sastry would like to thank S. Mitter for his hospitality at LIDS and CICS at MIT where some of this research was done in the fall of 1992</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brockett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bushnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Canny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Giralt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lafferiere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Laumond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mirtich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Montgomery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Normand-Cyrot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Sluis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shadwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sussmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Maddocks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SL4M J. Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>On the maneuvering of vehicles</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical systems In</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Encyclopedia of Mathematics HI</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On nonholonomic mobile robots and optimal maneuvering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barraquand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-C</forename><surname>Latombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">4th Int. Symp. Intelligent Contr</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Albany, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="83" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control theory and singular Riemannian geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brockett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">New Directions in Applied Mathematics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brockett</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Millman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sussman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York; Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Birkhauser</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="191" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Diremnrinl Geometric Control Theory</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Exterior Diffemntial System</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bryant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Goldschmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Griffiths</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1991. 1981</date>
			<publisher>New York Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="27" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steering three-input chained form nonholonomic systems using sinusoids: The tiretruck example</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bushnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tilbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pmc. European Contr. Conf</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Groningen, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993. 1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1432" to="1437" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Complexi@ of Robot Motion Planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Canny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mobile robot navigation: Space modeling and decisional processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chatila</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Robotics Research: The Third Internatwnal Symposium</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">%her systeme von linearen partiellen Wewitialgleichungen erster ordnung</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W-L</forename><surname>Chow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematische Annalen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="1940">1940</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A global approach to nonholonomic motion planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Divelbiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Con$ Decision and Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1597" to="1602" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<pubPlace>Tucson, AZ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Foundations of nonholonomic motion planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fernan&amp;</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gurvits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Robotics Research Lab., Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Tech. Rep.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Optimal nonholonomic motion planning for a falling cat</title>
		<editor>N0-c Morion PcMning, 2 Li and J. Canny, Eds. N-ll</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">379421</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On differentially flat nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Flies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Uvine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rouchon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">P m . IFAC Nonlinear C o m l Systems Design Symp. (NOLCOS)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bordeaux, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">408412</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The GS algorithm for exact linearkation to Brunovsky normal form</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Shadwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="224" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated navigation and motion control system for autonomous multisensory mobile robots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chatila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vaisset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Robotics Research: The First International Symposium</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MlT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="214" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Smooth time-periodic feedback solutions for nonholonmic d o n planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Guwits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Nonholonomic Motion Pkanning, Z. Li and J. Canny</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="108" />
			<pubPlace>Norwell, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Planning, Geometry, and Complexity of Robot Motion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hopcroft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sharir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<pubPlace>Norwood, N J Ablex</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motion planning by piecewise constant or polynomial inputs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Jacob</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">P m . IFAC Nonlinear Contr. Syst. Design Symp. (NOLCOS)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="628" to="633" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<pubPlace>Bordeaux, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Motion planning for controllable systems without</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lafknim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>S -</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>P m . IEEE Int. CO?&amp; Robot. Automation</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1148" to="1153" />
			<pubPlace>Sacramento, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-C</forename><surname>Latombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">R o b Motion P W n g</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feasible trajectories for mobile robots with kinematic and environment constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-P</forename><surname>Laumond</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">P m . Int. Joint Conj A m y InteU</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Intelligent</forename><surname>Autommous System</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">0</forename><surname>Hertzberger</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C A</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987. 1987</date>
			<pubPlace>New York North Holland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Finding collision-free smooth trajectorim for a non-holonomic mobile robot</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controllability of multibody mobile robof</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Automst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="755" to="763" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A motion planner for nonbolonomic mobile mbots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-P</forename><surname>Laumond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Th</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE &quot;hns. Robot. Automal</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in p s s</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonhalonomic Motion Planning</title>
		<editor>Z. Li and J. Canny</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Norwell, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Exponential stabilization of driftless nonlinear conml system via time-varying, homogeneous feedback</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Closkey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="943" to="948" />
			<pubPlace>San Antonio, TX</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using skeletons for nonholonomic path pg among obstacles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Miaich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Canny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">P m . IEEE Int. Conj Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2533" to="2540" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<pubPlace>Nice, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An introduction to motion planning under multirate digital control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Monaco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Normand-Cymt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Cmf Dec. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1780" to="1785" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<pubPlace>Tucson, AZ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nilpotent bases for a class of non-integrable distributions with applications to trajectory generation for nonholonomic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Cantr., Signals, Syst.: MCSS</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>in p s</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Mathematical Intduction to Robotic Munipularion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boca Raton, FL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graspi GpeSpi ng and manipulation using multifingered mbot hands</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Robotics: P m . of Symposia in Applied Marhemntics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brocket&amp;</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ed</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Philadelphia, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Mathematical Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="128" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonholonomic motion planning: Steering using sinusoids</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Tmns</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal paths for a car that goes both forwards and backwan%</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Reeds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Shepp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pac$c J. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">145</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="393" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flatness and motion planning: The car with n trailers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rouchon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Flies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">P m . European Contr. Conf. Groningen: The Netherlands</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1518" to="1522" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Conj</forename><surname>Dec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2700" to="2705" />
			<pubPlace>San Antonio, TX</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Limits of highly oscillatory controls and the approxi&quot; of general paths by admissible lrajectories,&quot; in Pmc</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sussmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Con$ Dec. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">437442</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1941-12">Dec. 1941</date>
			<pubPlace>Brighton, UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonholonomic control systems: From steering to stabilization with sinusoids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Teel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1603" to="1609" />
			<pubPlace>Tucson, AZ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear in Int. J. Confr</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steering car-like systems with trailers using sinusoids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tilbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-P</forename><surname>Laumond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">P m . IEEE Int. Con$ Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1993" to="1998" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<pubPlace>Nice, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trajectory generation for the Ntrailer problem using Goursat normal form</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tiibuy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>UCBlERL M93/12</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electron. Res. Lab., Univ. of California</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<pubPlace>Berkeley, Tech</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tbe multi-steering N-trailer system: A case study of Goursat normal forms and prolongations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tilbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robust Nonlinear Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">bilization of trajectories for systems with nonholonomic constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vershik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Applications</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yu</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Borisovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yu</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gliklikh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Global Analysis-Studies and</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984. 1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="216" to="222" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Classical and non-classical dynamics with consmts</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hamiltonian systems with constraints and their meaning in mechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Archive for Rational Mechanics and Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From 1989 to 1994, she was a graduate student in electrical engineering and computer sciences at the University of California, Berkeley, where she received the M.S. degree and the Ph.D. degree in 1992 and 1994, respectively. She has been a Visiting Scholar at LAAS (Toulouse), U S (paris), MIT, and Harvard. She is currently an Assistant Professor in the Depaament of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics at the University of Michigan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tibury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Muwy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-P</forename><surname>Laumond</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Dr. Tilbury received an AT&amp;T Ph.D. fellowship (1991-1995) while at Berkely and the Eliahu Jury Award for excellence in systems research. Richard M. Morray (S&apos;WM91) received the B.S. degree in electrical engineering from California Institute of Technology in 1985, and the M.S. and Ph.D. degrees in electrical engineering and computer sciences from the University of California</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ann Arbor; Berkeley</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988 and 1991</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of California, Berkeley</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>1991 and is currently an Assistant Professor of Mechanical ogy, Pasadam His current research bterest include nonlinear control of mechanical systems witb applications to fight control and robotics. and active control of fluids with applications to propuIsion systems. E n m g at the Califwnia histitUte Of TeCh00l-S. Shankar &amp;try (S79-MSOSM90-F&apos;95</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
