<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A computed torque controller for uncertain robotic manipulator systems: Fuzzy approach</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2005-04-08">8 April 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zuoshi</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Complex Systems and Intelligence Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100080</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P.R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Jianqiang</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
							<email>jianqiang.yi@mail.ia.ac.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Complex Systems and Intelligence Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100080</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P.R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dongbin</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Complex Systems and Intelligence Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100080</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P.R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xinchun</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Complex Systems and Intelligence Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100080</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">P.R. China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A computed torque controller for uncertain robotic manipulator systems: Fuzzy approach</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2005-04-08">8 April 2005</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C8C2449196B46AA2A4BC2BC0D1D8FC6D</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.fss.2005.03.007</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 6 February 2004; received in revised form 4 March 2005; accepted 17 March 2005</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T17:27+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Robotic manipulators</term>
					<term>Computed torque control</term>
					<term>Fuzzy control</term>
					<term>Fuzzy basis function</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Computed Torque Control (CTC) is an effective motion control strategy for robotic manipulator systems, which can ensure globally asymptotic stability. However, CTC scheme requires precise dynamical models of robotic manipulators. To handle this impossibility, in this paper, a new approach combing CTC and Fuzzy Control (FC) is developed for trajectory tracking problems of robotic manipulators with structured uncertainty and/or unstructured uncertainty. Fuzzy part with a set of tunable parameters is employed to approximate lumped uncertainty due to parameters variations, unmodeled dynamics and so on in robotic manipulators. Based on Lyapunov stability theorem, it is shown that the proposed controller can guarantee stability of closed-loop systems and satisfactory tracking performances. The proposed approach indicates that CTC method is also valid for controlling uncertain robotic manipulators as long as compensative controller is appropriately designed. Finally, computer simulation results on a two-link elbow planar robotic manipulator are presented to show tracking capability and effectiveness of the proposed scheme.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>It is well known that robotic manipulators are complicated, dynamically coupled, highly time-varying, highly nonlinear systems that are extensively used in tasks such as welding, paint spraying, accurate positioning systems and so on. In these tasks, end-effectors of robotic manipulators are commended to move from one place to another, or to follow some given trajectories as close as possible. Therefore, trajectory tracking problem is the most significant and fundamental task in control of robotic manipulators. Motivated by requirements such as a high degree of automation and fast speed operation from industry, in the past decades, various control methods are introduced in the publications such as proportional, integration, derivative (PID) control <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, feed-forward compensation control <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, adaptive control <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>, variable structure control <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, neural networks control <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>, fuzzy control <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref> and so on.</p><p>As a predominant method in industrial robotic manipulators, traditional PID control has simple structure and convenient implementation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. However, some strong assumptions are required to be made, which involve that each joint of robotic manipulators is decoupled from others and the system has to be in the status of slow motion. Control performance degrades quickly as operating speed increases. Therefore, a robotic manipulator controlled in this way is only appropriate for relatively slow motion.</p><p>Robotic manipulator systems are inevitably subject to structured and unstructured uncertainty. Structured uncertainty is characterized by a correct dynamical model with parameters variations, which results from difference in weights, sizes and mass distributions of payloads manipulated by robotic manipulators, difference in links properties of robotic manipulators, difference in inaccuracies on torque constants of actuators and so on. Unstructured uncertainty is characterized by unmodeled dynamics, which is due to the presence of external disturbances, high-frequency modes of robotic manipulators, neglected time-delays and nonlinear frictions and so on.</p><p>Structured uncertainty can result in imprecision of dynamical models of robotic manipulators, and controllers designed for nominal parameters may not properly work for all changes in parameters. Adaptive control techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref> can be used in this case. However, adaptive control law is unable to handle unstructured uncertainty. To overcome this difficulty, variable structure control <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> that can simultaneously attenuate influences of both structured and unstructured uncertainty is employed. Unfortunately, undesirable chattering on sliding surface due to high frequent switching can deteriorate system performances, which cannot be eliminated completely.</p><p>Neural networks-based controllers for robotic manipulators are also extensively studied from early CMAC controllers <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and simple backpropagation neural networks controllers without theoretical analysis and stability security to stable-neural networks adaptive controllers with rigorous stability analysis using Lyapunov stability theory or passive theory, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and the references therein. Justification for using neural networks for robotic control lies in their excellent capability in learning any complicated mapping from training examples such that designed controllers are able to respond to unexpected situations. However, size of such neural networks becomes so large that powerful computational facilities are required.</p><p>For practical and complex control problem of robotic manipulators, various control approaches mentioned above naturally occur in our mind, but traditional and effective schemes also cannot be ignored. Computed Torque Control <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> (here abbreviated as CTC) is worth noting, because CTC is easily understood and of good performances. Briefly speaking, CTC is a linear control method to linearize and decouple robotic dynamics by using perfect dynamical models of robotic manipulator systems in order that motion of each joint can be individually controlled using other well-developed linear control strategies. However, CTC method for robotic manipulators suffers from two difficulties. First, CTC requires exact dynamical knowledge of robotic manipulators, which is apparently impossible in practical situations. Second, CTC is not robust to structured uncertainty and/or unstructured uncertainty, which may result in performance devaluation. Can we say that CTC is invalid for actual robotic manipulators according to the drawbacks above? The answer is "No", of course. As a matter of fact, many researches have made great efforts in improvement of CTC-based control methods for uncertain robotic manipulators.</p><p>Wijesoma <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> considered a variable structure controller as a compensator for CTC, which required complex solution to inverse of inertial matrix. Neural networks as a function approximator to learn lumped uncertainty of robotic manipulator systems was added to CTC in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Tso <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> viewed error dynamical system as a reference model and designed a variable structure model reference adaptive controller to compensate for CTC. All of these schemes demonstrated that modified CTC scheme applying to uncertain robotic manipulator systems was also effective.</p><p>Fuzzy Logical System (here abbreviated as FLS) was introduced by Zadeh <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> in 1965. One of successful fuzzy applications is to model complex nonlinear systems by a set of fuzzy rules. One important property of fuzzy modeling approaches is that FLS is a universal approximator <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. In other words, FLS can approximate virtually any nonlinear functions to arbitrary accuracy provided that enough rules are given. FLS for control, i.e. Fuzzy Control (here abbreviated as FC) can integrate expertise of skilled personnel into control procedure and mathematical model is not required. Over the last few years, FC for complex nonlinear systems have been developed extensively <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>.</p><p>Recently, much attention has been devoted to FC for robotic manipulators. Sun <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> combined FC and variable structure control to construct a controller, where FLS was greatly simplified by using system representative point and its derivative as inputs. Control laws designed by Hsu <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> consisted of a regular fuzzy controller and a supervisory control term, which ensured stability of closed-loop systems. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, two FC schemes for a class of uncertain continuous-time multi-input multi-output nonlinear dynamical systems were derived. Satisfactory performances were achieved by applying them to robotic manipulators. The latest survey on FC for robotic manipulators can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and references cited therein.</p><p>In this paper, it is supposed that robotic manipulator systems with structured uncertainty and/or unstructured uncertainty can be separated as two subsystems: nominal system with precise dynamical knowledge and uncertain system with unknown knowledge. An approach of CTC plus FC compensator is proposed. The nominal system is controlled using CTC and for uncertain system, a fuzzy controller is designed. Here the fuzzy controller acts as compensator for CTC. Parameters updating laws of the fuzzy controller are derived using Lyapunov stability theorem. In this way, uniformly ultimate boundedness and asymptotic stability of closed-loop systems are achieved. The validity of the proposed control scheme is verified by simulations on a two-link elbow planar robotic manipulator.</p><p>This paper is organized into five sections. Following the introduction, in Section 2, some preliminaries are addressed, which consist of mathematical notations, mathematical definitions, stability lemmas, brief introduction of FLS, dynamical models of robotic manipulators with uncertainties, and detailed explanation related to CTC for robotic manipulators. Section 3 is devoted to controller design based on CTC plus fuzzy compensator and stability proof based on Lyapunov stability theory. Section 4 includes simulation results to illustrate feasibility of the proposed strategy. Some conclusion remarks are finally included in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Preliminaries</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Mathematical notations, definitions and stability lemmas</head><p>The following notations and definitions will be used extensively throughout the paper.</p><p>Let R, R n , R n×m be real numbers, real n-vectors, and real n × m matrices, respectively. min (Q) and max (Q) indicate the minimum and the maximum eigenvalue of matrix Q ∈ R n×n , respectively. Let A T denote the transpose of matrix A and diag[•] denote a diagonal matrix. It is assumed that all matrices are assumed compatible in dimension for the purpose of computations. Definition 1. The trace of a square matrix A = [a ij ] ∈ R n×n , denoted by Tr(A), is defined as the sum of diagonal elements of the matrix A.</p><p>Corollary 1. The trace of a matrix and the trace of its transpose are the same, i.e. Tr(A) = Tr(A T ) for ∀A ∈ R n×n .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corollary 2. The trace of a scalar is equal to itself, i.e. Tr(y)</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">= y, for ∀y ∈ R. Specially, if x ∈ R n , y ∈ R m and A ∈ R n×m , then x T Ay is a scalar satisfying Tr(x T Ay) = x T Ay. Corollary 3. If x, y ∈ R n , trace of scalar x T y is equal to that of matrix yx T , i.e. Tr(x T y) = Tr(yx T ).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corollary 4. The derivative of the trace of a time-varying matrix is equal to the trace of the derivative of the matrix. Specially, for a time-varying matrix</head><formula xml:id="formula_1">A(t) ∈ R n×n and a constant matrix ∈ R n×n , the relationship d(Tr(A T A))/dt = 2Tr(A T Ȧ) naturally holds.</formula><p>Definition 2. The norm of a vector x ∈ R n is defined as x = ( n i=1 x 2 i ) 1/2 and the Frobenius norm of a matrix A = [a ij ] ∈ R n×n is defined by A = [Tr(A T A)] 1/2 . In the case where x is a scalar, x denotes its absolute value. Definition 3. Let f (t) be a function on [0, ∞) of signal spaces. L 2 space and L ∞ space are defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">L 2 = {f : R + → R| f 2 = ∞ 0 |f | 2 dt &lt; ∞} and L ∞ = {f : R + → R| f ∞ = ∞ 0 sup t∈[0,∞) |f | dt &lt; ∞}, respectively.</formula><p>From a signal point of view, the signal in L 2 space has finite energy and that in L ∞ space is bounded. Definition 4. The solutions of ẋ = f (x, t) are said to uniformly ultimately bounded (UUB) if there exist constants b, c and T ( ) for every ∈ (0,c) such that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">|x(t 0 )| &lt; ⇒ |x(t)| &lt; b, ∀t &gt; t 0 + T .</formula><p>They are globally UUB if above condition holds for an arbitrarily large .</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Lemma 1. Let f (t) be a time-varying function. If f (t), ḟ (t) ∈ L ∞ and f (t) ∈ L 2 , then f (t) → 0 as t → ∞.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Description of fuzzy logic systems</head><p>An FLS is composed of four main components: a fuzzifier, a fuzzy rule base, a fuzzy inference engine and a defuzzfier as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The fuzzifier maps non-fuzzy input space to fuzzy sets and the defuzzifier performs an opposite task to map fuzzy sets to non-fuzzy output space. Fuzzy sets are characterized by their membership functions (•)'s. The fuzzy inference engine performs a mapping from fuzzy sets in input space U ∈ R n to fuzzy sets in output space V ∈ R m based on fuzzy rules. Finally, it is assumed that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">U = U 1 × U 2 × • • • × U n , U i ∈ R, (i = 1, 2, . . . , n) and V = V 1 × V 2 × • • • × V m , V k ∈ R, (k = 1, 2, . .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>. , m).</head><p>There are many choices for each part of an FLS. Therefore, a particular FLS could be any combination of these choices. In this paper, the following FLS is under the consideration. The fuzzy rule base consists of a collection of fuzzy IF-THEN rules:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">R j : if x 1 is A j 1 and x 2 is A j 2 and • • • • • • and x n is A j n , then y 1 is B j 1 and y 2 is B j 2 and • • • • • • and y m is B j m ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where x = [x 1 , x 2 , . . . , x n ] T and y = [y 1 , y 2 , . . . , y m ] T are input vectors and output vectors of the FLS, respectively. A j i (i = 1, 2, . . . , n) and B j k (k = 1, 2, . . . , m) are linguistic variables of fuzzy sets in subspace U i and V k , described by their membership functions A j i (x i ) and B j k (y k ), j = 1, 2, . . . , M. M is total number of the fuzzy rules. By using product inference, singleton-fuzzifier, and center-average defuzzifier strategies, output of the FLS can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">y(x) = ˆ (x| ˆ ) = M j =1 ȳj n i=1 A j i (x i ) M j =1 n i=1 A j i (x i ) = ˆ (x), (<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">)</formula><p>where </p><formula xml:id="formula_9">A j i (x i ) is</formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">( ȳj ) = 1. ˆ =       ȳ1 1 ȳ2 1 • • • ȳM 1 ȳ1 2 ȳ2 2 • • • ȳM 2 . . . . . . . . . . . . ȳ1 m ȳ2 m • • • ȳM m       ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>is adjustable parameter matrix and (x) = [ 1 (x), 2 (x), . . . , M (x)] T is fuzzy basis function vector, in which j (x) is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">j (x) = n i=1 A j i (x i ) M j =1 n i=1 A j i (x i ) (j = 1, 2, . . . , M). (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">)</formula><p>FLS is selected to control nonlinear and uncertain robotic manipulator systems for two reasons. First, FLS has been proven to be capable of universally approximating any well-defined nonlinear functions over a compact set to arbitrary accuracy. Second, there exist other types of universal approximators such as multi-layer neural networks, radial basis function neural networks and so on. However, only FLS is constructed from IF-THEN rules using some specific fuzzy inference, fuzzification, and defuzzification strategies. Therefore, linguistic information from human experts can be incorporated into FLS in a systematic way <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Problem formulation</head><p>In this subsection, dynamical models of robotic manipulators with uncertainties and idea of CTC for robotic manipulators will be presented in detail.</p><p>According to Lagrange theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, dynamical equations of robotic manipulators with n serial links incorporating external disturbances can be expressed as M(q) q + C(q, q) q + G(q) + f (q, q) = , <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> where q, q, q ∈ R n are vectors of joint accelerations, velocities, and positions, respectively. M(q) ∈ R n×n is a symmetric positive definite inertia matrix; C(q, q) q ∈ R n being a vector of centripetal and Coriolis forces. G(q) ∈ R n denotes gravity vectors and f (q, q) ∈ R n is unmodeled dynamics including friction terms and external disturbances and so on. ∈ R n represents torque vectors exerting on joints. The structural properties of robotic manipulators hold such as boundedness of M(q), C(q, q) and f (q, q). For convenience, dynamical model ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) can be rewritten as the following compact form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">M(q) q + H (q, q) + f (q, q) = ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where H (q, q) = C(q, q) q + G(q). The task of trajectory tracking for robotic manipulators can be describe as: given desired trajectories of manipulator joints q d ∈ R n , find control input such that actual trajectories q of manipulator joints in (6) can tend to q d as time goes to infinity. In this paper, the following assumption is required.</p><p>Assumption 1. The desired trajectories q d are continuous and bounded known functions of time with bounded known derivatives up to the second order.</p><p>The parameters M(q), C(q, q) and G(q) in dynamical model ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">6</ref>) are functions of physical parameters of manipulators like links masses, links lengths, moments of inertial and so on. The precise values of these parameters are difficult to acquire due to measuring errors, environment and payloads variations. Therefore, here it is assumed that actual values M(q), C(q, q) and G(q) can be separated as nominal parts denoted by M 0 (q), C 0 (q, q), G 0 (q) and uncertain parts denoted by M(q), C(q, q), G(q), respectively. These variables satisfy the following relationships:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">M(q) = M 0 (q) -M(q), C(q, q) = C 0 (q, q) -C(q, q), G(q) = G 0 (q) -G(q). (<label>7</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">)</formula><p>Suppose that dynamical models of robotic manipulators are known precisely and unmodeled dynamics are excluded, i.e. M(q), C(q, q), G(q) in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_14">7</ref>) and f (q, q) in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">6</ref>) are all zeros. At this time, dynamical models ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">6</ref>) can be converted into the following nominal models:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">M 0 (q) q + H 0 (q, q) = , (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">)</formula><p>where H 0 (q, q) = C 0 (q, q) q + G 0 (q). Now considering the control law</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">= M 0 (q)( qd -K v ė -K p e) + H 0 (q, q),<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where qd, qd , q d ∈ R n are desired trajectories vectors of joint accelerations, velocities, and positions, respectively. e = q -q d is defined as trajectory tracking error vectors. K p and K v are proportional and derivative constant matrices, respectively. Substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">9</ref>) into (8) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">ë + K v ė + K p e = 0.<label>(10)</label></formula><p>It is obvious that errors will asymptotically tend to zero if proportional gain K p and derivative gain K v are chosen in the favorable situation. The control law ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">9</ref>) is termed as Computed Torque Control <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p><p>Remark 1. It is simple to understand that CTC approach is based on feedback linearization technique, which results in a linear time-invariant closed-loop system <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, implying acquirement of globally asymptotical stability. Furthermore, explicit conditions for performance indices may be obtained in terms of controller gain matrices. More specifically, globally asymptotical stability is guaranteed provided that K p and K v in (9) are symmetric and positive definite constant matrices.</p><p>According to analysis above, CTC strategy relies on strong assumptions that exact knowledge of robotic dynamics is precisely known and unmodeled dynamics has to be ignored, which is impossible in practical engineering. Motivated by separation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, idea of CTC introduced above, and capability for approximating nonlinear functions of FLS, one can image that CTC is used to control nominal system and another FLS-based controller attaching to CTC for uncertain system can be designed. In this way, applying <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">9</ref>) to practical manipulator systems (6) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">ë + K v ė + K p e = , (<label>11</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">)</formula><p>where = M -1 0 [ M(q) q + H (q, q) -f (q, q)], in which H (q, q) satisfies H (q, q) = H 0 (q, q) -H (q, q). is a function of joint variables, physical parameters, parameters variations, unmodeled dynamics and so on. On the other hand, denotes the sum of structured uncertainty and unstructured uncertainty. Thus, here is termed as lumped uncertain function of robotic dynamics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Remark 2.</head><p>From expression of , it is easily seen that lumped uncertainty results from parameters variations including inertia uncertainty, gravity uncertainty, Coriolis uncertainty and unmodeled dynamics such as external disturbances. The existence of causes CTC invalid and makes stability of robotic manipulators difficult to acquire.</p><p>Up to now, control objective can be restated as: seek a control law based on FLS as a compensator for CTC such that joint motions of robotic systems (6) can follow desired trajectories. Overall control law becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">= 0 + c , (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">)</formula><p>where 0 is CTC defined like ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">9</ref>) and c is a compensating torque to be determined below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Design of fuzzy compensator controller</head><p>In this section, a fuzzy compensator controller serving as a compensator for CTC is considered and designed in detail. Firstly, it is assumed that the right-hand side in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">11</ref>) can be represented by an ideal FLS as</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">(z) = W * (z) + (z),<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where (z) is reconstruction error of FLS, (z) = [ 1 (z), 2 (z), . . . , N (z)] T is fuzzy basis function vector fixed by the designer and i (z) = (i = 1, 2, . . . , N) is corresponding to Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">4</ref>), and z(t) is given by <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">13</ref>) is an optimal weight matrix satisfying that</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">z(t) = [ qT , qT , q T ] T . (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">W * = [w ij ] ∈ R n×N in Eq. (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_28">W * = arg min W Sup x∈D z |ˆ (z| Ŵ ) -(z)| . (<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">)</formula><p>Here, D z denotes the sets of suitable bounds of z. It is assumed that z never reaches boundary of D z . In <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>, ˆ (z| Ŵ ) is an estimation of (z), which can be approximated using an FLS as (2):</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">ˆ (z| Ŵ ) = Ŵ (z), (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_31">)</formula><p>where Ŵ is adjustable weight matrix corresponding to Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">3</ref>). Define compensative control law c in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_32">as c = -M 0 (q)ˆ (z| Ŵ ). (<label>17</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">)</formula><p>Using control law <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>, closed-loop system becomes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">ë + K v ė + K p e = ˜ (z), (<label>18</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">)</formula><p>where expression of ˜ (z) is</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">˜ (z) = (z) -ˆ (z| Ŵ ) = (z) + W (z),<label>(19)</label></formula><p>with W = W * -Ŵ denoting error of weight matrix.</p><p>Supposed that state vector is defined as x = [e T , ėT ] T , the state-space equation has form as</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">ẋ = Ax + B ˜ (z),<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">A = 0 -K p I -K v , B = 0 I .</formula><p>To proceed with subsequent development and closed-loop stability analysis, the following assumptions are made: Assumption 2. The reconstruction error (z) is bounded, i.e. c for ∀z ∈ D z with known c .</p><p>Assumption 3. The norm of optimal weight matrix are bounded so that W * c w .</p><p>Remark 3. According to universal approximation theorem <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, the state variables of an FLS have to be limited in a given compact set so that optimal parameter exists. In this paper, compact set D z in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_28">15</ref>) is assumed to be large enough so that state variables remain within D z under closed-loop control. Thus, Assumption 2 is reasonably made. Moreover, the upper bound c of reconstruction error can be arbitrarily reduced by increasing number of fuzzy rules. Assumption 3 is used for stability analysis below <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>Theorem. Consider robotic manipulator systems with structured uncertainty and/or unstructured uncertainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>, supposed that Assumptions 1-3 are satisfied. The control law is provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>, which consists of CTC part <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> and fuzzy part <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. The parameters in fuzzy part are tuned by</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">˙Ŵ = -1 B T P x T , (<label>21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">)</formula><p>where = diag( 1 , 2 , . . . , n ), i &gt; 0 (i = 1, 2, . . . , n) is gain matrix and P is positive definite solution of the following Riccati equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">A T P + P A + P T BB T P + Q = 0, (<label>22</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">)</formula><p>where Q is a constant matrix with appropriate dimensions given in advance. Then:</p><p>(1) x(t) in closed-loop systems are uniformly ultimately bounded.</p><p>(2) If reconstruction error ∈ L 2 , i.e.</p><p>∞ 0 2 (t) dt &lt; ∞, trajectory tracking errors of robotic manipulators tend to zero as time goes to infinity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proof. (1) Consider the following Lyapunov-function candidate:</head><formula xml:id="formula_43">V = x T P x + Tr( W T W ), (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">)</formula><p>with W = W * -Ŵ . Taking the time derivative of V along <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_45">results in V = x T (A T P + P A)x + ˜ T B T P x + x T P B ˜ + 2Tr( W T ˙W ) = x T (A T P + P A)x + 2x T P B ˜ -2Tr( ˙Ŵ T W ). (<label>24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_46">)</formula><p>Applying repeatedly the properties of trace of matrix and substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_39">21</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_41">22</ref>) into (24) leads to</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">V = -x T (P T BB T P + Q)x + 2x T P B( + W ) -2Tr( W T ˙Ŵ ) = -x T (P T BB T P + Q)x + 2x T P B + 2x T P B W -2Tr( W T ˙Ŵ ) = -x T ( T BB T P + Q)x + 2x T P B + 2Tr( T W T B T P x) -2Tr( W T ˙Ŵ ) = -x T (P T BB T P + Q)x + 2x T P B + 2Tr( W T B T P x T ) -2Tr( W T ˙Ŵ ) = -x T (P T BB T P + Q)x + 2x T P B + 2T r[ W T (B T P x T -˙Ŵ )] = -x T (P T BB T P + Q)x + 2x T P B + 2T r[ W T (B T P x T -( -1 B T P x T ))]. (<label>25</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_48">)</formula><p>Then the equation above becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">V = -x T (P T BB T P + Q)x + 2x T P B = -x T Qx -(B T P x -) T (B T P x -) + T -x T Qx + T . (<label>26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_50">)</formula><p>It is easy to get Vmin (Q) x 2 + 2 , thus V (x, W ) is negative outside the following compact set x :</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">x = x(t)|0 x(t) 1 min (Q) . (<label>27</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">)</formula><p>Assumption 3 implies that W is bounded (equivalently, W is bounded), then x(t) in closed-loop systems are uniformly ultimately bounded.</p><p>(2) Integration of Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_49">26</ref>) from t = 0 to ∞ can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">∞ 0 x T Qx dt ∞ 0 T dt + V (0) -V (∞). (<label>28</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_55">Then ∞ 0 x 2 dt k/ min (Q), (<label>29</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_56">)</formula><p>where <ref type="formula" target="#formula_55">29</ref>), it is clear that x ∈ L 2 is satisfied. The boundedness of x(t) above implies x ∈ L ∞ . From closed-loop dynamic equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> and boundedness of x(t), W (t), and (t), one can get ẋ ∈ L ∞ . i.e. x ∈ L 2 ∩ L ∞ , ẋ ∈ L ∞ . Thus, lim t→∞ x(t) = 0 is achieved from Lemma 1. Therefore, whole closed-loop system is asymptotically stable, i.e. trajectory tracking errors converge to zero as time goes to infinity.</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">k = ∞ 0 T dt + V (0) -V (∞). Noting that V (t) is a non-increasing function of time and low bounded, this implies V (0) -V (∞) &lt; ∞ and ∞ 0 2 (t) dt &lt; ∞, resulting in k &lt; ∞. From (</formula><p>According to above analysis, the architecture of closed-loop system is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p><p>Remark 4. The core idea of the proposed scheme above lies in that lumped uncertainty can be approximated by an FLS. The updating law (21) of weight parameters is obtained using Lyapunov stability theorem. In expression <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>, is fuzzy basis function calculated by selected membership functions according to aforementioned Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">4</ref>).</p><p>Remark 5. The membership functions are designed by trial-and-play in the proposed scheme. In addition, the optimal weight is not required for fuzzy compensator as updating law <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> for parameter matrix of the FLS can result in convergence of trajectory tracking errors according to the proof above. What we need to know is only the existence of optimal weight, which is apparent from Remark 3.</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">K v K p Robotic Manipulator + + + + + + - - q d q d q d τ 0 τ τ c q q ) ( 0 q q, H u Fuzzy Compensator q M 0 (q)</formula><p>Riccati Equation Remark 6. All the parameters in the proposed scheme may be uncertain, which is true in practical situation. In some publications like <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, it is clearly unrealistic that only Coriolis terms, gravity terms, and friction terms may be uncertain, whereas inertia matrix was assumed known exactly.</p><p>Remark 7. Noted that the inputs of designed FLS include acceleration signal q and CTC part also requires acceleration signal qd , here it is assumed that accelerations are measurable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Simulation results</head><p>In this section, to illustrate validity of the proposed method, a two-link planar elbow manipulator <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> is simulated, whose dynamical model can be described by Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>. With respect to the manipulator, the matrices in (5) are listed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">M(q) = 1 + 3 + 2 2 cos(q 2 ) 3 + 2 cos(q 2 ) 3 + 2 cos(q 2 ) 3 , C(q, q) = -2 sin(q 2 ) q2 -2 sin(q 2 ) q1 -2 sin(q 2 ) q2 2 sin(q 2 ) q1 0 , G(q) = g 111 + g 112 g 12</formula><p>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">where 1 = I 1 + m 1 4 + m 2 l 2 1 , 2 = m 2 l 1 l 2 2 , 3 = I 2 + m 2 l 2 2 4 , g 111 = 1 2 m 1 l 1 + m 2 l 1 g cos(q 1 ), g 112 = g 12 = 1 2 m 2 l 2 g cos(q 1 + q 2 ),</formula><p>with q i (i = 1, 2) denote angular positions (rad), m i (i = 1, 2) are links masses (kg), l i (i = 1, 2) represent links lengths (m), I i (i = 1, 2) are inertia moment of link i about corresponding center of <ref type="figure">3</ref>. Two-link planar elbow manipulator. gravity (kg m 2 ). g = 10 m/s 2 is acceleration of gravity. Point E in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> denotes the end-effector of the robotic manipulator. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> shows parameters used in simulations. For the purpose of comparison, simulation studies in three cases are conducted. The object is to design control input in order to force joint variables q = [q 1 , q 2 ] T to track desired trajectories as time goes to infinity. Here, desired joint trajectories to be tracked are assumed to be q d = [q 1d , q 2d ] T with q 1d = 0.5 cos(t) + 0.2 sin(3t) and q 2d = -0.2 sin(2t) -0.5 cos(t). In the following three cases, it is all assumed that initial positions of joints are q 1 (0) = q 2 (0) = 4 and initial velocities of joints are zeros.</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">E C q 1 q 2 l 1 l 2 m 1 , I 1 m 2 , I 2 X Y Fig.</formula><p>Case 1: Firstly, CTC scheme applying to robotic manipulators with precise dynamical models is considered. The parameters of robotic manipulators are equal to nominal values in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>. The designed parameters in CTC (9) are picked as <ref type="bibr">(5.5, 5.5)</ref> and K p = diag <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">K v = diag</formula><p>Figs. <ref type="figure">4</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref> show tracking performances of two joints in this case, respectively. In the two figures, the solid lines depict desired trajectories and the dotted lines denote actual trajectories, respectively. As can be seen from Figs. <ref type="figure">4</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>, tracking errors of two joints occur at the very beginning of the process and after a few seconds, actual trajectories and desired trajectories almost overlap each other. Thus, CTC method exhibits Excellent tracking performances when precise dynamical knowledge of robotic manipulators without unmodeled dynamics is known. Remark 9. From expression <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, CTC approach is a linear control technique and relies on exact cancellation of nonlinear dynamics of robotic manipulators. Therefore, precise parameters in dynamical models have to be known. Additionally, there are only two design parameters so that they are easily adjusted according to system responses. However, requirements that exact knowledge of dynamics and ignorance of unmodeled dynamics make CTC method unattractive to industry.</p><p>Case 2: Here the same control laws with previous case in both forms and parameters are applied to robotic manipulators, which is supposed to be influenced by structured uncertainty (parameters variations) and unstructured uncertainty (external disturbances). In other words, the control schemes are designed according to nominal parameters instead of actual parameters. Moreover, external disturbances are considered and assumed to be f (q, q) = [sin(t), cos(t)] T . The simulation results of tracking performances for the first link and those for the second link are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>, respectively. In Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>, desired trajectories and actual trajectories are depicted with solid lines and dotted lines, respectively. Compared with previous case, it can be easily acquired that tracking performance of CTC method greatly deteriorates when there is no exact dynamical knowledge of robotic manipulators available and unmodeled dynamics of robotic manipulators are taken into considerations.</p><p>Remark 10. Here, the simulation results of robotic manipulators subjected to simultaneous structured uncertainty and unstructured uncertainty are shown. As a matter of fact, it is found from lots of conducted simulations in this case that if unmodeled dynamics, i.e. external disturbances, are neglected and  parameters variations are considered, or opposite case, parameters variations are excluded and unmodeled dynamics are considered, then tracking performances are also much worse than case 1. Therefore, it is safely said that CTC approach is of good performances only when dynamical models of robotic manipulators are known precisely and free from unmodeled dynamics.</p><p>Case 3: From theoretical analysis and simulations above, if CTC is applied to uncertain robotic manipulator, then additional controller compensating for CTC should be required and appropriately designed. In this case, the proposed CTC plus fuzzy compensator is used to control robotic manipulators with uncertainties. Here, FLS is used for estimating lumped uncertainty function in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> due to parameters variations and unmodeled dynamics. The FLS has joint accelerations q, joint velocities q, joint positions q as inputs. Namely, input vectors of the FLS are of form like z</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">= [z T 1 , z T 2 , z T 3 ] T with z T 1 = [z 11 , z 12 ], z T 2 = [z 21 , z 22 ] and z T 3 = [z 31 , z 32 ],</formula><p>where z 1i = qi , z 2i = qi and z 3i = q i for i = 1, 2. Additionally there are two joint angles. Therefore, it is clear that the dimension of the inputs and outputs of the FLS is 6 and 2, respectively. For each input vector, five Gaussian membership functions are defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">F 1 ij (z ij ) = exp - z ij + 2 0.5 2 , F 2 ij (z ij ) = exp - z ij + 1 0.5 2 , F 3 ij (z ij ) = exp - z ij 0.5 2 , F 4 ij (z ij ) = exp - z ij -1 0.5 2 , F 5 ij (z ij ) = exp - z ij -2 0.5 2 i = 1, 2; j = 1, 2, 3.</formula><p>To reduce the number of fuzzy rules, like <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, 30 (2 × 3 × 5) fuzzy rules are employed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">R k ij : if z ij is F k ij then 1 is B k 1 and</formula><p>2 is B k 2 , where i = 1, 2; j = 1, 2, 3 and k = 1, 2, . . . , 5. 1 and 2 are two outputs of the FLS satisfying = [ 1 , 2 ] T . In this case, the initial values of weight parameters Ŵ (0) are set equal to zero matrix. The positive definite matrix Q in Riccati equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> and the gain matrix in updating law <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> are selected as Q = diag <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15)</ref> and = diag <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9)</ref>, respectively. The external disturbances are assumed to be f (q, q) = [sin(t), cos(t)] T , also the same as case 2. The tracking performances for two joints of robotic manipulators with variations in parameters and unmodeled dynamics are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref>, respectively. The control efforts for joints 1 and 2 are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">10</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11</ref>, respectively.</p><p>Remark 11. The exclusive difference between case 2 and this case lies in that designed controller in this case includes a fuzzy compensator, however, used control law in case 2 does not have fuzzy part. From  the comparison between Figs. 8 and 6 and comparison between Figs. 9 and 7,it can be seen that fuzzy compensator greatly improves tracking performances.</p><p>Remark 12. The approaches combing FC and variable structure control are very popular in FC for robotic manipulators <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. It is well known that there exists inevitable chattering due to introduction of variable structure control. However, one can say from control input signals in Figs. 10 and 11 that there is almost no high-frequent chattering even in presence of external noisy disturbances and fast varying parameters. Noted that simulation time here is taken as 20 s unlike relatively short simulation time in other publications.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>This paper addresses trajectory tracking problems of robotic manipulators with structured uncertainty and unstructured uncertainty. Firstly, fundamental ideas and restrictions of conventional control method for robotic manipulators, so-called Computed Torque Control scheme, were presented in detail. Based on CTC as a nominal controller, a fuzzy compensation is designed to handle inevitable uncertainties. In the proposed scheme, the fuzzy compensative controller is used for approximating lumped uncertainty, whose weight parameters are adjusted based on Lyapunov stability theorem. In this way, stability of closed-loop systems can be guaranteed and tracking performances can be achieved. In order to illustrate feasibility of the proposed scheme, application of the proposed scheme to a two-link elbow planar manipulator is provided.</p><p>Furthermore, one contribution of this paper is that it provides a novel idea and method, i.e. CTC plus compensator, to design tracking controllers for robotic manipulators with uncertainties. It is indicated that tradition methods could not be neglected in designing controllers for complex plants. On the other hand, extensive applicable fields of FLS are also shown so that FC can handle control problems of complex systems by combining with other well-developed algorithms.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Configuration of fuzzy logic systems.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Diagram of closed-loop systems.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .Remark 8 .</head><label>48</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Tracking of joint 1 when CTC applying to robotic manipulators without uncertainties.</figDesc><graphic coords="13,164.96,96.07,211.32,179.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Tracking of joint 2 when CTC applying to robotic manipulators without uncertainties.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,164.46,96.47,212.40,176.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Tracking of joint 1 when CTC applying to robotic manipulators with uncertainties.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,163.46,309.00,213.84,182.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Tracking of joint 2 when CTC applying to robotic manipulators with uncertainties.</figDesc><graphic coords="15,163.46,96.71,213.84,179.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Tracking of joint 1 when CTC plus fuzzy compensator applying to robotic manipulator with uncertainties.</figDesc><graphic coords="16,163.46,96.71,213.84,179.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Tracking of joint 2 when CTC plus fuzzy compensator applying to robotic manipulator with uncertainties.</figDesc><graphic coords="16,163.46,326.88,213.84,179.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Control input u 1 for joint 1.</figDesc><graphic coords="17,163.46,96.19,213.84,149.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Control input u 2 for joint 2.</figDesc><graphic coords="17,163.46,288.62,213.84,153.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>membership function value of fuzzy variable x i , ȳj is the point at which B j</figDesc><table><row><cell>k</cell><cell>(y k ) achieves</cell></row><row><cell>its maximum value, and it is assumed that B j k</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Simulation parameters</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mass (m i /kg)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Length (l i /m)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Inertial of Moment (I i /kg m 2 )</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Nominal value</cell><cell>Actual value</cell><cell>Nominal value</cell><cell>Actual value</cell><cell>Nominal value</cell><cell>Actual value</cell></row><row><cell>Link 1</cell><cell>4.0</cell><cell>8.0</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell>0.4</cell></row><row><cell>Link 2</cell><cell>4.0</cell><cell>8.0</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell>0.4</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This work was partly supported by NSFC Projects (Grant Nos. 60334020, 60440420130, and 60475030), and MOST Projects (Grant Nos. 2003CB517106 and 2004DFB02100), China.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Indirect adaptive fuzzy sliding model control: part two: parameter projection with supervisory control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust tracking enhancement of robot systems including motor dynamics: a fuzzy-based dynamic game approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Uang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tseng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="538" to="552" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fuzzy adaptive variable structure controller with applications to robot manipulator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Hsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Systems Man Cybernet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variable structure adaptive fuzzy control for a class of nonlinear time delay systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="453" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental evaluation of nonlinear feedback and feedforward control schemes for manipulator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Khosla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kanade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust adaptive control in the presence of external disturbance and approximation error</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Bien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="393" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural network output feedback control of robot manipulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive fuzzy control of a class of MIMO nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Labiod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Boucherit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guerra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.elsevier.com/locate/fss" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conventional controller design for Industrial robots-a tutorial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y S</forename><surname>Luh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Systems Man Cybernet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="298" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A robust adaptive sliding mode tracking control using an RBF neural network for robotic manipulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Man</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ashraghian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2403" to="2408" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive computed torque control for rigid link manipulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Middleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Goodwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">System Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of a general learning algorithm to the control of robotic manipulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Glanz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kraft</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trajectory control of robotic manipulator using neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ozaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Furuhashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Okuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Uchikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adaptive control of robot manipulators using fuzzy logic systems under actuator constraints, Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Purwar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Jha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.elsevier.com/locate/fss" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An adaptive fuzzy controller based on sliding mode for robot manipulator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Systems Man Cybernet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="667" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural network-based adaptive controller design of robotic manipulators with an observer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Woo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Neural Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive manipulator control: a case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J E</forename><surname>Slotine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="995" to="1003" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J E</forename><surname>Slotine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Nonlinear Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall International Editions</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking control of nonlinear systems using sliding surface with application to robot manipulator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J E</forename><surname>Slotine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="465" to="492" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Spong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vidyasagar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Robot Dynamics and Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variable structure model reference adaptive control of robot manipulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Tso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Shum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Automat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2148" to="2153" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable adaptive fuzzy control of nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="146" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Indirect adaptive fuzzy sliding model control: part one: fuzzy switching</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy basis function universal approximation, and orthogonal least square learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Neural Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="807" to="814" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust trajectory following of robots using computed torque structure with VSS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wijesoma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="935" to="962" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A robust fuzzy logic controller for robot manipulators with uncertainties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Systems Man Cybernet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="706" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
