<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
							<email>gao@cse.uta.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Uni-versity of Texas at Arlington</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76019</postCode>
									<settlement>Arlington</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Texas at Arlington</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>76019</postCode>
									<settlement>Arlington</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FCE1A643164CA6A68AB713B1099F8CFF</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TFUZZ.2006.890668</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T10:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wireless Sensor Network Lifetime Analysis Using</head><p>Interval Type-2 Fuzzy Logic Systems</p><p>Haining Shu, Student Member, IEEE, Qilian Liang, Senior Member, IEEE, and Jean Gao, Member, IEEE Abstract-Extending the lifetime of the energy constrained wireless sensor networks is a crucial challenge in sensor network research. In this paper, we present a novel approach based on fuzzy logic systems to analyze the lifetime of a wireless sensor network. We demonstrate that a type-2 fuzzy membership function (MF), i.e., a Gaussian MF with uncertain standard deviation (std) is most appropriate to model a single node lifetime in wireless sensor networks. In our research, we study two basic sensor placement schemes: square-grid and hex-grid. Two fuzzy logic systems (FLSs): a singleton type-1 FLS and an interval type-2 FLS are designed to perform lifetime estimation of the sensor network. We compare our fuzzy approach with other nonfuzzy schemes in previous papers. Simulation results show that FLS offers a feasible method to analyze and estimate the sensor network lifetime and the interval type-2 FLS in which the antecedent and the consequent membership functions are modeled as Gaussian with uncertain std outperforms the singleton type-1 FLS and the nonfuzzy schemes.</p><p>Index Terms-Fuzzy logic system, interval type-2 fuzzy sets, lifetime distribution, network lifetime analysis, wireless sensor networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>R ESEARCH on sensor networks was originally motivated by military applications. Starting around 1980, networked microsensors technology has been widely used in military applications. One example of such applications is the cooperative engagement capability developed by the U.S. Navy. This network-centric warfare system consists of multiple radars collecting data on air targets <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Other military sensor networks include acoustic sensor arrays for antisubmarine warfare such as the fixed distributed system and the advanced deployable system, and unattended ground sensors such as the remote battlefield sensor system and the tactical remote sensor system.</p><p>Nowadays, although the majority of sensors are still wired, wireless sensors provide significant advantages over wired sensors. Two main problems within wired sensor networks-cost and delays in deployment-are tackled when low-cost sensors and communication networks become available.</p><p>Wireless sensor networks have recently come into research notability because they developed many other nonmilitary applications, from environment and habitat monitoring to industrial process control to infrastructure security <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> and transportation automation. One networked sensing experiment on Great Duck Island <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> provides a small lens into an expansive future of such applications. The experiment was conducted by a team of computer engineers from the University of California, Berkeley. To date, 190 wireless sensors have been deployed on a small island ten miles off the coast of Maine to study the nesting behaviors of petrels. Biologists are now monitoring the petrels on the island from their offices, browsing data from sensors linked by satellite.</p><p>A wireless sensor network consists of certain amount of small and energy-constrained nodes. Basic components of a sensor node include a single or multiple sensor modules, a wireless transmitter-receiver module, a computational module, and a power supply module. Such networks are normally deployed for data collection where human intervention after deployment, to recharge or replace node batteries, may not be feasible, resulting in limited network lifetime. Most applications have prespecified lifetime requirements, for instance, the petrels monitoring application in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> has a lifetime requirement of at least nine months. Thus estimation of lifetime of such networks prior to deployment becomes a necessity. Prior works on evaluating lifetime have considered networks where sensor nodes are randomly deployed. Reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> gives the upper bound on lifetime that any network with the specified number of randomly deployed nodes, source behavior, and energy can reach while <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> discusses the upper bounds on lifetime of networks with cooperative cell based strategies. Network lifetime of fixed deployment schemes were recently studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Jain and Liang observed that in wireless sensor networks, the behavior of a single node lifetime demonstrates the nature of normal Gaussian distribution, which brings the first light of exploring the network lifetime behavior given the knowledge of nodes' lifetimes <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p><p>In this paper, we address the issue of lifetime analysis and estimation for wireless sensor networks in which the sensor nodes are deployed at desired locations. Our approach is entirely different from all prior research. Instead of trying out various probability basis, we propose to apply an interval type-2 fuzzy logic system (FLS) for lifetime analysis and estimation in a wireless sensor network. We demonstrate that a type-2 fuzzy membership function (MF), i.e., a Gaussian MF with uncertain variance, is most appropriate to model a single node lifetime in wireless sensor networks. Two FLSs-a singleton type-1 FLS and an interval type-2 FLS-are constructed for lifetime analysis and estimation. Simulations are implemented on two basic placement schemes: square-grid and hex-grid. We believe that these two schemes can serve as basis for evaluating more complex schemes for their lifetime performance prior to deployment and help justify the deployment costs. We set up our fuzzy logic lifetime evaluator and compare it against the first-node-die methods in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and the upper bounds in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p><p>The rest of this paper is organized as follows. In Section II, we detail two sensor deployment schemes used for this paper and the basic concepts on network coverage, connectivity, and lifetime. Section III gives an overview of interval type-2 fuzzy logic systems. In Section IV, we demonstrate that a single node lifetime can be modeled with Gaussian MFs. We observe that a type-2 Gaussian MF with uncertain variance is most appropriate to model a single node lifetime in wireless sensor networks. We apply this knowledge and design an interval type-2 FLS in Section V to estimate network lifetime. A singleton type-1 FLS is constructed as well for performance comparison. Simulation results and discussions are presented in Section VI. Section VII concludes this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PRELIMINARIES</head><p>A sensor network is designed to perform high-level information processing tasks such as target detection and tracking. Applications of sensor networks are widely ranging and can vary significantly in modes of deployment, application requirements, sensing models, and quality of service. In this section, we discuss the key assumptions related to our approach, then formally characterize the basic modes of sensor placement in this paper, followed by the concept of coverage, connectivity, and network lifetime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Assumptions and Notations</head><p>The approach of network lifetime analysis developed in this paper is based on the following assumptions about the wireless sensor networks.</p><p>• Sensor nodes are placed in a two-dimensional field. Nodes operate with very limited energy resources, which shape the aspects of the node performance, for instance, the node's processing ability, sensing, and communication range. We assume all sensor nodes originally deployed are identical in power configuration and functionality. • Sensing and communications between sensor nodes are through radio links. We make the assumption that the radio range for a node is a disk of radius around the node where is taken as the same for all nodes. A sensor node can detect or sense any target or event within its sensing range, denoted by . We also define a communication range , which is the distance beyond which the transmitted signal is received with signal-to-noise ratio below the acceptable threshold level. In this paper, we assume the communication range to be equal to the sensing range . • To be more energy efficient, direct communication between any pair of sensor nodes is allowed only if the Euclidean distance between them satisfies . Such a pair of nodes is called neighboring nodes. Since communication within communication range is by broadcast, all immediate neighbors hear what a node transmits. Communication between nonneighboring nodes is achieved via peer-to-peer communication and may consists several short hops to relay the transmitted message. • Since the communication range denotes the maximum distance of direct communication between two sensor, a sensor network is said to be deployed with minimum density when the Euclidean distance between all neighboring nodes is .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Basic Modes of Sensor Placement</head><p>Sensor placement directly affects power resource management and background data processing, which is carried out with various sensed data in distributed sensor networks. An intelligent sensor placement enlarges the field coverage, facilitates the operation of sensors (detecting, communication, data aggregation, etc.), and minimizes the excessive communications in fulfilling a task.</p><p>The simplest placement modes involve uniform or regular placement of sensor nodes such that each sensor node in the network has the same number of neighbors. A sensor placement mode that regulates two neighbors per sensor node has been described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, we use the square-grid and hex-grid placement modes illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(a) and (b), respectively. Square-grid mode in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(a) shows that each sensor node in the network has four neighbors, and in the Hex-grid mode in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(b), the number of neighbors for every sensor node is three. We believe that these three elementary placement modes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> can serve as basis for other placement schemes, because a placement scheme of any complexity can be decomposed into two-neighbor, three-neighbor, and fourneighbor groups.</p><p>in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(a) and (b) denotes communication range. Sensor nodes in both square-grid and hex-grid are equidistant from their respective neighbors. According to our assumption, both grids are deployed with minimum density. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Coverage and Connectivity</head><p>Coverage and connectivity are two important performance metrics of networks, and hence a discussion on them becomes imperative before the lifetime of the network can be defined.</p><p>Coverage scales the adequacy with which the network covers the sensor field. A sensor with sensing range is said to cover or sense a circular region of radius around it. If every point in the sensor field is within distance from at least one sensor node, then the network is said to provide complete or 100% coverage.</p><p>Various levels of coverage are acceptable depending on the applications. In critical applications, complete coverage is required at all times. Any loss of coverage leads to a sensing gap in the field. Such gaps cause breach of security in case of surveillance applications. Also, in applications that require data with high precision, a sensing gap leads to inaccuracies. For such networks, any loss of coverage renders the network nonfunctional, while in some other applications a small loss of coverage may be acceptable.</p><p>Connectivity scales the adequacy with which nodes are able to communicate with their peers. One of the strengths of sensor networks arises from their ability to aggregate data collected from different sensor nodes. This requires adequate communication between sensor nodes. Any node should be able to communicate with any other node for proper functioning of the network. If a large number of nodes fail due to lack of energy, a part of the network may get completely disconnected from the rest. In this paper, we assume that only 100% connectivity is acceptable and the network fails with any loss of connectivity. An example of a sensor placement scheme that concentrates mainly on coverage as its parameter of interest can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, where a sensor placement algorithm for grid coverage has been proposed.</p><p>In our analysis, we require the network to provide complete coverage and connectivity. We give equal importance to both parameters and declare the network nonfunctional if either of them falls below their desired levels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Network Lifetime</head><p>The basic definition of lifetime or, more precisely, the postdeployment active lifetime of a network is the cumulative active time measured from deployment until network failure. Based on the levels of coverage and connectivity required to deem a network functional, network failure can be interpreted in different ways. Since we assume that a wireless sensor network is fully functioning with complete coverage and connectivity, network failure corresponds to the first loss of coverage or connectivity.</p><p>In this paper, we concentrate on finding the minimum lifetime of a network, the worst case scenario. To be able to evaluate this minimum lifetime, we need to know the lifetime of a single sensor node, the minimum number of node failures that cause network failure, and the positional relationship<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">2</ref> between the failed nodes.</p><p>Consider the square-grid and hex-grid networks deployed with minimum density. Both networks survive the failure of a single node without loss of either connectivity or coverage implying that the minimum number of node failures that can lead to network failure is greater than one. Now looking into the square-grid network in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2(a)</ref>, apparently failure of nodes 20 and 21 causes loss of coverage. Similarly, failure of nodes 20 and 25 in the hex-grid network brings the coverage down to less than 100%. It comes to a conclusion that the failure of any two neighboring nodes causes loss of coverage and hence network failure.</p><p>Thus the minimum number of node failures that cause network failure is two, and these two nodes must be adjacent to each other (neighbors). A network may undergo multiple node failures and still be connected and covered if any of the failed nodes are not neighbors. But the absolute minimum number of node failures that can cause network failure is two.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. INTRODUCTION TO TYPE-2 FUZZY SETS AND INTERVAL TYPE-2 FUZZY LOGIC SYSTEMS: AN OVERVIEW</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Introduction to Type-2 Fuzzy Sets</head><p>The concept of type-2 fuzzy sets was introduced by Zadeh <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> as an extension of the concept of an ordinary fuzzy set, i.e., a type-1 fuzzy set. Type-2 fuzzy sets have grades of membership that are themselves fuzzy <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. A type-2 membership grade can be any subset in [0,1]-the primary membership; and, corresponding to each primary membership, there is a secondary membership (which can also be in [0,1]) that defines the possibilities for the primary membership. A type-1 fuzzy set is a special case of a type-2 fuzzy set; its secondary membership function is a subset with only one element, crisp grades of membership. Type-2 fuzzy sets allow us to handle linguistic uncertainties, as typified by the adage "words can mean different things to different people." A fuzzy relation of higher type (e.g., type-2) has been regarded as one way to increase the fuzziness of a relation, and, according to Hisdal, "increased fuzziness in a description means increased ability to handle inexact information in a logically correct manner <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>." Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> shows an example of a type-2 set. The domain of the membership grade corresponding to is also shown. The membership grade for every point is a Gaussian type-1 set contained in [0,1]; we call such a set a "Gaussian type-2 set". When the membership grade for every point is a crisp set, the domain of which is an interval contained in [0,1], such type-2 sets are called "interval type-2 sets" and their membership grades "interval type-1 sets" <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Interval type-2 sets are very useful when we have no other knowledge about secondary memberships. An interval type-2 fuzzy set can be represented by its upper and lower MFs <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. An upper MF and a lower MF are two type-1 MFs that are bounds for the footprint of uncertainty (the union of all primary membership grades) of an interval type-2 MF. The upper MF is a subset that has the maximum membership grade of the footprint of uncertainty; and, the lower MF is a subset that has the minimum membership grade of the footprint of uncertainty.</p><p>We use an overbar (underbar) to denote the upper (lower) MF. For example, let denote the type-2 MF for the th antecedent of the th rule; then the upper and lower MFs of are and , respectively, so that </p><p>where ; is the number of antecedents; ; and is the number of rules. The upper MF is (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>)</p><p>(3) and the lower MF is (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>)</p><p>This example illustrates how to define and , so that it is clear how to define these membership functions for other situations (e.g., triangular, trapezoidal, bell MFs).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Introduction To Type-2 Fuzzy Logic Systems: An Overview</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> shows the structure of a type-2 FLS <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. It is very similar to the structure of a type-1 FLS <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. For a type-1 FLS, the output processing block only contains the defuzzifier. We assume that the reader is familiar with type-1 FLSs, so that here we focus only on the similarities and differences between the two FLSs. The fuzzifier maps the crisp input into a fuzzy set. This fuzzy set can, in general, be a type-2 set.</p><p>In the type-1 case, we generally have "IF-THEN" rules, where the th rule has the form " : IF is and is and and is , THEN is ," where s are inputs; s are antecedent sets ; is the output; and s are consequent sets. The distinction between type-1 and type-2 is associated with the nature of the membership functions, which is not important while forming rules; hence, the structure of the rules remains exactly the same in the type-2 case, the only difference being that now some or all of the sets involved are of type-2; so, the th rule in a type-2 FLS has the form " : IF is and is and and is , THEN is ." In the type-2 case, the inference process is very similar to that in type-1. The inference engine combines rules and gives a mapping from input type-2 fuzzy sets to output type-2 fuzzy sets. To do this, one needs to find unions and intersections of type-2 sets as well as compositions of type-2 relations.</p><p>In a type-1 FLS, the defuzzifier produces a crisp output from the fuzzy set that is the output of the inference engine, i.e., a type-0 (crisp) output is obtained from a type-1 set. In the type-2 case, the output of the inference engine is a type-2 set; so, "extended versions" (using Zadeh's extension principle <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>) of type-1 defuzzification methods was developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. This extended defuzzification gives a type-1 fuzzy set. Since this operation takes us from the type-2 output sets of the FLS to a type-1 set, this operation was called "type-reduction" and the type-reduced set so obtained was called a "type-reduced set" <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. To obtain a crisp output from a type-2 FLS, we can defuzzify the type-reduced set.</p><p>General type-2 FLSs are computationally intensive, because type-reduction is very intensive. Things simplify a lot when secondary MFs are interval sets (in this case, the secondary memberships are either zero or one). When the secondary MFs are interval sets, the type-2 FLSs were called "interval type-2 FLSs." In <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, Liang and Mendel proposed the theory and design of interval type-2 FLSs. They proposed an efficient and simplified method to compute the input and antecedent operations for interval type-2 FLSs, one that is based on a general inference formula for them. For interval type-2 FLSs, Liang and Mendel defined the concept of upper and lower MFs and illustrate their efficient inference method for the case of Gaussian primary MFs. They also proposed a method for designing an interval type-2 FLS in which they tuned its parameters.</p><p>In an interval type-2 FLS with singleton fuzzification and meet under minimum or product -norm, the result of the input and antecedent operations is an interval type-1 set, i.e.,</p><p>, where and simplify to</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(5)<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where denotes the location of the singleton. In this paper, we use center-of-sets type reduction, which can be expressed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> where is an interval set determined by two end points and ;</p><p>; and is the centroid of the type-2 interval consequent set ; and . Because is an interval set, we defuzzify it using the average of and ; hence, the defuzzified output of an interval type-2 FLS is (8)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Applications of Interval Type-2 Fuzzy Logic Systems</head><p>Liang and Mendel have developed theory and design methods for the most useful kind of type-2 FLSs, interval type-2 FLSs <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, and have applied them to a number of very important applications, such as the following.</p><p>1) Fading channel equalization <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> and cochannel interference elimination <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. The channel states in a fading channel or channel with cochannel interferences are uncertain, and they validated that an interval type-2 fuzzy set, Gaussian primary membership function with uncertain mean, can be used to represent such uncertainties. 2) Network video traffic modeling and classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>MPEG variable bit rate traffic are very bursty. They validated that the I, P, and B frame sizes are log-normal with fixed mean and uncertain variance, so an interval type-2 fuzzy sets can be used to model the bursty video traffic and an interval type-2 fuzzy logic system with such type-2 fuzzy set are demonstrated performing much better than a Bayesian classifier. 3) Connection admission control for ATM network <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Connection admission control is actually a decision making problem. Different factors such as incoming real-time video/audio packet sizes, non-real time packet sizes, and buffer sizes are uncertain. They applied an interval type-2 fuzzy logic to handle these uncertainties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. MODELING NODE LIFETIME WITH GAUSSIAN MEMBERSHIP FUNCTIONS</head><p>Though applications of sensor networks vary with task requirements, sensor nodes retain the basic elements within any sensor network. Behavior of individual sensor in a manner determines the network performance. As we have discussed in Section II-C, failure of sensor nodes due to lack of energy may cause the network to function improperly or completely break down. Thus it becomes significantly important to characterize a single node behavior before going into the network layer. A distinct identity of sensor nodes and wireless sensor network is its constrained energy resources, which is widely measured by the node and network lifetime. In this section, we study the lifetime behavior for single sensor node and try to find its probability characters from real network data.</p><p>Since wireless sensor nodes are severely energy constrained due to their compact form, hardware design and protocol approaches for different layers must take energy efficiency into account to increase the lifetime of sensor networks. However, a fundamental question-"what is the nature of sensor network lifetime?" has not been answered yet. Because the lifetime of each individual node is not a constant but a random variable, it Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>. A single node lifetime distribution in a hex-grid sensor network.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TABLE I MEAN AND STD VALUES FOR SEVEN SEGMENTS AND THE ENTIRE NODE LIFETIME, AND THEIR NORMALIZED STD</head><p>follows that the network lifetime is also a random variable. Recently, Jain and Liang <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> showed that in a wireless sensor network where the workloads are very well balanced, the behavior of a single node lifetime demonstrates the nature of normal Gaussian distribution. Their observation was also justified by the knowledge of probability and random process in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> illustrates the real node lifetime distribution in a hex-grid sensor network.</p><p>In the paper, we are first interested in setting up a precise MF for the single node lifetime. From the original data of single node lifetime shown in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>, we decomposed the whole data sets into seven segments and computed the mean and standard deviation of node lifetime for each segment, . The mean and standard deviation for the entire data set were also computed. We are also interested to know which value-mean or standard deviation -varies more. We first normalized the mean and standard deviation of each segment using and . Then we computed the standard deviation of their normalized values and . Results are presented in the end of Table <ref type="table">I</ref>.</p><p>From the last row of Table <ref type="table">I</ref>, we see that , which means standard deviation varies much more than the mean value . Therefore we conclude that if the single node lifetime follows normal Gaussian distribution, it is most appropriate to be modeled as a Gaussian MF with uncertain standard deviation. This result justifies the use of the Gaussian MFs to model single node lifetime in Section V.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. SENSOR NETWORK LIFETIME ANALYSIS USING INTERVAL TYPE-2 FUZZY LOGIC SYSTEMS</head><p>In Section IV, we came to a conclusion that in wireless sensor networks, the single node lifetime can be well modeled by a type-2 Gaussian MF with uncertain variance. This result offers a truly original approach to probe into the trait of network lifetime. Referring to <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, prior research on sensor network lifetime are mostly heuristic or application and protocol driven. In this paper, we propose to apply fuzzy logic systems to sensor network lifetime analysis, more specifically to evaluate or estimate network lifetime using interval type-2 FLSs. We name our network lifetime evaluation system type-2 fuzzy logic lifetime evaluator (FLLE2).</p><p>From the overview of type-2 FLSs in Section III-B, we know that in a type-2 FLS, when inputs are applied to the system, the inference engine computes the output set corresponding to each rule. After the unique type-reduction operation, the defuzzifier computes a crisp output from these rule output sets. We next expatiate the input-output parameters, type-2 antecedent and consequent MFs and fuzzy rules precisely designed for evaluating sensor network lifetime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Antecedent and Consequent Membership Functions</head><p>Let be the number of sensor nodes deployed in a sensor network. All sensor nodes are initially configured with the same battery level. After a period of time during which several tasks (detecting, target tracking and communication, etc.) were carried out by different sensors, the network is left with sensor nodes at various battery levels. We assume the sensor network of interest at this point retains complete coverage and connectivity and all sensor nodes are still alive. The problem of evaluating network lifetime is formulated like this: Given a set of data representing the various battery levels of all alive sensor nodes, denoted by , estimate the cumulative alive time of the network measured from the point of interest until network failure, where is the current battery level of sensor node .</p><p>The 1 values of battery levels, , are taken as input to the FLLE2 and the alive time of the network measured from the point of interest until network failure is taken as the output of FLLE2.</p><p>We depict one antecedent as "the remaining battery level of sensor node " and the consequent as "the cumulative network alive time from the point of interest until network failure" The linguistic variables to represent the antecedent are divided into three levels-high, moderate, and low-and the consequent is divided into five levels-very high, high, moderate, low, and very low.</p><p>Antecedent and consequent membership functions are chosen based on the result in Section IV. An interval type-2 Gaussian MF with uncertain standard deviation is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. In this paper, all antecedents and consequents use the same type of MFs and the MF parameters are initialized consistently. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Rules Design</head><p>We apply reliability theory from control system to design the fuzzy rules. In this section, we first treat the basics of reliability theory and then demonstrate how this knowledge is extracted for rules design with two simple examples.</p><p>1) Basics of Reliability Theory: For the sensor network lifetime issue studied in this paper, reliability theory provides a feasible method to design fuzzy rules. To understand this, we introduce the reliability block diagram (RBD). RBD is a graphical representation of the components of the system and provides a visual representation of the way components are reliability-wise connected. Thus the effect of the success or failure of a component on the system performance can be evaluated.</p><p>Consider a system with two components. If this system is such that a single component failure can render the system nonfunctional, then we say that the components are reliability-wise connected in series. If the system fails only when both its components fail, then we say that the components are reliabilitywise connected in parallel. Note that the physical connection between the component may or may not be different from their reliability-wise connection. The RBDs for both cases are given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>. Any complex system can be realized in the form of a combination of blocks connected in series and parallel.</p><p>2) Rules Design Using Reliability Theory: In our analysis, the wireless sensor network is the system under consideration, and the sensor nodes are the components of the system. We detail below how to design rules with the knowledge of reliability theory referring to the two basic RBDs in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>. We make the assumption that the workload among all components (sensor nodes) is very well balanced.</p><p>Example 1: Setup Fuzzy Rules for Parallel System in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>(a): In the parallel system, crisp logic claims that the system (network) fails only when both components (sensor nodes) fail. In fuzzy logic systems, the rules can be set up as one example shown below:</p><p>IF the remaining battery level of component 1 (sensor node 1) is high and the remaining battery level of component 2 (sensor node 2) is moderate, THEN the lifetime of the system (network) is very high.</p><p>Example 1: Setup Fuzzy Rules for Series system in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7(b):</ref> In the series system, crisp logic claims that the system (network) fails when either component fails. In fuzzy logic systems, the rules can be set up as one example shown below: IF the remaining battery level of component 1 (sensor node 1) is low and the remaining battery level of component 2 (sensor node 2) is moderate, THEN the lifetime of the system (network) is low.</p><p>Note that the parallel and series systems are the essential ways to model two sensor nodes. A wireless sensor network consisting of multiple sensor nodes can be hierarchically represented in the reliability block diagram.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Case Studies: Rules Design 1) Square-Grid Sensor Network:</head><p>As defined in Section II-D, the minimum network lifetime is the time to failure of any two neighboring nodes. We know that the failure of any single node does not cause network failure. The failure of any node coupled with the failure of any of its neighbors causes network failure. Using this definition, we build the RBD for the square-grid as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref>.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref> shows the RBD block for a single node in the network. A node can be modeled in two ways depending on its position in the sensor field. This distinction based on its position is made due to a simple observation that nodes at the right edge of the sensor field (region-2) do not have any neighbor (node b), as opposed to nodes in region-1. Also, nodes at the bottom edge of the sensor field (region-2) do not have a bottom neighbor (node c), as opposed to the nodes in region-1. Note that as every node in a square-grid, node has four neighbors, but its relationship with only two neighbors is modeled in its RBD block. This is because the relationship with the other two neighbors will be modeled when their RBD blocks are constructed. If this is not followed, then the relationship between every node-neighbor pair will be modeled twice.</p><p>We abstract three antecedents from the RBD of block-1 in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref>.</p><p>• Antecedent 1-The remaining battery level of node .</p><p>• Antecedent 2-The minimum remaining battery level of node and . • Antecedent 3-The remaining battery level of node . The consequent is depicted as "minimum network lifetime." The linguistic variables to represent the antecedent are divided into three levels, and the consequent is divided into five levels as detailed in Section V-A. A total of rules (three antecedents and each has three fuzzy subsets) are set up for square-grid block-1.   Two antecedents are chosen based on the RBD of block-2 in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref>, and consequent is defined the same as in block-1. A total of rules shown in Table III are constructed in this scheme.</p><p>• Antecedent 1-The remaining battery level of node .</p><p>• Antecedent 2-The remaining battery level of node .</p><p>2) Hex-Grid Sensor Network: The analysis for the hex-grid is carried out on the same lines as that of the square-grid. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>(b) shows that as in the case of a square grid, two neighboring node failures cause network failure. The RBD block of a single node is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref>.</p><p>Since the relation between a node and all of its neighbors is modeled by its corresponding RBD block, the RBD blocks for the neighbors are not constructed, as this causes the relationship between the nodes to be considered twice. In the hex-grid network, things simplify a lot when we abstract two antecedents from its hexagonal structure. The two antecedents are listed below.</p><p>• Antecedent 1-The remaining battery level of node .</p><p>• Antecedent 2-The minimum remaining battery level of node , and . Consequent definition, levels to represent antecedent and consequent are consistent with Section V.A. A total of rules for hex-grid network are constructed consistently with square-grid network block-2 as listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">III</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. SIMULATION AND DISCUSSION</head><p>In the previous sections, we have theoretically addressed the approach to analyze wireless sensor network lifetime using interval type-2 fuzzy logic systems. Research on the single node lifetime justified the use of Gaussian MFs with uncertain standard deviation (std) to model node lifetime and type-2 fuzzy logic systems for the network lifetime likewise. We are now ready to validate the feasibility of our approach. In this section, we will train the design parameters of FLLE2 with collected data and test our new FLLE2. We devised a Type-1 fuzzy logic lifetime evaluator (FLLE1) using singleton type-1 fuzzy logic system to compare the performance with FLLE2. FLLE1 is trained using the same algorithm as FLLE2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Energy Consumption Model and Test Data Generation</head><p>Simulation is implemented on two deployment modes: square-grid and hex-grid. For both modes, we consider the basic units in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref> block-1 and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref> and deploy the network with minimum density (referring to Section II-A). Our explicit goal is to evaluate the remnant active time of a network when some sensor nodes have consumed certain amount of energy in task performing. Thus we initialize the remaining power level of all sensor nodes by random variables within [0,10] .</p><p>A radio energy consumption model has been well studied in LEACH (Energy-Efficient Communication Protocols for Wireless Microsensor Networks) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> and ESO (Energy-Efficient Self-Organization for Wireless Sensor Networks) <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. Different applications consume energy resources in different manners. According to the path-loss model in wireless communication, the energy needed to transmit over distance is proportionate to , where is the path-loss exponent depending on the specific propagation environment. For example, will have a larger value for long-distance transmission than for short-distance transmission. In order to save energy resources and decrease interference, power control is widely used in wireless communications such that the radio could be adjusted for a certain range of output power level. The following model is adopted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, where perfect power control is assumed.</p><p>To transmit bits over distance , the sender's radio spends <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> and to receive this message, the receiver's radio spends <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> The electronics energy depends on factors such as digital coding, modulation, filtering, and spreading of the signal, whereas the amplifier energy in free space or in multipath environment depends on the distance to the receiver and the acceptable bit-error rate. For the simulations described in later sections, the communication energy parameters are set as m, the radio dissipates nJ per bit to run the transmitter or receiver circuitry, pJ/bit/m , and pJ/bit/m . In our simulation, we use the formula in ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) under the circumstances . Sensor nodes take turn to transmit data to their immediate neighbors by broadcast until network failure. We assume the transmission alternation is determined by the remaining power level of individual sensor nodes at the beginning of each epoch. The sensor node with the lowest power level gets to transmit with the least probability. We also make the assumption that the transmitted data bits per turn is a constant such that the energy dissipation varies only with the transmitting distance. We ran simulations for square-grid and hex-grid wireless sensor networks using the OPNET platform set up in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. The actual sensor network lifetime can be obtained for different sensor battery level [0,10] J settings.</p><p>We run 50 Monte-Carlo simulations to collect data sets, each of which contains lifetime data for square-grid and hex-grid networks, respectively. Each data set consists of battery levels of four nodes and actual network lifetime. In our FLS network lifetime analysis, we used 300 data sets for training, and the remaining 300 data sets were used for testing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Simulation Results and Discussion</head><p>We designed the FLLE2 and FLLE1 for a square-grid wireless sensor network. The initial 27 rules were designed according to Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">II</ref>. The antecedent and consequent MFs for FLLE1 and FLLE2 are plotted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">10</ref>. Then we tuned the parameters of FLLE1 and FLLE2 using steepest descent algorithm. We followed the training algorithm proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> for FLLE2. Three hundred data sets were used for training. Both FLLE1 and FLLE2 were trained for six epochs. After training, the parameters of FLLE1 and FLLE2 were fixed and the remaining 300 data sets were used for testing. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11</ref>, we summarized the root mean square errors (RMSEs) between the estimated lifetime and the actual lifetime. Observe that the RMSEs of both FLLE1 and FLLE2 for square-grid wireless sensor network decrease along with the tuning epoch and the FLLE2 performs much better than the FLLE1. For example, FLLE1 takes down RMSE from initial 0.1472 to around 0.037 at the sixth epoch while FLLE2 reduces RMSE from 0.104 to 0.006. FLLE2 achieves nearly 83.8% reduction in RMSE compared to FLLE1 at the sixth epoch.</p><p>Similarly, we designed a FLLE1 and a FLLE2 for hex-grid wireless sensor network. The initial nine rules were set according to Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">III</ref>. The same antecedent and consequent MFs as in square-grid network were used. We then trained and tested the FLLE1 and FLLE2. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12</ref>, we plotted the RMSE between the estimated lifetime and the actual lifetime. Results show that the FLLE1 and the FLLE2 for hex-grid sensor network decrease the RMSE along with the tuning epoch and FLLE2 outperforms FLLE1 likewise. For example, FLLE1  takes down RMSE from initial 0.1734 to around at the sixth epoch while FLLE2 reduces RMSE from 0.1038 to 0.006. FLLE2 achieves nearly 91.3% reduction in RMSE comparing to FLLE1 at the sixth epoch.</p><p>Next, we implement the basic units of square-grid and hexgrid into a wireless sensor network and compare the performance of FLLE1 and FLLE2 with the general nonfuzzy approach. We estimate the network lifetime in five consecutive windows. In each observing window, we run Monte Carlo simulation 100 times. We compare our fuzzy logic based evaluators with the first node die methods used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and normalized the network lifetime to the upper bound of data gathering sensor activities proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Simulation results are presented in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">13</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">14</ref>.</p><p>In both figures, we observe that the estimated lifetimes from FLLE2 and the first node die method are tight to the upper bound, and our fuzzy approach FLLE2 outperforms the nonfuzzy first node die method. Comparing the performance of FLLE1 and FLLE2, the results again validate the feasibility of modeling the sensor node lifetime with the type-2 interval fuzzy logic system.  Up to the present, we have discussed the basic units of squaregrid and hex-grid wireless sensor networks. Now, let be the number of sensor nodes required to be deployed with minimum density (referring to Section II-A). For square-grid sensor network, the network RBD in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref> consists of block-1s and 2 1 block-2s in series, the whole square grid network can actually be decomposed into multiple blocks serial connected together and the method of setting up rules can be applied likewise. Similarly, in hex-grid sensor network, 2 RBD blocks in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref> connected in series represent the network, which can be decomposed the same way as in the square-grid sensor network. While designing the FLSs, if the number of antecedents is more than three, we can union-rule configuration <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> to eliminate the rule explosion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORKS</head><p>In this paper, we described a new method based on fuzzy logic systems to analyze and estimate the network lifetime for wireless sensor networks. Our approach is illuminated by the research that a single node lifetime behaves the nature of normal Gaussian distribution. However, we showed that if the single node lifetime follows normal Gaussian distribution, it is most appropriate to be modeled as a Gaussian MF with uncertain standard deviation. We then set up the fuzzy logic lifetime evaluator based on interval type-2 FLSs for lifetime estimation and test its performance using real lifetime data. Simulation results convincingly justified the feasibility of applying type-2 FLSs into wireless sensor network lifetime analysis. We believe that our approaches opens up a new vision for research on wireless sensor network lifetime analysis.</p><p>Our future work will focus on lifetime evaluation under the circumstances that the task scheduling is variable and how the estimated network lifetime could be used to accommodate the scheduling change.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Two placement modes for a 36-node sensor network. r in both grids denotes the communication range: (a) square-grid and (b) hex-grid.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,39.60,67.40,251.00,412.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Loss of coverage due to failure of two neighboring nodes: (a) Squaregrid: failure of nodes 20 and 21 causes loss of coverage. (b)Hex-grid: failure of nodes 20 and 25 causes loss of coverage.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,40.62,69.44,246.00,508.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. (a) Pictorial representation of a Gaussian type-2 set. The secondary memberships in this type-1 fuzzy set are shown in (b) and are Gaussian. Note that this set is called a Gaussian type-2 set because all its secondary membership functions are Gaussian. The "principal" membership function (the bold line), which is triangular in this case, can be of any shape.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,311.82,66.42,229.00,270.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>( 1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>where denotes the union of individual points of each set in the continuum.Example 1: Gaussian Primary MF With Uncertain Standard Deviation: Consider the case of a Gaussian primary MF having a fixed mean and an uncertain standard deviation that takes on values in , i.e.,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .Fig. 5 .</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Type-2 Gaussian MF with uncertain standard deviation. The thick solid lines denote upper MFs, and the thick dashed lines denote lower MFs. The shaded regions are the footprints of uncertainty for interval secondaries. The center of the Gaussian MFs is five, and the variance varies from 1.0 to 2.0.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,39.60,66.54,251.00,195.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. RBDs for a system of two components. (a) RBD with parallel connected components and (b) RBD with series connected components.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,320.70,67.50,214.00,102.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. RBD of a single node in a square grid. Nodes belonging to region-1 are modeled as block-1, and nodes belonging to region-2 are modeled as block-2.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,38.10,66.72,252.00,99.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. RBD block for a single node in the hex-grid.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,42.12,67.02,246.00,72.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Membership functions. (a) Antecedent MFs: MFs with shaded regions are for FLLE2 and MFs with dashed lines are for FLLE1. (b) Consequent MFs: MFs with shaded regions are for FLLE2 and MFs with dashed lines are for FLLE1.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,38.10,67.26,252.00,420.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Square-grid: RMSE of FLLE1 and FLLE2.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,301.14,66.90,252.00,198.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Hex-grid: RMSE of and FLLE2.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,301.14,285.70,252.00,197.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13. Square-grid: fuzzy estimation and nonfuzzy approach.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,39.60,66.42,251.00,192.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14. Hex-grid: fuzzy estimation and nonfuzzy Approach.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,42.12,284.84,246.00,187.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Table II gives the complete 27 designed rules.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE II COMPLETE</head><label>II</label><figDesc>27 RULES FOR SQUARE-GRID BLOCK-1</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE III COMPLETE</head><label>III</label><figDesc>NINE RULES FOR SQUARE-GRID BLOCK-2</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>The hex-grid is observed to have lower density than the square-grid. Rough calculation shows that with 36 nodes deployed, the network with square-grid covers an area of approximate</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>25r , and the hex-grid covers an area of approximate 48r , almost double that of the square grid.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_2"><p>Positional relationship between two nodes can be that the two nodes are diagonal, adjacent, or completely unrelated.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors would like to thank L. Zhao for providing help on network lifetime simulations.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported by the U.S. Office of Naval Research Young Investigator Award under Grant N00014-03-1-0466. H. Shu and Q. Liang are with the</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sensor networks: Evolution, opportunities, and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-08">Aug. 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1247" to="1256" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wireless sensor networks for habitat monitoring</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mainwaring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Polastre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Szewczyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Culler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. WSNA&apos;02</title>
		<meeting>WSNA&apos;02<address><addrLine>Atlanta, GA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-09-28">Sep. 28, 2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="97" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two-tired wireless sensor network architecture for structural health monitoring</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kottapalli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kiremidjian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lynch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Carryer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-03">Mar. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Upper bounds on the lifetime of sensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bhardwaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Garnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chandrakasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Commun</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Commun</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="785" to="790" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bounding the lifetime of sensor networks via optimal role assignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bhardwaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chandrakasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1587" to="1596" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating upper bounds on network lifetime extension for cell-based energy conservation techniques in stationary ad hod networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Blough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Santi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. MOBICOM&apos;2002</title>
		<meeting>MOBICOM&apos;2002<address><addrLine>Atlanta, GA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-09">Sep. 2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="192" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sensor placement and lifetime of wireless sensor networks: Theory and performance analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Sensor Network Operations, S. Phoha, T. F. LaPorta, and C. Griffin</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Type-2 fuzzy logic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Karnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="643" to="658" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-12">Dec. 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ANFIS: Adaptive-network-based fuzzy inference system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst., Man, Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="665" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-06">May/Jun. 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Node placement for connected coverage in sensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Extended Abstract Proc. WiOpt</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Sophia-Antipolis, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-03">2003. Mar. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sensor placement for grid coverage under imprecise detections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dhillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chakrabarty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Iyengar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FUSION</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The concept of a linguistic variable and its application to approximate reasoning-I</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy logic systems for engineering: A tutorial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-03">Mar. 1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="377" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fuzzy Sets and Systems: Theory and Applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The IF THEN ELSE statement and interval-valued fuzzy sets of higher type</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Man-Machine Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MPEG VBR video traffic modeling and classification using fuzzy techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-02">Feb. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Connection admission control in ATM network using survey-based type-2 fuzzy logic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Karnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst., Man, Cybern., C</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="539" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-08">Aug. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interval type-2 fuzzy logic systems: Theory and design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="535" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-10">Oct. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Equalization of time-varying nonlinear channels using type-2 fuzzy adaptive filters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="563" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-10">Oct. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overcoming time-varying co-channel interference using type-2 fuzzy adaptive filters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Circuits Syst. II</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1419" to="1428" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-12">Dec. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy basis functions, universal approximation, and orthogonal least squares learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L.-X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Neural Netw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="807" to="814" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-09">Sep. 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Reliability Engineering Handbook</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kececioglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leemis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Reliability: Probabilistic Models and Statistical Methods</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Papoulis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Pillai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Probability, Random Varibales and Stochastic Processes, 4</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>th ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use of wireless sensor networks for mapping environmental conditions in buildings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Healy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.nist.gov/tc75/ASHRAESummer2003SeminarHealy.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ASHRAE Seminar</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-07">Jul. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An application-specific protocol architecture for wireless microsensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Heinzelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chandrakasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="660" to="670" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-10">Oct. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy-efficient self-organization for wireless sensor networks: A fully distributed approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE GLOBECOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE GLOBECOM<address><addrLine>Dallas, TX</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-11">Nov. 2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2728" to="2732" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combinatorial rule explosion eliminated by a fuzzy rule configuration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Combs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-02">Feb. 1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">She is currently pursuing the Ph.D. degree in electrical engineering at the University of Texas at Arlington. Prior to the master&apos;s program, she was a Systems Engineer with Telecom Planning and Research Institute, Beijing. Her research interests include fuzzy logic systems and applications, distributed source coding, sensor networks, and collaborative radar system. Qilian Liang (SM&apos;05) received the B.S. degree from Wuhan University, China, in 1993, the M.S. degree from Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Liang received the 2002 IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems Outstanding Paper Award, the 2003 Office of Naval Research Young Investigator Award, and the 2005 UTA College of Engineering Outstanding Young Faculty Award. Jean Gao (M&apos;96) received the B.S. and M.S. degrees in biomedical engineering from Shanghai Medical University, Shangai, China, and Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology, respectively. She received the Ph.D. degree in electrical engineering from Purdue University</title>
		<title level="s">received the B.S. degree in electronics and information systems from Peking University</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>China; Beijing, China; San Diego, CA; West Lafayette, IN</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>She is an Assitant Professor in the Computer Science and Engineering Department at the University of Texas at Arlington. Her research interests in computer vision and pattern recognition are object motion estimation. shape classification, multidimensional multiobject tracking, and reconstruction. Dr. Gao was the recipient of the prestigious CAREER Award from the National Science Foundation</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
