<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Lubin School of Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Pace University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10038</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Business</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">James Madison University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Har-risonburg</addrLine>
									<postCode>22807</postCode>
									<region>VA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2903F51B839BA7534736807A42128115</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T13:11+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Is Faster Really Better? An Empirical Test of the Implications of Innovation Speed Eric H. Kessler and Paul E. Bierly, III</p><p>Abstract-New product innovation is critical to the competitive advantage of many firms. However, there is much hoopla, but little evidence, regarding the benefit of innovation speed. Specifically, there exists insufficient, often conflicting evidence about how dimensions of innovation strategy (cost, quality, and speed) relate to one another and how they ultimately affect project success. Evidence from 75 new product development projects clearly indicates that speed is positively related to quality and has the greatest influence on success. However, several external and firm-level factors were found to moderate the effect of innovation strategy dimensions on project success. Results point to the fact that relationships between dimensions of innovation strategy and project success vary with level and source of uncertainty, with the clearest finding being that speed leads to success primarily in more predictable contexts. This suggests that a fast-paced innovation strategy is best when "you know where you're going." Index Terms-Competitive advantage, demographic dynamism, development cost, environmental uncertainty, innovation speed, new product development, product quality, product radicalness, technological dynamism, technology sourcing.</p><p>T HERE is a growing stream in the innovation literature ex- tolling the virtues of speedy development <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. The pressures for speed in the workplace and the subsequent need for managers to make decisions faster in high-velocity environments are bringing speed to the forefront of managerial thinking. This is particularly true for the management of innovation, because innovation speed is important to first-mover and fast-follower strategies <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. Innovation speed is defined as the time elapsed between: 1) initial development efforts, including the conception and definition of an innovation; and 2) ultimate commercialization, which is the introduction of a new product into the marketplace. It can be viewed as one of three dimensions of innovation strategy, with the others being quality and efficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>.</p><p>Notwithstanding the growing interest in this topic, innovation speed has been one of the least studied factors in the new product development literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> and among existing studies there has been little empirical evidence with regard to its bottom-line implications <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. Thus, Crawford <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> comments that "so far we have seen too much specious reasoning and hoopla (about innovation speed) and not enough hard data." Whereas most re-search on speed focuses on the process (i.e., the "how do you go faster" question) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, we instead examine its strategic implications (i.e., "what happens when you go fast").</p><p>Looking for a moment at the larger picture, successful new product development is among the most pressing challenges facing firms today, especially those in high-technology environments. New product development is a critical component of competitive strategy because it can be a used to leapfrog competition, create entry barriers, establish a leadership position, open up new distribution channels, and garner new customers to improve market position <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>. Due to shortening product life cycles, the strategic importance of new product innovation is growing to address new competitive, technological, and consumer challenges <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>. Although much has been written on factors that influence the success or failure of product innovation (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>), few researchers have empirically considered the relative influence of dimensions of innovation strategy-efficiency, quality, and speed <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>-on new product success <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>. As stated previously, this is especially true with regards to speed.</p><p>Despite the scant empirical attention on the implications of innovation speed, or perhaps because of it, the literature advances inconsistent predictions with regards to the relationships of innovation speed with other dimensions of innovation strategy, and with the overall success of a new product development project. For example, while many argue that increasing the pace of innovation reduces development costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> and improves product quality <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>, some claim that there are instead trade-offs between innovation speed and 1) the costs of development, since it may take more resources to get the product out earlier <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, and 2) the quality of the product, since increasing speed may entail reducing performance specifications <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. Further, there is an additional unresolved issue regarding the contextual dependence of speed's benefits <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. Specifically, the effects of external (e.g., technological and demographic environment) and internal (e.g., technology sourcing and product radicalness) factors are important to consider because they have been shown to influence the positioning and posturing of firms <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> and their innovation strategy <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>.</p><p>Thus, our research question is threefold. 1) How is innovation speed related to the other dimensions of innovation strategy-quality and efficiency? 2) How does innovation speed influence project success? 3) Is the relationship between innovation speed and project success moderated by external and internal levels of uncertainty? </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. THEORETICAL MODEL AND HYPOTHESES</head><p>This study represents a partial test of Kessler and Chakrabarti's <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> conceptual model of innovation speed. Although this model suggests a number of possible linkages, in this paper, we focus on innovation speed and its relationship with major project outcomes (cost and quality) and project success. We also consider how level and type of uncertainty may moderate these relationships. The hypothesized relationships are displayed in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Effect of Innovation Speed on Other Dimensions of Innovation Strategy</head><p>The literature assessing the relationships between dimensions of innovation strategy is loosely connected and often contradictory. While it has been shown that speed, cost, and quality are highly interrelated <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, the nature of their interrelation is debated. We make the falsifiable argument that speed, quality, and cost efficiency are synergistic. That is, a speedy process will cost less and better fit customer needs. This is consistent with the prevailing "positive bias" for speed.</p><p>Speed and Quality. A quality-based strategy may be at odds with a speed-based strategy because, for high-quality products, firms may refrain from freezing specifications early and instead change them to incorporate new technologies as they become available <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>. However, we propose a positive relationship between speed and quality, defined as the degree to which a product satisfies customer requirements <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. First, faster development tends to be associated with higher rates of employee learning and the construction of relevant competencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. Second, speed improves the accuracy of forecasting because firms are required to project environmental and technological forces into a shorter time period <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, thus making for a better customer fit. Third, reduced time-to-market allows more advanced components to be incorporated and faster products can, thus, be perceived as more current (i.e., cutting edge) than competitor products <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. These arguments point to a synergistic relationship between speed and quality.</p><p>Hypothesis 1: Innovation speed and product quality are positively related.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Speed and Costs.</head><p>A cost-based strategy may be at odds with a speed-based strategy because firms may have to "pay for speed" by committing more man-hours, materials, and/or equipment to projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. Also, accelerating innovation processes can burn resources through additional paralleling and communication expenditures. However, a negative relationship between speed and development costs, defined as a project's total financial requirements and human resources expenditures <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, is postulated. First, increased paralleling and more intense communication bring about higher levels of self-consciousness and increased efficiency of resource utilization <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Second, faster speed actually provides a cap upon man-hours and other fixed costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. Third, faster speed has been linked with increased coordination and subsequent reductions in costly work redundancy, errors, and recycling <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. However, there may be a -shaped relationship between time and cost, such that faster speed reduces cost up to a point and then requires greater investment. Even if this is true, we contend that most projects are on the right, upward sloping side of the " " (too long), insofar as they do not push the bounds of speed and have room to reduce costs. Thus, we propose a synergistic relationship between speed and cost.</p><p>Hypothesis 2: Innovation speed and development costs are negatively related.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Effects of Innovation Speed on Project Success</head><p>We argue that innovation speed will have a substantial positive impact on project success. Innovation speed represents the capability of firms to move quickly from ideas to actual products, increasing the potential to realize first-mover advantages. Lieberman and Montgomery <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> clearly outlined specific firstmover advantages, including the ability to:</p><p>1) legally exclude followers through patents or copyrights; 2) charge initial premium prices, which produce profits that can be used to further improve products and processes; 3) preempt competitors concerning access to scarce resources, critical suppliers, and key distribution channels; 4) develop a reputation as a leader; 5) set the industry standard; 6) build a cost advantage through economies of learning. Innovation speed is also important for followers' firms to be successful, by limiting some of the first mover advantages of the leader. In fact, a study by McKinsey et al. found that new products that come to market six months late, but on-budget, earn 33% less profit than if they were on time, while new products which come to market on-time, but 50% over budget, earn only 4% less profit than if they were on budget <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. With regard to market share, speed can help establish early segments and customer loyalty <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> while combating product obsolescence <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. In this vein, Gomory <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> comments, "one cannot overestimate the importance of getting through each turn of the (product development) cycle more quickly than a competitor. It takes only a few turns for the company to build up a commanding lead."</p><p>Hypothesis 3: Faster innovation speed will have a positive influence on project success.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Effect of External and Internal Contingency Factors</head><p>It is unwise to view the relationship between innovation speed and project success in a vacuum, because the interaction of the market and firm environment shape both strategy and performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. Unfortunately, shortcomings in this area are evidenced by the lack of multilevel studies of innovation <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>. In this study, we propose that the relationship between speed and project success is moderated by organizational uncertainty. Indeed, many external and internal dimensions influence uncertainty, including complexity, threat (e.g., discontinuities), instability (e.g., dynamism), and interconnectedness (e.g., sourcing) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. There is a multitude of potential perspectives on the speed-uncertainty relationship, for example that uncertain demand might put a "premium" on speed or warrant greater caution and better intelligence before one commits to action. Our basic premise is based in the latter, specifically that the link between speed and success is weaker when there is high uncertainty. We base this primarily on the increased forecasting error (less information is available), increased "noise" (shifting rules of the game), and shorter time to reap benefits during highly uncertain conditions (assailed and obscured profit windows). Together, greater uncertainty will reduce speed-based advantages because the direction of the speedy endeavor is less likely to be appropriate. That is, it is less advantageous to go fast if you can't see clearly and could be going the wrong way.</p><p>To measure external uncertainty, we use environmental dimensions used by Wheelwright and Clark <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>, and others: technological dynamism and demographic dynamism. Both of these constructs can be viewed as different dimensions of environmental uncertainty, meaning they influence the firm's ability to predict future market conditions. Technological dynamism, which refers to the rapid development and change of technology within an industry, creates market uncertainty by frequently changing the dominant designs and standards of the industry <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>. In such quickly changing environments, advantages are only temporary as all firms in the industry are aggressively trying to capture the market <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Speed advantages may be nonexistent if a competing dominant design emerges, and even if speed does create advantages they are usually quickly matched or improved on by competitors. Of course, during conditions of high technological dynamism, all successful firms must be able to move rapidly to compete <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. However, pushing faster and faster during these conditions does not necessarily increase project success because of the high degree of uncertainty in hitting ones target. Demographic dynamism refers to changing needs of customers due to social trends, population shifts, and changes in income and educational levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. These rapid changes in the demographic environment shorten product life cycles and create fleeting windows of opportunity <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. Similar to previous arguments, speed will only contribute to the success of new products if the firm can properly forecast and meet future demographic trends.</p><p>Hypothesis 4: Innovation speed will have a more positive influence on success when external (technological and demographic) uncertainty is low than when external uncertainty is high.</p><p>Firm-level factors also moderate the relationship between innovation speed and project success such that greater internal un-certainty makes it difficult to successfully pursue a speed-based strategy. We study two such factors, product radicalness and technology sourcing. First, new product development projects can be categorized by their radicalness or degree of attempted advancement, where more radical innovations are newer to the focal organization and represent a greater departure from existing practices <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Radicalness is a widely used and typically acknowledged contingency factor because the processes, structures, and outcomes involved in radical and incremental innovations are different <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Radical innovations are much more risky than incremental innovations, and are particularly problematic for established firms because new dominant designs and standards are often based on new, less familiar areas of technical expertise <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>. Whereas radical innovations promote "creative destruction" and uncertainty for these firms, incremental innovations strengthen their advantages, reduce uncertainty, and lead to more predictable success <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>Second, the relative balance of internal and external technology sourcing also influences uncertainty. Internal sourcing (e.g., corporate R&amp;D), by its nature, is a more risky venture and its success is less predictable. Externally sourcing established technologies (e.g., via alliances or licensing) is a safer, more predictable approach since the technology has usually been developed and tested. Thus, given the lower uncertainty of external sourcing, innovation speed should be a better predictor of success for externally-sourced innovations than for those that are internally-sourced. Moreover, since competitors may also have access to the external source of technology, speed is an even more critical differentiating factor for external than internal sourcing. However, it is important to note that successful external sourcing can only occur if the firm has already internally developed "absorptive capacity" so that it can effectively understand and apply the external knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Thus, in the long term, a balanced sourcing approach is needed to maximize the learning and efficiency of the organization <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p><p>Hypothesis 5: Innovation speed will have a more positive influence on success when internal (radicalness and sourcing) uncertainty is low than when internal uncertainty is high.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. METHODOLOGY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Research Sample</head><p>The selection of the research sample is motivated by the objective of being able to generalize the findings of this study beyond 1) the idiosyncratic nature of undeveloped, unconventional product development programs and instead across organizational boundaries, and 2) the idiosyncratic nature of one or two business environments and instead across industry boundaries. As a result, the sample consists of large companies (more likely to have established new product development programs) in a variety of industries (to have provided access to a range of task and institutional environments where product innovation is pursued). Given these criteria, thirty companies were chosen that met the criteria of the study and were headquartered locally, which was a practical research constraint (e.g., travel resources). A letter was sent to the chief executive officer or top research and development executive (e.g., VP, R&amp;D) of these firms, which provided a general overview of the study, ex-plained the nature of the commitment requested, and detailed the benefits of participation. Two to three weeks after these letters were sent, direct telephone calls were made to these individuals to answer any questions they had about the study and arrange a mutually convenient time for an on-site interview (to secure commitment). Ultimately, this resulted in a sample of ten large, U.S.-based companies (names withheld due to confidentiality agreements, averaging approximately 90 000 employees and $16 billion in sales) operating in a variety of industries: advanced/ scientific materials, chemicals/chemical materials, confectionery/consumer goods, industrial equipment/products. 1  The unit of analysis was the new product development project. This is because adopting a project level of analysis, defined as "a goal directed effort with a readily-identified end in view" <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, enables the study to capture unique situational attributes that influence the processes and outcomes of actual projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. A total of 86 projects were drawn from ten companies. Of the 86 products selected for the study, questionnaires representing 75 projects were returned (87% response rate): 25% from advanced/ scientific materials; 19% from chemicals/chemical materials; 40% from confectionery/consumer goods; and 16% from industrial equipment/ products. 2   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Data Collection Procedure</head><p>Data were collected using a detailed questionnaire instrument containing scales for independent and dependent variables relevant to the previously described propositions. Data gathering proceeded in several stages, and at each research site, a variety of people provided responses according to the specific information required <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. First, cooperation of the companies serving as field sites were secured from top management (e.g., CEO or VP R&amp;D) through telephone and personal interview. Second, once on-site, a principal contact person and/or a staff specialist was interviewed to jointly develop a list of projects that fit the objectives of the study. This was to insure that projects 1) were all recent and fully completed within the past five years, 1 The way in which companies were selected means that sample is not completely random. As a result, findings should be interpreted in the strictest sense as applying only to those companies in the sample. However, since a relatively broad cross-section of industries was studied, the study's findings may be generalizable to some degree to firms in these industries (Cooper &amp; Kleinschmidt, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>). 2 Because projects were drawn from several companies from different industries, tests for between-group differences in speed were undertaken. Separate analysis of variance procedures and post-hoc Tukey multiple-comparison procedures revealed that 1) there were between-company differences (F = 3:48; p &lt; :01), with the average speed of projects for two companies (#6 and #3) significantly slower than the other companies, and 2) there were between-industry differences, (F = 7:55; p &lt; :01), with the average speed of projects from the chemical/chemical products and confectionary/consumer products industries significantly faster than those from the advanced/scientific materials and industrial equipment/products industries. Thus, strictly speaking, the results are generalizable only to the specific firms and industries represented in the sample because of the divergent nature of macro-level context. That is, company and industry may be important variables to consider. However, to the extent that differences were in response to general variations in external environmental uncertainty, generalizability might not be so limited. In fact, the results might be more generalizable because it is harder to find significant effects that hold across different company and industry contexts (especially divergent ones) than it is to find significant effects within a single company or industry. Additionally, sampling projects from companies and industries varying in speed might be beneficial for avoiding restriction in range problems.</p><p>2) contained significant technological components, 3) were seen as typical for their respective companies. For each company, we requested that about half of the projects were perceived as "relatively successful" and the other half "relatively unsuccessful" as to increase the likelihood of obtaining variability on the primary variables. Moreover, examining several projects from each firm (versus only one or two) provides a more representative picture of the firm's overall new product development program and is less likely to result in a sample of exception and outlier projects, which would restrict the range of the sample.</p><p>These interviews also provided a list of the project leader and, when available, one marketing person and one technical person directly involved on each of the project development projects chosen. Multiple respondents were polled for each project to increase the validity and reliability of retrospective reports <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. Surveys were mailed to the contact persons for distribution to the respondents and then mailed directly back by the respondents. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">3</ref> To aggregate the individual responses to the project level of analysis, one-way analyses of variance were used to test intraproject variance <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. This is necessary to address the "perceptual agreement problem" of using multiple informants <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. Respondents' scores were aggregated into project scores via unweighted average when there was low rater disagreement (i.e., nonsignificant -scores). Notwithstanding, since the theory and hypotheses require a project level of analysis, aggregation may be appropriate without statistical justification <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. Therefore, when there was significant disagreement, the project leader's information was used with the assumption that they were the most familiar with the project <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>.</p><p>The nature of the data collection (retrospective responses to both independent and dependent variables via mailed questionnaire) raises the issue of common methods variance problems. Of course, in collecting data through mailed questionnaires, a trade-off is made with respect to efficiency (e.g., lower cost, time, and staff requirements) versus accuracy (e.g., lower degree of objectivity in the data). In this vein, Fowler <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> reports that there are four basic reasons why survey respondents may report events with less than perfect accuracy: 1) they do not know the information; 2) they cannot recall the information; 3) they do not want to report the information; 4) they do not understand the questions. While no precautions can completely eliminate these potential problems, several actions were taken to limit them. To the issue of knowledge level, respondents were jointly selected to identify those that were most knowledgeable about the specific projects being studied. Additionally, by providing respondents with a relatively lengthy time period for response (several weeks or, in some cases, months), they were given the opportunity to con-sult with archival sources of data (e.g., progress reports) to support their responses on appropriate items. To the issue of information recall, only relatively recent projects were requested (i.e., fully completed within the past five years). To the issue of willingness, participants were informed that their organization would receive feedback on the study's findings. In addition, a written confidentiality policy assured participants that the names of individuals, projects, and firms would remain anonymous and only reported in the aggregate. To the issue of clarity, the questionnaire was piloted by several individuals experienced in new product development. It was then revised as per information gained through pilot testing before being administered to the research sample. For example, questions were sharpened and information was added to facilitate respondents' understanding. Additionally, included with the survey were detailed instructions, definitions of key terms, and the names and phone numbers of researchers to contact if they had any questions.</p><p>Moreover, various checks were undertaken to limit such bias resulting from sampling the same individuals for both independent and dependent variables. Projects with single respondents tend to be more vulnerable to this bias, given the single perspective. One might also expect project leaders to be more vulnerable to social desirability bias, given their overall responsibilities and motivation for impression management. Analysis of variance procedures revealed that there were no significant between-group differences 1) at the project level of analysis, for projects with one, two, or three respondents, and 2) at the individual level of analysis, for type of respondent (i.e., leaders, marketing members, and technical members). While not perfect, these checks suggest limits to common methods variance problems. In addition to these methodological steps and statistical checks, we have followed Parke <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> and others in performing Harman's post-hoc single factor test. If a substantial amount of common method variance exists in the data, a single factor will emerge from factor analysis when all variables are entered together, or a general factor that accounts for most of the variance will result. The results of unrotated factor analysis revealed neither a single factor nor a general factor, suggesting that the threat to validity posed by systematic variance common to the measures is lacking.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Measurement of Variables</head><p>Innovation Speed. This was operationalized through three items utilizing 13-point scales:</p><p>1) relative to schedule, or "on-time performance" <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>;</p><p>2) relative to similar completed projects in ones organization, or "acceleration" <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>; 3) relative to similar projects of competitors, or "competitive speed" <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>. The use of 13-point scales was borrowed from McDonough's <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> measurement of innovation speed relative to time goals <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">4</ref> . We copied this scale and, to be consistent, amended it for our other two measures of speed as well as the corresponding measures of cost and quality. The fact that we used relative measures enabled us to compare dissimilar product development projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. The scales had a moderate degree of internal reliability 0.6824) and loaded onto one factor with eigenvalues equal to or greater than one. Thus, an aggregate innovation speed variable was derived, weighted by factor scores, ranging from one (slowest speed) to 13 (fastest speed).</p><p>Development Costs. This was also measured using three items utilizing 13-point scales, mirroring speed. A project's cost was measured relative to:</p><p>1) budget;</p><p>2) similar past projects; 3) similar competitor projects. The three scales had a moderate degree of internal reliability 0.6173) and loaded onto one factor with eigenvalues equal to or greater than one. Thus, an aggregate development cost variable was derived, weighted by factor scores, ranging from one (lowest cost) to 13 (highest cost).</p><p>Product Quality. Quality was also measured through three similar items utilizing 13-point scales, but relative to:</p><p>1) preset performance specifications, 2) similar past projects, 3) similar competitor projects. The three scales had a moderate degree of internal reliability 0.7825) and loaded onto one factor with eigenvalues equal to or greater than one. Thus, an aggregate product quality variable was derived, weighted by factor scores, ranging from one (lowest quality) to 13 (highest quality).</p><p>Project Success. This was measured using two five-point Likert scales. First, internal success was measured by asking to what extent the project met expectations and attained organizational goals, ranging from not-at-all to completely <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>. Second, external success was measured by asking to what extent the project was a marketplace success-i.e., to what extent did it "win" in competitive situations, ranging from product-flop to completely-successful <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. The two scales had a moderate degree of internal reliability 0.6839) and loaded onto one factor with eigenvalues equal to or greater than one. Thus, an aggregate project success variable was derived, weighted by factor scores, ranging from one (least successful) to five (most successful).</p><p>Technological Dynamism. This was measured through a five-point scale asking the degree to which the respondent would characterize the technological environment of this innovation-e.g., advances in research and development of new products, devices, and processes-ranging from very dynamic (changing rapidly) to very stable (virtually no change) <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>.</p><p>Demographic Dynamism. This was measured through a five-point scale asking the degree to which the respondent would characterize the demographic environment of this innovation-e.g., social trends, population shifts, income and educational levels-ranging from very dynamic (changing rapidly) to very stable (virtually no change) <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>.</p><p>Project Radicalness. This was measured through 1) a sixpoint scale asking respondents to evaluate the type of work done on the project, ranging from pure applications engineering to the development or application of new technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, and 2) a four-point scale asking respondents to evaluate the degree of change involved in the project, ranging from an imitation of existing products to a radically new product <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. These responses were pooled with a score of ten indicating a high degree of radicalness and two indicating low radicalness.</p><p>Internal Sourcing. This was measured on two five-point scales asking to what extent 1) ideas for this product and 2) technological developments for this product came from internal sources (i.e., members of the research and/or development staff) as opposed to external sources (i.e., capital goods, suppliers, licensing arrangements) <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. These responses were pooled with ten indicating a high degree of internal sourcing and two indicating low internal sourcing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. ANALYSIS AND RESULTS</head><p>As Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref> indicates, projects were, on the average, slightly faster than the midpoint of their scales (about 10% faster than benchmarks); however, they ranged from very fast (about 75% faster) to very slow (about 75% slower). Cost and quality had broad ranges and central means. Projects tended to be on the average quite successful, although they represented all values on the measurement scale. 5 Measures of external and internal uncertainty also had central means and broad ranges. On the average, external contexts were slightly below scale midpoints (moderate-to-low uncertainty) whereas internal contexts were slightly above midpoints (moderate-to-high radicalness and internal sourcing). 5 Project success underwent a square-transformation due to negative skewness-i.e., there was a disproportionately large number of projects with high levels of success <ref type="bibr">(SPSS, 1994: 336)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Bobko [4,</ref><ref type="bibr">p. 152</ref>] states that "Transformations can clearly reduce the impact of outliers and help allay concerns about violating assumptions of normality and homoscedasticity." Although not excessive, this reinforces the earlier warning of nonrandomness.</p><p>To test Hypotheses 1 and 2, bivariate correlation analysis was used to quantify the strength of the association between the strategic dimensions of speed, quality and cost. Supporting Hypothesis 1, there is a positive and statistically significant correlation between process speed and product quality .345 .01 . In other words, faster development time is related to higher quality products. Hypothesis 2 is not supported since the correlation of speed and cost is not statistically significant. However, though not significant, speed was found to be negatively related to cost, as predicted.</p><p>To test Hypothesis 3, correlation analysis and multiple linear regression (MLR) analysis were used to test the relationship between speed and project success. 6 The former test determined there is a positive correlation between project success and process speed 0.433 0.01 , supporting Hypotheses 3. The MLR analysis, illustrated in Model 1 of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">II</ref>, determined that only speed significantly increases success 0.39 0.01 . Thus, Hypothesis 3 is supported by both methods. The full MLR model was significant 0.05 and explained 20% of the variance in project success.</p><p>To test the moderation effects proposed in Hypotheses 4 and 5, we used two different, but complementary, techniques: 1) a series of MLR models using the interaction terms of variables to account for the moderating effects; and 2) a series of split-sample MLR analyses using median splits to compare two 6 Regression models were also run, but are not displayed, with 1) the squared terms of speed, quality and cost to test for nonlinear relationships, and 2) the interactions of speed, quality and cost. In these models, the R was not increased significantly and none of the additional terms were significant. Further tests verified that the technological dynamism, demographic dynamism, and internal sourcing moderating effects were monotonic <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. The radicalness moderating effect was nonmonotonic but the inflection point (9.72) was barely within the 2-10 variable range.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TABLE II SELECTED REGRESSION MODELS WITH THE SQUARE OF PROJECT SUCCESS AS THE DEPENDENT VARIABLE. STANDARDIZED REGRESSION COEFFICIENTS DISPLAYED</head><p>different groups of projects. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">7</ref> Each of these techniques possesses certain limitations but provides different insight into the relationships being studied and has distinct theoretical meaning. The MLR analysis with interaction terms determines whether there exists a moderating effect between two variables. The hypothesis is supported if the regression coefficient for the interaction term differs significantly from zero. The significance of all the interactions combined is tested by analyzing the change in the model . Inherent in this type of analysis are high levels of multicollinearity, particularly between the independent variables and the interaction terms, which may cause difficulty in interpreting results <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>. For this reason, and for the fact that the relative influence of the main and interaction effects cannot be compared, this type of analysis is best used only to determine whether there is an existence of an interaction effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>. The split-sample MLR analysis, which also tests for a moderation type of relationship, relies on splitting the sample into two subgroups based on a contextual factor, and comparing standardized regression coefficients between an independent variable and a dependent variable for each group. The hypothesis is supported if the difference in regression coefficients is sig-nificantly different, as determined by a -test <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Whereas, the MLR analysis with interaction terms is best for determining an existence of a moderation effect, the split-sample MLR analysis is best for testing the strength of moderation <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>. However, the split-sample MLR analysis is less robust than other techniques since the quantitative values of the moderating variable are not being used in the analysis.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">II</ref> reports the results of the MLR analyses with interaction terms. Models 2, 4, 6, and 8 add to the baseline model (Model 1) one of the moderating variables proposed in Hypotheses 4 and 5: technological dynamism, demographic dynamism, project radicalness, and internal sourcing, respectively. In all of these models, the does not increase significantly and none of the additional terms are significant. This indicates that the main effect of none of these variables influences project success. In each of the subsequent models (Models 3, 5, 7, and 9), the moderating variable and the interactions of the moderating variable with Speed, Quality and Cost were entered into the model. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">8</ref> In three of these (3, 5, 7) models, the increased significantly and interaction terms were significant, supporting the proposed effect of the moderating variables. Overall, it is observed that speed consistently exerts a strong, positive influence on project success. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">III</ref> reports the inferential statistics from the split-sample MLR analysis. It was found that all four moderating variables influence the relationship in the proposed direction. For each model, speed is highly and significantly related to project success only in the more predictable, less uncertain situations-low technological dynamism 0.50 0.05 , low demographic dynamism 0.57 0.05 , low product radicalness 0.60 0.01 , and low internal sourcing 0.82 0.01 . The regression coefficients for speed are significantly different between the low and high uncertain contexts for demographic dynamism, product radicalness and internal sourcing (each at the 0.05 level). These findings provide partial support for Hypotheses 4 and 5 and can be interpreted as implying that speed leads to success, but only in contexts where uncertainty is not too high. In other words, speed is good if you know where you are going. The significant findings concerning the moderating effects of demographic dynamism and product radicalness are consistent with the MLR analysis with continuous variables. The overall regression models for all of the less uncertain contexts were significant or marginally significant and better predicted project success than the models for the more uncertain contexts. All of the overall regression models with more uncertain contexts were not significant. The two most powerful models were with low product radicalness 0.01 0.59 and low internal sourcing 0.01 0.63 .</p><p>IV. DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION New environments are forcing managers to abandon traditional approaches to strategy and search for new approaches to restore competitiveness to their firms <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Innovation is a critical part of modern strategies, yet there is a lack of empirical support concerning factors that influence new product performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>. This study seeks to address these issues by testing the outcomes of innovation speed in a sample of 75 projects. With regard to the first research question (Hypotheses 1 and 2), correlation analysis revealed that faster innovation speed is associated with higher product quality. Thus, there was not a trade-off between speed and quality; on the contrary, the two dimensions were symbiotic. This supports the notion that fast speed facilitates product quality (or vice versa), perhaps due to the hypothesized synergistic issues of learning, accuracy, and updated technology. It is also possible that this relationship is due to a third variable, perhaps the extent of technical barriers encountered. Notwithstanding, this finding is important because it suggests that one of the strategic goals can be pursued without necessarily sacrificing the other. On the other hand, development costs are not significantly correlated with speed, which was proposed in Hypothesis 2. This indicates that even though there is not a tradeoff between costs and speed, they are not symbiotic.</p><p>With regard to the second research question (Hypothesis 3), regression analyses revealed that in the projects studied, innovation speed is the most critical determinant of success. The main effects of quality and costs on success were significant only in a few regressions that added interaction terms. Since speed and quality were correlated, the regression results do not necessarily contradict those championing a "high-quality" strategy, because fast speed may be an element of a high-quality focus (or vice versa). The finding that speed exerts a greater influence on success than does cost is consistent with Rubenstein et al.'s <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> finding that a project's ability to meet time schedules was significantly related to project success while a project's ability to meet cost estimates was not. It is also consistent with the previously cited McKinsey study. The clearest managerial implication of this finding is that, in this sample, innovation speed more than any other factors drives project success. This suggests that greater management attention should be devoted to increasing new product development speed.</p><p>With regard to the third research question (Hypotheses 4 and 5), MLR and the split-sample analyses showed that external and firm level factors moderated the relationship between innovation speed and project success. Three out of four moderating variables are statistically significant using the MLR (technological dynamism, demographic dynamism, and project radicalness) and the split-sample (demographic dynamism, project radicalness, and internal sourcing) methods. All of the significant moderation effects indicate that innovation speed better predicts project success under conditions of less uncertainty. The implications concerning innovation speed are clear: Speed is more effective for more predictable innovations (i.e., less radical, externally sourced) and in more predictable environments (i.e., simple, stable). This implies that, although speed is generally good, it is most functional under low uncertainty. Thus, managers should pursue speed most vigorously when they have a "clear target," that is, when the technology is known and markets can be forecast.</p><p>Interestingly, the relationship between development costs and project success was also influenced by our moderating variables. The regression coefficients in the split-sample regression were positive for all low uncertainty conditions and negative for all high uncertainty conditions. Thus, for low uncertainty conditions, especially low technological dynamism, increasing the costs of development produces more successful projects. At first glance, this appears counter-intuitive, because it implies a more inefficient new product development process is linked to success. However, this is probably misinterpreting the results. Alternatively, these results indicate that under conditions of low uncertainty, innovation speed, and to a lesser degree, quality, are so important to project success that firms should not skimp on any costs that may reduce speed or quality. Quite the contrary, firms that spend money to accelerate new product development and improve quality are rewarded. Additionally, these results offer absolutely no support for a cost-based innovation strategy. That is, a strategy where management focuses attention on being efficient in the innovation process is not an effective innovation strategy. They would be better off investing in speed and quality.</p><p>Internal sourcing turns out to be a very interesting moderating variable. According to the split-sample regression, internal sourcing significantly moderates the relationships between project success and speed 0.05 , quality 0.05 , and perhaps costs 0.10 ; and the three dimensions of innovation strategy account for more variance of project success when internal sourcing is low 0.63 , than when internal sourcing is high 0.14 . However, a finer analysis of the data reveals some insightful findings. First, the results indicate that speed is crucial to success if one relies more on external sources (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">III</ref>, 0.82), but not that important if one relies more on internal sources 0.14 . From a strategic standpoint, this makes sense. Since the technology is obtained via the market and available to all competitors, the firm that can get to market first and take advantage of first-in advantages will clearly have the upper hand. However, correlation analysis reveals that the more firms internally source, the faster will be the innovation process. This is counter to the theoretical reasoning by some researchers, who argue that relying on external sourcing increases new product development speed by limiting the number of internal tasks and redoing what others have already done <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. What may be missing in this line of reasoning is to realize the difficulty in bringing outside technologies into the organization, interpreting the "foreign" knowledge, and integrating the different knowledge areas with the organization's knowledge base <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Thus, speed, sourcing, and project success have a complicated, intertwined relationship. Project speed increases the more an organization internally sources, but fast internal sourcing is less important to success due to the uncertainty of the new idea. Alternatively, when externally sourcing, speed is critical to success. Thus, firms face the challenge of speeding up knowledge integration processes when external sourcing.</p><p>Second, the split-sample regression (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">III</ref>) and the regression with interaction terms (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">II</ref>) provide different results when internal sourcing is used as the moderating variable; it is a strongly significant moderating variable using the split-sample regression, but it is not when the regression with interaction terms method is used. This apparent contradiction is addressed by Venkatraman <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref> who explains that these two methods, while both testing for a moderating effect, actually test for different types of fit. Split-sample regression best indicates the predictive ability of certain strategies across different environments, and the regression with interaction terms best indicates performance when it is jointly determined by the interaction of the predictor and the moderator. Thus, the classification of internal and external sourcing as two different contexts is valuable for determining when innovation speed will be more or less effective, but internal sourcing and innovation speed do not jointly determine project success via their interaction across the entire range of internal sourcing.</p><p>Overall, the results of this study inform both academic and practical concerns. First, they offer scholars empirical information regarding much discussed, but less frequently tested, relationships between innovation speed and other project outcomes. In this sense, the study represents a partial empirical test of Kessler and Chakrabarti's <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> conceptual model of innovation speed. Specifically, the results suggest that speed of a new product innovation is generally positively related to its eventual success, however, a contingency relationship exists insofar as the consequences of a fast innovation vary with levels of internal and external uncertainty. These findings also have implications for the management of innovation. The results inform managers that pursuing speed in innovation need not be at the sacrifice of lower cost or higher quality; in fact, there does not seem to be a necessary tradeoff between these objectives. However, it is probably better to strain for speed not as an end but rather as a means toward improved cost and quality performance. That is, firms should pursue focused improvements in speed as opposed to blind haste. This is similar in spirit to Deming's insight that pursuing higher quality need not be at the sacrifice of lower costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</p><p>Of course, there are limitations to the study that necessitate a provisional approach to these findings and suggest further avenues for research. For instance, the reliability coefficients for the measures were only moderate, the sample size was relatively small within the context of the statistical analyses, and the interrater reliability was less than desirable. These all require that the interpretation of the results be more conservative and provide motivation for future research to replicate and ex-tend the study. Additionally, several of our scales were single or double-item measures (e.g., project success, internal sourcing) and could have been richer. There is also the issue of how dimensions of innovation strategy failed to predict success in uncertain environments. To this point, there may be additional explanatory factors, perhaps based in the institutional environments of firms. Additionally, there is the issue of time-perspective when assessing new product success. Hultink and Robben <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> argue that in the short-term firms tend to emphasize speed, whereas meeting quality guidelines were both a short-term and long-term concern. Thus, our findings might reflect time-bound conceptions of new product success.</p><p>Moreover, there is the issue of culture on assessing new product success. For example, Gupta et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, and Mansfield <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> found differences in how U.S. managers and their German and Japanese counterparts viewed innovation strategy. These differences may be attributed to judgement (i.e., "Japanese" and "German" approaches are superior to a "U.S." cost-driven approach) or to context (i.e., dissimilar demands are placed on projects in different national settings). If the former is true, our findings suggest that U.S. managers should emphasize speed more, especially in predictable contexts. If the latter is true, our findings may not apply outside the U.S. environment.</p><p>The outcomes of innovation speed are complex; there are important tradeoffs (and nontradeoffs) and contingency relationships to consider. Perhaps our most important finding is that the "hoopla" surrounding speed is largely justified but needs qualification. Innovation speed is related to higher quality products and increases project success even more so than traditional criteria of high quality and low cost. However, fast-paced innovation is best in more predictable contexts, consistent with the finding that forcing rapid development under high uncertainty may produce failure <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. Thus, speed is good, but it is better "when you know where you are going."</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Conceptual model of the implications of innovation speed.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,38.10,62.28,252.00,211.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,78.84,84.24,432.72,270.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="7,79.02,98.22,435.36,358.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,47.58,101.22,495.12,200.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE I DESCRIPTIVE</head><label>I</label><figDesc>STATISTICS AND CORRELATIONS</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE III STANDARDIZED</head><label>III</label><figDesc>REGRESSION COEFFICIENTS () FOR MAIN-EFFECT AND SPLIT-SAMPLE REGRESSION ANALYSES: THE SQUARE OF PROJECT SUCCESS IS THE DEPENDENT VARIABLE</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Over half of the projects (54.7%) had multiple respondents. Sixty of the 127 responses (47.2%) were from project leaders, with the remaining responses almost equally split between marketing members (34 responses) technical members (33 responses). As indicated, separate analysis of variance procedures revealed that there were no significant between-group differences at the project level of analysis for number of respondents nor at the individual level of analysis for type of respondent.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_1"><p>McDonough asked respondents to assess whether a project was a certain percentage slower (6-levels), equal, or faster (6-levels) than its time goal.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_2"><p>The limited sample size within the context of these analyses restricts the models we consider and makes the results more conservative in nature.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Variable transformations were required in the interaction models to adjust for high levels of multicollinearity.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Innovation: Mapping the winds of creative destruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Abernathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Res. Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing construct validity in organizational research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bagozzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administ. Sci. Quart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="421" to="458" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generic knowledge strategies in the U.S. pharmaceutical industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bierly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strat. Manage. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>Winter Special Issue</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Correlation and Regression: Principles and Applications for Industrial/Organizational Psychology and Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bobko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technology indicators: Conceptual issues and measurement problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Eng. Technol. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Product Development Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fujimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Harvard Business School Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Applied Multiple Regression/Correlation Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hillside, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Absorptive capacity: A new perspective on learning and innovation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administ. Sci. Quart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="128" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determinants of timeliness in product development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kleinschmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing for speed to avoid product obsolescence: A survey of techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cordero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="294" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The hidden costs of accelerated product development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Crawford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="199" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hypercompetition: Managing the Dynamics of Strategic Maneuvering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Aveni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organizational innovation: A meta-analysis of effects of determinants and moderators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Damanpour</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad. Manage. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="555" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dimensions of organizational task environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Dess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administ. Sci. Quart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conceptual issues in the study of innovation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Downs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mohr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administ. Sci. Quart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="700" to="714" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An examination of alternative forms of fit in contingency theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Drazin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van De Ven</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administ. Sci. Quart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="514" to="539" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerating adaptive processes: Product innovation in the global computer industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eisenhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tabrizi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administ. Sci. Quart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward an integrative framework of performance in product development projects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Emmanuelides</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Eng. Technol. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="392" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fowler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Survey Research Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Sage</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Newbury Park, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Deming Guide to Quality and Competitive Position</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gitlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gitlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From the ladder of science to the product development cycle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gomory</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harv. Bus. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of project and process characteristics on product development cycle time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Griffin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Market. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metrics for measuring product development cycle time</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="112" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing trade-offs in the new product development process: A German-US comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Brockhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Weisenfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerating the development of technology-based new products</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wilemon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Calif. Manage. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The interactions of organizational and competitive influences on strategy and performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strat. Manage. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Summer Special Issue</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The return map: Tracking product teams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>House</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Harv. Bus. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991-02">Jan.-Feb. 1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring new product success: The difference that time perspective makes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hultink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S J</forename><surname>Robben</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="392" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aggregation bias in estimates of perceptual agreement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="229" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predictors of the performance of project groups in R&amp;D organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad. Manage. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="715" to="726" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Speeding up the pace of new product innovations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Innovation speed: A conceptual model of context, antecedents and outcomes</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad. Manage. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1143" to="1191" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conducting interorganizational research using key informants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad. Manage. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1633" to="1651" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">First mover advantages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lieberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Montgomery</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strat. Manage. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The speed and cost of industrial innovation in Japan and the United States: External vs. internal technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mansfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Manage. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1169" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Faster new product development: Investigating the effects of technology and characteristics of the project leader and team</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mcdonough</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="250" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Speeding up new product development: The effects of leadership style and source of technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mcdonough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Barczak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fast Cycle Time: How to Align Purpose, Strategy, and Structure for Speed</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Product development cycle time and commercial success</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Utterback</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Eng. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="304" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-11">Nov. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determinants of new product performance: A review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Montoya-Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Calantone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Prod. Innov. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="417" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategic alliance structuring: A game theoretic and transaction cost examination of interfirm cooperation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Parke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad. Manage. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="794" to="829" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Effective Product Design and Development: How to Cut Lead Time and Increase Customer Satisfaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rosenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<publisher>Business One Irwin</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Homewood, IL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors influencing innovation success at the project level</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rubenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>O'keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Souder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Res. Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Problems with contingency theory: Testing assumptions hidden within the language of contingency theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schoonhoven</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administ. Sci. Quart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="377" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Developing Products in Half the Time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Reinertsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>Van Nostrand Reinhold</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Competing Against Time: How Time-Based Competition is Reshaping Global Markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Stalk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technological discontinuities and organizational environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tushman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Administrative Science Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="465" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Research on the Management of Innovation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Van De Ven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Angle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Poole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Harper &amp; Row</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The concept of fit in strategy research: Toward verbal and statistical correspondence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Venkatraman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad. Manage. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="444" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Revolutionizing Product Development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wheelwright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<publisher>Free Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">His research has been widely published in leading management and technology journals and practitioner book series. His current research focus is on decision making in organizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Eric</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Kessler received the Ph.D. degree in organization management from Rutgers University</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Newark, NJ; New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>He is currently an Associate Professor of management at the Lubin School of Business, Pace University. particularly as it applies to the management of innovation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He has authored numerous published articles in the areas of the management of technology, knowledge management, and strategic alliances</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bierly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">III received the Ph.D. degree in organization management from Rutgers University</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Newark, NJ; Harrisonburg, VA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>James Madison University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>He is currently an Associate Professor and CSX Professor of Management at the College of Business. Previously, he was an Officer on a U.S. fast-attack nuclear submarine</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
