<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Networks Evolving Step by Step: Statistical Analysis of Dyadic Event Data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ulrik</forename><surname>Brandes</surname></persName>
							<email>ulrik.brandes@uni-konstanz.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. Computer &amp; Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jürgen</forename><surname>Lerner</surname></persName>
							<email>lerner@inf.uni-konstanz.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. Computer &amp; Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tom</forename><forename type="middle">A B</forename><surname>Snijders</surname></persName>
							<email>tom.snijders@nuffield.ox.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Fact. Behavioral &amp; Social Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Groningen</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="NL">Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Networks Evolving Step by Step: Statistical Analysis of Dyadic Event Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FFFA3BE2EB9AB838577E8BE9A9AB150C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/ASONAM.2009.28</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T17:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>With few exceptions, statistical analysis of social networks is currently focused on cross-sectional or panel data. On the other hand, automated collection of network-data often produces event data, i. e., data encoding the exact time of interaction between social actors. In this paper we propose models and methods to analyze such networks of dyadic events and to determine the factors that influence the frequency and quality of interaction. We apply our methods to empirical datasets about political conflicts and test several hypotheses concerning reciprocity and structural balance theory.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Most social networks are inherently dynamic. Actors repeatedly create ties and break up others. Since the adjustment of ties is influenced by the existence and non-existence of other ties, the network is both, the dependent and the explanatory variable in this process. Methods designed to detect rules and regularities in network-dynamics can be distinguished by the type of data they work with.</p><p>The most common form of longitudinal data in network analysis are panel data, i. e., sequences of networks on the same set of actors, observed at two or more timepoints. Network panel data can be fitted to actor-based Markovchain models <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, where actors can change their ties at any moment between observations. Clearly, panel data do not represent these dynamics well, since the sequence of changes is not observed but has to be estimated by statistical methods. The prevalence of panel data in longitudinal network analysis is rather due to the fact that data are typically collected by the use of questionnaires.</p><p>Another form of longitudinal network data (typically called event data) consists of sequences of time-stamped events encoding interactions between actors. The availability of event data has grown considerably with the advent of automated data-collection facilities. Examples include log-data of computer mediated communication (e. g., email, Usenetgroups, or social network services), open collaboration in wikis, phone-call data, or events that are routinely observed and reported in the news. Note that event data typically do not encode affective relations, such as friendship, but rather dyadic interaction, such as communicating, working together, etc. However, apart from the advantage of a finer time-granularity, event data are often available in larger quantities and are independent of respondents' subjectivity in assessing their relations.</p><p>In this paper we propose models and methods for network data consisting of time-stamped, dyadic, weighted events, where the weight indicates the quality (hostile vs. friendly) of an event. Specifically our methods attempt to determine how the rate and quality of events is influenced by the state of the network.</p><p>In the remainder of this introduction we introduce a dataset used for illustration and present related work. Our newly proposed model is described completely in Sect. 2. The results of an illustrative application of the model and a summary are given in Sect. 3 and Sect. 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1.">Exemplary Data: Political Events</head><p>We apply our newly proposed model to datasets from the Kansas Event Data System (KEDS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, which is a software tool that automatically extracts daily events from news reports. Events encode who did when what to whom and, thus, describe time-stamped dyadic interaction of specific types. The actors involved in events are political actors, such as countries, international organizations, or ethnic groups. Event types are classified using the World Event/Interaction Survey (WEIS) codes <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and each event type is assigned a psychometrically determined weight (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>) from the interval [-10, 8.3], where -10 stands for the most hostile and +8.3 for the most cooperative type of interaction. Examples or cooperative events are visits, agreements, and provision of military aid; hostile events include accusations, threats, and military actions against another actor. On those empirical event networks we test hypotheses concerning reciprocity and structural balance theory (e. g., "the enemy of my enemy is my friend"), see Sect. 3.</p><p>To evaluate how our method performs on networks of different size and density, we apply it to several datasets that are publically available from the KEDS website 1 and that have the following numbers of actors and events. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2.">Further Related Work</head><p>The analysis of event data (alternatively referred to as time-to-event analysis, survival analysis, or lifetime analysis) is an established area in statistics, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> for a general reference. Although, event data analysis is common in political science <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, network dependencies are rarely considered there. A notable exception is given by Goldstein et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> who applied vector-autoregression to the dyadwise aggregated levels of cooperation/conflict over short timeintervals. The influence of common friends and enemies on dyads in political networks has been analyzed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Both references do not use event data, but rather data coding the yearly state of the world system on the country-level in terms of alliances and wars (among others).</p><p>Research about event networks include the following. De Nooy <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> analyzed a network of literary authors and critics, where the interaction-events encode positive or negative literature reviews. In a paper closely related to ours, Butts <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> proposed a general framework for modeling the rate of relational events. Our paper extends this by modeling the conditional quality (weight) of events. Work dealing with the prediction of events in networks includes <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>Methods to visualize networks constructed from event data have been presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. The contribution of the current paper is different, since here we propose methods for statistical testing of hypotheses in such networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Model Specification</head><p>We assume that the probability of events is dependent on previous events. It is the goal of the analyst to determine the form of this dependency and thereby establishing rules that govern the behavior of actors. For instance, the happening that an actor a performs some hostile action targeted at an actor b may increase the probability that b acts hostile towards a. If this can be validated statistically, the analyst will have learned the rule that (in the specific context at hand) actors show a tendency to retaliate which, in turn, improves the ability to predict future events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Model Overview</head><p>For modeling the probability of an observed sequence of events E = (e 1 , . . . , e N ), we assume that each event e i is only dependent on events that happened earlier, i. e., e i is dependent on (e 1 , . . . , e i-1 ). To obtain a tractable model, we further assume that this dependence is completely captured by a dynamic network encoding the past interaction among actors: The past events (e 1 , . . . , e i-1 ) determine an event network G i (see Sect. 2.3) and, given the state of G i , the next event e i is assumed to be conditionally independent on (e 1 , . . . , e i-1 ). The probability of e i , given G i , is modeled parametrically so that the estimated parameters give the information which properties of G i increase/decrease the rate (frequency) of events and which properties of the network influence actors to act more friendly/hostile towards other actors.</p><p>More formally, let E = (e 1 , . . . , e N ) be a sequence of events and let</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">θ = (θ (λ) ; θ (μ) ) = (θ (λ) 1 , . . . , θ (λ) k λ ; θ (μ) 1 , . . . , θ (μ) kμ )</formula><p>be the parameters of the model (where the rate parameters θ (λ) stochastically determine the event rate and the weight parameters θ (μ) stochastically determine the event weight, as we shall see later). The probability density function for the event sequence E (given specific parameter values) is</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">f (E; θ) = f (e 1 G e1 ; θ) • . . . • f (e N G e N ; θ) . (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">)</formula><p>Here f (e i G ei ; θ) denotes the probability density for the event e i , given the network G ei and parameter values θ. For a given observed sequence of events E = (e 1 , . . . , e N ) we obtain a likelihood function on the space of parameters Θ by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">L : Θ → R; θ → L(θ) = f (E; θ) (2)</formula><p>and our goal is to determine those parameter values θ that maximize L (Maximum Likelihood Estimation (MLE), compare <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>).</p><p>In the next subsections we give details on the input format, the construction of G ei , the form of the probability density, and the estimation of the parameters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Input Data Format</head><p>The input data we consider consists of sequences of (dyadic, weighted) events E = (e 1 , . . . , e N ). An event e ∈ E is defined to be a tuple e = (a e , b e , w e , t e ), where</p><p>• a e is the source (initiator) of e;</p><p>• b e is the target (addressee) of e;</p><p>• w e ∈ R is the weight coding the quality of e; and • t e is the time when e happens. Time is given on some scale, e. g., by second, minute, hour, day, month, or year. In the datasets that we consider in this paper, time is given by the day. Several events may happen during the same time unit. The input event sequence is assumed to be in non-decreasing order with respect to time. The order of events that happen within the same time unit is considered as undefined.</p><p>The weight indicates the quality of the event, i. e., its level of hostility (negative weight) or cooperativeness (positive weight). We assume in this paper that event weights are normalized to the interval [-1, 1]. (So that, for instance, Goldstein weights of KEDS events are divided by ten.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Explanatory Variable: Network of Past Interaction</head><p>Given a sequence of events E = (e 1 , . . . , e N ) and a timepoint t (denoting the current time), the event network</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">G t = G t (E) = (A; ω + t , ω - t )</formula><p>is a weighted network encoding the past interaction between actors. Here, A is the set of actors that are involved in any event in E (thus, A does not change over time) and ω + t and ω - t are functions defined on dyads encoding cooperative respectively hostile interaction before time t.</p><p>The value of cooperative/hostile interaction of a particular dyad (a, b) increases whenever a initiates a cooperative/hostile event e targeted at b. When the difference between the current time t and the event time t e increases, the influence of e diminishes. The latter property is motivated by the assumption that actors forget (or forgive) cooperative and hostile actions.</p><p>More precisely, let D = {(i, j) : i, j ∈ A, i = j} denote the set of all dyads and T 1/2 ∈ R &gt;0 a given positive number denoting the halflife of the influence of events. Then, the function ω + t : D → R ≥0 , is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">ω + t (i, j) = e : ae =i, be =j, we &gt;0, te&lt;t |w e | • ln(2) T 1/2 • e -(t-te)• ln(2) T 1/2 .</formula><p>The function ω - t : D → R ≥0 is defined by the same formula, where the condition w &gt; 0 is replaced by w e &lt; 0. (Note that ω -still maps to the non-negative numbers, since the absolute value |w e | is taken.) Thus, the function ω + t (i, j) is defined as the sum over all weights of events e that involve i as source (a e = i) and j as target (b e = j), that happen before the current time t (t e &lt; t), and that have positive weight (w e &gt; 0). Similarly, ω - t (i, j) is the sum over events with negative weight w e &lt; 0.</p><p>How strongly an event e is counted at time t depends on the time-difference tt e : each time this difference increases by T 1/2 the factor for w e is halved. The choice of T 1/2 is dependent on whether the analyst is interested in short-term or long-term responses.</p><p>If e is an event in E, we sometimes write G e for G te . Note that G e is only dependent on events that happen earlier than e (and not on events that happen in the same time unit as e). Here f λ (a e , b e , Δt e G e ; θ (λ) ) is the probability density that the i'th event happens after a waiting time of Δt e and involves a e as source and b e as target-given the state of the network G e and the rate parameters θ (λ) . Likewise, f μ (w e a e , b e ; G e ; θ (μ) ) is the probability density that event e has weight w e -given the network G e and values for the weight-parameters θ (μ) and given the fact that the next event involves a e as source and b e as target. Section 2.4.1 clarify the functional form of the density for the event weight (event quality); for space limitations we do not give details on how the event rate (frequency) is modeled (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> for how this can be done). We emphasize that the weight parameters and the rate parameters are uncorrelated and, thus, the former can be estimated even if the model for the event rate is unspecified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Dependent Variable: The Next Event</head><p>2.4.1. Event Quality. We assume that the weight of an event e from actor a to actor b has an expected value μ ab = μ ab (G e ; θ (μ) ) that is dependent on the current state of the network G e and the parameters θ (μ) . The deviation of the actual (observed) weight from the expected value μ ab is modeled as a normal distribution.</p><p>More precisely, for parameters θ (μ) = (θ</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">(μ) 1 , . . . , θ (μ)</formula><p>kμ , σ), the conditional distribution of the weight w of event e = (a, b, w, t) is modeled as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">f μ (w a, b; G e ; θ (μ) ) = 1 σ √ 2π e -[w-μ ab (Ge ;θ (μ) )] 2 2σ 2</formula><p>.</p><p>The expected event weight μ ab (G e ; θ (μ) ) is postulated to be dependent on the parameters (θ</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">(μ) 1 , . . . , θ (μ)</formula><p>kμ ) and the values of various statistics s h (G e ; a, b), h = 1, . . . , k μ that characterize the network around a and b. More precisely, the average event weight is assumed to be a function</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">μ ab (G e ; θ (μ) ) = kμ h=1 θ (μ) h • s h (G e ; a, b) . (<label>3</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">)</formula><p>The maximum likelihood estimates of the weight parameters θ(μ) h reveal dependencies between characteristics of the network and future event weights. For instance, if a certain statistic s h (G e ; i, j) encodes how much j attacked i in the past, then a (significantly) negative value for θ(μ) h would imply that actors show a tendency to initiate hostile events towards attackers. (This tendency to retaliate can indeed be observed, see Sect. 3.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Network Statistics</head><p>The general model outlined so far can be applied to test many hypotheses concerning the interplay between network structure and the quality of dyadic events. The specialization is done by plugging various statistics into Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">3</ref>). The particular statistics that we define below are motivated by previous statistical models for cross-sectional <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> or longitudinal networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>It should be noted that some of these statistics are used to test hypotheses (e. g., reciprocity or structural balance theory), while others mostly serve to control for certain trivial regularities (e. g., inertia). A control statistic that always has to be taken to obtain meaningful results is the constant statistic, defined by constant(G t ; a, b) = 1. The constant statistic just controls for possible deviation from zero of the average event weight. The function constant(G t ; a, b), as well as the ones whose definition follows, correspond to the statistics s h (G t ; a, b) in Eq. (3).</p><p>2.5.1. Dyad Inertia and Reciprocity. The most simple model would assume that actors just continue to act in the way they did in the past. For instance, if actor a often initiated hostilities targeted at actor b, the dyad (a, b) is likely to be a hostile one in the future. This effect is controlled for by the two statistics capturing the inertia of positive/negative events, defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">inertia ± (G t ; a, b) = ω ± t (a, b) .</formula><p>A non-trivial, but very reasonable, network effect would be that actors reciprocate, i. e., actor a adapts its events towards actor b dependent on how b treated a in the past. This is captured by the two statistics</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">reciprocity ± (G t ; a, b) = ω ± t (b, a)</formula><p>equal to the positive/negative weights on the reverse ties.</p><p>A positive estimate for the weight parameter associated to reciprocity + would imply that actors reward cooperation; a negative estimate for the weight parameter associated to reciprocity -would imply that actors retaliate when receiving hostilities. Interestingly, these two effects are not satisfied to the same extent in some datasets, compare Sect. 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.2.">Structural Balance Effects.</head><p>Structural balance theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> predicts that the relation of two actors a and b is (among others) dependent on their common friends and foes. In the following we take it as an indicator for being friends, if two actors cooperate (in either direction) and as an indicator for being enemies, if they exchange hostilities. Let ω + t,sy (i, j) = ω + t (i, j) + ω + t (j, i) denote the symmetric positive weight on a dyad (i, j) and let ω - t,sy (i, j) = ω - t (i, j) + ω - t (j, i) denote the symmetric negative weight.</p><p>The friends-of-enemies-statistic for a dyad (a, b) indicates whether there are actors who are enemies of a and friends of b.</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">friendOfEnemy(G t ; a, b) = i∈A ω - t,sy (a, i) • ω + t,sy (i, b)</formula><p>The square-root expresses the assumption that a second (third, forth, etc.) friend of an enemy has a decreasing marginal effect, compare <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. By varying the plus/minus-signs, we obtain in a similar manner the statistics friendOfFriend, enemyOfFriend, and enemyOfEnemy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.3.">Activity and Popularity Effects.</head><p>As a matter of fact, some actors are more active than others, some do rather initiate hostile events (aggressive actors), others are more cooperative. Likewise, some actors are typical targets of hostilities, while others tend to experience cooperation. To control for such differences in actors' position or power, we introduce a set of statistics dependent on the degree of actors.</p><p>These statistics vary in three dimensions: (1) outdegree (activity) vs. indegree (popularity), (2) positive vs. negative weight, and (3) whether we want to analyze the influence of these degree statistics on the initiator of events (source) or on the addressee of events (target). Together we obtain eight different statistics, one of which is defined below (the others are implied by analogy). The statistic</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">activitySource + (G t ; a, b) = i∈A ω + t (a, i)</formula><p>measures the activity of the source actor with respect to positive events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Parameter Estimation</head><p>Given an observed event sequence, the log-likelihood function (compare Eq. ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>)) on the parameters is</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">log L(θ) = log L λ (θ (λ) ) + log L μ (θ (μ) ) = e∈E log f λ (a e , b e , Δt e G e ; θ (λ) ) + e∈E log f μ (w e a e , b e ; G e ; θ (μ) ) .</formula><p>Hence the maximum likelihood estimation of the rate parameters θ (λ) is independent from the maximum likelihood estimation of the weight parameters θ (μ) . This has the nice implication that a misspecification of one of the two submodels does not jeopardize the estimation of the other set of parameters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Application to Political Event Networks</head><p>For illustration, we apply our newly developed method to test several hypotheses in political network analysis. The concrete datasets are introduced in Sect. 1.1. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Exemplary Hypotheses</head><p>One of the most widely satisfied hypotheses in network analysis is the one that actors tend to reciprocate; this has also been observed for political conflicts, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. In signed networks, we got two types of reciprocation that need not to be fulfilled to the same extent. H 1 Actors behave more cooperatively towards those who cooperated with them in the past (tendency to reward). H 2 Actors behave more hostile towards those who behaved hostile towards them in the past (tendency to retaliate). Besides the dependency of a dyad on its reverse dyad, it is very reasonable to assume that interaction between two actors is influenced by their common friends or enemies. More precisely, structural balance theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> (also compare <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>) predicts that actors behave more . . . H 3 . . . cooperatively towards the friends of their friends; H 4 . . . hostile towards the friends of their enemies; H 5 . . . hostile towards the enemies of their friends; and H 6 . . . cooperatively towards the enemies of their enemies. The choice of the value of the halflife parameter T 1/2 (see Sect. 2.3) depends on whether we want to test a tendency to, say, retaliate in the short run or rather in the long run. We estimated the model with T 1/2 being set to one day, seven days, 30 days, and 180 days; results were surprisingly consistent. Estimated parameters and their standard errors for T 1/2 = 30 days are reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Results and Discussion</head><p>A first observation is that, while hypothesis H 2 (tendency to retaliate) is consistently confirmed over all four datasets, hypothesis H 1 (tendency to reward) could only be validated for one of the four datasets.</p><p>Similarly, the four structural balance hypotheses are not satisfied to the same extent. The rule that "the friend of my friend is my friend" (H 3 ) indeed holds in all conflicts that we analyzed. The rules that actors fight the friends of their enemies (H 4 ), as well as the enemies of their friends (H 5 ) is validated in two datasets (BALKANS and GULF) while the other two yield non-significant parameters. Hypothesis H 6 ("the enemy of my enemy is my friend") is only validated in the BALKANS and GULF conflicts; by contrast, it has a significantly negative effect in the LEVANT and TURKEY conflicts. This might support the reasoning of Doreian and Mrvar <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, who argued that networks are often not perfectly balanced but might contain more than two mutually hostile subgroups. Saperstein <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> argued that application of the rule "the enemy of my enemy is my friend" often leads to undesirable political behavior.</p><p>It is interesting to note that the validity of hypotheses varies over conflicts of different type: the Gulf conflict is mostly a war among state actors, the Balkan conflict a civil war among ethic groups, and the Levant and Turkey datasets encode asymmetric conflicts involving state actors and nonstate actors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusion</head><p>We propose a general model for longitudinal networks that are given as sequences of time-stamped, weighted events. The maximum likelihood estimates of the parameters of this model reveal how the network of past events influences the rate and quality of future events. Specializations of this general model-used to test hypotheses that are motivated by social science theory-are obtained by plugging specific network statistics into Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">3</ref>). In this paper we employed several statistics modeling dependencies of a dyad on its reverse dyad, on the network positions of its source and target, and on indirect relations such as enemies of enemies. It is straightforward to construct statistics modeling dependencies on actor or dyad covariates (see, e. g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>); in the case of political actors such covariates could encode, for instance, national capability, ethnic composition, level of democracy, trade relations, formal alliances, or geographic adjacency (compare <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>).</p><p>The concrete analysis of networks of political actorsalthough it has been included mostly for illustration purposes-yields interesting insight. Most notably are that, while negative reciprocity (tendency to retaliate) seems to be universally satisfied, positive reciprocity (tendency to reward) seems to be much rarer. Similarly, the four hypotheses resulting from structural balance theory (H 3 to H 6 ) do not seem to hold to the same extent. Clearly a sound validation of these hypotheses must control for certain covariates (see above and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Let e = (a e , b e , w e , t e ) be the i'th event in the observed sequence E and and let Δt e denote the time difference between the i'th and the (i -1)'th event. The probability density of e, given the state of the network G e (compare Eq. (1)), is decomposed into two factors f (e G e ; θ) = f λ (a e , b e , Δt e G e ; θ (λ) ) • f μ (w e a e , b e ; G e ; θ (μ) )</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>3. 1 . 1 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Operationalization. All hypotheses are operationalized by testing whether the estimated parameters of appropriate statistics are significantly positive (for the weight parameters this indicates a tendency towards cooperation) or negative (indicating a tendency towards hostility). The appropriate statistics for the event quality hypotheses H 1 to H 6 are given in Sect. 2.5. To control for other obvious network effects we include the inertia, activity, and popularity statistics in our model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Estimated weight parameters and their standard errors (in brackets), computed with the halflife parameter T 1/2 (see Sect. 2.3) set to 30 days. Parameter values are bold if they are significantly positive (tendency towards cooperation) or negative (tendency towards hostility) at the 5% level. The rightmost column indicates which hypothesis predicts positive/negative values for which parameter.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>LEVANT</cell><cell>BALKANS</cell><cell>GULF</cell><cell>TURKEY</cell><cell>predicts</cell></row><row><cell>weight parameters</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>reciprocity + reciprocity -</cell><cell cols="5">0.048 (0.120) -0.137 (0.013) -0.225 (0.036) -0.096 (0.003) -0.729 (0.307) H 2 (-) -0.129 (0.100) 0.132 (0.014) 0.665 (0.758) H 1 (+)</cell></row><row><cell>inertia +</cell><cell>0.272 (0.113)</cell><cell>0.718 (0.081)</cell><cell>0.252 (0.012)</cell><cell>4.184 (0.693)</cell></row><row><cell>inertia -</cell><cell cols="4">-0.088 (0.008) -0.368 (0.030) -0.092 (0.003) -0.657 (0.230)</cell></row><row><cell>friendOfFriend</cell><cell>1.557 (0.073)</cell><cell>0.886 (0.122)</cell><cell>0.223 (0.023)</cell><cell cols="2">2.216 (0.620) H 3 (+)</cell></row><row><cell>friendOfEnemy</cell><cell>-0.061 (0.044)</cell><cell cols="2">-0.818 (0.084) -0.134 (0.013)</cell><cell cols="2">0.518 (0.574) H 4 (-)</cell></row><row><cell>enemyOfFriend</cell><cell>-0.069 (0.040)</cell><cell cols="2">-0.679 (0.081) -0.157 (0.013)</cell><cell cols="2">0.091 (0.566) H 5 (-)</cell></row><row><cell>enemyOfEnemy</cell><cell>-0.305 (0.015)</cell><cell>0.198 (0.051)</cell><cell cols="3">0.060 (0.007) -3.110 (0.439) H 6 (+)</cell></row><row><cell>activitySource +</cell><cell>0.135 (0.019)</cell><cell>0.222 (0.022)</cell><cell>0.061 (0.003)</cell><cell>1.140 (0.169)</cell></row><row><cell>activitySource -</cell><cell cols="4">-0.107 (0.003) -0.058 (0.010) -0.013 (0.001) -1.272 (0.097)</cell></row><row><cell>activityTarget +</cell><cell>0.008 (0.017)</cell><cell>0.231 (0.021)</cell><cell>0.042 (0.003)</cell><cell>1.264 (0.163)</cell></row><row><cell>activityTarget -</cell><cell cols="2">-0.045 (0.003) -0.017 (0.008)</cell><cell cols="2">0.001 (0.001) -0.488 (0.095)</cell></row><row><cell>popularitySource +</cell><cell>0.078 (0.017)</cell><cell cols="2">0.033 (0.018) -0.025 (0.004)</cell><cell>0.396 (0.166)</cell></row><row><cell>popularitySource -</cell><cell>-0.017 (0.004)</cell><cell>-0.009 (0.012)</cell><cell>0.005 (0.001)</cell><cell>-0.123 (0.090)</cell></row><row><cell>popularityTarget +</cell><cell>0.127 (0.014)</cell><cell cols="2">0.058 (0.014) -0.028 (0.004)</cell><cell>0.080 (0.156)</cell></row><row><cell>popularityTarget -</cell><cell cols="2">-0.045 (0.003) -0.061 (0.010)</cell><cell cols="2">0.004 (0.001) -0.685 (0.078)</cell></row><row><cell>constant</cell><cell cols="4">-0.087 (0.002) -0.038 (0.002) -0.078 (0.001) -0.013 (0.004)</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The statistical evaluation of social network dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A B</forename><surname>Snijders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Basil Blackwell</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Models for longitudinal network data</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Models and Methods in Social Network Analysis</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Carrington</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wasserman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Political science: KEDS-a program for the machine coding of event data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schrodt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Weddle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Science Computer Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="588" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">World event/interaction survey codebook (icpsr 5211)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcclelland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A conflict-cooperation scale for WEIS international events data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Conflict Resolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lawless</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Statistical Models and Methods for Lifetime Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time is of the essence: Event history models in political science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Box-Steffensmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1414" to="1461" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocity, triangularity, and cooperation in the Middle East, 1979-97</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pevehouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gerner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Telhami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Conflict Resolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="594" to="620" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is the enemy of my enemy? Causes and consequences of imbalanced international relations, 1816-2001</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Maoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Terris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kuperman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Talmud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Politics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reputation and interstate conflict</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J C</forename><surname>Crescenzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="382" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Signs over time: Statistical and visual analysis of a longitudinal signed network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>De Nooy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Structure</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A relational event framework for social action</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Butts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociological Methodology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction and ranking algorithms for event-based network data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>O'madadhain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hutchins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Smyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM SIGKDD Explorations Newsletter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The time-series link prediction problem with application in communication surveillance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Informs Journal on Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Summarizing dynamic bipolar conflict structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Brandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fleischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lerner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1486" to="1499" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visualization of conflict networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Brandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lerner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>M. Kauffmann</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Ed. IOS Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Essentials of Statistical Inference</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent developments in exponential random graph (p * ) models for social networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Snijders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Handcock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pattison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attitudes and cognitive organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Heider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="1946">1946</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural balance: A generalization of Heider&apos;s theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cartwright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Harary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Psychological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patitioning signed social networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Doreian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mrvar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The enemy of my enemy is my friend&apos; is the enemy: Dealing with the war-provoking rules of intent</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Saperstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Conflict Management and Peace Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="296" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
