<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Deriving three-way decisions from intuitionistic fuzzy decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-12-26">26 December 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Decui</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
							<email>decuiliang@126.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Management and Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology of China</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>610054</postCode>
									<settlement>Chengdu</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dun</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Economics and Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southwest Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>610031</postCode>
									<settlement>Chengdu</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Deriving three-way decisions from intuitionistic fuzzy decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-12-26">26 December 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BA9CC6273F96F5F05B7F0B8312E218F3</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ins.2014.12.036</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 4 May 2014 Received in revised form 9 December 2014 Accepted 12 December 2014</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T05:57+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Three-way decisions Intuitionistic fuzzy sets Loss function Decision-theoretic rough sets Multi-period decision making</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Three-way decisions with decision-theoretic rough sets (DTRSs) provide a new methodology to confront risk decision problems. The risk is associated with the loss function of DTRSs. Under the intuitionistic fuzzy environment, we combine the loss functions of DTRSs with intuitionistic fuzzy sets (IFSs). Considering the new evaluation format of loss function with intuitionistic fuzzy numbers (IFNs), we propose a naive model of intuitionistic fuzzy decision-theoretic rough sets (IFDTRSs) and elaborate its relevant properties in advance. At this point, a critical issue is the determination of three-way decisions. In the frame of IFDTRSs, we then explore deriving three-way decisions for single-period decision making. Based on the positive and negative characteristics of IFNs, we design three strategies to address IFNs and derive corresponding three-way decisions. Meanwhile, we compare the three strategies and summarize their own applicabilities. In order to accommodate multi-period scenarios, we further extend IFDTRSs to the multi-period situation. With the aid of the results of the single period decision making, we analyze three aggregation operations of IFDTRSs for multi-period information, which are DIFWA, DIFPA and DIFOA, respectively. By comparing these operations, an algorithm for deriving three-way decisions in multi-period decision making is designed. These results help us to make a reasonable decision in the intuitionistic fuzzy environment. Finally, an example is presented to elaborate on three-way decisions with IFDTRSs.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Three-way decisions, consisting of acceptance, non-commitment (or further investigation) and rejection, are commonly encountered in problem solving strategies <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref>, such as investment decision <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref>, information filtering <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, text classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, risk decision <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>, cluster analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59]</ref>, government decision <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, web-based support systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>, etc. The notion of three-way decisions is initially developed in the framework of rough sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33]</ref>. More specifically, considering three pairwise disjoint regions of rough sets (i.e., positive region POSðCÞ, boundary region BNDðCÞ and negative region NEGðCÞ), Yao <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref> proposed three-way decisions with the aid of the risk decision semantics. The three-way decisions comprise positive rules, boundary rules and negative rules <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57]</ref>. The positive rules associated with the positive region produce acceptance decisions. The negative rules coming with the negative region give rise to rejection decisions, while the boundary rules (coming with the boundary region) result in decisions of non-commitment. In connection with the three basic elements of three-way decisions, Hu <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> systematically discussed three-way decisions space and three-way decisions. As an extended model of rough sets, decision-theoretic rough sets (DTRSs) vastly push the development of threeway decisions <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57]</ref>. In light of Bayesian decision procedure, DTRSs were proposed by Yao et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52]</ref>. The model involves practical decision semantics and considers relevant risks. Three-way decisions with DTRSs are derived from the minimum of the overall risk.</p><p>For three-way decisions with DTRSs, Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> summarized the existing literatures and classified these researches in detail. Azam and Yao <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> investigated the use of game-theoretic rough set (GTRS) model in exploring the relationship between the changes of probabilistic thresholds and their impacts on uncertainty levels of different regions. Deng and Yao <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> presented an information-theoretic approach to the interpretation and determination of probabilistic thresholds. Considering the costs of misclassification, Greco et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> proposed a new dominance-based rough set approach based on DTRSs. In the viewpoint of the optimization, Jia et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref> discussed the determination of the thresholds and the reduction technology for DTRSs. In light of different attitudes of decision makers, Li and Zhou <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> discussed the relationships of loss functions and proposed a multi-view DTRS decision model. Considering both the misclassification cost and test cost, Li et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> designed an algorithm for attribute reduction with the minimum total cost. In the context of DTRSs, Li et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> verified its non-monotonic feature of attribute reduction and designed a corresponding algorithm. Based on the DTRS model, Lingras et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> redefined a loss function and proposed a cluster quality index for rough clusters. With respect to an investment decision-making, Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> proposed a profit-based three-way approach with DTRSs. By analyzing the different combinations of loss functions, Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> proposed four-level probabilistic rules choosing criteria. In addition, Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> also listed some methods for estimating the loss function. Min and Zhu <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> studied the attribute reduction of data with error ranges and test costs. Through combining DTRSs and granular structures, Qian et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> developed a multigranulation decision-theoretic rough set. With respect to multiple sets of decision preferences, Yang and Yao <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref> discussed some aggregations of loss functions in a multi-agent DTRS model. Yao <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> employed relative values between loss functions to express the thresholds and reduced the estimation amount. In light of the loss function of DTRSs, Yu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref> constructed a new clustering validity evaluation function. Zhang and Miao <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref> established a fundamental reduction framework for two-category DTRSs. Under a multi-class environment, Zhou <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref> provided a new formulation of multi-class DTRSs. With the aforementioned literatures, the determination of loss function of DTRSs is a pivotal issue. Nowadays, some uncertain evaluation scenarios enrich the determination of loss function and make it adapt to a certain decision making environment. For example, Liang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, Liang and Liu <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref> and Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> effectively estimated the loss functions in the format of triangular fuzzy numbers, hesitant fuzzy sets, intervals, and typical stochastic functions. These works extend the range of applications of three-way decision with DTRSs.</p><p>Inspired by the researches reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>, intuitionistic fuzzy sets (IFSs) proposed by Atanassov <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, are also a significant evaluation format to describe the uncertainty. Unlike an ordinary fuzzy set <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60]</ref>, the concept of IFSs is a more flexible way to capture the uncertainty and has a duality property, which is characterized both by a membership degree and by a non-membership degree <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. IFSs have been witnessed in numerous situations and mainly utilize intuitionistic fuzzy numbers (IFNs) to support the decisions <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>. For instance, Boran and Akay <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> proposed a new general type of similarity measure of IFSs and applied it to pattern recognition. Chaira and Ray <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> used IFSs for solving image edge detection. Based on the degrees of membership and non-membership of IFSs, Chen <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> elucidated the positive and negative evaluation effects (or optimism and pessimism) and developed a unipolar bivariate approach. Considering a combination of multigranulation rough sets with intuitionistic fuzzy rough sets, Huang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> developed a new multigranulation rough set model. Vlachos and Sergiadis <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> presented an information-theoretic approach to discrimination measures for IFNs and wielded it in the context of pattern recognition. In the field of multi-criteria decision making, Li <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, Liu and Wang <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, Xu <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> and Yager <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> discussed some aggregation operations of IFNs with different contexts. Unlike the existing works presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>, this paper introduces the IFN into DTRSs and proposes a new model of intuitionistic fuzzy decisiontheoretic rough sets (IFDTRSs). By utilizing the positive and negative characteristic of IFNs <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, we design three strategies to address IFNs and deduce appropriate three-way decisions. In addition, there also exist some multi-period scenarios in real decision making procedure, e.g., multi-period (multi-stage) investment decision making, medical diagnosis, personnel dynamic examination, and military system efficiency dynamic evaluation <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref>. In order to accommodate multi-period scenarios <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58]</ref>, we further extend IFDTRSs with the single period decision making to the multi-period situation. With the aid of the results of the single period decision making, we analyze the determination for the aggregation of the loss function by comparing three typical operations and then design a corresponding algorithm for deriving three-way decisions. This study provides us with a series of decision analysis methodologies when the loss functions of DTRSs are IFNs and extends the range of applications.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows: Section 2 provides some basic concepts of Bayesian decision procedure and IFSs. Basic model of IFDTRSs is designed in Section 3. Then, decision analysis of IFDTRSs for single-period decision making and its relevant properties are explored in Section 4. With the above analysis, decision analysis of IFDTRSs for multiperiod decision making is further studied in Section 5. An example is presented to illustrate the application of the novel three-way decisions in Section 6. Section 7 concludes the paper and elaborates on future studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Preliminaries</head><p>Basic concepts, notations and results of Bayesian decision procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> and IFSs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47]</ref> are briefly reviewed in this section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Bayesian decision procedure</head><p>The theoretical framework of DTRSs is Bayesian decision procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52]</ref>. With respect to the results presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>,</p><p>Bayesian decision procedure is elaborated as follows. The set of states given by X ¼ fw 1 ; w 2 ; . . . ; w m g is a finite set of m states and A ¼ fa 1 ; a 2 ; . . . ; a n g is a finite set of n possible actions. Prðw i jxÞ is the conditional probability of an object x being in state w i given that the object is described by x. Without loss of generality, we simply assume that these conditional probabilities Prðw i jxÞ and PrðxÞ are known. Let kða j jw i Þ denote the loss or cost for taking action a j in the state w i . For an object x, suppose action a j is taken. Since Prðw i jxÞ is the probability of the state w i by given x, the expected loss associated with taking action a j is given below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Rða j jxÞ ¼ X m i¼1 kða j jw i ÞPrðw i jxÞ:<label>ð1Þ</label></formula><p>Given description x of the object x, a decision rule can be conceived as a function sðxÞ that specifies which action to take, and the overall risk R is calculated by: R ¼ X</p><p>x</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RðsðxÞjxÞPrðxÞ; ð2Þ</head><p>where the summation is over the set of all possible descriptions of objects. If sðxÞ is chosen so that RðsðxÞjxÞ is as small as possible for every x, the overall risk R is minimum. For every object x, we compute the conditional risk Rða j jxÞ for every action by (1) and select the action for which the conditional risk is minimum. If more than one action minimizes, any tiebreaking rule can be used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Intuitionistic fuzzy sets (IFSs)</head><p>The concept of IFSs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> is an extension of the concept of fuzzy sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref>. In the following, we review some basic concepts of IFSs and their operations <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47]</ref>. Definition 1. Let U be a fixed set. An intuitionistic fuzzy set (IFS) E on U can be represented as the following mathematical symbol:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">E ¼ f&lt; f ; l E ðf Þ; m E ðf Þ &gt; jf 2 Ug;<label>ð3Þ</label></formula><p>where the functions l E ðf Þ : U ! ½0; 1 and m E ðf Þ : U ! ½0; 1 are the membership degree and non-membership degree of f to E, respectively.</p><p>Definition 1 provides a way to evaluate the same problem with the positive and the negative perspectives. In light of Definition 1, the relationship between l E ðf Þ and m E ðf Þ for 8f 2 U is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">0 6 l E ðf Þ þ m E ðf Þ 6 1.</formula><p>Meanwhile, the hesitation (or uncertainty) membership of f in U can be calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">p E ðf Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðf Þ À m E ðf Þ;<label>ð4Þ</label></formula><p>where the value of p E ðf Þ satisfies 0 6 p E ðf Þ 6 1. If the value of p E ðf Þ is small, then the knowledge of f is more certain and vice versa <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. According to the notations reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref>, an intuitionistic fuzzy number (IFN) can be denoted as</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Eðf Þ ¼ ðl E ðf Þ; m E ðf ÞÞ.</formula><p>In light of the results presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45]</ref>, we discuss the three-way decisions based on IFNs below.</p><p>Example 1. Inspired by the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, let E be an intuitionistic fuzzy concept of excellence and the set of alternatives be U ¼ ff 1 ; f 2 ; f 3 g. Under the intuitionistic fuzzy environment, assume that we have three IFNs:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Eðf 1 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 1 Þ; m E ðf 1 ÞÞ ¼ ð0:8; 0:2Þ; Eðf 2 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 2 Þ; m E ðf 2 ÞÞ ¼ ð0:8; 0:1Þ; Eðf 3 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 3 Þ; m E ðf 3 ÞÞ ¼ ð0:8;<label>0Þ</label></formula><p>, which represent the membership degree and non-membership degree of each alternative to the concept E, respectively. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">p E ðf 1 Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðf 1 Þ Àm E ðf 1 Þ ¼ 1 À 0:8 À 0:2 ¼ 0; p E ðf 2 Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðf 2 Þ À m E ðf 2 Þ ¼ 1 À 0:8 À 0:1 ¼ 0:1 and p E ðf 3 Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðf 3 Þ À m E ðf 3 Þ ¼ 1 À 0:8 À0 ¼ 0:2.</formula><p>Hence, the alternative f 1 in U is certain and alternatives f 2 and f 3 are uncertain. Compared with f 3 , we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">p E ðf 2 Þ &lt; p E ðf 3 Þ. Given two IFNs Eðf 1 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 1 Þ; m E ðf 1 ÞÞ; Eðf 2 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 2 Þ; m E ðf 2 ÞÞ</formula><p>, their basic operations are <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">(1) Eðf 1 Þ ¼ ðm E ðf 1 Þ; l E ðf 1 ÞÞ; (2) Eðf 1 Þ È Eðf 2 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 1 Þ þ l E ðf 2 Þ À l E ðf 1 Þl E ðf 2 Þ; m E ðf 1 Þm E ðf 2 ÞÞ; (3) Eðf 1 Þ Eðf 2 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 1 Þl E ðf 2 Þ; m E ðf 1 Þ þ m E ðf 2 Þ À m E ðf 1 Þm E ðf 2 ÞÞ; (4) kEðf 1 Þ ¼ ð1 À ð1 À l E ðf 1 ÞÞ k ; ðm E ðf 1 ÞÞ k Þ, where k 2 R and k P 0; (5) Eðf 1 Þ \ Eðf 2 Þ ¼ ðminðl E ðf 1 Þ; l E ðf 2 ÞÞ; maxðm E ðf 1 Þ; m E ðf 2 ÞÞÞ; (6) Eðf 1 Þ [ Eðf 2 Þ ¼ ðmaxðl E ðf 1 Þ; l E ðf 2 ÞÞ; minðm E ðf 1 Þ; m E ðf 2 ÞÞÞ.</formula><p>In order to compare IFNs, the score function and the accuracy function of an IFN are defined in advance <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Definition 2. Let an IFN Eðf 1 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 1 Þ; m E ðf 1 ÞÞ, then the score function of Eðf 1 Þ is calculated as: SðEðf 1 ÞÞ ¼ l E ðf 1 Þ À m E ðf 1 Þ:<label>ð5Þ</label></formula><p>The accuracy function of Eðf 1 Þ is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">HðEðf 1 ÞÞ ¼ l E ðf 1 Þ þ m E ðf 1 Þ;<label>ð6Þ</label></formula><p>where À1 6 SðEðf 1 ÞÞ 6 1 and 0 6 HðEðf 1 ÞÞ 6 1.</p><p>With respect to Definition 2, Xu and Yager <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> and Xu <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> proposed the following rules for ranking of IFNs <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">Definition 3. Let two IFNs Eðf 1 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 1 Þ; m E ðf 1 ÞÞ; Eðf 2 Þ ¼ ðl E ðf 2 Þ</formula><p>; m E ðf 2 ÞÞ, then we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">(1) If SðEðf 1 ÞÞ &gt; SðEðf 2 ÞÞ, then Eðf 2 Þ is smaller than Eðf 1 Þ, denoted by Eðf 1 Þ &gt; Eðf 2 Þ; (2) If SðEðf 1 ÞÞ &lt; SðEðf 2 ÞÞ, then Eðf 1 Þ is smaller than Eðf 2 Þ, denoted by Eðf 1 Þ &lt; Eðf 2 Þ; (3) If SðEðf 1 ÞÞ ¼ SðEðf 2 ÞÞ, then (i) If HðEðf 1 ÞÞ ¼ HðEðf 2 ÞÞ, then Eðf 1 Þ is equal to Eðf 2 Þ, denoted by Eðf 1 Þ ¼ Eðf 2 Þ; (ii) If HðEðf 1 ÞÞ &gt; HðEðf 2 ÞÞ, then Eðf 2 Þ is smaller than Eðf 1 Þ, denoted by Eðf 1 Þ &gt; Eðf 2 Þ; (iii) If HðEðf 1 ÞÞ &lt; HðEðf 2 ÞÞ, then Eðf 1 Þ is smaller than Eðf 2 Þ, denoted by Eðf 1 Þ &lt; Eðf 2 Þ.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Intuitionistic fuzzy decision-theoretic rough set model</head><p>Considering the new uncertainty measurement of IFSs, we discuss the loss function of DTRSs with IFNs in this section. In light of Bayesian decision procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52]</ref>, we construct intuitionistic fuzzy decision-theoretic rough sets (IFDTRSs).</p><p>The IFDTRS model is composed of two states and three actions. The set of states is given by X ¼ fC; :Cg indicating that an object is in C and not in C, respectively. The set of actions is given by A ¼ fa P ; a B ; a N g, where a P ; a B , and a N represent three actions when classifying object x, namely, deciding x 2 POSðCÞ, deciding x should be further investigated x 2 BNDðCÞ, and deciding x 2 NEGðCÞ, respectively. The intuitionistic fuzzy loss function matrix regarding the risk or cost of actions in the different states is given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, E is an intuitionistic fuzzy concept of the loss and the loss functions Eðk Þ are IFNsð ¼ P; B; NÞ. Eðk PP Þ; Eðk BP Þ and Eðk NP Þ denote the loss degrees in the E with IFNs incurred for taking actions of a P ; a B and a N , respectively, when an object belongs to C, e.g., Eðk PP Þ ¼ ð0; 1Þ; Eðk BP Þ ¼ ð0:1; 0:8Þ and Eðk NP Þ ¼ ð0:9; 0Þ. Similarly, Eðk PN Þ; Eðk BN Þ and Eðk NN Þ denote the loss degrees incurred for taking the same actions when the object belongs to :C. By considering a reasonable kind of loss functions with:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">l E ðk PP Þ &lt; l E ðk BP Þ &lt; l E ðk NP Þ; ð7Þ m E ðk NP Þ &lt; m E ðk BP Þ &lt; m E ðk PP Þ; ð8Þ l E ðk NN Þ &lt; l E ðk BN Þ &lt; l E ðk PN Þ; ð9Þ m E ðk PN Þ &lt; m E ðk BN Þ &lt; m E ðk NN Þ:<label>ð10Þ</label></formula><p>Proposition 1. Based on (7)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, they imply the following relationships:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">Eðk PP Þ &lt; Eðk BP Þ &lt; Eðk NP Þ;<label>ð11Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">Eðk NN Þ &lt; Eðk BN Þ &lt; Eðk PN Þ:<label>ð12Þ</label></formula><p>For Proposition 1, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> illustrate that the loss of classifying an object x belonging to C into the positive region POSðCÞ is less than the loss of classifying x into the boundary region BNDðCÞ, and both of these losses are strictly less than the loss of classifying x into the negative region NEGðCÞ <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. The reverse orders of these losses are suitable for classifying an object not in C. It is notable that ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> are the prerequisite of the IFDTRSs. PrðCj½xÞ is the conditional probability of an object x belonging to C given that the object is described by its equivalence class ½x. Analogously, Prð:Cj½xÞ is the conditional probability of an object x belonging to :C, i.e. PrðCj½xÞ þ Prð:Cj½xÞ ¼ 1. For an object x, the expected loss Rða j½xÞð ¼ P; B; NÞ associated with taking the individual actions is expressed as: The intuitionistic fuzzy loss function matrix regarding the risk or cost of actions in the different states.</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">Rða</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CðPÞ</head><p>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">CðNÞ a P Eðk PP Þ ¼ ðl E ðk PP Þ; m E ðk PP ÞÞ Eðk PN Þ ¼ ðl E ðk PN Þ; m E ðk PN ÞÞ a B Eðk BP Þ ¼ ðl E ðk BP Þ; m E ðk BP ÞÞ Eðk BN Þ ¼ ðl E ðk BN Þ; m E ðk BN ÞÞ a N Eðk NP Þ ¼ ðl E ðk NP Þ; m E ðk NP ÞÞ Eðk NN Þ ¼ ðl E ðk NN Þ; m E ðk NN ÞÞ</formula><p>In this case, the expected losses are IFNs. According to the operations of IFNs, ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">15</ref>) can be calculated as:</p><p>Rða P j½xÞ ¼ ð1 </p><p>From Proposition 2, one can see that the result is captured as follows.</p><p>Proposition 3. Based on ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">21</ref>), the expected loss Rða j½xÞð ¼ P; B; NÞ is calculated as:</p><p>Rða j½xÞ ¼ ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ:</p><p>Proposition 3 provides a general expression of the expected losses. Let Rða j½xÞ ¼ ðl ; m Þð ¼ P; B; NÞ. In light of the results reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, we discuss the variations of the elements in the expected losses with the loss functions of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Proposition 4. Let l ¼ 1 À ð1 À l E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ . When PrðCj½xÞ is constant, l is non-monotonic decreasing with increasing of l E ðk P Þ and l E ðk N Þð ¼ P; B; NÞ.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">Proof. Considering l E ðk P Þ; l E ðk N Þ are independent variables of l , we take the partial derivative of l to l E ðk P Þ and l E ðk N Þ, respectively. When l E ðk N Þ is constant, the partial derivative of l to l E ðk P Þ is computed as: @l @l E ðk P Þ ¼ ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ 0 ; ¼ PrðCj½xÞð1 À l E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞÀ1 ð1 À l E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ P 0:</formula><p>Analogously, when l E ðk P Þ is constant, the partial derivative of l to l E ðk N Þ is computed as: @l @l E ðk N Þ ¼ Prð:Cj½xÞð1 À l E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞÀ1 ð1 À l E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ P 0:</p><p>In view of @l @l E ðk P Þ P 0 and @l @l E ðk N Þ P 0, the statement in Proposition 4 holds. h Proposition 5. Let m ¼ ðm E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ . When PrðCj½xÞ is constant, m is non-monotonic decreasing with increasing of m E ðk P Þ and m E ðk N Þð ¼ P; B; NÞ.</p><p>Proof. With respect to the proposition, we take the partial derivative of m to m</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">E ðk P Þ and m E ðk N Þ, respectively. When m E ðk N Þ is constant, the partial derivative of m to m E ðk P Þ is computed as: @m @m E ðk P Þ ¼ ððm E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ 0 ;</formula><p>¼ PrðCj½xÞðm E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞÀ1 ðm E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ P 0:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">Analogously, when m E ðk P Þ is constant, the partial derivative of m to m E ðk N Þ is computed as: @m @m E ðk N Þ ¼ Prð:Cj½xÞðm E ðk N ÞÞ Prð:</formula><p>Cj½xÞÀ1 ðm E ðk P ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ P 0:</p><p>In view of @m @m E ðk P Þ P 0 and @m @m E ðk N Þ P 0, the statement in Proposition 5 is satisfied. h</p><p>From Propositions 4, 5, the variations of l (or m ) are accompanied with the increasing of l E ðk P Þ and l E ðk N Þ (or m E ðk P Þ and m E ðk N Þ)ð ¼ P; B; NÞ. For clarity, we use Example 2 to illustrate the variations.</p><p>Example 2. Take the expected loss Rða P j½xÞ ¼ ðl P ; m P Þ as an example. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>, l P ¼ 1À ð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; m P ¼ ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ . In light of Definition 1,</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">l E ðk PP Þ; l E ðk PN Þ 2 ½0; 1.</formula><p>Assume that l E ðk PP Þ and l E ðk PN Þ can be assigned in the range of ½0; 1. Under the possible combinations between l E ðk PP Þ and l E ðk PN Þ; l P are described in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p><p>From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, nine types of PrðCj½xÞ are discussed. When the value of PrðCj½xÞ is constant, l P is non-monotonic decreasing with the increasing of l E ðk PP Þ and l E ðk PN Þ. This example validates Proposition 4. With respect to the variation of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, we find the variation of l P in the Rða P j½xÞ is uncertain when l E ðk PP Þ is increasing and l E ðk PN Þ is simultaneously decreasing.</p><p>In the same way, suppose m E ðk PP Þ and m E ðk PN Þ can be assigned in the range of ½0; 1. Under the possible combinations between m E ðk PP Þ and m E ðk PN Þ; m P are outlined in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>.</p><p>From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>, nine types of PrðCj½xÞ are discussed and m P is non-monotonic decreasing with the increasing of m E ðk PP Þ and m E ðk PN Þ, when the value of PrðCj½xÞ is constant. This figure verifies the result of Proposition 5. With respect to the variation of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>, we find the variation of m P in the Rða P j½xÞ is uncertain when m E ðk PP Þ is increasing and m E ðk PN Þ is simultaneously decreasing.</p><p>According to ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">21</ref>), the values of the expected losses (i.e., Rða P j½xÞ; Rða B j½xÞ and Rða N j½xÞ) are determined by the loss functions of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Propositions 3-5 display the variations of the elements in the expected losses with the increasing of the loss functions. From Example 2, the variations of the elements in the expected losses may be uncertain when one loss associated with the expected loss is increasing and the other is simultaneously decreasing. Hence, we elicit the following proposition. Proposition 6. Under (11), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_15">12</ref>), the relationships among Rða P j½xÞ; Rða B j½xÞ and Rða N j½xÞ depend on the values of loss functions in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, which are uncertain and need be further compared with each other.</p><p>The purpose of DTRSs is to provide some decision rules replied on the Bayesian decision procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Under the intuitionist fuzzy environment, the Bayesian decision procedure suggests the following minimum-cost decision rules: where Rða P j½xÞ; Rða B j½xÞ and Rða N j½xÞ are IFNs. According to the result presented in Proposition 6, the decision rules (P)-(N) need to be further investigated based on ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">21</ref>) and the operations of IFNs. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Decision analysis of IFDTRSs for single-period decision making</head><p>As we stated in Section 3, the decision rules (P)-(N) need to be further discussed. From Definition 1, an IFN characterized both by a membership degree and a non-membership degree, provides a way to evaluate the decision problem with the positive and the negative viewpoints <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. Under the limited evaluation information of single-period decision making, we mainly adopt the concepts of IFNs and design three types of strategies to deduce three-way decisions (i.e., Strategies 1-3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Strategy 1: A positive viewpoint</head><p>For decision rules (P)-(N), the expected losses Rða P j½xÞ ¼ ðl P ; m P Þ; Rða B j½xÞ ¼ ðl B ; m B Þ and Rða N j½xÞ ¼ ðl N ; m N Þ are IFNs. With regard to the positive viewpoint, we directly use the membership degrees of IFNs to represent the expected losses. When we compare the expected losses, the membership degrees of the expected losses keep in step with them. According to this scenario, decision rules (P)-(N) can be re-expressed as: where l P ¼ 1 À ð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; l B ¼ 1 À ð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ and l N ¼ 1À ð1 À l E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ . Under conditions of ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>), we simplify the decision rules ðP1Þ-ðN1Þ. For the rule ðP1Þ, the first condition is expressed as: l P 6 l B () 1 À ð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ 6 1 À ð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ () ð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ P ð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ () logðð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ P logðð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ () logð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ þ log ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ P logð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ þ logð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ () Similarly, the second condition of rule ðP1Þ can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">PrðCj½xÞlogð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ þ Prð:Cj½xÞlogð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ P PrðCj½xÞlogð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ þ Prð:Cj½xÞlogð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ () PrðCj½xÞ P log 1 À l E ðk BN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ log 1 À l E ðk PP Þ 1 À l E ðk BP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk BN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ :</formula><p>l P 6 l N () 1 À ð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ 6 1 À ð1 À l E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ () PrðCj½xÞ P log</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ log 1 À l E ðk PP Þ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ :</formula><p>The first condition of rule ðB1Þ is the converse of the first condition of rule ðP1Þ. It follows,</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">l B 6 l P () PrðCj½xÞ 6 log 1 À l E ðk BN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ log 1 À l E ðk PP Þ 1 À l E ðk BP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk BN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ :</formula><p>For the second condition of rule ðB1Þ, we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">l B 6 l N () 1 À ð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ 6 1 À ð1 À l E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ () PrðCj½xÞ P log 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ log 1 À l E ðk BP Þ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ :</formula><p>The first condition of rule ðN1Þ is the converse of the second condition of rule ðP1Þ and the second condition of rule ðN1Þ is the converse of the second condition of rule ðB1Þ. It follows,</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">l N 6 l P () PrðCj½xÞ 6 log 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ log 1 À l E ðk PP Þ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ : l N 6 l B () PrðCj½xÞ 6 log 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ log 1 À l E ðk BP Þ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ :</formula><p>On basis of the derivation of decision rules ðP1Þ-ðN1Þ, we denote the three expressions in these conditions by the following three thresholds:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">a 1 ¼ log 1 À l E ðk BN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ log 1 À l E ðk PP Þ 1 À l E ðk BP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk BN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ ;<label>ð22Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">b 1 ¼ log 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ log 1 À l E ðk BP Þ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ ;<label>ð23Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">c 1 ¼ log 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ log 1 À l E ðk PP Þ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ :<label>ð24Þ</label></formula><p>Therefore, the decision rules (P1)-(N1) can be re-expressed concisely as:  </p><formula xml:id="formula_32">m E ðk BN Þ m E ðk PN Þ log m E ðk PP Þ m E ðk BP Þ Ã m E ðk BN Þ m E ðk PN Þ :</formula><p>Similarly, the second condition of rule ðP2Þ can be expressed as: </p><formula xml:id="formula_33">m P P m N ()</formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk PN Þ log m E ðk PP Þ m E ðk NP Þ Ã m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk PN Þ :</formula><p>The first condition of rule ðB2Þ is the converse of the first condition of rule ðP2Þ. It follows,</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">m B P m P () PrðCj½xÞ 6 log m E ðk BN Þ m E ðk PN Þ log m E ðk PP Þ m E ðk BP Þ Ã m E ðk BN Þ m E ðk PN Þ :</formula><p>For the second condition of rule ðB2Þ, we have: </p><formula xml:id="formula_36">m B P m N ()</formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk BN Þ log m E ðk BP Þ m E ðk NP Þ ast m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk BN Þ :</formula><p>The first condition of rule ðN2Þ is the converse of the second condition of rule ðP2Þ and the second condition of rule ðN2Þ is the converse of the second condition of rule ðB2Þ. It follows,</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">m N P m P () PrðCj½xÞ 6 log m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk PN Þ log m E ðk PP Þ m E ðk NP Þ Ã m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk PN Þ : m N P m B () PrðCj½xÞ 6 log m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk BN Þ log m E ðk BP Þ m E ðk NP Þ Ã m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk BN Þ :</formula><p>For the decision rules ðP2Þ-ðN2Þ, the three thresholds in these conditions are deduced as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">a 2 ¼ log m E ðk BN Þ m E ðk PN Þ log m E ðk PP Þ m E ðk BP Þ Ã m E ðk BN Þ m E ðk PN Þ ;<label>ð25Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">b 2 ¼ log m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk BN Þ log m E ðk BP Þ m E ðk NP Þ Ã m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk BN Þ ;<label>ð26Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">c 2 ¼ log m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk PN Þ log m E ðk PP Þ m E ðk NP Þ Ã m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk PN Þ :<label>ð27Þ</label></formula><p>Therefore, the decision rules (P2)-(N2) can be re-expressed concisely as:</p><p>If PrðCj½xÞ P a 2 and PrðCj½xÞ P c 2 ; decide x 2 POSðCÞ; Proof. On the basis of p E ðk Þ ¼ 0ð ¼ P; B; NÞ and (4), we deduce the following relationships:</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">If<label>ðB2Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">m E ðk PP Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk PP Þ; m E ðk BP Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk BP Þ; m E ðk NP Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ; m E ðk PN Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ; m E ðk BN Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ and m E ðk NN Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk NN Þ.</formula><p>With the above relationships, the thresholds ða 2 ; b 2 ; c 2 Þ are recalculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">a 2 ¼ log m E ðk BN Þ m E ðk PN Þ log m E ðk PP Þ m E ðk BP Þ Ã m E ðk BN Þ m E ðk PN Þ ¼ log 1 À l E ðk BN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ log 1 À l E ðk PP Þ 1 À l E ðk BP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk BN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ ; b 2 ¼ log m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk BN Þ log m E ðk BP Þ m E ðk NP Þ Ã m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk BN Þ ¼ log 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ log 1 À l E ðk BP Þ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ ; c 2 ¼ log m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk PN Þ log m E ðk PP Þ m E ðk NP Þ Ã m E ðk NN Þ m E ðk PN Þ ¼ log 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ log 1 À l E ðk PP Þ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ Ã 1 À l E ðk NN Þ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ :</formula><p>In this case, the thresholds ða 2 ; b 2 ; c 2 Þ correspond to the thresholds ða 1 ; b 1 ; c 1 Þ of (P1)-(N1). The statement in Proposition 7</p><p>holds. h For Proposition 7, the condition l E ðk P Þ þ m E ðk P Þ ¼ 1 ensures the consistency between (P1)-(N1) and (P2)-(N2)ð ¼ P; B; NÞ. Take the case of Eðk PP Þ ¼ ðl E ðk PP Þ; m E ðk PP ÞÞ, the relationship between the elements l E ðk PP Þ and m E ðk PP Þ is described by the case (1) of Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>.</p><p>However, the condition l E ðk P Þ þ m E ðk P Þ ¼ 1 may not always be tenable ð ¼ P; B; NÞ, e.g., the case (2) of Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. In this case, Example 3. Let E be an intuitionistic fuzzy concept of loss. In view of the loss functions of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, we evaluate their values, respectively. In this example, suppose</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">l E ðk PP Þ þ m E ðk PP Þ &lt; 1 and l E ðk PP Þ þ p E ðk PP Þ þ m E ðk PP Þ ¼ 1. p E ðk PP Þ</formula><formula xml:id="formula_47">Eðk PP Þ ¼ ðl E ðk PP Þ; m E ðk PP ÞÞ ¼ ð0; 0:9Þ; Eðk BP Þ ¼ ðl E ðk BP Þ; m E ðk BP ÞÞ ¼ ð0:3; 0:7Þ; Eðk NP Þ ¼ ðl E ðk NP Þ; m E ðk NP ÞÞ ¼ ð0:9; 0:1Þ; Eðk PN Þ ¼ ðl E ðk PN Þ; m E ðk PN ÞÞ ¼ ð0:8; 0:1Þ; Eðk BN Þ ¼ ðl E ðk BN Þ; m E ðk BN ÞÞ ¼ ð0:5; 0:4Þ and Eðk NN Þ ¼ ðl E ðk NN Þ; m E ðk NN ÞÞ ¼ ð0:05; 0:8Þ.</formula><p>With the aid of Strategy 1, the thresholds ða 1 ; b 1 ; c 1 Þ of (P1)-(N1) are calculated using ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_28">22</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_30">24</ref>): a 1 ¼ 0:7198; b 1 ¼ 0:2480; c 1 ¼ 0:4036. Thus, the decision rules (P1)-(N1) can be simply expressed as: Analogously, with the aid of Strategy 2, the thresholds ða 2 ; b 2 ; c 2 Þ of (P2)-(N2) are calculated using ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_39">25</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_41">27</ref>  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_42">P2</ref>)-(N2) are asymmetrical. Hence, there may be inconsistency when we individually use these rules to make the decision.</p><p>According to the discussions shown in Example 3, Proposition 7 is the precondition of Strategies 1 and 2. That is to say, decision rules derived from Strategies 1 and 2 are available, only when Proposition 7 holds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Strategy 3: A composite viewpoint</head><p>With regards to Strategy 1, it merely uses the membership degrees of IFNs to generate decision rules with the positive viewpoint. In the negative viewpoint, Strategy 2 only uses the non-membership degrees of IFNs to deduce decision rules. From Example 3, we find the inconsistency of Strategies 1 and 2. For solving this problem, we need to synchronously consider the membership degrees and the non-membership degrees of IFNs, which is called as a composite viewpoint. In order to compare the expected losses Rða P j½xÞ ¼ ðl P ; m P Þ; Rða B j½xÞ ¼ ðl B ; m B Þ and Rða N j½xÞ ¼ ðl N ; m N Þ, we introduce the score function and the accuracy function of an IFN <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39]</ref>.</p><p>In light of Definition 2, the score functions of the expected losses can be determined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">SðRða P j½xÞÞ ¼ l P À m P ;<label>ð28Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">SðRða B j½xÞÞ ¼ l B À m B ;<label>ð29Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_50">SðRða N j½xÞÞ ¼ l N À m N :<label>ð30Þ</label></formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. The relationship between l E ðkPP Þ and mEðkPPÞ.   Proof. With respect to p E ðk Þ ¼ 0ð ¼ P; B; NÞ and (4), the following results are obtained:</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">HðRða P j½xÞÞ ¼ l P þ m P ;<label>ð31Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">HðRða B j½xÞÞ ¼ l B þ m B ;<label>ð32Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">HðRða N j½xÞÞ ¼ l N þ m N :<label>ð33Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">m E ðk PP Þ ¼ 1 Àl E ðk PP Þ; m E ðk BP Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk BP Þ; m E ðk NP Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk NP Þ; m E ðk PN Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk PN Þ; m E ðk BN Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk BN Þ and m E ðk NN Þ ¼ 1 À l E ðk NN Þ.</formula><p>At this point, we calculate the expected losses: </p><formula xml:id="formula_55">Rða P j½xÞ ¼ ðl P ; m P Þ ¼ ð1 À</formula><formula xml:id="formula_56">where l P þ m P ¼ 1; l B þ m B ¼ 1 and l N þ m N ¼ 1.</formula><p>The accuracy functions of the expected losses are calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">HðRða P j½xÞÞ ¼ l P þ m P ¼ 1; HðRða B j½xÞÞ ¼ l B þ m B ¼ 1 and HðRða N j½xÞÞ ¼ l N þ m N ¼ 1.</formula><p>They show that the accuracy functions of the expected losses do not impact on the comparisons among the expected losses. Considering the prerequisites of  For the rule ðP3Þ, the first condition can be expressed under ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">28</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_50">30</ref>):</p><p>SðRða P j½xÞÞ 6 SðRða B j½xÞÞ</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">() l P À m P 6 l B À m B () l P À ð1 À l P Þ 6 l B À ð1 À l B Þ () l P 6 l B :</formula><p>Analogously, other conditions can be deduced using the similar way. The final decision rules of (P3)-(N3) are: From Proposition 8, decision rules (P1)-(N1) and (P2)-(N2) using Strategies 1 and 2 are special cases of (P3)-(N3). Note that only the hesitation (or uncertainty) membership of each loss presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> is 0, we can adopt Strategies 1 and 2. The applicability of each strategy is summarized in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Decision analysis of IFDTRSs for multi-period decision making</head><p>With the above-mentioned decision analysis of Section 4, it focuses on the single-period decision making and all the original decision information are provided at one period. However, the original argument information may be collected from different periods <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref>, e.g. climate policy <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, multi-period (multi-stage) investment decision making <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref>. Take the Shanghai composite index as an example, the trend is described in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>, it shows the Shanghai composite index of each day from 2013/8/11 to 2014/8/11. When we ascertain the stock investment decision, we not only use the latest data, but also synthetically utilize these historical information. As the results shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref>, every period may have different weight to impact on our decision. To the multi-period decision making issue, it has also attracted the attention of the domain of three-way decisions. For example, Yao and Deng <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref> considered the cost of obtaining the necessary evidence for making a classification decision and proposed a sequential three-way decisions by adding one or more attributes each time. Yao <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref> further presented a granular computing perspective on sequential three-way decisions. Considering the dynamic change of loss functions presented in DTRSs, Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> proposed a dynamic decision-theoretic rough sets with the time. Hu <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> introduced novel dynamic two-way decisions and dynamic three-way decisions based on three-way decisions spaces and three-way decisions with a pair of evaluation functions. Inspired by these works, we extend the IFDTRSs with single-period decision making to adapt the multi-period situation by using Strategy 3 of Section 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Basic notations</head><p>On the basis of the results reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref>, we describe the associated concepts of IFDTRSs with time. Suppose there are q periods, whose weight vector is w ¼ ðwðt 1 Þ; wðt 2 Þ; . . . ; wðt k Þ; . . . ; wðt q ÞÞ T ; wðt k Þ P 0 and t k ðk ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; qÞ, the intuitionistic fuzzy loss function regarding the risk or cost of actions in the different states is given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">4</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">P q k¼1 wðt k Þ ¼ 1. At the period of</formula><p>In </p><formula xml:id="formula_61">l E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞ &lt; l E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞ &lt; l E ðk NP ðt k ÞÞ;<label>ð34Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_62">m E ðk NP ðt k ÞÞ &lt; m E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞ &lt; m E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞ;<label>ð35Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_63">l E ðk NN ðt k ÞÞ &lt; l E ðk BN ðt k ÞÞ &lt; l E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞ;<label>ð36Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_64">m E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞ &lt; m E ðk BN ðt k ÞÞ &lt; m E ðk NN ðt k ÞÞ:<label>ð37Þ</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">The determination for the aggregation of the loss function at all periods</head><p>With the insightful gain from a dynamic intuitionistic fuzzy weighted averaging (DIFWA) operator presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>, we can aggregate the intuitionistic fuzzy loss function matrices at each period by using an integrated intuitionistic fuzzy loss function matrix. The aggregation operation of the loss function is: DIFWA w ðEðk ðt 1 ÞÞ; Eðk ðt 2 ÞÞ; . . . ; Eðk ðt q ÞÞÞ ¼ wðt 1 ÞEðk ðt 1 ÞÞ È wðt 2 ÞEðk ðt 2 ÞÞ È Á Á Á È wðt p ÞEðk ðt q ÞÞ; ð38Þ</p><p>where ¼ P; B; N. Based on the operation of IFNs, the aggregation of the loss function is calculated as:</p><p>DIFWA w ðEðk ðt 1 ÞÞ; Eðk ðt 2 ÞÞ; . . .</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">; Eðk ðt q ÞÞÞ ¼ 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ ; Y q k¼1 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ ! :<label>ð39Þ</label></formula><p>For example, the aggregation result of the loss function Eðk PP Þ is calculated as:</p><p>DIFWA w ðEðk PP ðt 1 ÞÞ; Eðk PP ðt 2 ÞÞ; . . . ;</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">Eðk PP ðt q ÞÞÞ ¼ 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ ; Y q k¼1 m E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ ! :</formula><p>For the sake of convenience, the integrated intuitionistic fuzzy loss function matrix continues to use the notations of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. At this point,</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">Eðk Þ ¼ DIFWA w ðEðk ðt 1 Þ; Eðk ðt 2 Þ; . . . ; Eðk ðt q ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk Þ; m E ðk ÞÞ,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">l E ðk Þ ¼ 1 À Q q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ ; m E ðk Þ ¼ Q q k¼1 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ ð ¼ P; B; NÞ.</formula><p>Proposition 9. For the aggregation of each loss function at all periods, i.e., Eðk Þ ¼ ðl E ðk Þ; m E ðk ÞÞ, we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">l E ðk Þ þ m E ðk Þ 6 1ð ¼ P; B; NÞ.</formula><p>Proof. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(39)</ref>, the elements in the loss function Eðk Þ are denoted as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">l E ðk Þ ¼ 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ ; m E ðk Þ ¼ Y q k¼1 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ :</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>. The trend of Shanghai composite index.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 3</head><p>The applicability of each strategy.</p><p>Strategy</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">l E ðkÞ þ m E ðkÞ ¼ 1 l E ðkÞ þ m E ðkÞ &lt; 1 Strategy 1 p</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strategy 2 p</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strategy 3 p p</head><p>Note: In the table, ¼ P; B; N and p denotes the applicability.</p><p>On the basis of Definition 1 and (4), 0 6 l E ðk ðt k ÞÞ þ m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ 6 1. It implies that: 0 6 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ 6 1 À l E ðk ðt k ÞÞ.</p><p>In consideration of the precondition wðt k Þ P 0, the power functions m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ and ð1 À l E ðk ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ have the following relationship:</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ 6 ð1 À l E ðk ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ :</formula><p>We can deduce the relationship:</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">Q q k¼1 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ 6 Q q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ , i.e., m E ðk Þ 6 1 À l E ðk Þ.</formula><p>Therefore, the statement in Proposition 9 holds. h Propositions 4, 5 demonstrate the variation of the membership degree (non-membership degree) with increasing of their independent variables. Learning from Propositions 4 and 5, one can deduce the following corollaries based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(39)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">Corollary 1. Let l E ðk Þ ¼ 1 À Q q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ , then l E ðk</formula><p>Þ is non-monotonic decreasing with increasing of l E ðk ðt k ÞÞ when the weight vector w ¼ ðwðt 1 Þ; wðt 2 Þ; . . . ; wðt k Þ; . . . ; wðt q ÞÞ T and the losses at the other periods are constantð ¼ P; B; N; k ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; qÞ.</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">Proof. It is similar to Proposition 4. h Corollary 2. Let m E ðk Þ ¼ Q q k¼1 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ , then m E ðk Þ</formula><p>is non-monotonic decreasing with increasing of m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ when the weight vector w ¼ ðwðt 1 Þ; wðt 2 Þ; . . . ; wðt k Þ; . . . ; wðt q ÞÞ T and the losses at the other periods are constant ð ¼ P; B; N; k ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; qÞ.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proof. It is similar to Proposition 5. h</head><p>On the basis of the results reported in Corollaries 1, 2, we also deduce the following relationship between the membership degree (non-membership degree) of each loss and its special cases.</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">Corollary 3. Suppose l E ðk Þ ¼ 1 À Q q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ , we can obtain the relationship: 1 À Q q k¼1 ð1 À l À Þ wðt k Þ ¼ l À 6 l E ðk Þ 6 1 À Q q k¼1 ð1 À l þ Þ wðt k Þ ¼ l þ , where l À ¼ min q k¼1 l E ðk ðt k ÞÞ;l þ ¼ max q k¼1 l E ðk ðt k ÞÞð ¼ P; B; N;k ¼ 1; 2;...;qÞ. Corollary 4. Suppose m E ðk Þ ¼ Q q k¼1 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ ,</formula><p>we can obtain the relationship:</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">Q q k¼1 ðm À Þ wðt k Þ ¼ m À 6 m E ðk Þ 6 Q q k¼1 ðm þ Þ wðt k Þ ¼ m þ , where m À ¼ min q k¼1 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ; m þ ¼ max q k¼1 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞð ¼ P; B; N; k ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; qÞ.</formula><p>From the viewpoint of the multiple source information, Qian et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> introduced the multigranulation into DTRSs and mainly utilized the intersection and union operations to reflect the decision makers' risk attitude <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. In the multi-period decision making, it also can be regarded as multiple source information. Under the pessimistic decision maker, we obtain the aggregation of the loss function as follows.</p><p>DIFPAðEðk ðt 1 ÞÞ; Eðk ðt 2 ÞÞ; . . .</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">; Eðk ðt q ÞÞÞ ¼ [ q k¼1 Eðk ðt k ÞÞ;<label>ð40Þ</label></formula><p>where the pessimistic decision maker may overstate the loss. On the other hand, the aggregation of the loss function under the optimistic decision maker is:</p><p>DIFOAðEðk ðt 1 ÞÞ; Eðk ðt 2 ÞÞ; . . . ; Eðk ðt q ÞÞÞ ¼ \ q k¼1 Eðk ðt k ÞÞ; ð41Þ</p><p>where the optimistic decision maker underestimates the loss. The two aggregations are denoted as</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">E I ðk Þ ¼ DIFPAðEðk ðt 1 Þ; Eðk ðt 2 Þ; . . . ; Eðk ðt q ÞÞ ¼ ðl I E ðk Þ; m I E ðk ÞÞ and E O ðk Þ ¼ DIFOAðEðk ðt 1 Þ; Eðk ðt 2 Þ; . . . ; Eðk ðt q ÞÞ ¼ ðl O E ðk Þ; m O E<label>ðk</label></formula><p>ÞÞ, respectively ð ¼ P; B; NÞ. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref> and the operations of IFNs, the elements in E I ðk Þ can be calculated as follows: In the same way, the elements in E O ðk Þ can be calculated below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">l I E ðk Þ ¼ max q k¼1 l E ðk ðt k ÞÞ; m I E ðk Þ ¼ min q k¼1 m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ:</formula><formula xml:id="formula_81">l O E ðk Þ ¼ min q k¼1 l E ðk ðt k ÞÞ; m O E ðk Þ ¼ max q k¼1</formula><p>m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ:</p><p>In light of Corollaries 3, 4, we have:</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">l O E ðk Þ 6 l E ðk Þ 6 l I E ðk Þ and m I E ðk Þ 6 m E ðk Þ 6 m O E ðk Þ.</formula><p>Proposition 10. Based on (5) and Definition 3, the aggregation loss function with the operators DIFWA, DIFPA and DIFOA imply the following relationship:</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">E O ðk Þ &lt; Eðk Þ &lt; E I ðk Þ;<label>ð42Þ</label></formula><p>where ¼ P; B; N. In the following, we use an example to illustrate Proposition 10.</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">Proof. Due to l O E ðk Þ 6 l E ðk Þ 6 l I E ðk Þ and m I E ðk Þ 6 m E ðk Þ 6 m O E ðk Þ,</formula><p>Example 4. Let E be an intuitionistic fuzzy concept of loss. Suppose that there are 3 periods and the corresponding weight vector is w ¼ ðwðt 1 Þ; wðt 2 Þ; wðt 3 ÞÞ T ¼ ð0:2; 0:3; 0:5Þ T . In view of the loss functions of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">4</ref> and<ref type="table">(</ref> <ref type="formula">7</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">10</ref>), we evaluate their values, respectively. The values of the loss functions at the different period are assigned in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">5</ref>.</p><p>According to Definition 2, we compute the aggregations of loss functions with the operators DIFWA, DIFPA and DIFOA. The results are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">6</ref>.</p><p>In additions, the scores of the loss functions presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">6</ref> are described in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6</ref>. From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6</ref>, the relationships among the scores of the loss functions with different aggregation operations validates the statement of Proposition 10.</p><p>With respect to the results presented in Proposition 10 and Example 4, we find the score of loss function with DIFWA is between DIFPA and DIFOA. The reason is DIFWA involves the importance of each period. Meanwhile, DIFPA and DIFOA merely consider some special cases. In order to synthetically utilize the historical information, DIFWA is more suitable for the following decision analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.">Decision rules</head><p>With the aid of the aggregation operation DIFWA, we discuss the comparisons among the aggregation results of the loss functions in the following proposition.</p><p>Proposition 11. Under the conditions (34)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref>, the relationships among the aggregation results of the loss functions using <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref> comply with (7)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</p><p>Proof. For the loss functions Eðk PP Þ and Eðk BP Þ, their elements can be described as: At the period t k ðk ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; qÞ, we can obtain the following relationships based on (34), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_62">35</ref>): 1 À l E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞ &gt; 1 À l E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞ and m E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞ &lt; m E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞ. In addition, we further deduce the following relationships:</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">l E ðk PP Þ ¼ 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ ; l E ðk BP Þ ¼ 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ ; m E ðk PP Þ ¼ Y q k¼1 m E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ ; m E ðk BP Þ ¼ Y q k¼1 m E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ :</formula><formula xml:id="formula_86">ð1 À l E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ &gt; ð1 À l E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ and m E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ &lt; m E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ .</formula><p>Considering all periods, we finally get the relationships:</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ &lt; 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k Þ ; Y q k¼1 m E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ &lt; Y q k¼1 m E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞ wðt k Þ : Hence, l E ðk PP Þ &lt; l E ðk BP Þ and m E ðk BP Þ &lt; m E ðk PP Þ.</formula><p>Analogously, we can deduce the other relationships presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</p><p>The statement in Proposition 10 holds. h Proposition 12. In light of (39), the expected losses Rða i j½xÞði ¼ P; B; NÞ in the multi-period decision making are reexpressed as: </p><formula xml:id="formula_88">Rða P j½xÞ ¼ 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk</formula><p>On account of Proposition 11, we draw lessons from Proposition 6 and summary Proposition 13.</p><p>Proposition 13. Under (34)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_64">37</ref>), the relationships among Rða P j½xÞ; Rða B j½xÞ and Rða N j½xÞ depend on the values of loss functions in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>, which are uncertain and need to be further compared with each other.</p><p>From the results presented in Proposition 13, the decision rules (P)-(N) need to be further investigated. In light of Definition 2, the scores of the expected losses are determined as follows: </p><p>Meanwhile, the accuracies of the expected losses can also be computed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">HðRða P j½xÞÞ ¼ 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ þ Y q k¼1 ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ ;<label>ð49Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_92">HðRða B j½xÞÞ ¼ 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ þ Y q k¼1 ðm E ðk BP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ ;<label>ð50Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_93">HðRða N j½xÞÞ ¼ 1 À Y q k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk NP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk NN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ þ Y q k¼1</formula><p>ðm E ðk NP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ :</p><p>Finally, we design an algorithm to deduce three-way decisions for multi-period decision making as follows:</p><p>Step 1: Determine the weight vector w ¼ ðwðt 1 Þ; wðt 2 Þ; . . . ; wðt k Þ; . . . ; wðt q ÞÞ T for q periods, the concept of C in accordance with the decision problem and the conditional probability of the object belonging to C, i.e., PrðCj½xÞ.</p><p>Step 2: In light of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_61">34</ref>)- <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">4</ref>, we collect the loss function information at each period, respectively.</p><p>Step 3: Using the operation DIFWA, we calculate the scores and the accuracies of the expected losses based on ( <ref type="formula">46</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_94">51</ref>), i.e., SðRða P j½xÞÞ; SðRða B j½xÞÞ; SðRða N j½xÞÞ; HðRða P j½xÞÞ; HðRða B j½xÞÞ; HðRða N j½xÞÞ.</p><p>Step 4: Comparing the scores of the expected losses, we select the expected loss with the minimum score. If the number of the expected loss with the minimum score is equal to 1, the action of x depends on the action with the minimum score, go to Step 7. Otherwise, go to Step 5.</p><p>Step 5: For the expected losses with the same minimum score, we continue to compare their accuracies. If the number of the expected loss with the minimum accuracy is equal to 1, the action of x depends on the corresponding action with the minimum accuracy and go to Step 7. Otherwise, go to Step 6.</p><p>Step 6: In light of the preference of the decision maker to POSðCÞ; BNDðCÞ and NEGðCÞ, we select the more preference from the actions with the minimum score of expected losses.</p><p>Step 7: End. With the above-mentioned algorithm, Step 6 is associated with the preference of the decision maker to POSðCÞ; BNDðCÞ and NEGðCÞ. For example, if the decision maker has a preference order POSðCÞ 1 BNDðCÞ 1 NEGðCÞ, it means that the alternatives classified into POSðCÞ dominate into BNDðCÞ, and the alternatives into both of these regions dominate into NEGðCÞ <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. If BNDðCÞ and NEGðCÞ simultaneously hold in Step 6, we will finally select the action BNDðCÞ.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">An illustrative example</head><p>In this section, we use three-way decisions with IFDTRSs to support the investment decisions of agroecological regions of Hubei Province and illustrate the decision process of the novel three-way decisions. For the agroecological regions of Hubei Province, Xu <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>  With respect to the limited resources, we need to make a choice under the intuitionistic fuzzy environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. On the one hand, we want to rightly allocate resource, especially for the backward area <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. On the other hand, we also consider that some possible decision results of the selection may result in different losses. Hence, the investment decisions of agroecological regions of Hubei Province are consistent with three-way decisions. According to the decision strategies of three-way decisions, we have the acceptance decision, the rejection decision and the non-commitment decision <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57]</ref>. In order to evaluate these agroecological regions, a committee has been set up to provide assessment information on x i ði ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; 7Þ <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>.</p><p>For the investment decisions of agroecological regions of Hubei Province, we have two states X ¼ fC; :Cg indicating that the agroecological region is a backward area or not. The set of actions for the new agroecological region x i ði ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; 7Þ is given by A ¼ fa P ; a B ; a N g, where a P ; a B , and a N represent the investment, need for further investigation and not to make an investment, respectively. The committee evaluates the performance of agroecological regions in the years 2004-2006. Let t 1 ; t 2 ; t 3 denote the year ''2004'', the year ''2005'' and the year ''2006'', respectively. There are 3 periods and the corresponding weight vector w ¼ ðwðt 1 Þ; wðt 2 Þ; wðt 3 ÞÞ T is ð0:2; 0:3; 0:5Þ T . Thus, we use the algorithm of decision analysis based on IFDTRSs for multi-period decision making.</p><p>Step 1: In this example, we assume that the conditional probability of each alternative region to C is shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_18">7</ref>.</p><p>Step 2: The values of the loss functions at the different period are listed in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_19">8</ref><ref type="table" target="#tab_16">9</ref><ref type="table" target="#tab_17">10</ref>.</p><p>Step 3: Based on ( <ref type="formula">46</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_94">51</ref>), we calculate the scores of the expected losses and the accuracies of the expected losses for each region. The results are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">7</ref>.</p><p>In order to illustrate the calculation procedure, we take the region x 3 as an example. In light of the results presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_18">7</ref>, the conditional probability PrðCj½x 3 Þ is 0.4. Hence, Prð:Cj½x 3 Þ ¼ 0:6. For the region x 3 , the score of Rða P j½x 3 is calculated based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref>    </p><formula xml:id="formula_95">¼ 1 À Y 3 k¼1 ð1 À l E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ 0:4wðt k Þ ð1 À l E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞÞ 0:6wðt k Þ À Y 3 k¼1 ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ 0:4wðt k Þ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ 0:6wðt k Þ ¼ 0:4888:</formula><formula xml:id="formula_96">0:4wðt k Þ ð1 À l E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞÞ 0:6wðt k Þ þ Y 3</formula><p>k¼1 ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ 0:4wðt k Þ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ 0:6wðt k Þ ¼ 0:8687:</p><p>Similarly, the accuracies of other expected losses are calculated: HðRða B j½x 3 ÞÞ ¼ 0:9404 and HðRða N j½x 3 ÞÞ ¼ 0:8913.</p><p>Step 4: According to the results reported in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">7</ref>, we find each region has just one minimum score. As the number of the expected loss with the minimum score is equal to 1, the action of each region depends on the action with its minimum score. The decision results of each region are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_21">11</ref>.</p><p>As we state above, the scores of the expected losses of x 3 are calculated: SðRða P j½x 3 ÞÞ ¼ 0:4888; SðRða B j½x 3 ÞÞ ¼ 0:1228 and SðRða N j½x 3 ÞÞ ¼ 0:2030. Following Step 4, we compare the scores of the expected losses and find that SðRða B j½xÞÞ ¼ 0:1228 is minimum. At this point, the number of the expected loss with the minimum score is equal to 1. Hence, we classify the region x 3 into BNDðCÞ and take the non-commitment decision (further investigation), namely, a B . According to the decision results of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_21">11</ref>, the committee believes that x 1 and x 4 need to be invested immediately, while x 2 and x 7 should not be selected for investment. In addition, the committee also suggest x 3 ; x 5 and x 6 need to be further investigated.  In order to validate the effectiveness of IFDTRSs for multi-period decision making, we compare the decision results based on IFDTRSs for single-period decision making in the year 2005. In light of decision rules (P3)-(N3), we directly provide the investment decision of each region in the year 2005. The decision results are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_20">12</ref>.</p><p>From Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_20">12</ref>, the committee believes that x 1 ; x 4 ; x 5 and x 6 need to be invested immediately, while x 2 ; x 3 and x 7 should not be selected for investment. The decision results of x 3 ; x 5 and x 6 in the year 2005 are different from Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_21">11</ref>. The reason is that most of the values of the loss functions in the year 2005 are different from other years. Compared with the results of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_20">12</ref>, the results of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_21">11</ref> synthetically utilize the historical information of three periods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Conclusions</head><p>In this paper, we propose a naive model of IFDTRSs based on DTRSs and IFNs. Then, we successively derive three-way decisions from the single period decision making to the multi-period situation. Meanwhile, we elaborate their relevant properties. With respect to the single-period decision making, we design three strategies and obtain their applicabilities. Under the multi-period scenarios, we analyze three aggregation operations of IFDTRSs, i.e., DIFWA, DIFPA and DIFOA. Finally, we determine DIFWA as a suitable aggregation operation for the loss function at all periods and design an algorithm for deriving three-way decisions. This study considers the uncertainty format of IFSs and extends the range of applications of DTRSs. Our future researches will focus on studying generalization models based on the IFDTRSs model.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. The variation of l P with increasing values of l E ðkPPÞ and l E ðkPNÞ.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,56.69,378.48,425.54,294.63" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>ðP1Þ</head><label></label><figDesc>If l P 6 l B and l P 6 l N ; decide x 2 POSðCÞ; ðB1Þ If l B 6 l P and l B 6 l N ; decide x 2 BNDðCÞ; ðN1Þ If l N 6 l P and l N 6 l B ; decide x 2 NEGðCÞ;</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The variation of mP with increasing values of mEðkPPÞ and mEðkPNÞ.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,61.00,54.71,425.28,297.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>If PrðCj½xÞ P a 1 and</head><label>1</label><figDesc>PrðCj½xÞ P c 1 ; decide x 2 POSðCÞ; ðB1Þ If PrðCj½xÞ 6 a 1 and PrðCj½xÞ P b 1 ; decide x 2 BNDðCÞ; ðN1Þ If PrðCj½xÞ 6 b 1 and PrðCj½xÞ 6 c 1 ; decide x 2 NEGðCÞ: From the positive viewpoint, we finally determine the decision rule of the object x by comparing the conditional probability PrðCj½xÞ and the thresholds ða 1 ; b 1 ; c 1 Þ.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>PrðCj½xÞ 6 a 2 andProposition 7 .</head><label>27</label><figDesc>PrðCj½xÞ P b 2 ; decide x 2 BNDðCÞ; ðN2Þ If PrðCj½xÞ 6 b 2 and PrðCj½xÞ 6 c 2 ; decide x 2 NEGðCÞ;with respect to the negative viewpoint, we can determine the decision rule of the object x by comparing the conditional probability PrðCj½xÞ and the thresholds ða 2 ; b 2 ; c 2 Þ.Comparing decision rules (P1)-(N1) with (P2)-(N2), the following proposition is obtained. If 8p E ðk Þ ¼ 0 is true ð ¼ P; B; NÞ, we obtain that the decision rules (P2)-(N2) derived from the negative viewpoint are consistent with (P1)-(N1) of the positive viewpoint.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>presents an uncertainty during the evaluation of Eðk PP Þ. It may lead to an inconsistency between (P1)-(N1) and (P2)-(N2). For clarity, we employ Example 3 to illustrate the inconsistency.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>ðP1Þ</head><label></label><figDesc>If PrðCj½xÞ P 0:7198; decide x 2 POSðCÞ; ðB1Þ If 0:2480 &lt; PrðCj½xÞ &lt; 0:7198; decide x 2 BNDðCÞ; ðN1Þ If PrðCj½xÞ 6 0:2480; decide x 2 NEGðCÞ:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>): a 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>¼ 0:8465; b 2 ¼ 0:2626; c 2 ¼ 0:4862. Hence, the decision rules (P2)-(N2) can be simply expressed as: ðP2Þ If PrðCj½xÞ P 0:8465; decide x 2 POSðCÞ; ðB2Þ If 0:2626 &lt; PrðCj½xÞ &lt; 0:8465; decide x 2 BNDðCÞ; ðN2Þ If PrðCj½xÞ 6 0:2626; decide x 2 NEGðCÞ: Furthermore, we visualize these decision rules (P1)-(N1) and (P2)-(N2) in Fig. 4. In Fig. 4, the decision rules (P1)-(N1) correspond to the figure above the horizontal line and the decision rules (P2)-(N2) are associated with the figure under the horizontal line. From Fig. 4, we find the decision rules (P1)-(N1) and (</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>D</head><label></label><figDesc>. Liang, D. Liu / Information Sciences 300 (2015) 28-48 where l P ¼ 1 À ð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; l B ¼ 1 À ð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; l N ¼ 1 À ð1 Àl E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; m P ¼ ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; m B ¼ ðm E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ and m N ¼ ðm E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ . Meanwhile, the accuracy functions of the expected losses can also be computed:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>ForProposition 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>decision rules (P3)-(N3), they involve the hesitation situations of IFNs. Inspired by Proposition 7, we discuss the relationship between decision rules (P3)-(N3) and decision rules (P1)-(N1) and (P2)-(N2) using Strategies 1 and 2 based on the hesitations of loss functionsp E ðk Þð ¼ P; B; NÞ. If 8p E ðk Þ ¼ 0 is true ð ¼ P; B; NÞ, the decision rules (P3)-(N3) derived from the composite viewpoint are consistent with (P1)-(N1) and (P2)-(N2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. The inconsistency between (P1)-(N1) and (P2)-(N2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>If l P 6 l</head><label>6</label><figDesc>B and l P 6 l N ; decide x 2 POSðCÞ; ðB3Þ If l B 6 l P and l B 6 l N ; decide x 2 BNDðCÞ; ðN3Þ If l N 6 l P and l N 6 l B ; decide x 2 NEGðCÞ: Hence, the decision rules (P3)-(N3) derived from the composite viewpoint are consistent with (P1)-(N1). With the aid of Proposition 7, the statement in Proposition 8 holds. h</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>they ensure that SðE O ðk ÞÞ &lt; SðEðk ÞÞ &lt; SðE I ðk ÞÞ. With regards to Definition 3, the statement in Proposition 10 holds. h</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>listed seven agroecological regions: (1) x 1 : Wuhan-Ezhou-Huanggang; (2) x 2 : Northeast of Hubei; (3) x 3 : Southeast of Hubei; (4) x 4 : Jianghan region; (5) x 5 : North of Hubei; (6) x 6 : Northwest of Hubei; (7) x 7 : Southwest of Hubei.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. The scores and the accuracies of the expected losses for each region with multi-periods.</figDesc><graphic coords="19,75.18,54.71,396.95,228.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>P j½xÞ ¼ Eðk PP ÞPrðCj½xÞ È Eðk PN ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ;</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>À ð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ Þ È ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ; ð16Þ Rða B j½xÞ ¼ ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ Þ È ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ; ð17Þ Rða N j½xÞ ¼ ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ Þ È ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ: ð18Þ Proposition 2. Based on (16)-(18), the expected losses Rða j½xÞð ¼ P; B; NÞ are re-expressed as: Rða P j½xÞ ¼ ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ; ð19Þ Rða B j½xÞ ¼ ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ; ð20Þ Rða N j½xÞ ¼ ð1 À ð1 À l E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ:</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>P ¼ ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; m B ¼ ðm E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ and m N ¼ ðm E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ .</figDesc><table><row><cell>Under conditions of (8) and (10), we simplify the decision rules ðP2Þ-ðN2Þ. For the rule ðP2Þ, the first condition can be</cell></row><row><cell>expressed as:</cell></row></table><note><p><p>4.2. Strategy 2: A negative viewpoint</p>For decision rules (P)-(N), the expected losses are Rða P j½xÞ ¼ ðl P ; m P Þ; Rða B j½xÞ ¼ ðl B ; m B Þ and Rða N j½xÞ ¼ ðl N ; m N Þ. In the light of the negative viewpoint, we straightly adopt the non-membership degrees of IFNs to analyze decision rules (P)-(N). Under this situation, the non-membership degrees of the expected losses have opposite directions with the expected losses. Following this scenario, decision rules (P)-(N) can be re-expressed as: ðP2Þ If m P P m B and m P P m N ; decide x 2 POSðCÞ; ðB2Þ If m B P m P and m B P m N ; decide x 2 BNDðCÞ; ðN2Þ If m N P m P and m N P m B ; decide x 2 NEGðCÞ; where m m P P m B () ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ P ðm E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ () logððm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ P logððm E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ () PrðCj½xÞ logðm E ðk PP ÞÞ þ Prð:Cj½xÞ logðl E ðk PN ÞÞ P PrðCj½xÞ logðm E ðk BP ÞÞ þ Prð:Cj½xÞ logðm E ðk BN ÞÞ () PrðCj½xÞ P log</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ P ðm E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ</figDesc><table /><note><p>() PrðCj½xÞ P log</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ðm E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ P ðm E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ</figDesc><table /><note><p>() PrðCj½xÞ P log</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>For the rule ðPÞ, the first condition Rða P j½xÞ 6 Rða B j½xÞ based on Definition 3 implies the following prerequisites: (C1) SðRða P j½xÞÞ &lt; SðRða B j½xÞÞ or (C2) SðRða P j½xÞÞ ¼ SðRða B j½xÞÞ ^HðRða P j½xÞÞ 6 HðRða B j½xÞÞ. In the same way, the prerequisites for the second condition Rða P j½xÞ 6 Rða N j½xÞ of rule ðPÞ are: (C3) SðRða P j½xÞÞ &lt; SðRða N j½xÞÞ or (C4) SðRða P j½xÞÞ ¼ SðRða N j½xÞÞ ^HðRða P j½xÞÞ 6 HðRða N j½xÞÞ. The first condition of rule ðBÞ is the converse of the first condition of rule ðPÞ. Its prerequisites are: (C5) SðRða B j½xÞÞ &lt; SðRða P j½xÞÞ or (C6) SðRða B j½xÞÞ ¼ SðRða P j½xÞÞ ^HðRða B j½xÞÞ 6 HðRða P j½xÞÞ. For the second condition of rule ðBÞ, we have: (C7) SðRða B j½xÞÞ &lt; SðRða N j½xÞÞ or (C8) SðRða B j½xÞÞ ¼ SðRða N j½xÞÞ ^HðRða B j½xÞÞ 6 HðRða N j½xÞÞ. The first condition of rule ðNÞ is the converse of the second condition of rule ðPÞ and the second condition of rule ðNÞ is the converse of the second condition of rule ðBÞ. For Rða N j½xÞ 6 Rða P j½xÞ, its prerequisites are:</figDesc><table><row><cell>ðP3Þ</cell><cell>If ððC1Þ _ ðC2ÞÞ ^ððC3Þ _ ðC4ÞÞ; decide x 2 POSðCÞ;</cell></row><row><cell>ðB3Þ</cell><cell>If ððC5Þ _ ðC6ÞÞ ^ððC7Þ _ ðC8ÞÞ; decide x 2 BNDðCÞ;</cell></row><row><cell>ðN3Þ</cell><cell>If ððC9Þ _ ðC10ÞÞ ^ððC11Þ _ ðC12ÞÞ; decide x 2 NEGðCÞ:</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p><p>(C9) SðRða N j½xÞÞ &lt; SðRða P j½xÞÞ or (C10) SðRða N j½xÞÞ ¼ SðRða P j½xÞÞ ^HðRða N j½xÞÞ 6 HðRða P j½xÞÞ. For Rða N j½xÞ 6 Rða B j½xÞ, its prerequisites are: (C11) SðRða N j½xÞÞ &lt; SðRða B j½xÞÞ or (C12) SðRða N j½xÞÞ ¼ SðRða B j½xÞÞ ^HðRða N j½xÞÞ 6 HðRða B j½xÞÞ. Therefore, the prerequisites of decision rules (P)-(N) are listed in Table</p>2</p>. On the basis of Table</p>2</p>, decision rules (P)-(N) can be re-expressed as:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ; Rða B j½xÞ ¼ ðl B ; m B Þ ¼ ð1 À ðm E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk BP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ; Rða N j½xÞ ¼ ðl N ; m N Þ ¼ ð1 À ðm E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ ; ðm E ðk NP ÞÞ PrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ Prð:Cj½xÞ Þ;</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p>, the decision rules (P3)-(N3) can be simply expressed as: ðP3Þ If SðRða P j½xÞÞ 6 SðRða B j½xÞÞ and SðRða P j½xÞÞ 6 SðRða N j½xÞÞ; decide x 2 POSðCÞ; ðB3Þ If SðRða B j½xÞÞ 6 SðRða P j½xÞÞ and SðRða B j½xÞÞ 6 SðRða N j½xÞÞ; decide x 2 BNDðCÞ; ðN3Þ If SðRða N j½xÞÞ 6 SðRða P j½xÞÞ and SðRða N j½xÞÞ 6 SðRða B j½xÞÞ; decide x 2 NEGðCÞ:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The prerequisites of decision rules (P)-(N).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Decision rule</cell><cell>ðC1Þ</cell><cell>ð C2Þ</cell><cell>ð C3Þ</cell><cell>ð C4Þ</cell></row><row><cell>POS(C)</cell><cell>p p</cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell><cell>p</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ðC5Þ</cell><cell>ð C6Þ</cell><cell>ð C7Þ</cell><cell>ð C8Þ</cell></row><row><cell>BND(C)</cell><cell>p p</cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell><cell>p</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ðC9Þ</cell><cell>ð C10Þ</cell><cell>ð C11Þ</cell><cell>ð C12Þ</cell></row><row><cell>NEG(C)</cell><cell>p p</cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell><cell>p</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell><cell></cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell>Note: In the table,</cell><cell>p denotes the prerequisites of decision rules.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 4 ,</head><label>4</label><figDesc>l E ðk ðt k ÞÞ 2 ½0; 1; m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ 2 ½0; 1ð ¼ P; B; NÞ and 0 6 l E ðk ðt k ÞÞ þ m E ðk ðt k ÞÞ 6 1. Comparing with Table1, each loss function in Table4is associated with time. For each loss function, it collects an IFN at each period, i.e., Eðk ðt k ÞÞð ¼ P; B; NÞ. We also consider a reasonable kind of losses at the period t k :</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>The intuitionistic fuzzy loss function matrix regarding the risk or cost of actions in the different states with the period t k . Eðk PP ðt k ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞ; m E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ Eðk PN ðt k ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞ; m E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞÞ a B Eðk BP ðt k ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞ; m E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞÞ Eðk BN ðt k ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk BN ðt k ÞÞ; m E ðk BN ðt k ÞÞÞ a N Eðk NP ðt k ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk NP ðt k ÞÞ; m E ðk NP ðt k ÞÞÞ Eðk NN ðt k ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk NN ðt k ÞÞ; m E ðk NN ðt k ÞÞÞ</figDesc><table><row><cell>t k</cell><cell>CðPÞ</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>The values of the losses at the different period.</figDesc><table><row><cell>k</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Eðk PP ðt k ÞÞ</cell><cell>(0, 1)</cell><cell>(0, 0.9)</cell><cell>(0.01, 0.95)</cell></row><row><cell>Eðk BP ðt k ÞÞ</cell><cell>(0.3, 0.7)</cell><cell>(0.4, 0.5)</cell><cell>(0.25, 0.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Eðk NP ðt k ÞÞ</cell><cell>(0.9, 0.1)</cell><cell>(0.85, 0.1)</cell><cell>(0.8, 0.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Eðk PN ðt k ÞÞ</cell><cell>(0.8, 0.1)</cell><cell>(0.85, 0.1)</cell><cell>(0.9, 0.05)</cell></row><row><cell>Eðk BN ðt k ÞÞ</cell><cell>(0.5, 0.4)</cell><cell>(0.7, 0.3)</cell><cell>(0.45, 0.4)</cell></row><row><cell>Eðk NN ðt k ÞÞ</cell><cell>(0.05, 0.8)</cell><cell>(0.02, 0.75)</cell><cell>(0, 0.8)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>PP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ ; ðk PP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ ; ðk BP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ E ðk NP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk NN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ ; ðk NP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Y q</cell><cell cols="2">ðm E !</cell><cell>; ð43Þ</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>k¼1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rða B j½xÞ ¼ 1 À</cell><cell>Y q</cell><cell cols="3">ð1 À l Y q</cell><cell>ðm E !</cell><cell>; ð44Þ</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>k¼1</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">k¼1</cell></row><row><cell>Rða N j½xÞ ¼ 1 À</cell><cell cols="2">Y q</cell><cell cols="3">ð1 À l Y q</cell><cell>ðm E</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">k¼1</cell><cell cols="3">k¼1</cell></row></table><note><p><p>!</p>:</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>The aggregations of the losses with the operators DIFWA, DIFPA and DIFOA. E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ À Y q k¼1 ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ ; ð46Þ E ðk BP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk BN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ ðk BP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk BN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ ; ð47Þ E ðk NP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk NN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ ðk NP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk NN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ :</figDesc><table><row><cell>k</cell><cell>k PP</cell><cell>k BP</cell><cell>k NP</cell><cell>k PN</cell><cell>k BN</cell><cell>k NN</cell></row><row><cell>E O ðkÞ</cell><cell>(0, 1)</cell><cell>(0.25, 0.7)</cell><cell>(0.8, 0.1)</cell><cell>(0.8, 0.1)</cell><cell>(0.45, 0.4)</cell><cell>(0, 0.8)</cell></row><row><cell>EðkÞ</cell><cell>(0.0050, 0.9444)</cell><cell>(0.3082, 0.6328)</cell><cell>(0.8403, 0.1000)</cell><cell>(0.8703, 0.0707)</cell><cell>(0.5501, 0.3669)</cell><cell>(0.0162, 0.7847)</cell></row><row><cell>E I ðkÞ</cell><cell>(0.01, 0.9)</cell><cell>(0.4, 0.5)</cell><cell>(0.9, 0.1)</cell><cell>(0.9, 0.05)</cell><cell>(0.7, 0.3)</cell><cell>(0.05, 0.75)</cell></row></table><note><p>Fig. 6. The scores of the losses with the operators DIFWA, DIFPA and DIFOA.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, i.e., E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ð1 À l E ðk PN ðt k ÞÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ À</figDesc><table><row><cell>SðRða P j½x 3 ÞÞ ¼ 1 À</cell><cell>Y 3</cell><cell>ð1 À l Y 3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>k¼1</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>k¼1 ðm E ðk PP ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrðCj½xÞ ðm E ðk PN ÞÞ wðt k ÞPrð:Cj½xÞ</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Table 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>The intuitionistic fuzzy loss function matrix regarding the risk or cost of actions in the different states with the period t2. Eðk PP ðt 2 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk PP ðt 2 ÞÞ; m E ðk PP ðt 2 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0; 0:6Þ Eðk PN ðt 2 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk PN ðt 2 ÞÞ; m E ðk PN ðt 2 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:75; 0:1Þ a B Eðk BP ðt 2 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk BP ðt 2 ÞÞ; m E ðk BP ðt 2 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:8; 0:2Þ Eðk BN ðt 2 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk BN ðt 2 ÞÞ; m E ðk BN ðt 2 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:7; 0:3Þ a N Eðk NP ðt 2 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk NP ðt 2 ÞÞ; m E ðk NP ðt 2 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:9; 0:1Þ Eðk NN ðt 2 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk NN ðt 2 ÞÞ; m E ðk NN ðt 2 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:02; 0:75Þ</figDesc><table><row><cell>t 2</cell><cell>CðPÞ</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Table 10</head><label>10</label><figDesc>The intuitionistic fuzzy loss function matrix regarding the risk or cost of actions in the different states with the period t3. Eðk PP ðt 3 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk PP ðt 3 ÞÞ; m E ðk PP ðt 3 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:01; 0:95Þ Eðk PN ðt 3 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk PN ðt 3 ÞÞ; m E ðk PN ðt 3 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:9; 0:05Þ a B Eðk BP ðt 3 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk BP ðt 3 ÞÞ; m E ðk BP ðt 3 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:25; 0:7Þ Eðk BN ðt 3 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk BN ðt 3 ÞÞ; m E ðk BN ðt 3 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:45; 0:4Þ a N Eðk NP ðt 3 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk NP ðt 3 ÞÞ; m E ðk NP ðt 3 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:8; 0:1Þ Eðk NN ðt 3 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk NN ðt 3 ÞÞ; m E ðk NN ðt 3 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0; 0:8Þ</figDesc><table><row><cell>t 3</cell><cell>CðPÞ</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>Table 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>The conditional probability of each region to C.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Region</cell><cell>x 1</cell><cell>x 2</cell><cell>x 3</cell><cell>x 4</cell><cell>x 5</cell><cell>x 6</cell><cell>x 7</cell></row><row><cell>PrðCj½xÞ</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0.4</cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell>0.6</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>0.3</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Table 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>The intuitionistic fuzzy loss function matrix regarding the risk or cost of actions in the different states with the period t1. Eðk PP ðt 1 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk PP ðt 1 ÞÞ; m E ðk PP ðt 1 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0; 1Þ Eðk PN ðt 1 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk PN ðt 1 ÞÞ; m E ðk PN ðt 1 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:8; 0:1Þ a B Eðk BP ðt 1 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk BP ðt 1 ÞÞ; m E ðk BP ðt 1 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:3; 0:7Þ Eðk BN ðt 1 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk BN ðt 1 ÞÞ; m E ðk BN ðt 1 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:5; 0:4Þ a N Eðk NP ðt 1 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk NP ðt 1 ÞÞ; m E ðk NP ðt 1 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:9; 0:1Þ Eðk NN ðt 1 ÞÞ ¼ ðl E ðk NN ðt 1 ÞÞ; m E ðk NN ðt 1 ÞÞÞ ¼ ð0:05; 0:8Þ Analogously, the scores of other expected losses are calculated: SðRða B j½x 3 ÞÞ ¼ 0:1228 and SðRða N j½x 3 ÞÞ ¼ 0:2030. The accuracy of Rða P j½x 3 is computed based on (49), i.e., E ðk PP ðt k ÞÞÞ</figDesc><table><row><cell>t 1</cell><cell>CðPÞ</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>Table 12</head><label>12</label><figDesc>The decision results of agroecological regions of Hubei Province in the year 2005.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Region</cell><cell>x 1</cell><cell>x 2</cell><cell>x 3</cell><cell>x 4</cell><cell>x 5</cell><cell>x 6</cell><cell>x 7</cell></row><row><cell>The investment decision</cell><cell>POSðCÞ</cell><cell>NEGðCÞ</cell><cell>NEGðCÞ</cell><cell>POSðCÞ</cell><cell>POSðCÞ</cell><cell>POSðCÞ</cell><cell>NEGðCÞ</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head>Table 11</head><label>11</label><figDesc>The decision results of agroecological regions of Hubei Province with multi-periods.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Region</cell><cell>The minimum score</cell><cell>The decision action</cell><cell>The investment decision</cell></row><row><cell>x 1</cell><cell>SðRða P j½x 1 ÞÞ</cell><cell>a P</cell><cell>POSðCÞ</cell></row><row><cell>x 2</cell><cell>SðRða N j½x 2 ÞÞ</cell><cell>a N</cell><cell>NEGðCÞ</cell></row><row><cell>x 3</cell><cell>SðRða B j½x 3 ÞÞ</cell><cell>a B</cell><cell>BNDðCÞ</cell></row><row><cell>x 4</cell><cell>SðRða P j½x 4 ÞÞ</cell><cell>a P</cell><cell>POSðCÞ</cell></row><row><cell>x 5</cell><cell>SðRða B j½x 5 ÞÞ</cell><cell>a B</cell><cell>BNDðCÞ</cell></row><row><cell>x 6</cell><cell>SðRða B j½x 6 ÞÞ</cell><cell>a B</cell><cell>BNDðCÞ</cell></row><row><cell>x 7</cell><cell>SðRða N j½x 7 ÞÞ</cell><cell>a N</cell><cell>NEGðCÞ</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>D. Liang, D. Liu / Information Sciences 300 (2015) 28-48</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>D. Liang, D. Liu / Information Sciences 300 (2015) </p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors wish to thank the anonymous reviewers for their constructive comments on this study. The authors are grateful to Agbodah Kobina at University of Electronic Science and Technology of China for his suggestions and comments. This work is partially supported by the National Science Foundation of China (Nos. 71401026, 71432003, 71201133, 71201076, 71490722), the Youth Social Science Foundation of the Chinese Education Commission (No. 11YJC630127), the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities of China (No. SWJTU12CX117) and the Research Fund for the Doctoral Program of Higher Education of China (No. 20120184120028).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intuitionistic fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Atanassov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing uncertainties of probabilistic rough set regions with game-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Azam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A biparametric similarity measure on intuitionistic fuzzy sets with applications to pattern recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Boran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Akay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">255</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new measure using intuitionistic fuzzy set theory and its application to edge detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chaira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Soft Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="919" to="927" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bivariate models of optimism and pessimism in multi-criteria decision-making based on intuitionistic fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2139" to="2165" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Duda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Pattern classification and scene analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An information-theoretic interpretation of thresholds in probabilistic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">RSKT 2012</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7414</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="378" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decision-theoretic three-way approximations of fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="702" to="715" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian decision theory for dominance-based rough set approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Slowinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">LNAI</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4481</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007. 2007</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-way decisions space and three-way decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intuitionistic fuzzy multigranulation rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">277</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimum cost attribute reduction in decision-theoretic rough set models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">219</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="167" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On an optimization representation of decision-theoretic rough set model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Swan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">An information filtering model on the web and its application in JobAgent</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="296" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiattribute decision making models and methods using intuitionistic fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Syst. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchical rough decision theoretic framework for text classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Miao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 9th IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Informatics</title>
		<meeting>the 9th IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Informatics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="484" to="489" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk decision making based on decision-theoretic rough set: a three-way view decision model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cost-sensitive classification based on decision-theoretic rough set model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">RSKT 2012</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7414</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="388" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-monotonic attribute reduction in decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fundam. Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Triangular fuzzy decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pedrycz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1087" to="1106" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel risk decision-making based on decision-theoretic rough sets under hesitant fuzzy information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TFUZZ.2014.2310495</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/TFUZZ.2014.2310495" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic studies on three-way decisions with interval-valued decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rough cluster quality index based on decision theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lingras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Miao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Knowl. Data Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1014" to="1026" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-criteria decision-making methods based on intuitionistic fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-way investment decisions with decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic model criteria with decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ruan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3709" to="3722" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decision-theoretic rough sets with probabilistic distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Rough Sets and Knowledge Technology</title>
		<meeting>the 7th International Conference on Rough Sets and Knowledge Technology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7414</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="398" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-way government decision analysis with decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Uncertainty Fuzziness Knowl.-Based Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-way decisions in dynamic decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Rough Sets and Knowledge Technology</title>
		<meeting>the 8th International Conference on Rough Sets and Knowledge Technology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="288" to="299" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incorporating logistic regression to decision-theoretic rough sets for classifications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decision region distribution preservation reduction in decision-theoretic rough set model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">278</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="614" to="640" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attribute reduction of data with error ranges and test costs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Min</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Pawlak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="356" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Granular Computing: Analysis and Design of Intelligent Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pedrycz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Francis Taylor, Boca Raton</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MGRS: a multigranulation rough set</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Dang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="970" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multigranulation decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decision-theoretic rough fuzzy set model and application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">283</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intuitionistic fuzzy information-applications to pattern recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Vlachos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sergiadis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recogn. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some geometric aggregation operators based on intuitionistic fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Yager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. General Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intuitionistic fuzzy aggregation operators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1179" to="1187" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intuitionistic preference relations and their application in group decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">177</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2363" to="2379" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering algorithm for intuitionistic fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3775" to="3790" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On multi-period multi-attribute decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Knowl.-Based Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="164" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic intuitionistic fuzzy multi-attribute decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Yager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="246" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Choquet integrals of weighted intuitionistic fuzzy information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="726" to="736" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent advances in intuitionistic fuzzy information aggregation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Optim. Decis. Making</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="381" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OWA aggregation of intuitionistic fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Yager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. General Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="617" to="641" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some aspects of intuitionistic fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Yager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Optim. Decis. Making</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling multi-agen three-way decisions with decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fundam. Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Web-based support systems with rough set analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Herbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">RSEIP 2007</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kryszkiewicz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4585</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="360" to="370" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A decision-theoretic rough set model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K M</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lingras</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Methodologies for Intelligent Systems</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ras</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zemankova</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Emrich</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>North-Holland, New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="24" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A decision theoretic framework for approximating concepts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K M</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Man-Machine Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="793" to="809" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-way decisions with probabilistic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The superiority of three-way decision in probabilistic rough set models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1080" to="1096" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequential three-way decisions with probabilistic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 10th IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Informatics and Cognitive Computing</title>
		<meeting>10th IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Informatics and Cognitive Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="125" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-way decisions using rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Rough Sets: Selected Methods and Applications in Management and Engineering, Advanced Information and Knowledge Processing</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="93" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An outline of a theory of three-way decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">RSCTC 2012</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7413</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Granular computing and sequential three-way decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">RSKT 2013</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lingras</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="27" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An automatic method to determine the number of clusters using decision-theoretic rough set</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="353" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reduction target structure-based hierarchical attribute reduction for two-category decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Miao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inform. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">277</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="755" to="776" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-class decision-theoretic rough sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
