<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014">JANUARY 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gonzalo</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><surname>Carin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Henry</forename><surname>Arguello</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kittle</surname></persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014">JANUARY 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">082E226562156A719FB3F4CAE88A477C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/MSP.2013.2278763</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T16:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>maging spectroscopy involves the sensing of a large amount of spatial information across a multitude of wavelengths. Conventional approaches to hyperspectral sensing scan adjacent zones of the underlying spectral scene and merge the results to construct a spectral data cube. Push broom spectral imaging sensors, for instance, capture a spectral cube with one focal plane array (FPA) measurement per spatial line of the scene [1], <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[2]</ref>. Spectrometers based on optical bandpass filters sequentially scan the scene by tuning the bandpass filters in steps. The disadvantage of these techniques is that they require scanning a number of zones linearly in proportion to the desired spatial and spectral resolution. This article surveys compressive coded aperture spectral imagers, also known as coded aperture snapshot spectral imagers (CASSI) [1], [3], [4], which naturally embody the principles of compressive sensing (CS) [5], <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[6]</ref>. The remarkable advantage of CASSI is that the entire data cube is sensed with just a few FPA measurements and, in some cases, with as little as a single FPA shot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IntroductIon</head><p>CS dictates that one can recover spectral scenes from far fewer measurements than that required by conventional linear scanning spectral sensors. To make this possible, CS relies on two principles: sparsity, which characterizes the spectral scenes of interest, and incoherence, which shapes the sensing structure [5], <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[7]</ref>. Sparsity indicates that spectral images found in nature can be concisely represented in some basis W with just a small</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>number of coefficients. This is indeed the case in spectral imaging where natural scenes exhibit correlation among adjacent pixels and also across spectral bands <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[2]</ref>. Incoherence refers to the structure of the sampling waveforms used in CS that, unlike the signals of interest, have a dense representation in the basis W <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[7]</ref>. The remarkable discovery behind CS is that it is possible to design sensing protocols capable of capturing the essential information content in sparse signals with just a small number of compressive measurements. The sensing modality simply correlates incoming signals with a small number of fixed waveforms that satisfy the incoherence principle. The signals of interest are then accurately reconstructed from the small number of compressive measurements by numerical optimization <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[8]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[11]</ref>. In CASSI, the random projections occur naturally as the result of the optical dispersion phenomena affecting coded aperture light fields as they transverse a prism before these are integrated by the imaging detector.</p><p>Our intent in this article is to overview the fundamental optical phenomena behind compressive spectral imaging sensors, present the key mathematical concepts embodying the sensing and reconstruction mechanisms, and describe the optimization framework used to design optimal coded apertures in a number of applications, including hyperspectral image reconstruction, spectral selectivity, and superresolution. The article describes many practical aspects of the instrumentation, including calibration, discretization models, parameter design, and physical limitations, and it illustrates results with real data and imagery. A fascinating aspect of compressive spectral sensing is that it draws from various disciplines within optics, signal processing, and probability theory. Our survey is to highlight the rich interaction among these fields of study as they come together in the discovery of novel compressive spectral sensors. Our treatment explains as plainly as possible four fundamental aspects of CASSI:</p><p>1) the sensing problem 2) coded aperture optimization 3) reconstruction algorithms 4) computational spectral imaging. It should be noted that compressive spectral imaging is of interest in many fields and advances in this area are growing rapidly. Consequently, it is not possible to review all work in the field, and we focus on CASSI type compressive optical sensing. The topics in this tutorial are complemented by a companion article in this issue <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[12]</ref>, where other approaches and methods are described.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>tHE SPEctrAL SEnSInG ProBLEM</head><p>The sensing physical phenomena in CASSI is strikingly simple, yet it adheres to the incoherence principles required in CS. In its simplest form, CASSI measurements are realized optically by a coded aperture, a dispersive element such as a prism, and an FPA detector <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[3]</ref>. The coding is applied to the (spatial-spectral) image source density ( ; ; ) f x y 0 m by means of a coded aperture ( ; ) T x y as realized by the CASSI system depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>, where ( ; )</p><p>x y are the spatial coordinates and m is the wavelength <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[3]</ref>. The resulting coded field ( ; ; ) f x y 1 m is subsequently modified by a dispersive element before it impinges onto the FPA detector. The compressive measurements across the FPA are realized by the integration of the dispersed field ( ; ; ) f x y 2 m over the detector's spectral range sensitivity. The sensing mechanism is illustrated by the discretized model shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>, where the spectral data cube F having L spectral bands and N N # spatial pixels is first amplitude modulated by a pixelated N N # coded aperture T. In this case, T is a block-or unblock-coded aperture such that the energy along the spectral coordinate of the data cube is punched out when a block-coded aperture element is encountered. As the coded field transverses the prism, it is then spatially sheared along one spatial axis. In essence, each coded image plane at a fixed wavelength is shifted along the x-axis where the amount of shifting increases with the wavelength coordinate index. Finally, the coded and dispersed field is "collapsed" in the spectral dimension by the integration of the energy impinging on each detector element over its spectral range sensitivity. The integrated field is then measured by the FPA detector elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Focal Plane Array</head><note type="other">Dispersive Element Relay Lens Bandpass Filter Aperture Code Objective Lens Object Data Cube</note><p>Several properties of the sensing phenomena model should be pointed out <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[14]</ref>. First, note that the N N # spatial dimensions of the spectral data cube are mapped to an array of V N # FPA measurements, where . V N L 1 = + -This is due to the dispersion of the optical field as it transverses the prism. Second, observe that the optical coding across rows of the FPA measurements are mutually independent. That is, the aperture coding affecting one row slice of the data cube is independent from the coding affecting other row slices in the data cube. These characteristics of the sensing phenomena are important, as they shape subsequent signal processing algorithms. Third, note how the sequence of optical transformations altogether end up in a set of compressive linear measurements in the FPA detector. As Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> illustrates, each FPA shot captures a massive set of compressive measurements.</p><p>The discretized output at the detector can thus be modeled as <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[3]</ref> ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Y T F ( ) ( )( ) k j j k k L j k j 0 1 = + , , , , = - + + / (1)</formula><p>where Y j, is the intensity measured at the , j , position of the detector whose dimensions are ( ) N N L 1 # + -, L is the number of spectral bands, T j, is the binary coded aperture, and j ~, is the noise of the system. In essence, (1) sums each of the spectral image slices that have been coded and spatially shifted in proportion to the wavelength index k . Notice in (1) that each discrete spectral band is defined such that a continuous region of the analog spectrum span one pixel in the detector.</p><p>Assume that the bandpass filter of the instrument limits the spectral components between 1 m and 2 m . If the pixel width of the detector and of the coded aperture are both equal to D , then the number of resolvable bands L is limited by ((</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">)/( )), L 2 1 a m m D = -</formula><p>where for a given wavelength m , am corresponds to the dispersion induced by the prism, i.e., to the displacement of light in the focal plane along the x-axis.</p><p>The spectral resolution is limited by /a D . The horizontal and vertical spatial resolutions are limited by D , and the number of spatially resolvable pixels of the underlying scene is N N # . For spectrally rich scenes or very detailed spatial scenes, a single-shot FPA measurement is not sufficient, and additional shots are required, each with a distinct coded aperture that remains fixed during the integration time of the detector. Timevarying coded apertures can be realized by a spatial light modulator or by a lithographic mask actioned by a piezoelectric device <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[16]</ref>. It was also shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[15]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[16]</ref> that the ensemble of say, K L 11 FPA shots in one-dimensional vectorized form , , , y y y</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">T K T T 0 1 f = - 6</formula><p>@ can be rewritten in the standard form of an underdetermined system of linear equations</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>, y A H</head><formula xml:id="formula_3">i i W = = +<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where A H R KN LN W is the cosine basis <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[17]</ref>. The matrix H in (2) accounts for the effects of the coded aperture and the prism. The sensing matrix A thus couples H with the representation basis W. The coded aperture is considered binary, and the dispersive element is considered linear. In practice, it is necessary to take into account the various optical artifacts and nonideal characteristic of the optical system. Furthermore, the underlying principles of CASSI described above are general and are thus, in principle, applicable to imaging with FPAs sensitive to any region of the visible and infrared (IR) radiation of the electromagnetic spectrum.</p><p>Signal recovery in CASSI entails solving an underdetermined linear system of equations. Given the set of measurements y , the inverse CS problem consists on recovering i such that the </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">i i m - + i (<label>3</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">)</formula><p>where m is a regularization constant. The inverse problem in (3) will be addressed next. At this point, however, it should be emphasized that the sensing matrix A will play a pivotal role in sensing and thus its design is of key importance. Other cost functions could be used instead of (3). For example, an approach based on the stable recovery of a low-rank and joint-sparse matrix can be used to reconstruct the hyperspectral information.</p><p>In this case, the optimization problem is regularized to minimize jointly a nuclear norm and a 2 1 , , -norm <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[18]</ref>. To illustrate the underlying concepts above, a wide spectral bandwidth reconstruction is shown in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>, acquired with a recently developed UV-visible CASSI instrument <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[19]</ref>. The object was illuminated using SoLux daylight emulation bulbs and bandpass filtered by a Baader Planetarium (Germany) UV-IR cut filter with transmission from to 420 680 nm. A random, binary coded aperture was used in the instrument with a minimum feature size of two pixels and total area on the detector of , , 1 988 1 988 # pixels. Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the comparison between a snapshot reconstruction and a multishot reconstruction with 24 frames. The prism dispersion is nonlinear, where the shorter wavelengths disperse significantly more than longer wavelengths. This yields higher spectral resolution and lower spatial resolution in the shorter wavelengths and corresponding higher spatial resolution and lower spectral resolution for longer wavelengths, shown in the blue spectral channel in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>(a) and the red spectral channel in (b), respectively.</p><p>Code features fewer than two pixels place high demands on the optics, alignment, and calibration of the CASSI instrument, especially for small pixel size detectors. The coded aperture is required to disambiguate the spatial and spectral information that is multiplexed at the detector. For smaller code features, the optical blur, forward model, calibration, detector noise, and pixel sampling of the code have a larger impact on the reconstruction. A code feature size of two pixels (total area of four pixels) guarantees that regardless of where the feature is sampled on the detector, it will cover at least one pixel to fully modulate the signal. Smaller features will generally modulate less, where the worst case scenario involves a one-pixel feature sampled by four pixels, reducing the modulation to % 25 . In general, sampling a square wave (in our case, the coded aperture) requires infinite sample points. Even a sine wave would require at least two pixels assuming spatial Nyquist sampling and interpolation under the assumption of lowpass filtering. At the limits of small code features, adequate models <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[14]</ref> are required to compensate for undersampling the coded aperture.</p><p>A calibration process is realized in CASSI in which the spectral channels are determined so that the centers of each channel, at the finest scale, are separated by one column of detector pixels. Thus, the position of a channel corresponds to a fixed dispersion in terms of detector pixels relative to a fixed spectral channel. Charge-coupled device (CCD) measurements at equally spaced wavelengths are taken after uniformly illuminating the coded aperture with monochromatic wavelength of light within the bandpass of the system. These calibration measurements are used to build a modified system operator that accounts for the optical blur and nonlinear dispersion. The set of measurements is obtained with careful efforts to reduce or remove certain data corruptive processes, including the dark noise on the CCD, the nonuniform spectral intensity of the calibrating light source, and the nonuniform spectral sensitivity of the CCD. An alternative calibration procedure can be realized using specifically designed coded apertures for calibration and by using a high-order model of the CASSI phenomena <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[14]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>codEd APErturE oPtIMIZAtIon</head><p>The sensing matrix A in (1) plays a crucial role in the mathematics of the inverse CS problem. A large body of literature in CS specifically deals with characterizing the "goodness" of A <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[6]</ref>. In CASSI, A is determined by the matrix , H which can be shown to have the structure shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">4</ref> [4], <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[16]</ref>. It consists of a set of diagonal patterns (circled) that repeat in the horizontal direction, each time with a unit downward shift, as many times as the number of spectral channels. Each diagonal pattern, circled in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">4</ref>, is the coded aperture pattern itself. Just below, the next set of diagonal patterns are determined by the coded aperture pattern used in the next FPA shot. The matrix H will thus have as many sets of diagonal as FPA measurements. Initially, commonly used coded apertures in CASSI included Hadamard matrices, S matrices, and Bernoulli random matrices <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[1]</ref>.</p><p>The use of these coded apertures was principally motivated by the realization that they are well conditioned when used in least square estimation <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[1]</ref>. However, these code designs do not fully exploit the rich theory of CS. Given that the coded apertures determine the nonzero entries of the sensing matrix, the important question can be asked: Can the coded apertures be optimally designed? Remarkably, the answer is yes, where the restricted isometry property (RIP) provides the optimization criteria <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[6]</ref>.</p><p>The RIP establishes the conditions necessary for A such that the <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">2</ref> , norm of the underlying 3-D spectral image is approximately preserved under the transformation Ai . More precisely, for each integer , , ,  -The design strategy is then formulated as seeking the set of coded apertures { , , }, T T</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">S</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">j j K 0 1 f , , - such that , , ( ) , argmin max T T A A I { , , } | | | | | | , | | max j j K T T n S T 0 1 T T T T T j j K 0 1 f m = - f , , 1 # - , , -<label>6 @ (4)</label></formula><p>where the entries of A| || | T T are determined by the coded apertures. For a set of K coded apertures { , , , }, T T T</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">j j j K 0 1 1 f , , ,</formula><p>as depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>, it turns out that the correlation variable [Figure <ref type="figure">5(b)</ref>]</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">z T T T T T T j j j j j j K j K 0 0 1 1 1 1 1 2 1 2 1 2 1 2 g = + + + , , , ,<label>, , , , - - (5)</label></formula><p>strongly influences (4) and consequently the RIP in CASSI <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[20]</ref>. As depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>, T T j j</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">1 2</formula><p>, , i i is the product of two elements of the ith coded aperture, both at the jth row, but at the column positions 1</p><p>, and 2 , . The first-and second-order statistics of z  It was also shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[20]</ref> that the entries in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">6</ref>) can be roughly approximated as independent and identically distributed Gaussian variables ( , ( ) )</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">C m 0 A N | || | k k 1 2 2 T T 1 2 - v +</formula><p>^h such that the concentration of measure for this type of matrices can be applied <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[21]</ref>. A relation between the statistics of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">6</ref>) and the probability of correct reconstruction is then established using the concentration of measure. The variance of the entries in the Gaussian approximation depends on the variance 2  v and mean m of the variables .</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">z i 1 2</formula><p>, , To guarantee that the diagonal elements of</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">A| || | T T satisfy 1 E A| || | k k T T = ^h h</formula><p>for all , k these are normalized by constraining the coded apertures to satisfy</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">T C j i K 2 0 1 = , = - i ^h /</formula><p>for all j and , , where C is a selectable constant. The so-called Boolean-coded apertures are defined as those whose entries satisfy { , }.</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">T 0 1 j ! , i In which case, / m C K 2 2 = and ( ) / K C 2 2 v = - ( ( )) . K K 1 2 -</formula><p>The term m 2 2 v + can be minimized by setting C 1 = implying that in each spatial position, only one coded aperture from the ensemble of K-codes contains a nonzero value. Thus, for each j and , the optimal coded aperture entries under the criterion (4) are obtained by satisfying the constraints T 1 <ref type="figure">5</ref>(a) illustrates an optimal Boolean ensemble for four coded apertures of size . 64 64 # As indicated in the zoomed-in regions of the coded apertures, there is only one nonzero element for each , j , position of the ensemble. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>(a)</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">j 0 = , i and T 0 j = , i for . i i0 ! Figure</formula><p>illustrates a portion of the ground truth of a 16-band spectral data cube sensed with a monochromator. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>(b) illustrates a corresponding compressive measurement. Figure <ref type="figure">6(c)</ref> shows the reconstruction of a data cube of 16 bands using the optimal Boolean-coded apertures. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>(d) depicts the reconstruction using an ensemble with random entries. Notice in Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> that the resulting spectral data cubes are shown as they would be viewed by a Stingray F-033C CCD color camera.</p><p>rEconStructIon FroM coMPrESSEd MEASurEMEntS Several numerical algorithms are available to solve the inverse problem in (3). These can be grouped into one of five computational approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[10]</ref>. Algorithms based on greedy pursuit iteratively find an estimate of the solution by selecting atoms of a dictionary and the correspondent weighting factors such that the signal can be represented as a linear combination of these vectors. This approach is implemented by algorithms such as the orthogonal matching pursuit (OMP) and compressive sampling matching pursuit (CoSaMP). The second type of algorithms solve a convex optimization problem. This includes interior-point methods such as 1 , -magic software and gradient-descent methods like the sparse reconstruction via separable approximation (SpaRSA), the two-step iterative shrinkage/thresholding algorithm (TwIST), and the gradient projections for sparse reconstruction algorithm (GPSR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[22]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[23]</ref>. The third approach uses a Bayesian framework that finds a maximum a posteriori estimator assuming a prior distribution of the unknown coefficients of the signal to recover <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[8]</ref>. Other techniques include (a)</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">T 0 T 0 T 1 T K-1 T 0 T 1 T 1 T K-1 T K-1</formula><p>Off On (b)  nonconvex optimization <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[24]</ref> and brute force, which attempts to find the solution by trying all possible support sets. A tutorial review of the algorithms in each of these class-types and their associated complexity is found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[10]</ref>. Typical computations performed by these algorithms include matrix pseudoinverses, sparse basis transformations, and vector-matrix multiplications.</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">j 1 j 2 j 1 j 2 j 1</formula><p>Given that the underlying signals are high dimensional, these calculations require a large number of floating point operations. For instance, in each iteration of the GPSR algorithm, approximately ( ) O KN L 4 operations are computed where K is the number of measurement shots, N is the spatial dimensions, and L is the number of spectral channels of the data cube. Reconstructions of large scenes are indeed overwhelming since they can take hours in desktop architectures <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[16]</ref>.</p><p>The computational burden can be ameliorated by working with separable sensing operators <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[25]</ref> or fast field-programmable gate array and graphics processing unit implementations of the reconstruction algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[26]</ref>. Instead of relying on hardware solutions, the computational complexity can be also addressed by exploiting the physical properties of the CASSI optical sensing phenomena. In particular, it is possible to reconstruct the underlying 3-D data cube from a set of reconstructions obtained from nonoverlapping FPA windowed measurements. In this manner, the GPSR reconstruction algorithm performs ( ) O KB L within the FPA detector at the ith shot, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>, where the energy in the windowed measurements is traced back through the optical system. After the prism, the energy to be collected by the B B # FPA window is a coded and dispersed square source cube with L spectral bands. If these voxels are traced back before they impinge on the prism and the coded aperture, the voxels no longer form a cube but instead they form an oblique parallelepiped consisting of L spectral bands, with each one shifted one spatial position in the horizontal axis. Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref> illustrates how an oblique parallelepiped Fmn of the data cube, which is amplitude modulated by a coded aperture of size ( ) B B L 1 # + -and spectrally sheared by the prism, results on a B B # block of measurements at the detector. In other words, the voxels that are sensed in a B B # area of the detector emanate from an oblique volume in the source and not from a cube. Furthermore, the oblique parallelepiped volume, once it is sheared by the prism, is transformed into a B B # cube before it impinges onto the detector. The energy impinging on an adjacent nonoverlapping window at the FPA can be traced back to the source in a similar manner, such that the entire FPA measurement Y i can be expressed as an ensemble of B B # nonoverlapping measurement windows as</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">. Y Y Y Y Y Y Y , , , , , , i i N i i N i V i N V i 0 0 1 0 0 1 1 1 0 1 1 1 h h g j g h = - - - - - l l l l l &gt; H<label>(7)</label></formula><p>The total number of windows in the set is , </p><formula xml:id="formula_20">N V l l with / N B N = l and ( ) /( ) , B V N L 1 = + - l ^h with</formula><p>where   (10)   where il is a sparse representation of fmn t in the basis . Wl Notice that the inverse problem in ( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) is similar to that in (3) of the traditional approach. The difference lies in that the sparsifying basis Wl representing the Kronecker product of a wavelet basis and the cosine basis has smaller dimensions than W since Fmn is a smaller section of the data cube . F The full data cube F t is assembled by tiling all the reconstructed oblique parallelepipeds. Since the number of operations per iteration in CS reconstruction algorithm grows rapidly with the size of the measurement vector, the computational complexity in the block CASSI model decreases rapidly as the number of partitions increase. In particular, the GPSR in CASSI performs approximately ( ) O KN L l blocks, then the number of operations per core is . O KB L 4 ^h Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> illustrates the reconstruction quality attained by the block CASSI model. A detailed analysis of the block CS performance in PSNR is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[13]</ref> where the improvements in image reconstruction are described at length. Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> shows an original 512 512 32 # # data cube, the block model reconstructed data cube, and the traditional CASSI model reconstruction. Using an Intel Core i7 3.30 GHz processor PC with 32 GB RAM memory, the block model and the standard CASSI take approximately .</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">Hmn i is a B B L</formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">mn i i x W W = - + i , l l l t `j</formula><p>. K 0 71 36 + min and . . K 1 58 78 + min, respectively, to reconstruct the complete data cube, where K is the number of shots. The reconstruction of one parallelepiped associated with a single block takes .</p><p>. K 0 045 0 28 + min; thus, if multiple processing is available, the block reconstruction can offer significant faster processing.</p><p>The block CASSI model is general and can be used with any CS reconstruction algorithm. For instance, the Bayesian reconstruction framework introduced in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[27]</ref> is noteworthy, with an approximate posterior distribution on model parameters inferred assuming a prior distribution of the unknown coefficients of the signal to recover. In this approach, one seeks to recover not only multiple fmn but to also infer on the underlying dictionary with which the data may be represented. Specifically, we wish to jointly recover all { } fmn and , Wl where the latter is an overcomplete dictionary. It is assumed that , fmn The theoretical underpinnings are developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[28]</ref>, where a number of illustrative experiments are given. A key distinction of this approach with conventional CS reconstruction algorithms is that Wl and mn i are estimated simultaneously, implying that the measurements are "blind" to the underlying W in which each fmn may be sparsely rendered. This is achievable because N V l l different signals ymn are jointly processed and analyzed. This framework has been coined as blind CS <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[28]</ref>. In this framework, a prior is placed on the noise variance, and this is inferred within the analysis. The noise statistics are assumed Gaussian within the prior, but the posterior may differ from the Gaussian assumption. The dictionary learning employed here represents each patch of data in terms of a sparse subset of dictionary elements. One may show that this model has close similarities to Gaussian mixture modeling (GMM) with (near) low-rank covariance matrices <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[29]</ref>, with this in turn closely related to recent work on low-rank data modeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[30]</ref>. Low-rank models assume the data live in a single linear subspace, with the GMM assume the data live in a union of linear subspaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[29]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">mn mn i W = + l where R B L U 2 ! W # l with ; U B L</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>coMPutAtIonAL SPEctrAL IMAGInG</head><p>The coded aperture patterns determine the quality of CASSI measurements. Good codes provide better measurements that, in turn, render more accurate signal reconstructions. Computational spectral imaging goes a step further by jointly optimizing the coded apertures and the computational modules to produce new types of imagery that could benefit vision in different applications. This tutorial describes computational algorithms for spectral selectivity and super resolution. Computational tools exist for a number of other applications as detailed in the recent literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[31]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[36]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[37]</ref> and in the companion article <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[12]</ref> in this issue.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SPECTRAL SELECTIVITY</head><p>It is often known a priori that objects of interest in a scene do not contain a spectral component over the full range of wavelengths but in a subset of wavelengths. Notably, the coded aperture patterns can be designed so as to maximize the information content on a prespecified subset of spectral bands of particular interest. Spectral selectivity is of interest in many applications, including wide-area airborne surveillance, remote sensing, and tissue spectroscopy in medicine. The optimal spectral bands in airborne surveillance, for instance, depend on atmospheric conditions, time of day, the targets of interest, and the background against which the targets are viewed <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[15]</ref>. Efforts placed on acquiring the entire spectral image cube, to then throw away a large portion of this data is wasteful in many regards.</p><p>To this end, coded apertures can be used to attain spectrally selective compressive measurements <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[15]</ref>. A spectrally selective coded aperture, denoted as , T i is formed from two concatenated coded apertures, which simplifies the optimization. The first coded aperture w i is a structured code optimized to attain the spectral band selectivity. The second coded aperture r i is a pseudorandom binary code necessary to attain randomized measurements in CASSI. The coded aperture used in each measurement is obtained by the Hadamard product , T w r</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">i i i 5 =</formula><p>and its optimization is divided in two parts. Since row measurements in CASSI are independently coded, the model in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>) is first rewritten as , y HC w</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">k k V T k 0 1 1 H = = - + l ^h</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>/</head><p>where y is the compressive measurement and Hk l representing a row of the data cube F and the prism effect, C is an antidiagonal matrix with all the nonzero entries equal to one, and H is a permutation matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[4]</ref>. Note that the term C w</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">T k 1 H + ^h</formula><p>represents the effects of the coded aperture operations on the sheared data cube . Hk l Since the desired spectral bands of interest are known a priori, an approach to design the coded apertures is to create a desired compressive measurement d where the data cube is first modified such that the spectral bands that are of no interest are zeroed out. A compressive measurement based on the modified data cube would be ideal in the sense that it would only contain information from the spectral bands of interest. The desired compressive measurement is then obtained as d H</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">K V k 0 1 m = = - l /</formula><p>where the entries of m are 1 j m = if the jth band is desired and zero elsewhere. The desired compressive measurement d is next equated to the compressive measurement y attained with the full data cube sensed by the CASSI imager leading to the following structures for the coded apertures ( ) , , .</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">j L 0 1 w C j j1 1 f H m = = - + -<label>(11)</label></formula><p>The solution in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(11)</ref> requires L vectors, however, the number of vectors can be reduced by exploiting their interdependence. More specifically, to estimate K L 1 linearly independent weight vectors, the coded apertures are arranged into the matrix , , . M w w</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">w L 0 1 f = - 6 @</formula><p>The minimum number of shots K for a given set of bands of interest is the number of independent column K of Mw determined by , K rank Mw = ^h the rank of the matrix Mw <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[4]</ref>. The K linear independent columns of Mw are the linear independent weight vectors , ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">w w W K 0 1 f = a a-</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6</head><p>@ selected from . Mw The remaining L K columns of Mw can be estimated using the ensemble of vectors in . W Once the components w j of the coded apertures have been optimized, these are fixed and the companion pseudorandom components r i are then optimized so as to further minimize the required number of shots. This is achieved by minimizing the rank of the matrix M r r</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">W t K 0 1 &amp; f = - 6 @ such that ( ) ( ), rank rank M M t w 1</formula><p>where &amp; is the element by element multiplication operator and where the search of the vectors r i is such that the CASSI measurements better satisfy the RIP. The rank minimization of Mt is an NP hard problem such that a stochastic algorithm can be used to approximately solve this optimization <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[4]</ref>.</p><p>To illustrate the design of coded apertures with spectral selectivity, consider again the data cube F with 512 512 # pixels of spatial resolution and L 24 = spectral bands ranging from 460 nm to 668 nm. The desired spectral bands are set to , 461 479 641 668 nm nm nm nm m = --6 @ as depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref>(e). In this case, the initial rank of the matrix Mt is 24. Using a stochastic based optimization algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[4]</ref>, the rank of the matrix Mt is minimized to 12. The resulting spectral data cubes are shown as they would be viewed by a Stingray F-033C CCD color camera: Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref>(a) shows the original bands, Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref>(b) depicts the reconstruction of the same scene from 12 Bernoulli random coded aperture compressive measurements, Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref>(c) shows the results when 12 optimized coded apertures are used in the sensing and reconstruction, and Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref>(d) shows one of the optimal spectrally selective coded apertures. Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref> illustrates the gain attained by optimal coded apertures in terms of spectral resolution and higher quality of reconstruction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SuPERRESOLuTION</head><p>While FPAs are available across the IR spectrum, there is continued interest in the development of larger format FPAs for increased resolution <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[32]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[33]</ref>. Increasing the size and resolution of FPAs comes with ever-increasing costs. Notably, coded apertures can be designed to yield superresolved reconstruction by leveraging computational imaging <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[34]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[35]</ref>. The goal is to translate high-resolution scenes into compressed signals measured by low-resolution or small-format detectors. Superresolution can be attained not only spatially but also spectrally, where the number of spectrally resolved image planes is increased.</p><p>Let c D and D be the coded aperture pitch and FPA pitch, respectively, and let / .</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">r c D D = A critical requirement to achieve superresolution is that . c 1 D D If , c D D =</formula><p>the resultant spectral imaging system is equivalent to the standard CASSI architecture. On the other hand, when the pitch resolution of the coded aperture is reduced to the extreme where all the elements of the coded aperture are mapped to just one pixel in the detector , N c D D = ^h the imaging system becomes the single pixel camera <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[12]</ref>. Superresolution CASSI is realized when the pitch resolution lies somewhere between these two extremes, i. where the CASSI image reconstruction quality after 48 shots (24.95 dB) is compared with the superresolved CASSI, which attains over a 3 dB gain in PSNR by exploiting subpixel information. concLuSIonS Compressive spectral imaging with coded apertures benefits from the use of simple optical sensing elements to harness compressive projections. CASSI snapshot spectral imagers are both, remarkably simple and surprisingly efficient, making them attractive in a number of applications in remote sensing and surveillance. Their power emerges from the combination of optics with the rich theories of CS and computational imaging. While CASSI spectral imagers naturally embody the congruence of these fields, new spectral imagers as well as more general multidimensional imaging sensors are being discovered by the use of more advanced optical and photonic devices as sensor elements. The potential of coded aperture optimization and optical sensing in multimode and multidimensional imaging holds great promise in the near future, providing fertile ground for signal processing exploration.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AcKnoWLEdGMEntS</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>f 2 (</head><label>2</label><figDesc>x, y, ) f 1 (x, y, ) f 0 (x, y, ) compressive cASSI sensor components. (Image courtesy of david J. Brady and david S. Kittle.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>#</head><label></label><figDesc>is the CASSI sensing matrix, i is a sparse representation of the data cube in a three-dimensional (3-D) basis W, and ~ represents the noise of the system. A An illustration of the spectral optical flow in cASSI. the th q slice of the data cube F with 11 nonzero voxels is coded by a row of the coded aperture and dispersed by the prism. the detector captures the intensity y by integrating the coded light. , where 1 W is the two-dimensional-wavelet Symmlet-8 basis and 2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A comparison between snapshot and multishot cASSI reconstructions: (a) snapshot, 490 nm and 24-frame reconstruction at 490 nm, (b) snapshot, 612 nm and a 24-frame reconstruction at 612 nm, and (c) selected wavelengths from the 24-frame, reconstructed data cube. An rGB image of the object taken with an SLr digital camera is shown in the upper left part of (c). notice the relative spatial resolution for the blue and red spectral channels.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>2 =</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The probability of satisfying the RIP condition is thus calculated by estimating the statistical distribution of the maximum eigenvalue max m</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>j 1 2 ,</head><label>2</label><figDesc>, , specifically the mean { } have a critical effect on (4). The expectation in this case is over the random selection of the entries .Let the entries of W be , , j k W then using the structure of the matrices H in Figure4, the entries A| || | k k</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the sensing matrix H where the (circled) diagonal patterns repeating horizontally correspond to the coded aperture pattern used in the first FPA shot. the second coded aperture pattern determines the next set of diagonals. the figure depicts the sensing of four spectral bands and two FPA shots.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>in areas show that each spatial coordinate in the ensemble contains only one onevalued entry. (b) the elements T ( the products are then added to obtain one realization of the random variable z in (5).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) the original data cube and (b) compressive FPA measurement. reconstructions from six shots using (c) Boolean (PSnr 40.41 dB) and (d) random (PSnr 27.72 dB). the resulting spectral data cubes are shown as they would be viewed by a Stingray F-033c ccd color camera. (Image courtesy of G.r. Arce and H. Arguello.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>4 %</head><label>4</label><figDesc>After the recovery of the set of images, these are tiled together to assemble the complete data cube reconstruction. Consider a B B # measurement window Y , m n i</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>2 2 # 6 @</head><label>226</label><figDesc>submatrix of H i obtained by choosing the rows and columns that affect each windowed FPA measurement, ymn i and fmn are the vectorized representations of Y , m n i and , Fmn respectively. Equation (8) is referred to as the block-model projection. The set of windowed measurements from sequential FPA shots can then be assembled as in the CASSI model to obtain , , The matrices Hmn i preserve the structure of H i in Figure4except that the dimensions are now considerably smaller. The multishot block CASSI model can be rewritten as . Each B B # window at the detector results from sensing a B B L # # oblique parallelepiped block of the data cube. (reprinted and used with permission from [13].)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>to recover a N N L # # data cube using K FPA measurements. The block model reduces the number of operations to O KN B L 2 2 ^h operations. If distinct processors are used to reconstruct separately each of the N 2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) the original rGB and zoomed-in version of the 512 512 32 # # data cube. reconstructions for 10 FPA measurement shots using (b) the block approach with block size B 64 = , 31.84 dB and (c) the traditional reconstruction approach, 30.99 dB. Block overlapped was used in this example [13].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>e., when c D lies in the interval ( / ), . N D D ^h It is important to observe that the minimum value for cD is limited by the diffraction limit of the instrument.The random projections in superresolution CASSI are given by ,y DH i W =where H is the CASSI measurement matrix shown in Figure4, and D is a decimation matrix with size ( r represents the decimation ratio induced by the low-resolution FPA<ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[35]</ref>. The decimation matrix D accounts for the integration of light in the detector when pixel mismatch c 1 D D is introduced. A set of K low-resolution FPA measurements are first captured, each one having N being the low-resolution detector height and width, respectively. Superresolution CASSI allows one to exploit subpixel information of a scene to obtain a high-resolution spectral image from low-resolution measurements. As the number of FPA measurement increases, the superresolved measurements lead to a rapid increase of image reconstruction quality. The standard CASSI measurements, on the other hand, cannot provide improved performance after a few shots. Figure10illustrates this concept for , r 4 =</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This research was supported in part by the Office of Naval Research under contract NOOO14-1O-C-0 199, by the National Science Foundation under grants EECS-0725422 and CCF-0915800, and by the Air Force Office for Scientific Research under grant FA9550-11-1-0194. AutHorS Gonzalo R. Arce (arce@udel.edu) is the Charles Black Evans Professor of electrical and computer engineering at the University of Delaware, Newark. He received the Ph.D. degree in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the resulting spectral data cubes are shown as they would be viewed by a Stingray F-033c ccd color camera. (a) the original desired bands. reconstructed images with 12 shots using (b) random codes (26.92 dB) and (c) optimized codes (31.02 dB). (d) An optimal coded aperture is illustrated. (e) Wavelengths of desired bands. (reprinted and used with permission from [4].) (a) (b) [FIG10] (a) cASSI reconstruction (PSnr 24.95 dB) versus (b) superresolution cASSI reconstruction (PSnr 29.31 dB) for the sixth spectral band. In both cases 48 shots are used. (Images courtesy G.r. Arce and H. Arguello.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="1,132.34,241.32,302.13,241.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Each individual set of windowed measurements ymn in (9) is now used to recover an oblique parallelepiped Fmn t within the data cube. A vectorized representation of Fmn t is then recovered</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">by solving</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>f</cell><cell>mn</cell><cell>argmin</cell><cell>||</cell><cell>y</cell><cell>mn</cell><cell>H</cell><cell>mn</cell><cell>||</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>||</cell><cell>mn</cell><cell>||</cell><cell>1</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">He was the</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinguished Chair in information and communications technologies. His research interests include statistical signal processing and computational imaging, and he is a coauthor of several books in these areas. He was an associate editor and guest editor of several journals of the IEEE</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fulbright-Nokia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">He is an IEEE Fellow</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Optical Society of America (OSA), and International Society for Optics and Photonics</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He is a Fellow of the IEEE, OSA, and SPIE. Lawrence Carin (lcarin@ece.duke.edu) earned the Ph.D. degree in electrical engineering at the University of Maryland in 1989. Since 1995, he has been with the Electrical Engineering Department at Duke University, where he is now the William H. Younger Distinguished Professor. He was an associate editor of several journals of the</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE and the Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>His research interests include high-dimensional signal coding and processing. optical imaging, CS, hyperspectral imaging, optical code design, and computational imaging</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">earned the Ph.D. degree in electrical and computer engineering at Duke University in May 2013. He received the B.S. degree in electrical engineering in 2005 from Walla College in College Place, Washington. His research interests lie in computational imaging systems design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kittle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>validation. rEFErEncES</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>dsk12@duke.edu</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Optical Imaging and Spectroscopy</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Hoboken, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eismann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Hyperspectral Remote Sensing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bellingham, WA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>SPIE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single disperser design for coded aperture snapshot spectral imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wagadarikar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>John</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Willett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008-04">Apr. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rank minimization code aperture design for spectrally selective compressive imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arguello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="941" to="954" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compressed sensing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Donoho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1289" to="1306" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-04">Apr. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust uncertainty principles: Exact signal reconstruction from highly incomplete frequency information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cands</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Romberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="489" to="509" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An introduction to compressive sampling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cands</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wakin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Processing Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-03">Mar. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian compressive sensing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shihao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2346" to="2356" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compressive sensing signal reconstruction by weighted median regression estimates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Paredes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2585" to="2601" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-06">June 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational methods for sparse solution of linear inverse problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tropp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-06">June 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="948" to="958" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gradient projection for sparse reconstruction: Application to compressed sensing and other inverse problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Figueiredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Select. Topics Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="586" to="597" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-12">Dec. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sparsity and structure in hyperspectral imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Willett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Duarte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Davenport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Baraniuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Processing Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-01">Jan. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast lapped block reconstructions in compressive spectral imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arguello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Correa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Higher-order computational model for coded aperture spectral imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arguello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rueda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Prather</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="D21" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Code aperture optimization for spectrally agile compressive imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arguello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Opt. Soc. Amer. A, Opt. Image Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2400" to="2413" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-11">Nov. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiframe image estimation for coded aperture snapshot spectral imagers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kittle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wagadarikar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6824" to="6833" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-12">Dec. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kronecker compressive sensing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Duarte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Baraniuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="494" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Compressed sensing of simultaneous low-rank and joint-sparse matrices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golbabaee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vandergheynst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted for publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design and fabrication of an ultraviolet-visible coded aperture snapshot spectral imager</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kittle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Marks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Opt. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71403" to="71404" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Restricted isometry property in coded aperture compressive spectral imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arguello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2012 IEEE SSP Workshop</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="716" to="719" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Concentration of Measure Phenomenon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ledoux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>American Mathematical Society</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Providence, RI</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gradient projection for sparse reconstruction: Application to compressed sensing and other inverse problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Figueiredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Select. Topics Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="586" to="597" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternating direction algorithms for constrained sparse regression: Application to hyperspectral unmixing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bioucas-Dias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Figueiredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2010 2nd Workshop on Hyperspectral Image and Signal Processing: Evolution in Remote Sensing (WHISPERS)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exact reconstruction of sparse signals via nonconvex minimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chartrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Processing Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-10">Oct. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compressed imaging with a separable sensing operator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rivensons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stern</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Processing Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GPU implementation of orthogonal matching pursuit for compressive sensing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2011 IEEE 17th Int. Conf. Parallel and Distributed Systems (ICPADS)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1044" to="1047" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coded hyperspectral imaging and blind compressive sensing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rajwade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kittle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T.-H</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Imaging Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="782" to="812" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blind compressed sensing over a structured union of subspaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Eldar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted for publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Task-driven adaptive statistical compressive sensing of gaussian mixture models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Duarte-Carvajalino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="600" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exact matrix completion via convex optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cands</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Recht</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Found. Comput. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="717" to="772" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spectral image classification from optimal coded-aperture compressive measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ramirez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arguello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TGRS.2013.2272378</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characteristics of infrared imaging systems that benefit from superresolution reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Krapels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Driggers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Burks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Opt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4594" to="4603" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-07">July 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rogalski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fundamentals of Infrared Detector Technologies</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boca Raton, FL</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compressed sensing for practical optical imaging systems: A tutorial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Willett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Marcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nichols</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Opt. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72601" to="072601" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-07">July 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial super-resolution in code aperture spectral imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arguello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rueda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SPIE Conf. Defense, Security and Sensing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Baltimore, MD</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-04">Apr. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83650A" to="83650A" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compressive spectral image classification using redundant dictionaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ramirez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted for publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spectral image unmixing from optical coded-aperture compressive measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ramirez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Arce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sensing</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted for publication</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
