<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Correlating Events with Time Series for Incident Diagnosis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jian-Guang</forename><surname>Lou</surname></persName>
							<email>jlou@microsoft.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Qingwei</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
							<email>qlin@microsoft.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Qiang</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
							<email>qifu@microsoft.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rui</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
							<email>juding@microsoft.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dongmei</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<email>dongmeiz@microsoft.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zhe</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Jilin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Microsoft Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Microsoft Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Microsoft Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Microsoft Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Microsoft Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">Jilin University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">Microsoft Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Correlating Events with Time Series for Incident Diagnosis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">834083147C0B8E0A16749344556D41A4</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1145/2623330.2623374</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T08:15+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Correlation</term>
					<term>Incident Diagnosis</term>
					<term>Two-sample Problem</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>As online services have more and more popular, incident diagnosis has emerged as a critical task in minimizing the service downtime and ensuring high quality of the services provided. For most online services, incident diagnosis is mainly conducted by analyzing a large amount of telemetry data collected from the services at runtime. Time series data and event sequence data are two major types of telemetry data. Techniques of correlation analysis are important tools that are widely used by engineers for data-driven incident diagnosis. Despite their importance, there has been little previous work addressing the correlation between two types of heterogeneous data for incident diagnosis: continuous time series data and temporal event data. In this paper, we propose an approach to evaluate the correlation between time series data and event data. Our approach is capable of discovering three important aspects of event-timeseries correlation in the context of incident diagnosis: existence of correlation, temporal order, and monotonic effect. Our experimental results on simulation data sets and two real data sets demonstrate the effectiveness of the algorithm.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The research in this paper is motivated by a real-world application in incident investigation of online services <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>. Unlike traditional shrink-wrapped software, online service systems are designed to run continuously and be available all time(24x7). However, during the operation of an online service, live-site service incidents (unplanned interruption/outage of the service) are often unavoidable, and can lead to significant economic loss or other serious consequences. For example, many reputable online services such as those provided by Amazon, Google, and Citrix have experienced live-site incidents during the past couple of years <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14]</ref>. In order to minimize service downtime caused by service incidents, much effort has been invested in improving the efficiency of service-incident diagnosis.</p><p>Diagnosis of service incidents mainly depends on analyzing the telemetry data collected at the runtime of the service <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>. Unlike a desktop application, the back-end system of an online service is often a large-scale distributed system. It is usually impractical to attach a debugger to the service to investigate service incidents. In most online systems, data analysis is the only way for engineers to diagnose service incidents. Telemetry data such as service-level logs, performance counters, and machine/process/service-level events can often provide enough information for incident diagnosis. Most telemetry data can be grouped into two categories: continuous time series data and temporal event data. A time series is a sequence of real-valued data points, measured typically at successive time points equally spaced with a uniform time interval. A typical example of time series in an online service system is the performance counter of CPU usage. An event sequence in an online service is used to record the occurrences of a specific software message indicating that something has happened in the system, e.g., an event sequence of "Out of memory" contains events of "Out of memory", which occur when there is not enough memory in the system. Among all data-driven techniques for incident diagnosis, correlation analysis between telemetry data and system states plays a very important role <ref type="bibr">[7]</ref> because correlation relationships often provide hints for causality analysis. Although the correlated metrics may not exactly be the root causes of incidents, they could be intermediate useful information that pinpoints the root causes. In practice, engineers usually start their incident investigation by searching for a small set of system metrics that are correlated to the Key Performance Indicators (KPI) of the service (Here, a KPI is an indicator that can be used to manifest system's health state, e.g., service availability or request latency) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CPU Usage</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>System Event</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CPU Intensive Program CPU Intensive Program Disk Intensive Program Disk Intensive Program</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1</ref>: The relationships between CPU usage and two system tasks (disk intensive task and CPU intensive task )</p><p>Because of the importance of correlation analysis, a lot of tools have been built to analyze the correlation between time series <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref> and the correlation between system events <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">2]</ref>. However, how to evaluate the correlation between a time series and an event sequence is still not well studied. Because of the heterogeneous property of these two types of data, traditional correlation analysis, such as Pearson correlation and Spearman correlation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>, often cannot provide satisfying results. Furthermore, in a large-scale system, an occurrence of an event may be related to a change of a time series during a time period rather than a point-to-point corresponding relationship in the traditional correlation analysis techniques.</p><p>In this paper, we propose an approach to evaluate the correlation between a time series and an event sequence. Motivated by the real requirement of incident management, our correlation technique tries to answer the following three questions: a. Are they correlated? b. What is the delay relationship between them? c. What is the monotonic effect between them (refer to Section 2 for the definition of monotonic effect)? In the context of service incident management, the answers to these questions can provide rich information to engineers for incident diagnosis. We formulate the correlation problem as a two-sample problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>, and then use the nearest neighbors method to evaluate the existence of the correlation. At the same time, we identify temporal relationships and monotonic effects by analyzing the relationships between sub-series before and after the occurrence of each event(refer to Section 2).</p><p>The contributions of this paper are as follows:</p><p>1. Motivated by real applications, we articulate the correlation problem as the aforementioned three questions.</p><p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first attempt to evaluate the three aspects of correlation between a time series and an event sequence for incident diagnosis.</p><p>2. We formulate the correlation problem as a two-sample problem, and propose a novel framework to resolve the problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The experiments on simulated data and real data from</head><p>Microsoft services show the effectiveness of our method.</p><p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows: The problem statement and formulation are introduced in Section 2. We propose our approach in Section 3. The Empirical evaluation is shown in Section 4. In Section 5, we introduce some related works. Finally, we conclude our work in Section 6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">PROBLEM STATEMENT AND FORMU-LATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Problem Statement</head><p>In statistics, correlation is any statistical relationship between two random variables in which random variables do not satisfy a mathematical condition of probabilistic independence. Let us give an example first to demonstrate the correlation between event data and the time series data. Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows two types of events (e.g., starting a disk intensive program and a CPU intensive program ) and a time series (e.g., a performance counter of CPU Usage). Every time a CPU intensive program starts, the performance counter of CPU Usage will increase significantly. On the other hand, the value of CPU Usage does not have any specific pattern related to the starting events of a disk intensive program. As a result, we can say that the starting events of the CPU intensive program and the performance counter of CPU Usage have a correlating relationship, while there is no correlation between the starting events of a disk intensive program and the CPU Usage. Such kind of correlation analysis is an important step for incident diagnosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6]</ref>.</p><p>In incident diagnosis scenarios, engineers typically study the following three aspects of the correlation among telemetric data when they are investigating service incidents.</p><p>• Existence of Dependency. Is there a correlation between an event sequence and a time series? Although statistical correlation is not sufficient to demonstrate the presence of a causal relationship, it is still quite useful for incident diagnosis because it can often provide hints to engineers for causal analysis.</p><p>• Temporal Order of Dependency. Given a pair of dependent data streams, the direction of the correlation is useful information in causal analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref>. The temporal order of the occurrence often provides information about the cause-effect direction in the context of incident diagnosis. For example, for a given dependent pair: an event sequence E and a time series S, if events in E always occur before corresponding significant changes of S, we can often propose a hypothesis that E might be related to a cause of the changes of S, and then take actions to verify this hypothesis based on other aspects of data from the service system.</p><p>• Monotonic Effect of Dependency. In many cases, some event occurrence is related to a significant valueincrease (or value-decrease) of a time series. Such a positive (or negative) monotonic effect between two dependent data streams is also a very important property of correlation for causal inference <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref>. For example, during diagnosis, our domain knowledge tells us that significant increase of CPU usage may cause the service to violate its quality SLA (Service Level Agreement) but the decreases of CPU usage should not.</p><p>Given an event sequence (or event type) denoted as E, the timestamps of the events are denoted as TE = (t1, t2, • • • , tn), where n is the number of events that happened. A time series, denoted as S = (s1, s2, • • • , sm), where m is the number of points in the time series. Unlike the timestamps of an event sequence, the timestamps of a time series, denoted as TS = (t(s1), t(s2), • • • , t(sn)), have the relationship of t(si) = t(si-1) + τ , where τ is the sampling interval.</p><p>Here, we assume that each time series has an even sampling interval, which is true in many applications. In our analysis, we also assume that the effect of an event on a time series only lasts a certain time interval that is very small compared to the total lasting time of the time series. This assumption is valid in a real-world online service system which is in a normal and healthy state most of the time. Any incident will be resolved soon after its occurrence by the system operation team.</p><p>As mentioned before, if an event type E and a time series S have a correlation relationship, every time an event E happens, there is a corresponding change of the time series S. The potential temporal relationships between an occurrence of an event ei ∈ E and its corresponding change of the time series are illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Here, each change is represented as a sub-series of S.</p><p>Supposing rear k (S, ei) denotes a sub-series of S after ei happens with length of k, and f ront k (S, ei) denotes a subseries of S before the ei happens. Intuitively, if event E does not correlate to time series S, then both rear k (S, ei) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">f ront k (S, ei) (i = 1 • • • n) are not</formula><p>related to the occurrences of ei. In other words, the sub-series</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Γ f ront = { f ront k (S, ei), i = 1 • • • n} (or Γ rear = { rear k (S, ei), i = 1 • • • n})</formula><p>are not statistically different from other sub-series with length of k (denoted as Θ) that are randomly sampled from S. On the other hand, if there is a correlation relationship between E and S, the sub-series</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Γ f ront = { f ront k (S, ei), i = 1 • • • n} (or Γ rear = { rear k (S, ei), i = 1 • • • n})</formula><p>will be statistically different from the randomly sampled sub-series Θ.</p><p>Based on this information, we have the following definitions. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Modeling as a Two-Sample Problem</head><p>Based on the above definitions, our correlation analysis problem can be transformed to a multivariate two-sample hypothesis-testing problem. Two-sample tests are commonly used when checking whether two samples come from the same underlying distribution, which is assumed to be unknown. In our context, one sample is the set Γ f ront or Γ rear , the other sample is Θ that is the set of sub-series randomly sampled from S. Each data point is actually a sub-series, which can be represented as a vector of k dimensions. Therefore, the original problem becomes a multivariate two-sample test.</p><p>Here, we use one set Γ f ront and Θ as our example. Let Γ f ront and Θ be independent random samples generated from unknown distributions F and G, respectively. The distributions are assumed to be absolutely continuous with respect to Lebesgue measure. Their densities are denoted as f and g, respectively. The hypotheses of the two-sample test can be stated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">H0 : F = G H1 : F = G (1)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">THE APPROACH</head><p>In this section, we propose a nearest-neighbor based method algorithm to analyze the three aspects of correlation, and then analyze the complexity of the proposed approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Nearest Neighbor Method</head><p>Multivariate two-sample tests have been of continuous interest to the statistics community. Several different algorithms of this kind have been proposed <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28]</ref>. To utilize some structure based distance measures such as DTW <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref> or DTW-D <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>, we apply the nearest neighbor statistic based method <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> in our scenario. It is worth pointing out that, other two-sample tests algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref> can also be used in our method.</p><p>In this subsection, we take Γ f ront as an example. Given the two samples </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Γ f ront = { f ront k (S, ei), i = 1 • • • n} and Θ = {θ1, θ2, • • • , θñ},</formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">Zi = f ront k (S, ei), if i = 1, • • • , n θi-n, if i = n + 1, • • • , p.<label>(2)</label></formula><p>For a finite set of sub-series A and a sub-series x ∈ A, let N Nr(x, A) denote the r-th nearest neighbor of x within the set {A\x}. For two mutually exclusive subsets A1, A2 and a point x ∈ A, we define an indicator function:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">Ir(x, A1, A2) = 1, if x ∈ Ai &amp;&amp; N Nr(x, A) ∈ Ai, 0, otherwise.<label>(3)</label></formula><p>The function Ir(x, A1, A2) indicates whether x and its r-th nearest neighbor in A\x belong to the same subset.</p><p>In our problem, the nearest-neighbor based tests rely on the following quantity and its generalizations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">Tr,p = 1 pr p i=1 r j=1 Ij(x, A1, A2)<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Here, p = |n + ñ| is the size of the sample. The test statistic Tr,p is the proportion of pairs containing two subseries from the same sample, among all pairs formed by a sample sub-series and one of its nearest neighbors in the pooled sample Z. Intuitively Tr,p is small under the null hypothesis when the two samples are mixed well, while Tr,p is large when the two underlying distributions are different.</p><p>Then, as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>, when p is large enough, (pr) 1/2 (Tr,pµr)/σr obeys a standard Gaussian distribution with the following parameters:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">µr = (λ1) 2 + (λ2) 2<label>(5)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">σ 2 r = λ1λ2 + 4λ 2 1 λ 2 2 (<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">)</formula><p>where λ1 = n/p and λ2 = ñ/p. The traditional Gaussian distribution test, Γ f ront and Θ are significantly different when: (pr) 1/2 (Tr,p -µr)/σ 2 r &gt; α, where α = 1.96 for P = 0.025 (or α = 2.58 for P = 0.001). For more about the hypothesis test in a Gaussian distribution, please refer to <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Mining Existence and Temporal Order</head><p>According to the definitions in Section 2, we can summarize that if event E and time series S are correlated, the following statement must be true: the front sub-series Γ f ront  and randomly sampled sub-series Θ are statistically different; or the rear sub-series Γ rear and randomly sampled subseries Θ is statistically different. In our approach, we use the above nearest-neighbor method to determine whether two sets of sub-series have an identical distribution.</p><p>If the front sub-series Γ f ront and randomly sampled subseries Θ are statistically different, then S → E. Otherwise, if the rear sub-series Γ rear and Θ is statistically different, then E → S. Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows an example of Correlation Temporal Order. From Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>, we can see CPU Intensive Program → CPU Usage, and CPU Usage → SQL Query Alert.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Mining Effect Type</head><p>As explained in Definition 4, in order to determine the monotonic effects such as E + → S (or E -→ S) of correlation, we need to check whether there exists a significant value increase (or decrease) on the time series S after an event E happens. Similarly, it can also be formulated as a problem of statistical hypotheses testing. In this research, we use t -test <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref> to check whether there is a significant value increase (or decrease) from Γ f ront to Γ rear .</p><p>Here, the tscore between Γ f ront and Γ rear can be calculated by the following equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">tscore = µ Γ f ront -µΓ rear (n 1 -1)σ 2 Γ f ront +(n 2 -1)σ 2 Γ rear n 1 +n 2 -2 ( 1 n 1 -1 n 2 ) (7)</formula><p>Algorithm 1: The Overall Algorithm Input: Event E = (e1, e2, ..., en), and Time Series S = (s1, s2, ..., sm), and the sub-series length k. Output: The correlation flag C, the direction D, and the effect type T 1 Initialize Γ f ront and Γ rear ; 2 Initialize Θ; where µ Γ f ront and µΓ rear are the mean values of Γ f ront and Γ rear . σ Γ f ront and σΓ rear are their variance values. In our research, n1 = n2 = n, and n is the event number in E, thus Equation 7 can be reduced to:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">3 Initialize R = f alse, D = N U LL, T = N U LL; 4 Normalize each f ront k (S,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">tscore = µ Γ f ront -µΓ rear σ 2 Γ f ront +σ 2 Γ rear n<label>(8)</label></formula><p>Then, if tscore &gt; α, we have a negative monotonic effect (e.g, E -→ S or S -→ E); and if tscore &lt; -α, we have a positive monotonic effect (e.g., E</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">+ → S or S + → E).</formula><p>Here, α = 1.96 for P = 0.025 (or α = 2.58 for P = 0.001) <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>.</p><p>At the same time, for a given α,if |tscore| &lt; α, we cannot determine the effect type with a high level of confidence. However, such situations are seldom found in the real scenarios of incident diagnosis. Most services have be designed with a large certain margin to fault-tolerate. When a service incident is detected, the corresponding time-series must have a significant difference from its normal behavior (i.e., tscore &gt; α) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">The Overall Algorithm</head><p>The overall algorithm is then summarized as Algorithm 1. This algorithm implements the methods we have introduced in the above subsections. It performs two two-sample tests based on the sub-series Γ f ront , Γ rear , and Θ. The output of this algorithm contains all three aspects of the correlation between a time series and an event sequence. In this section, we discuss details of the algorithm implementation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.1">Setting Parameters</head><p>The length of sub-series k is an important parameter which can directly influence the performance of our algorithm. We use one example to illustrate the influence of k. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref> shows two curves, where the vertical axis represents the value of (N k) 1/2 (T k,N -µ k )/σ 2 k . For a given α, its value is directly related to the confidence of hypotheses</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">H1. A larger (N k) 1/2 (T k,N -µ k )/σ 2</formula><p>k means a high confidence of H1. We denote it as "Confidence Coefficient". In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>, the black curve is the confidence coefficient obtained by evaluating the correlation between a pair of "CPU Extensive Program" and "CPU Usage". We know there does exist any correlation between the pair of data. This means the higher confidence of H1 is better. Because the front sub-series (or the rear sub-series) with a very small length (i.e., k &lt; 4) only contains limited information, the confidence in testing is not high enough. As the length increases, we can see a significant increase in confidence in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>. However, when the length is larger than a certain value (e.g., 8), the confidence decreases after the maximum value. The reason is that as the sub-series length increases thereby the effect of event to time series starts to diminish which makes the subsequence closer to the population Θ. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>, the blue curve is the confidence coefficient obtained from the pair of "Disk Transfer Extensive Program" and "CPU Usage". Domain knowledge clearly tells us this pair is not correlated. The result also confirms this fact. The curve of confidence coefficient is flat and very close to 0 for any value of k. It means the rejection of H1 is not influenced by k if two data sets are not correlated.</p><p>In some cases, the value of k can be selected based on domain knowledge and experiments. However, in most real world situations, there are millions of time series and events, and we do not have enough domain knowledge to pre-select the values of all sub-series lengths. In this research, we design a method to auto-select the sub-series length for a time series based on the autocorrelation function <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> of the time series. Given a time series S = (s1, s2, ..., sn), the autocorrelation is showed as follows:  </p><formula xml:id="formula_16">R(l) = E(si * s i-l ). (<label>9</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">)</formula><p>where l denotes the lag of the correlation. The autocorrelation function of a time series can be used to represent the energy of signals in the time series with a period of l <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>. Therefore, our length k can be assigned the value of the first peak to include the significant signal of the time series. The experiment (Section 4.5) shows the effectiveness of this method and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref> shows an example. Besides k, the number of neighbors r is also a very important parameter. It has been demonstrated that r = ln(p) is a good choice in literatures <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>. In this paper, we directly follow their suggestion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">EMPIRICAL EVALUATION</head><p>In this section, we make an empirical evaluation of our algorithm by performing a set of experiments on a data set from a controlled environment and two real data sets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Baseline</head><p>In order to evaluate the effectiveness of our algorithm, we choose two baseline algorithms in our experiment. The first one is the Pearson correlation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>, which is the widely used method for correlation mining in time series. The second baseline is J-measure <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref>, which is a widely used method for correlating event data <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>. In the rest of this section, we brief introduce these two baseline algorithms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1">Pearson Correlation</head><p>The Pearson correlation method is one of the most widely used methods for measuring the correlation between two time series. The Pearson correlation coefficient, denoted as ρ. is calculated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">ρX,Y = cov(X, Y ) σX σY = E[(X -µX )(Y -µY )]</formula><p>σX σY where cov is the covariance, σX is the standard deviation of X, µX is the mean of X and E[ * ] denotes the expectation.</p><p>The Pearson correlation can not be directly used in the correlation evaluation between time series and event data. In order to make it comparable, we transform the event E to a time series, denoted as</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">S E = (s E 1 , s E 2 , ..., s E m )</formula><p>, where m is the size of time series S, and s E i is calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">s E i = 1, if t(si) ∈ TE 0, otherwise.</formula><p>where t(si) and TE is the same meaning as before (see section 2.1).</p><p>After transforming the event data to the time series form, we directly calculate the Pearson correlation coefficient ρ between the S E and S. As introduced in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>, due to our application background, we assign the threshold as 0.1 (weak correlation as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>). If ρ &gt; 0.1, then E + ∼ S. And if ρ &lt; -0.1, then E -∼ S. Else (|ρ| &lt; 0.1), E and S are not correlated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2">J-measure Correlation</head><p>We choose the widely used event correlation method, Jmeasure <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref>, as the second baseline. J-measure has been used in many research efforts <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>.</p><p>However, J-measure is proposed for the event correlation and can not be used directly. Therefore, in our experiment, we first transform each time series to an event sequence as follows: Given a time series S = (s1, s2, ..., sm), its corresponding event sequence is</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">E S = (e E</formula><p>1 , e E 2 , ..., e E n ), where each e E i is the change point in the time series, and n is the number of changes in the time series. In this research, we use a widely used GLR algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref> to detect changes in time series.</p><p>After transforming each time series to its corresponding event sequence, we can obtain a complete event sequence by combining all the event sequences from two sets: (1) event sequences transformed by time series, (2) event sequences from the original data set. Then we can directly use Jmeasure to evaluate the correlation between these complete event sequences. Similar to the first baseline (Pearson correlation), we assign a correlation threshold as 0.1 (weak correlation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>). If the J-Measure is larger than 0.1, then E ∼ S. Otherwise, E and S are not correlated. Considering this, the Temporal Order and the Monotonic Effect Type of the correlation can not be determined using this method.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Effectiveness Study on Simulation Datasets</head><p>In this section, we introduce the experiment on the data from a controlled environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">The Controlled Experiment</head><p>In this research, we setup a SQL environment for a controlled experiment to demonstrate the mutual influencing behavior in a system. For example, when a CPU Intensive program starts, the performance counter of CPU usage may increase. In a SQL server, database operations can be influenced by the increase of CPU usage or memory usage. In the experiment, three types of programs including Disk Intensive program, CPU Intensive program and Memory Intensive program are launched several times randomly. Each running lasts for an interval of <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15]</ref> minutes. At the same time, we query a SQL server database every second. If the query latency exceeds the maximum latency limitation (200ms), the query will trigger a time-out alert.</p><p>We conduct the experiment for 6 hours. The CPU Intensive program run 43 times; the Memory Intensive program run 41 times; the Disk Intensive program run 38 times ; and 285 Query Alerts are triggered. At the same time, we collect four system events (e.g., the starting events of each program and query time-out alerts) and three system performance counters (CPU usage, memory usage, and disk I/O usage) as showed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.2">Result and Analysis</head><p>After obtaining the data from the controlled environment, we run the three algorithms on this data. The results produced by the proposed algorithm and two baseline algorithms are showed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>.</p><p>The sub-series length k of the three time series (CPU usage, Memory Usage, Disk Transfer Rate) is assigned using the first peak of the autocorrelation (as introduced in section 3.4.1). We choose DTW distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref> as the distance measure in Nearest neighbors method of our algorithm.</p><p>In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>, we see that the correlation relationship, produced using our method, can reflect real system behavior: the CPU Intensive program has a positive effect on the CPU usage; the Memory Intensive program has a positive effect on both Memory usage and CPU usage; the Disk Intensive program has a positive effect on the Disk Transfer rate. The Query Alert depends on the high usage of CPU and Memory.</p><p>On the other hand, in the results of the Pearson Correlation Algorithm, some of the correlation relations are lost (Memory Using Task + → CPU usage, and Memory Usage + ← Query Alert). The result produced by J-Measure is very bad, because J-Measure can only encode the occurrence between event and changes. In addition, the Temporal Order and the Monotonic Effect of Dependencies can not be calculated using J-measure. From this view, our algorithm has great advantages compared to the baseline algorithms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Effectiveness Study on Real Datasets</head><p>In this section, we will compare the proposed algorithm with the baseline algorithms on two real data sets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1">Dataset</head><p>The first real world dataset is a System Monitoring Dataset. This dataset is collected from a large scale online service of Microsoft. We collect 24 different kinds of time series as our input time-series from a number of machines including performance counters of Memory usage, CPU usage, Physical Disk usage etc. The sampling interval of each time series is 5 minutes. At the same time, we also collect a set of event sequences. Each event sequence contains the starting events of a specific job that is automatically submitted by a timer in the system. There are 52 different event in this dataset. The ground truth of this data is labeled by a software engineer in the product team.</p><p>The second real world dataset is the Custom Support Dataset. In Microsoft, the customer support team is in charge of the support requests from customers about the above online service. Customers may send us support requests when they do not know how to use the service or they encounter some service quality issues. In this paper, we only collect the requests caused by service issues. The requests are grouped to different categories based on their problem phenomena and root causes (also called support topic ) by the support team. The occurrences of requests in a single category form an event sequence in this study, because we try to understand what kind of service telemetry data is related to a specific request topic. There are 57 different events in this dataset. The time series data in this study is collected from the runtime system. The front end of our system is a Web Server. For every HTTP request from an end user, we have a HTTP status code. We group the requests from every hour based on their HTTP status code into 7 groups: "200 ∼ 300" (it means the status code is in the range from 200 to 300.), "300 ∼ 400", "400 ∼ 500", "500 ∼ 600", "&gt; 600", "Exception" (it means no HTTP response, the program throws an exception.) and "Sum" ("Sum" means all the status code larger than "300"). Each group will form a time series to record the number of requests hourly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2">Evaluation Metric</head><p>The basic model of our algorithm is a hypothesis-test model , we use the F1 score to evaluate our method, which has been used in many research works <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref> for analyzing hypothesis-test accuracy. As introduced in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>, F1 score can be calculated as follow: F1 = 2 * T rueP ositive 2 * T rueP ositive + F alseN egative + F alseP ositive</p><p>In the above, T rueP ositive = 1 -F alseN egative. Given a time series S and an event E, for the test of dependency existence, a F alseN egative is a case where the algorithm result shows S ∼ E, but actually S and E are not correlated. A F alseP ositive is a case where S and E are not correlated, but the result shows that S ∼ E. For the test of temporal ordering, a F alseP ositive is a case where the result shows S → E, while the actual temporal order is E → S. A F alseN egative is a case where the result does not show S → E, while the actual temporal order is S → E. For the Monotonic Effect Problem, a F alseP ositive is a case that the result shows a positive monotonic effect while the actual effect type is not positive. A F alseN egative is a case that the result does not show a positive monotonic effect while the actual effect type is positive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.3">Result Analysis</head><p>We choose three distance measures for the nearest neighbor method of our algorithm, including: DTW <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref> , L1 distance and L2 distance. The result is shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">3</ref>.</p><p>For the different distance measures, we can see that there is no significant difference among them. It seems that the DTW distance has a slightly better performances than others in the experiment on Custom Support Data. When a DTW distance can decrease the influence of latency values <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>. By comparing our algorithm with the baseline algorithms (Pearson correlation and J-Measure), we can see that our algorithm has significant advantages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Efficiency Study</head><p>Now, we shall study the efficiency of our algorithm. We use synthetic datasets to evaluate the efficiency of our algorithm, because we can manipulate the size of the dataset flexibly.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>(a), we fix the value of sub-series length k, and vary the event data size n. We can see that the CPU execution time increased by enlarging the data size. Because we need to calculate the pair-wise distance among sub-series, the computational cost is at O(n 2 ). In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>(b), we fix the size of event data, and vary the value of length k. Based on the results, we can see that the running time of the program is almost linear to the value of length k (note: we use L2 as our distance measure in this experiment.).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Length of Sub-series</head><p>In this subsection, we study the influence caused by different length values of sub-series k in the algorithm. We select two event-time series pairs which are really correlated (CPU Extensive Program and CPU usage; Memory Extensive Program and Memory Usage). In this experiment, we use the confidence coefficient as an indicator to evaluate the per-   The first peak of the autocorrelation of CPU usage appears at the index of 5, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8(b</ref>). In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8(a)</ref>, the largest value of the Confidence coefficient appears just at the index of k = 5. Similarly, in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8(d)</ref>, the first peak of the autocorrelation of Memory Usage appears is at the index of 11. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8(c</ref>), the value of the Confidence Coefficient is also at a peak when k = 11. From these results, we can see that by using the first peak of the autocorrelation, one can obtain a good configuration of the length k.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">RELATED WORK</head><p>In this section, we briefly introduce some related research efforts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Correlation between Time Series Data</head><p>The correlation between two time series has been widely studied, and some of them have been included in text books <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>. The Pearson correlation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref> is a basic correlation measure  between time series, which has been widely used in practice <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref>. Some extensions of the Pearson correlation are also widely used. For example, lagged correlation is an extension to correlate a lagged dataset with another unlagged dataset using the Pearson product-moment method. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>, the author uses the lagged-correlation to estimate the lead relationship between a set of time series. Because the Pearson correlation is sensitive outliers in data set, Spearman Rank correlation and Kendall Rank correlation have been used in some scenarios <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref> to overcome the drawbacks of Pearson correlation. In the Spearman correlation, data is first sorted and ranked, e.g., rank 1 is assigned to the lowest value. The Spearman Rank correlation is calculated by taking the Pearson product-moment correlation of the ranks in the dataset. The Kendall correlation tries to measure the similarity of the orderings in the dataset. Because there is no ordering relationship among the different events, the above rank based algorithms cannot be directly used in our scenario.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Correlation between Event Data</head><p>Correlation between events have also been studied in many works <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11]</ref>. Here, correlation mainly means the co-occurrence of different types of events. Because event data generated in online services can naturally be regarded as sequences, association rule mining algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref> for sequence data can be directly used to analyze the correlation among event data. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>, the authors try to construct the dependency relationships between different system components by mining the co-occurrence among the unconstructed log events generated from the system. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>, the authors add user guided information during the event correlation mining. Therefore, this algorithm allows users to effectively navigate the result. Correlation Mining algorithms have also been used in some natural science. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>, the authors apply a correlation mining algorithm to mine the correlation between climate events by analyzing the historical climate data of the North Atlantic and China.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Two-sample Test</head><p>Two-sample Test is an important part of our work. For univariate data, the classical two-sample test includes the nonparametric Kolmogorov-Smirnov test and Mann Whitney U test <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>. For multi-variant data, many methods have been proposed in previous works <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>, the author uses the proportion of all r nearest neighbors in which observations and their neighbors belong to the same sample as a statistic. The algorithm proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref> is a kernel method for the two sample problem, this method maps the distance between two observations into a reproducing kernel Hilbert space (RKHS), and then uses Maximum Mean Discrepancy to solve the problem. They further propose a unifying framework by linking the two classes of statistics (i.e., energy distances in statistics and distances between distributions in RKHS) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>. In this paper, we use the nearest neighbor based algorithm in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> for simplicity. In fact, the kernel based algorithms can also be applied in our scenarios.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORKS</head><p>In this paper, we have investigated the problem of correlation mining between time series data and event data. We have defined the correlation problem and proposed a novel approach which is able to discover three important aspects of event-time-series correlation: existence of correlation, temporal ordering, and monotonic effect. In our approach, we first transform the correlation problem to a two-sample problem, use the nearest neighbors method to solve such a two-sample problem and then evaluate the correlation existence. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to answer the three correlation questions between event sequences and time series data for incident diagnosis. The experiments on the data from a controlled environment and two real datasets demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of our algorithm. The proposed method has already been implemented to an internal tool-set designed for service problem diagnosis.</p><p>Our current method does not consider the event combination problem, that only a certain combination of multiple events rather than a single type of event is correlated to a time series. This problem is much more complex, and will be a part of our future work.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Definition 1 .Figure 2 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Example of front sub-series and rear-series</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>and the pooled sample by Z = Γ ∪ Θ, we label the pooled sample as Z1, • • • , Zp with p = n + ñ where</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Effect examples: loading data task + → memory and program exiting -→ memory</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Confidence vs. sub-series length k.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Example of a time series and the corresponding autocorrelation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>1 "</head><label>1</label><figDesc>NC" denotes not correlated 2 "N/A" denotes no result.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Efficiency by varying data size and subseries length</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: The confidence coefficient value vs. sub-series length k, (a) (b):CPU intensive program and CPU usage, (c) (d): memory intensive program and memory usage</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Example of temporal order, CPU intensive program → CPU usage and CPU usage → query alert</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>CPU Usage</cell></row><row><cell>CPU Intensive Program</cell><cell>SQL Query Alert</cell><cell>System Event</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Figure 3: Memory Usage</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Loading Data Task</cell><cell>System Event</cell><cell>Program Quit</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Test Γ f ront and Θ using Nearest Neighbors Method. The result is denoted as D f .; 6 Test Γ rear and Θ using Nearest Neighbors Method.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ei) and rear k</cell><cell>(S, ei).;</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">5 The result is denoted as Dr.;</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">7 if (Dr == true&amp;&amp;D f == f alse) then</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>R = true.;</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell cols="3">Calculate tscore using Equation (8).;</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell cols="2">if (tscore &gt; α) then</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell>T = E</cell><cell>-→ S.;</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell cols="2">else if (tscore &lt; -α) then</cell></row><row><cell>13</cell><cell>T = E</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>+ → S.; 14 else if (Dr == f alse&amp;&amp;D f == true) || (Dr == true&amp;&amp;D f == true) then 15 R = true.; 16 Calculate tscore using Equation (8).; 17 if (tscore &gt; α) then 18 T = S -→ E.; 19 else if (tscore &lt; -α) then 20 T = S + → E.; 21 Out put R, D and T ; 22 Algorithm End.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Time series and event data in the controlled experiment</figDesc><table><row><cell>Name</cell><cell>Type</cell><cell>Description</cell></row><row><cell>CPU Intensive program</cell><cell>Event</cell><cell>A multi-thread process, which will let the CPU Usage achieve nearly 90%</cell></row><row><cell>Memory Intensive program</cell><cell>Event</cell><cell>A process that will apply for a nearly 2G memory space</cell></row><row><cell>Disk Intensive program</cell><cell>Event</cell><cell>A copy files process which can sharply increase disk transfer rate</cell></row><row><cell>Query Alert</cell><cell>Event</cell><cell>When SQL query delay exceed the maximum limit, an alert occurrence.</cell></row><row><cell>CPU Usage</cell><cell>Time Series</cell><cell>record the CPU usage every second</cell></row><row><cell>Memory Usage</cell><cell>Time Series</cell><cell>record the Memory usage every second</cell></row><row><cell>Disk Transfer Rate</cell><cell>Time Series</cell><cell>record the Disk Transfer Rate every second</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Results of the data from controlled environment</figDesc><table><row><cell>Name</cell><cell cols="9">Proposed Method CPU Memory Disk CPU Memory Disk CPU Memory Disk Pearson Correlation J-Measure</cell></row><row><cell>CPU Intensive Program</cell><cell>+ →</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>+ ∼</cell><cell>NC 1</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>∼</cell><cell>∼</cell></row><row><cell>Memory Intensive Program</cell><cell>+ →</cell><cell>+ →</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>+ ∼</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>∼</cell><cell>∼</cell></row><row><cell>Disk Intensive Program</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>+ →</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>+ ∼</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>∼</cell><cell>∼</cell></row><row><cell>Query Alert</cell><cell>+ ←</cell><cell>+ ←</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>+ ∼</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>NC</cell><cell>∼</cell><cell>∼</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Result in real data set Many of them often try several times to make sure they cannot fix by themselves before they call in. Different customers have different delay time before their calls.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Data Set</cell><cell>Methods</cell><cell cols="3">Existence Temporal Order Effect Type F1 Score F1 Score F1 Score</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Correlation Mining (L1)</cell><cell>0.7916</cell><cell>0.8020</cell><cell>0.8016</cell></row><row><cell>System Monitoring Data</cell><cell>Correlation Mining (L2) Correlation Mining (DTW)</cell><cell>0.8205 0.7962</cell><cell>0.7612 0.8021</cell><cell>0.8780 0.8210</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pearson Correlation</cell><cell>0.6974</cell><cell>N/A 2</cell><cell>0.6732</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>J-Measure</cell><cell>0.6148</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Correlation Mining (L1)</cell><cell>0.7915</cell><cell>0.7659</cell><cell>0.7204</cell></row><row><cell>Custom Support Data</cell><cell>Correlation Mining (L2) Correlation Mining (DTW)</cell><cell>0.8423 0.8631</cell><cell>0.7870 0.8205</cell><cell>0.8334 0.8532</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pearson Correlation</cell><cell>0.6030</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>0.6501</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>J-Measure</cell><cell>0.7398</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">customer encounters a problem, s/he may not call Microsoft</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>immediately.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>If H1 is true, that means the probabilistic distribution of Γ f ront is statistically different from the randomly sampled sub-series Θ. In addition, as Definition 1, time series S and event E are correlated. Otherwise, if H0 is true, then time series S and event E may not be correlated.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>References</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Amazon&apos;s s3 cloud service turns into a puff of smoke. Information Week</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-08">Aug 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards highly reliable enter-prise network services via inference of multi-level dependencies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chandra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kandula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maltz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIGCOMM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Detection of abrupt changes: theory and application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Basseville</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikiforov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall Englewood Cliffs</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using dynamic time warping to find patterns in time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Berndt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Clifford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="370" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dtw-d: time series semi-supervised learning from a single example</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Keogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Batista</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">KDD</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="383" to="391" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlating instrumentation data to system states: A building block for automated diagnosis and control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goldszmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Symons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">OSDI</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="244" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capturing, indexing, clustering, and retrieving system history</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goldszmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Symons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SOSP</title>
		<meeting>SOSP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="118" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance issue diagnosis for online service systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-G</forename><surname>Lou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q.-W</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SRDS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-10">October 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A kernel method for the two-sample-problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gretton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Borgwardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rasch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schölkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Smola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998. 2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">513</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated event management: Event correlation using dependency graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gruschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. DSOM 98</title>
		<meeting>DSOM 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="141" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Time series analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Princeton university press Princeton</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Data mining: concepts and techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kamber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Morgan kaufmann</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Outages force cloud computing users to rethink tactics. Information Week</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hoover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-08">Aug 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied multivariate statistical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wichern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Pearson</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What&apos;s going on? learning communication rules in edge networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kandula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chandra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Katabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIGCOMM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detailed diagnosis in enterprise networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kandula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mahajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Verkaik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Padhye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="254" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mining dependency in distributed systems through unstructured logs analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-G</forename><surname>Lou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIGOPS Operating Systems Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mining program workflow from interleaved traces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-G</forename><surname>Lou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">KDD</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="622" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Software analytics for incident management of online services: An experience report</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-G</forename><surname>Lou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ASE</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013-11">November 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On a test of whether one of two random variables is stochastically larger than the other. The annals of mathematical statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Whitney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1947">1947</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event correlation for process discovery from web service interaction logs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Motahari-Nezhad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Saint-Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Casati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Benatallah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">VLDBJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="444" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Causality: Models, Reasoning, and Inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pearl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Knowledge discovery in databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Piateski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Frawley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>MIT press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation between climate events in the north atlantic and china during the last glaciation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Porter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zhisheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">375</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation: from precision, recall and f-measure to roc, informedness, markedness &amp; correlation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Powers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JMLT</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rosner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fundamentals of biostatistics. Cengage Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multivariate two-sample tests based on nearest neighbors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Schilling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">395</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="806" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hypothesis testing using pairwise distances and associated kernels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sejdinovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gretton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fukumizu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sriperumbudur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICML-12</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1111" to="1118" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Signed directed acyclic graphs for causal inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vanderweele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting leaders from correlated time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Philip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Database Systems for Advanced Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="352" to="367" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statstream: Statistical monitoring of thousands of data streams in real time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shasha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">VLDB</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>VLDB Endowment</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="369" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
