<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free genetic sequence comparisons: a review of recent approaches by word analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Oliver</forename><surname>Bonham-Carter</surname></persName>
							<email>obonhamcarter@unomaha.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joe</forename><surname>Steele</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dhundy</forename><surname>Bastola</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Information Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Nebraska at Omaha</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Information Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Nebraska at Omaha</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Interdisciplinary Informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Nebraska at Omaha</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">College of Information Science &amp; Technology School of Interdisciplinary Informatics Peter</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kiewit Institute University of Nebraska Omaha</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>NE</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free genetic sequence comparisons: a review of recent approaches by word analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BEB3F339630546A86118AC6909A5C7FC</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bib/bbt052</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted: 11th April 2013; Received (in revised form) : 31st May 2013</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T04:15+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>alignment-free</term>
					<term>sequence-alignment</term>
					<term>information theory</term>
					<term>word-analysis</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Modern sequencing and genome assembly technologies have provided a wealth of data, which will soon require an analysis by comparison for discovery. Sequence alignment, a fundamental task in bioinformatics research, may be used but with some caveats. Seminal techniques and methods from dynamic programming are proving ineffective for this work owing to their inherent computational expense when processing large amounts of sequence data. These methods are prone to giving misleading information because of genetic recombination, genetic shuffling and other inherent biological events. New approaches from information theory, frequency analysis and data compression are available and provide powerful alternatives to dynamic programming. These new methods are often preferred, as their algorithms are simpler and are not affected by synteny-related problems. In this review, we provide a detailed discussion of computational tools, which stem from alignment-free methods based on statistical analysis from word frequencies. We provide several clear examples to demonstrate applications and the interpretations over several different areas of alignment-free analysis such as base ^base correlations, feature frequency profiles, compositional vectors, an improved string composition and the D 2 statistic metric. Additionally, we provide detailed discussion and an example of analysis by Lempel ^Ziv techniques from data compression.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Gene structure, function and phylogenetic relations are discovered by the basic comparison of known to unknown genetic material across organisms. Sequence comparison is pivotal to the success of basic phylogenetic and metagenomics research. For instance, large portions of common genetic material between organisms provide much evidence to suggest that they are somehow related. Furthermore, similar sequence data fuels conjecture that the associated functions are also similar.</p><p>Comparative research came from computer science that provided tools and algorithms to find specific substrings in larger sequences <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> for discovery. For instance, the Knuth-Morris-Pratt algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and the Boyer-Moore <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> algorithm were used initially in the 1970's <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> to locate regions of common DNA by exact matching of larger sequences. Later, a modified version of the Boyer-Moore <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> was applied in the 1980's. As these algorithms assumed that the input strings contained exact matches, tiny mismatches found in DNA interrupted performance. This led to algorithms for approximate pattern matching <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and others <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</p><p>Owing to the growth of inexpensive computing and improvements in sequence assembly technologies, there is now more sequence data available to bioinformatics research than ever before. Comparative genomics has been an obstacle to discovery <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref> and still manages to be a major factor in more current applications. Some of these applications include sequence assembly <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, evolutionary history comparison involving complications from synteny <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, horizontal gene transfer (HGT) discovery <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>, analysis by gene-shuffling <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and many other applications where proper sequence comparison must be used <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>Dynamic programming <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> has often been applied to comparing sequences in the aforementioned applications. As global and local alignment algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref> work base-by-base, they stand to be confused by the inherent mismatches, gaps, alternating blocks of sequence material and inversions that are easily found in genetic material. These methods may erroneously conclude that the functionally related sequences are largely unrelated, as they do not demonstrate any statistically significant alignment. Sequence length is also important to address when running an alignment from dynamic programming. For example, local and global, implemented in softwares such as ClustalW <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, have complexities of O(mn), and therefore it is clear that their resource requirements quickly escalate for larger sequences of lengths, m and n. It is often infeasible to perform comparisons of complete genomes by this approach owing to the large amount of time this would involve. For this reason, technologies requiring databases for speed such as BLAST <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, BLASTZ <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and BLAT <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> have gained popularity. Other methods to help overcome some of the limitations of dynamic programming have come from diverse fields such as cloud computing <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, distributed computing <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> and parallel computing for multiple sequence comparison <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</p><p>Frequency-based algorithms, which are driven by the statistics of word usage or similar, are becoming popular in research for discovery. This is because these approaches are not typically confused by the complexities caused by mismatches, gaps and sequence inversions that are often found between sequences for comparison <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. For example, these methods function by evaluating the informational content between sequences, and therefore alternating blocks of DNA between two sequences will not be problematic. This form of alignment does not depend on where the features are found in the sequence, only that the sequence contains the features.</p><p>Methods using frequency analysis also do not suffer from high algorithmic complexities as they are generally linear. They are, therefore, able to process larger sequences with fewer resources than dynamic programming algorithms and do not rely on having database support, as would BLAST, BLASTZ and BLAT. There is clearly a call for an alternative approach for sequence comparison done by methods that are not of dynamic programming, and therefore alignment-free methods are becoming attractive to bioinformatics research where the data are substantial and naturally dynamic.</p><p>In this article, we discuss some of the prominent methods stemming from vector or frequency-based analysis such as base-base correlations (BBC), feature frequency profiles (FFPs), compositional vectors (CVs), improved string composition and the D 2 statistic metric. These methods have been chosen for discussion because of their simplistic nature and ease of application to research. We provide clear examples for the implementation of these methods and discuss their interpretation. We also provide discussion and an example of a method inspired by the Lempel-Ziv (LZ) compression techniques. This review aims to show how these alignment-free methods are integral to the quantification and discovery of sequence function and structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BACKGROUND</head><p>Methods for differentiating sequence data by using statistical concepts (factor frequencies and approaches from data compression) have attracted much interest. In their often-cited 2003 publication, Vinga et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> reviewed some related methods, metrics and algorithmic implementations. Mantaci et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> continued by illustrating other methods recently introduced for the alignment-free comparison, which were also based on a statistical approach. The authors organize the comparison algorithms in the following basic groups: (i) count factor frequencies, (ii) data compression and (ii) edit distances or on block edit distance-a special case involving moving entire blocks of a sequence.</p><p>Recent developments and the release of new technologies from the scientific community have caused the aforementioned references to become out-dated. Here, we discuss some of the more recent statistical methods, which involve frequency data for comparison. The approaches that we cover were chosen based on their simplicity of application page 2 of 16</p><p>Bonham-Carter et al.</p><p>and can be divided into the following categories: factor frequencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, composition vectors <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, improved CVs <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, data compression <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> and common substrings <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FACTOR FREQUENCIES</head><p>Producing seminary ideas in 1948, C.E. Shannon's InformationTheory is the branch of mathematics, which is concerned with quantifying information and signal processing <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. As DNA contains observable structures and patterns <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, tools from information theory (e. To perform a k-mer study, the size of the motif is an important factor to consider. When collecting word frequencies from motifs, the size of the motif does make a difference to the results. According to Wu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, where the length of motif or window size is extensively discussed, there is a general rule of play when collecting word frequencies. When the sequences are obviously different (e.g. they are not related), then size of k-mers or window-size should be short. However, when the sequences are similar (known to be related), then the k-mers or window sizes can be longer. The reader is invited to consult the aforementioned reference for the details behind their general rule.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BBC by analysis of mutual information</head><p>Mutual information is a tool from information theory, which measures the amount of common information (or interaction) between two entities. Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> described the development of BBC, an algorithmic approach for determining sequence similarity by mutual information to infer phylogenetic relationships from complete genomes. In their work, an interval is established containing r-bases, making up strings of DNA to be used for multiple sequence comparison. In this interval, a vector is created from all possible joint probabilities of DNA pairs, as the total possible pairs ¼ 4 Ã 4 ¼ 4 2 ¼ 16. In their article, they showed that the interval containing these joint probabilities in the sequence can often be expanded to get a better measurement of the difference between sequences.</p><p>For ða 1 , a 2 , a 3 , a 4 Þ ðA, C, G, TÞ, the probability of finding base a i is denoted p i for 1 i 4. For T ij ðrÞ, the average relevance of the two-base combination (the feature) with different gaps from 1 to r (a range of r), the authors define a BBC by the following:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">T ij ðrÞ ¼ X d¼1 r p ij ðd Þ Á log 2 p ij ðdÞ p i p j<label>ð1Þ</label></formula><p>for i, j 2 f1, 2, 3, 4g where p ij ðdÞ signifies the joint probabilities (e.g. the 4 2 ¼ 16 possible length-2 DNA words, which we refer to as features) of bases i and j at a distance of d. A BBC feature constitutes a 16D feature vector, V S 1 for a sequence S 1 having a length of n 1 .</p><p>The statistical independence of two bases for a sequence of length-l is defined by p ij ðlÞ ¼ p i p j and its deviation is defined, D ij ¼ p ij ðdÞ À p i p j . Let S 1 ¼ ACGTGCTATG and S 2 ¼ ACGCGCTA. We find the joint probabilities to populate the vector, ðAA, AC, AG, AT, CA, CC, CG, CT, GA, GC, GG, GT, TA, TC, TG, TT), with the following equation for frequency, f ðW k Þ, from <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">f ðW k Þ ¼ cðW k Þ n À k þ 1 ,<label>ð2Þ</label></formula><p>where cðW k Þ signifies the number of occurrences of a length-k word in a sequence of length-n 1 . The finalized vectors are the following.</p><p>V S 1 ¼ ð0:0, 0:2, 0:0, 0:1, 0:0, 0:0, 0:1, 0:1, 0:0, 0:1, 0:0, 0:0, 0:1, 0:0, 0:3, 0:0Þ V S 2 ¼ ð0:0, 0:3, 0:0, 0:0, 0:0, 0:0, 0:5, 0:5, 0:0, 0:5, 0:0, 0:0, 0:5, 0:0, 0:0, 0:0Þ</p><p>For two sequences S 1 and S 2 having the same length n 1 , the authors define the distance H S 1 S 2 in the following equation.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">H S 1 S 2 ¼ ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi X 16 i¼1 ðV S 1 i À V S 2 i Þ 2 v u u t<label>ð3Þ</label></formula><p>By this calculation, we find that H S 1 S 2 ¼ 0:8890 for the example aforementioned. Higher values for this metric indicate a greater spread in the frequency distribution and increasing dissimilarity; however, lower values indicate levels of increasing similarity (e.g. 0 if and only if the distributions being compared are equivalent). The authors note that H S 1 S 2 satisfies the definition of a sequence distance because (i)</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">H S 1 S 2 &gt; 0 for different sequence lengths; n 1 6 ¼ n 2 ; (ii) H S 1 S 2 ¼ 0; (iii) H S 1 S 2 ¼ H S 2 S 1 (symmetric); and (iv) H S 1 S 2 H S 1 þ H S 2 (triangle inequality).</formula><p>Liu et al. used phylogenetic trees, using branch weights gained from their BBC mutual information calculations. From the sequence data of 48 different Hepatitis E viruses, they constructed a phylogenetic tree, which was consistent with previous studies by diverse approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FFPs</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, a feature frequency approach (UVWORD) was presented, which compares the DNA words from two sequences. Known as oligonucleotide profiling, the sliding-window method compared the encountered word frequencies of one sequence (the target) with another (the source). The sequence similarity was determined by how many words were common to both sequences. Word-based statistical models were also presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, which investigated the occurrence, type and frequency of overlapping and embedded DNA words for sequence comparison.</p><p>Sims et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> were interested in comparing whole genomes, even in situations where there are no common genes with high homology. To do this, they developed a variation of text compression, where the distance between word frequency profiles of two texts would be taken as a measure of dissimilarity. They substituted relative k-mer frequencies (FFP) for word frequencies.</p><p>A sliding window of size k is run through the sequence from position 1 to n À k þ 1 and counts the number of all t ¼ 4 k possible k-mers (the total number of features, for example) where four is the number of DNA bases. Although the k-mers extend themselves throughout the entire genome, the window is only allowed to span over the regions, which are completely free of sequencing gaps. The vector C ¼&lt; c 1 , . . . , c t &gt; holds the t number of raw frequency counts for all possible words of length-k and is conventionally found by the following equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">F ¼ C= X i c i :<label>ð4Þ</label></formula><p>The length of the genome must be considered carefully at this vector-forming stage. If the genomes are of approximately equal length, and a &lt;4-fold difference exists between sequences (four is the number of bases), then the method is conveniently used. However, if the sequences for comparison have extremely different lengths, then it is necessary to implement the block-FFP method, which is similar to the method described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. This pre-processing step works to ensure that diverse genome lengths do not yield misleading results. This step breaks up each sequence into smaller, manageable fragments of length-n 1 (called FFPblocks). In the case where the length of the shorter sequence is evenly divisible by the length of the longer sequence, the intervals (e.g. blocks) are made so that they have the same length as the shorter sequence. If a sequence (length n 2 ) is not evenly divisible by the shorter sequence (length n 1 ), then the total number of possible blocks for comparative analysis that can be made is n 2 modulus n 1 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A comparison by frequencies and the Jensen^Shannon Divergence test</head><p>Comparing genomes is actually comparing the sets of frequencies, which have been taken over an interval of sequence data. To make this comparison, we will follow Sims et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> approach to use the Jensen-Shannon Divergence (JSD) test. The JSD test is a close relation to the Kullback-Leibler Divergence test, an information theoretic non-symmetric divergence measure of two probability distributions, that is extensively discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>.</p><p>Once the vectors have been properly created, we are ready to apply the calculations that determine their distance apart. For two arbitrary vectors, V S 1 and V S 2 , prepared from sequences S 1 and S 2 for t, the number of features collected, the JSD is given below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">JSðV S 1 , V S 2 Þ ¼ 1 2 KLðV S 1 , V M Þ þ 1 2 KLðV S 2 , V M Þ,<label>ð5Þ</label></formula><p>where,</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">V M i ¼ V S 1 i þ V S 2 i 2<label>ð6Þ</label></formula><p>for i ¼ f1, . . . , tg and KL is the Kullback-Leibler Divergence, below.</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">KLðV S 1 , V M Þ ¼ X t i¼1 V S 1 i log 2 V S 1 i V M i ,<label>ð7Þ</label></formula><p>where t is the number of features. We now return to our earlier example of the two sequences S 1 ¼ ACGTGCTATG and S 2 ¼ ACGCGCTA, which we compared by this JSD analysis. In this example, we populate vectors for these sequences using all length-2 words (2mers) in the sequences. The possible 2mers are ordered in the following order: AA, AC, AG, AT, CA, CC, CG, CT, GA, GC, GG, GT, TA, TC, TG, TT:</p><p>The FFP vectors V S 1 and V S 2 are created and populated by all available 2mers from sequences S 1 and S 2 .</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">V S 1 ¼&lt; 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 0, 1, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 1, 0, 2, 0 &gt; Ã 1 9 V S 2 ¼&lt; 0, 1, 0, 0, 0, 0, 2, 1, 0, 2, 0, 0, 1, 0, 0, 0 &gt; Ã 1 7</formula><p>At each position i of both vectors, we apply</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">V M i ¼ V S 1 i þV S 2 i 2</formula><p>to get an average vector V M . The calculated values for all three vectors are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>.</p><p>To help the reader to keep track of the vectors and their frequencies at each position, we offer Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>. We apply vectors V S 1 and V M (and then vectors V S 2 and V M ) to Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">7</ref>), which we illustrate below.</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">KLðV S 1 , V M Þ ¼ X t i¼1 V S 1 i log 2 V S 1 i V M i ¼ 1 9 Ã log 2 1 9 8 63 þ 1 9 Ã log 2 1 9 1 18 ¼ 1 9 Ã log 2 1 9 8 63 þ 1 9 Ã log 2 1 9 1 18 þ 1 9 Ã log 2 1 9 25 126 þ 1 9 Ã log 2 1 9 1 18 þ 1 9 Ã log 2 1 9 8 63 þ 2 9 Ã log 2 2 9 1 9 ¼ 0:1943</formula><p>Following this theme for sequence S 2 (vector</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">V S 2 ), we find that KLðV S 2 , V M Þ ¼ 0:3734. JSðV S 1 , V S 2 Þ ¼ 1 2 KLðV S 1 , V M Þ þ 1 2 KLðV S 2 , V M Þ ¼ 1 2 Ã 0:1943 ð Þþ 1 2 Ã 0:3734 ð Þ ¼ 0:2839</formula><p>Provided the base 2 logarithm is used, the JSD is bounded below by 0 and 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. Higher values indicate increasing dissimilarity, but lower values indicate increasing similarity (e.g. 0 if and only if the distributions are identical). As JSðV S 1 , V S 2 Þ ¼ 0:2839 is close to zero, we conclude that the sequences S 1 and S 2 are similar by this test.</p><p>Sims et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> reconstructed phylogenies from concatenated mammalian 'intronic genomes' by this method and found that their method closely reflected the accepted evolutionary history and agreed to results from a codon-sequence-based alignment technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Suffix trees by k-mer frequencies</head><p>The abundance of sequence noise (e.g. insertions, mismatches and similar) often necessitates frequency-based analysis. Similar to the work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> earlier in the text, another method of applying frequency data have been extensively explored by Soares et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> to measure Euclidean distance between sequence data. When collecting frequency data, typically a window is opened at the beginning of the sequence, and the frequencies are found for all encountered words. The authors depart from this method by presenting a new approach that determines a single optimal word length (k-mers) from which to generate a frequency distribution for application to suffix trees.</p><p>To collect these optimal k-mer frequencies, Soares et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> began by determining all words in the DNA alphabet (e.g. {A,C,G,T}) of length-k. An optimal resolution range of k-mers for the given  set of genomes was described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> and later applied to the work of Soares et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> for instance, k H max ¼ log 4 ðn 1 Þ for a sequence of length-n 1 . To find a value applicable to all sequences under analysis, we choose n 1 as the length of the greater sequence and K as the smaller integer greater than log 4 ðmÞ. For m sequences of different lengths, the peak value of word length (K) that is applicable to all sequences of the study is described by the following two equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">n 1 ¼ maxflengthðS i Þ, 1 i mg; K ¼ log 4 ðn 1 Þ AE Ç</formula><p>In the logarithmic equation, L is given the smallest integer not less than the calculated value. The exhaustive lists of DNA L-words for n sequences were created by combinatorial means. For words of length-L, the size of the list can be described mathematically: t ¼ 4 L . The frequencies of these words are similarly found as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. Once amassed, they are added to an n Â t matrix to create a global profile of all L-word frequencies of all input sequences. Next is the development of the genetic distance for the suffix trees. This pairwise standard Euclidean distance between pairs of sequences is calculated by the following:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">SEDðS 1 , S 2 Þ ¼ ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi X w2t ðf S 1 w À f S 2 w Þ 2 r<label>ð8Þ</label></formula><p>for w, representing the k-mer and t representing the exhaustive list of words, respectively, and f S i w represents the relative frequency of w in the sequence S i . These values may be applied to suffix trees for convenient sequence analysis across large sets of sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Composition vectors based on k-mer frequencies</head><p>There are two main string composition vectors that we will discuss; the CV and the complete composition vector (CCV). Discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>, a k-mer frequency CV for a genomic sequence is a distribution of frequencies of length-k motifs, which are used for comparison across sequences. The CV method contains motif frequencies of the same length, whereas the CCVs contain motif frequencies of unequal length. The basic steps of creating CVs are the following: (i) find the frequencies of the motifs in a sequence, (ii) create a vector by organizing the frequencies in some order, (iii) compute the distance between every two composition vectors to form a distance matrix, and optionally (iv) construct the phylogenic tree based on the differences. This last step is not essential but may be helpful when evaluating the degree of closeness between a set of sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Creation of CompositionVectors (CVs, CCVs)</head><p>The creation of a CCV is similar to that of a CV except that the input frequencies are made from strings of differing lengths. Despite its extra computational expense, the CCV method was found to provide finer evolutionary information than the CV method <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>.</p><p>Following the discussion from <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32]</ref>, we define S 1 to be a sequence consisting of n 1 nucleotides and let f ða 1 . . . a k Þ to be the observed frequency of the length-k motif in S 1 . We define a i for 1 i k to be a nucleotide such that a i 2 {A, C, G, T} for 1 k &lt; n 1 . Next, for some constant K, the largest string length we consider, we define</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">V S 1 ¼ ðf 1 , f 2 , . . . , f 4 K Þ as the combined vector.</formula><p>Finally, we define V S ¼ ðS 1 , S 2 , . . . , S K Þ as the combined vector. The vectors, V S 1 and V S , reflect both random mutation and selection. Lu et al. noted that there is an underestimation of selective evolution for both these vectors when the data are normalized according to Equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, which is also discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>. For the observed frequency of a 1 ; a 2 ; Á Á Á ; a k , the normalizing equation is described by the following:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">aða 1 . . . a k Þ ¼ f ða 1 . . . a k Þ À f e ða 1 . . . a k Þ f e ða 1 . . . a k Þ<label>ð9Þ</label></formula><p>where f e represents the expected frequency and is defined by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">f e ða 1 . . . a k Þ ¼ f ða 1 . . . a kÀ1 Þf ða 2 . . . a k Þ f ða 2 . . . a kÀ1 Þ Â ðn 1 À k þ 1Þðn 1 À k þ 3Þ ðn 1 À k þ 2Þ 2 :</formula><p>for k ! 3 and f e ða 1 . . . a k Þ. Lu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> note that this normalization method underestimates the actual reality of the data. Next, we describe their modified method, which overcomes this problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Creation of improved CCVs</head><p>To overcome this setback, Lu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> propose an improvement to CVs and CCVs. The improved CCV (ICCV) is made assuming that the sequence bases all occur with equal probability, according to the expected frequency of a k-mer string.</p><p>The variance of frequency of a given sequence S 1 of length-n 1 is also based on this assumption. We first define the expected motif frequencies and their variance in the vectors. For any given k-mer, a position in the sequence is given as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">x i ¼ 1, if the kÀmer begins at position i 0, otherwise &amp; for integer i such that 1 i ðn 1 À k þ 1Þ</formula><p>. This upper bound is the maximum observed frequency for a string a 1 Á Á Á a k in S 1 . Therefore, it can be shown that</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">f ða 1 Á Á Á a k Þ ¼ X n 1 Àkþ1 i¼1 x i :<label>ð10Þ</label></formula><p>The expectation and variance of f ða 1 Á Á Á a k Þ are described in the following equations.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">E½f ða 1 Á Á Á a k Þ ¼ X n 1 Àkþ1 i¼1 E½x i ¼ n 1 À k þ 1 4 k<label>ð11Þ</label></formula><p>and the variance;</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">Var½f ða 1 Á Á Á a k Þ ¼ n 1 À k þ 1 4 k ð1 À 1 4 k Þ À 2 4 2k ðk À 1Þðn 1 À 3 2 k þ 1Þ þ 2 4 k X kÀ1 i¼1 ðn 1 À k þ 1 À tÞ J r 4 t ,</formula><p>where J r , is defined by the following.</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">J r ¼ 1, if ða 1 Á Á Á a kÀr Þ ¼ ða rþ1 Á Á Á a k Þ 0, otherwise &amp;</formula><p>for integer r such that 1 r k À 1. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> for a full derivation. One of the problems with the original CV and CCV concerns the denominator, which requires a square root operation without which Lu et al. warn of a problem of over-estimation. To mitigate the over-estimation problem, the authors apply the data's expectation and variance to the normalizing equation given later in the text and complete the construction of the ICCV. The normalization of each observed frequency of a k-mer string, k norm is given by the following equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">k norm ¼ f ða 1 Á Á Á a k Þ À E½ða 1 Á Á Á a k Þ ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi Var½f ða 1 Á Á Á a k Þ p<label>ð12Þ</label></formula><p>for k ! 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distance measurement</head><p>We next discuss how the distance between vectors is measured. For two sequences, S 1 and S 2 , let their vectors be defined,</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">V S 1 ¼ ða 1 , a 2 , Á Á Á , a k Þ of length-k and V S 2 ¼ ðb 1 , b 2 , Á Á Á , b k Þ, also of length-k.</formula><p>We define the normalized distance between the vectors by the following:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">DðV S 1 , V S 2 Þ ¼ 1 À CðV S 1 , V S 2 Þ 2 ,<label>ð13Þ</label></formula><p>where CðV S 1 , V S 2 Þ is the cosine distance of the angle between V S 1 and V S 2 and is described by the following.</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">CðV S 1 , V S 2 Þ ¼ P k i¼1 a i Á b i ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi P k i¼1 a 2 i Á P k i¼1 b 2 i s<label>ð14Þ</label></formula><p>Lu et al. show that the ICCV method fixes the observed overestimation problems with the previous method and generates more accurate and robust results. They also show that its results are consistent with methods based on alignment by dynamic programming in phylogeny.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A revised string composition method</head><p>Chan et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> revisit the composition vector method and apply an analysis of entropy from information theory and operations research. Their method begins by finding the frequencies of each base of a k-string sequence. For example, from ACTGCTATGC, the base frequencies are the following: f ðAÞ ¼ 1  5 ; f ðCÞ ¼ 3 10 ; f ðGÞ ¼ 1 5 ; f ðTÞ ¼ 3 10 : The second step is to estimate the expected frequency q(u) for each k-string. For this step, the authors suggested determining the relationship between qðÁÞ and f ðÁÞ by maximizing the following system of equations from Hua et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>. Here, the entropy in qðÁÞ is maximized given the frequency f(v) for all ðk À 1Þ-strings v.</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">qðvAÞ þ qðvCÞ þ qðvGÞ þ qðvTÞ ¼ f ðvÞ, qðAvÞ þ qðCvÞ þ qðGvÞ þ qðTvÞ ¼ f ðvÞ &amp;<label>ð15Þ</label></formula><p>Chan et al. depart from the work of Hua et al. by making no assumptions between qðÁÞ and f ðÁÞ. Instead, they maximized the following equations, which estimate the expected frequencies q(u). for k ! 3, which was introduced by, Qi et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref> and,</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">qðLwRÞ ¼ f ðLÞf ðwRÞ þ f ðLwÞðRÞ 2<label>ð17Þ</label></formula><p>for k ! 2, from Yu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref>. For any k-string u, L and R represent the left and right nucleotides of the word and w represents the middle ðk À 2Þ-string located between them. In the second equation, all these elements are assumed to occur independently. From these equations, the authors created a new system of equations (later in the text) to solve where the right-hand side concerns sequence frequencies and the left-hand side concerns the estimations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">qðvAÞ þ qðvCÞ þ qðvGÞ þ qðvTÞ ¼ f ðLwÞ f ðwÞ f ðwAÞ þ f ðwCÞ þ f ðwGÞ þ f ðwTÞ Â Ã qðAvÞ þ qðCvÞ þ qðGvÞ þ qðTvÞ ¼ f ðxRÞ f ðxÞ f ðAxÞ þ f ðCxÞ þ f ðGxÞ þ f ðTxÞ Â Ã : 8 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; :<label>ð18Þ</label></formula><p>When this system is maximized, Chan et al.</p><p>[31] note that the system generates a set of all possible estimation formulas qðÁÞ from which one can be selected to maximize the entropy. In general, from any existing estimation formula qðÁÞ given in terms of f ðÁÞ, the authors note that the set of constraints such as the following can be derived:</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">qðvAÞ þ qðvCÞ þ qðvGÞ þ qðvTÞ ¼ lðvÞ, qðAvÞ þ qðCvÞ þ qðGvÞ þ qðTvÞ ¼ rðvÞ &amp;<label>ð19Þ</label></formula><p>where the left-and right-side frequency values, l(v) and r(v) are derived from frequency information (f(v)) for each length-ðm À 1Þ motif v. To obtain the unique q(u) for all u, the following optimization problem is solved: maximize : À X 4 k i¼1 q i log q i subject to : q i satisfies the system of equations q i ! 0 for all i &amp; where Àq i log q i is Shannon's entropy calculation.</p><p>The authors apply this information to phylogenetic tree analysis in a similar fashion as we saw in Lu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. Maximum Entropy Principle. After solving the problem aforementioned, a system of noise estimation formulas is provided. Note: a motif appears as the following: ða 1 Á Á Á a m a n Á Á Á a k Þ and can be split into to sub words.</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">q MEP ða 1 Á Á Á a m a n Á Á Á a k Þ ¼ lða 1 Á Á Á a m Þrða n Á Á Á a k Þ s ,<label>ð20Þ</label></formula><p>where, q MEP is the maximized entropy principle score for the sequence data and,</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">s ¼ X L2fA, C, G, Tg lða 1 Á Á Á a m Þ ¼ X R2fA, C, G, Tg rða n Á Á Á a k Þ:<label>ð21Þ</label></formula><p>We note that q MEP ¼ 0 if s ¼ 0 and that lðÁÞ and rðÁÞ are parametric functions. Different lðÁÞ and rðÁÞ will give different estimation formulas and will have varying levels of success. The authors applied this test to create phylogenetic trees from simulated data sets.</p><p>Their results showed differentiation of 'closely related' sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D 2 statistic</head><p>The statistic D 2 , is the number of approximate word matches of length k between sequences</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">S 1 ¼ ða 1 , . . . , a k Þ and S 2 ¼ ðb 1 , . . . , b k Þ,</formula><p>with a i and b j belonging to an alphabet A (in this case, the DNA bases), which is distributed according to a letter distribution parameterized by Z <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>. This statistic is applied to two populations of differing means, but identical dispersion matrices <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref>, to determine distance. Recently, the statistic has evolved to provide more exact approximations by asymptotic regimes for uniform and non-uniform distributions <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59]</ref>. Mathematically, the D 2 statistic is defined by the following. From <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref>, given sequences</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">S 1 ¼ ða 1 , . . . , a n 1 Þ of length-n 1 and S 2 ¼ ðb 1 , . . . , b n 2 Þ of length- n 2 and W ¼ fw 1 , . . . , w k g 2 A k , then D 2 is</formula><p>defined by the following:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">D 2 ¼ X W2A k C s 1 ðWÞC s 2 ðWÞ ð<label>22Þ</label></formula><p>where C s i ðWÞ is the number of occurrences of W in sequence S i . The D2Z statistic <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref> was developed to compare gene regulatory sequences and offered an improvement in performance to D 2 , but could still fail due to noise complications <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60]</ref>. To combat this problem of noise, Reinert et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref>  Reinert et al. also proposed a second statistic, D Ã 2 , which we shall presently define. To introduce this statistic, we replace p(a), the unobserved feature probabilities, by pðaÞ (the observed) for the relative count of letter a in the concatenation of the two sequences that are based on the assumption that the two sequences are independent. We note that these sequences are both independent and contain identically distributed (i.i.d.) bases. The estimated probability of occurrence of W ¼ fw 1 , . . . , w k g is obtained by pW ¼ Q k i¼1 pw i . We now define D Ã 2 by the following.</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">D Ã 2 ¼ X W2A k Cs 1 ðWÞ Cs 2 ðWÞ ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi ñ1 ñ2 p pW<label>ð24Þ</label></formula><p>The authors found that the D Ã 2 statistic outperformed both the D 2 and D S 2 statistics in terms of accurate detection of relatedness between two sequences. The statistical power of both D Ã 2 and D S 2 increases with sequence length and tends to 1 as the sequence length tends to infinity under a common motif model. When applied to organizing sequence reads of next-generation sequence assembly tasks, and to phylogeny tasks, the D S 2 statistic provided a powerful alignment-free comparison tool <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref>. However, when studying phenomena in the patten transfer model such as HGT, the power of these statistics declines and converges to a limit that is generally &lt;1 as the sequence length tends to infinity. The primary reason for this limitation is that the means of the word counts in these statistics eventually become increasingly similar to each other. This resemblance works to desensitize the detection of patterns between the sequences.</p><p>To improve the detection of relationships across sequences using alignment-free methods in the pattern transfer model, Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref> developed new statistics (T Ã , T S and T Ã sum , described later in the text), which they claim have a better statistical power. The authors present them with simulations to demonstrate their power and to show that they are more appropriate for applications where long sequence-lengths are a concern.</p><p>Based on approximating the mean by a sample mean, the approach of the new statistic is to partition a long sequence of length-n 1 into consecutive nonoverlapping (discrete) subintervals of length-r,</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">d sub ¼ n 1 r Ä Å</formula><p>. Then, the D Ã 2 and D S 2 values are calculated over each i th subinterval for word counts w and are denoted DðiÞ Ã 2 and DðiÞ S 2 , respectively. For, two sequences of length n 1 where, S 1 ¼ fa 1 , . . . , a k g and S 2 ¼ fb 1 , . . . , b k g, these statistics are defined by the following equations.</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">T Ã ¼ X d sub i¼1 D Ã 2 ðiÞ ð<label>25Þ</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">T S ¼ X d sub i¼1 D S 2 ðiÞ ð<label>26Þ</label></formula><p>The final statistic from <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref> is drawn over two sequences S 1 and S 2 of lengths n 1 and n 2 , respectively, to conclude the degree of relatedness.</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">T Ã sum ¼ X n 1 Àkþ1 i¼1 S Ã 1i þ X n 2 Àkþ1 i¼1 S Ã 2i<label>ð27Þ</label></formula><p>for,</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">S Ã 1i ¼ max f1 j n 1 Àkþ1g M Ã ½i, j, k ð 28Þ</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">S Ã 2i ¼ max f1 i n 1 Àkþ1g M Ã ½i, j, k ð<label>29Þ</label></formula><p>where,</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">M Ã ½i, j, k ¼ D Ã 2 ðS 1 ½i, i þ k À 1, S 2 ½j, j þ k À 1Þ<label>ð30Þ</label></formula><p>Although D Ã 2 and D S 2 are generally more powerful statistics than T Ã sum and T s sum for the common motif model, this is not the case for studies concerning the pattern transfer model. For this reason, the statistics presented by Liu et al. are desirable in pattern transfer model applications when the sequence data are long.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DATA COMPRESSION AND DICTIONARIES</head><p>Alignment-free methods, involving data compression and dictionaries, are based on the idea that the more similar two sequences are to each other, then the better one sequence can be created from the parts of another. Inspired by LZ compression technologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>, we offer an example of sequence comparison, from Otu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>.</p><p>For the sequences S 1 , S 2 and S Q , we define</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">H E ðS 1 Þ, H E ðS 2 Þ and H E ðS Q Þ to</formula><p>be the exhaustive sets of all words found using an approach from LZ-compression. We then analyze the sets of sequence histories to determine how much of one sequence can be built out of the sequence histories of another. We define c H ðÁÞ to be the number of components in a history of a sequence S and c min ðfc H ðSÞg over all histories of S.</p><p>For S 1 and S 2 , we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">c min ðS 1 S Q Þ c min ðS 1 Þ þ c min ðS Q Þ,</formula><p>by the sub-additivity of the LZ-complexity. To compute the closest similarity of S 1 and S Q , dðS 1 , S Q Þ, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">S 2 to S Q , dðS 2 , S Q Þ, we take the smallest value of maxfc min ðS 1 S Q Þ À c min ðS 1 Þ, c min ðS Q S 1 Þ À c min ðS Q Þ} and maxfc min ðS 2 S Q Þ À c min ðS 2 Þ, c min ðS Q S 2 Þ Àc min ðS Q Þ}, respectively.</formula><p>Compare the sequence similarity of S 1 to S Q and S 2 to S Q . We first find the sequence histories to compare distances. We introduce an example to demonstrate how this is performed.</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">S 1 = ATGGC S 2 = ACGGT S Q = ATGGC • S 1 = ATGGC -H E (S 1 ) = A,T, G, GC -c min (S 1 ) = 4 • S 2 = ACGGT -H E (S 2 ) = A, C, G, GT -c min (S 2 ) = 4 • S Q = ATGGC -H E (S Q ) = A, T, G, GC -c min (S Q ) = 4 • S 1 S Q = ATGGCATGGC -A, T, G, GC, ATGGC -c min (XS Q ) = c min (S Q S 1 ) = 5 • S 2 S Q = ACGGTATGGC -A, , C G, GT, AT, GGC -c min (S 2 S Q ) = c min (S Q S 2 ) = 6 • d(S 1 , S Q ) = max {c min (S 1 S Q ) -c min (S 1 ), c min (QS 1 ) -c min (S Q )} =1 • d(S 2 , S Q ) = max {c min (S 2 S Q ) -c min (S 2 ), c min (S Q S 2 ) -c min (S Q )} =2</formula><p>By the author's method, we conclude that S 1 and S Q are more similar, as 1</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">¼ dðS 1 , S Q Þ &lt; dðS 2 , S Q Þ ¼ 2.</formula><p>The authors used this method to populate phylogenetic trees from simulated sequences to show clusterings of 'related' sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Text compression algorithms</head><p>Data compression is nearly out of the scope of this article; however, they are worth mentioning because they also provide an alignment-free approach to comparing sequence data. These general purpose compression algorithms may be based on the Ziv and Lempel <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref> methods (as seen earlier in the text). Recent advances have been developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68]</ref>. Cao et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> proposed a memory-based algorithm called expert model to compress DNA by applying statistical information, gained from previous encounters of a particular symbol.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Average common substring</head><p>Ulitsky et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> built on information theoretic tools, such as Kullback-Leibler relative entropy, to find a distance between entire genomes, even if their lengths vary. The average common substring measure that they proposed is based on computing the average lengths of maximum common substrings. They used these average lengths between the sequences to construct phylogenetic trees from an efficient algorithm.</p><p>Let S 1 and S 2 be sequences, of lengths n 1 and n 2 where,</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">S 1 ¼ ða 1 , . . . , a n 1 Þ and S 2 ¼ ðb 1 , . . . , b n 2 Þ.</formula><p>For any position i, let r(i) be the length of longest substring in S 1 that exactly matches a substring in S 2 starting at some position j. These lengths r(i) are averaged to get a measure, LðS 1 , S 2 Þ ¼ P n i¼1 rðiÞ=n 1 . As LðS 1 , S 2 Þ represents a common sequence found in both sequences, then the longer it is, the more similar the sequences are to each other. This value is only a similarity measure and must still be converted to a distance value. The inverse is taken to get the distance, and then a 'correction term' is subtracted to ensure that the distance dðS 1 , S 1 Þ ¼ 0 (will always be zero). This allows for,</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">dðS 1 , S 2 Þ ¼ log n 2 LðS 1 , S 2 Þ À log n 1 LðS 1 , S 1 Þ where LðS 1 , S 1 Þ ¼ n 1 2 to provide the correctional term, 2 Á logðn 1 Þ</formula><p>n 1 , which converges to 0 as n 1 ! 1. As the measure, dðS 1 , S 2 Þ is not symmetric, the authors compute the final average common substring measurement between the two strings, d s ðS 1 , S 2 Þ by the following.</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">d s ðS 1 , S 2 Þ ¼ d s ðS 2 , S 1 Þ ¼ dðS 1 , S 2 Þ þ dðS 2 , S 1 Þ 2<label>ð31Þ</label></formula><p>We now show how to apply this method to determine the distance between two sequences. Let S 1 ¼ ACGTGCTATG and S 2 ¼ ACGCGCTA, of lengths n 1 ¼ 10 and n 2 ¼ 8, the method finds all common substrings as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>page 10 of 16</head><p>Bonham-Carter et al.</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">LðS 1 , S 2 Þ ¼ ð1 þ 2 þ 3Þ þ ð1Þ þ ð1 þ 2 þ 3 þ 4Þ þ ð1Þ þ ð1Þ<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">¼ 19 10 ¼ 1:9</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">LðS 1 , S 1 Þ ¼ 1 þ 2 þ 3 þ 4 þ 5 þ 6 þ 7 þ 8 þ 9 þ 10 10 ¼ 55 10 ¼ 5:5</formula><p>Then the distance between the two sequences is</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">dðS 1 , S 2 Þ ¼ log 8 1:9 À log 10 5:5 ¼ 0:293</formula><p>Similarly, we can calculate DðB, AÞ as follows: For our example aforementioned, where</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">LðS 2 , S 1 Þ ¼ ð1 þ 2 þ 3Þ þ ð1Þ þ ð1 þ 2 þ 3 þ 4Þ þ ð1Þ þ ð1Þ 8 ¼ 19 8 ¼ 2:375, LðS 2 , S 2 Þ ¼ 1 þ 2 þ 3 þ 4 þ 5 þ 6 þ 7 þ</formula><formula xml:id="formula_56">d s ðS 1 , S 2 Þ is not symmetric, the symmetric distance is d s ðS 1 , S 2 Þ ¼ d s ðS 2 , S 1 Þ ¼ dðS 1 , S 2 ÞþdðS 2 , S 1 Þ 2 ¼ 0:293þ0:220 2</formula><p>¼ 0:257. This value can be used as a weight for a sequence in a phylogenetic tree to show relations between sequences of a set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPLICATIONS OF ALIGNMENT-FREE METHODS Biological data and sequence assembly</head><p>In genetic sequence assembly work, alignment technologies are important for determining the adjacency of reads (or contigs which are partially combined reads) to reconstruct the original sequence. During a typical de novo assembly task, a sequencing machine may split the genome into many millions (trillions) of reads that must be reassembled like from a jigsaw puzzle. This reconstruction task is computationally intensive, as each piece must be compared with every other piece in the pool to determine adjacency. This task is frustrated when there are foreign reads of other sequences to be assembled in the same data pool. The extra sequence data serve to massively broaden the search space when determining the adjacency of a read, as there are many more comparison operations to perform. To reduce the workload of the assembly project, it is therefore desirable to place all related reads into a unique groups (bins) and apply the main assembly algorithms to each organism separately.</p><p>A novel approach, requiring no database support, was introduced by <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[69,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">70]</ref> to order the organisms in the pool into separate bins. The authors' method creates CVs from restriction sites <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">[71]</ref> to determine inter-sequence relatedness and place the sequences from the mixed pool into separate groups. This type of proposed alignment is for a global analysis, as it is able to process and compare sequences in a pool of arbitrarily size. They applied their work to the sequence assembly reads and contigs of Bifidobacterium longum, Mycobacterium bovis, Clostridium tetani, Staphylococcus aureus, Burkholderia pseudomallei and Campylobacter jejuni. Based on the similarity of proportional values contained in the CVs, the authors were able to differentiate the sequence material by organism.</p><p>The method uses spectrum sets that are lists of motifs made up of permutations of restriction enzymes, which are specific and unique sites in DNA where enzymes are able to cleave. To create a spectrum set from the bacterial restriction site, GAATTC, we observe that the motif contains, two A 0 s, two T 0 s, one C and one G. A spectrum set contains all motifs, which have exactly the same number of each base. For example, for the bacterial restriction site, GAATTC, there are 156 motifs in the spectrum set that have the same base composition. A vector of length-156 is constructed from the proportions of each of these motifs, which are contained in the sequence data. For example, to populate the vector V S 1 of the motif proportions of w i for i ¼ f1, . . . , 156g for sequence S 1 of length-n 1 , the following equation is used, </p><formula xml:id="formula_57">V S 1 ¼ cðw i Þ Ã jw i j n 1 ,<label>ð32Þ</label></formula><p>where cðÁÞ represents the number of occurrences of the motif in the sequence. This equation serves to normalize the proportions so that the values can be compared across diverse data sets. The authors noted that similar sequence data gave rise to similar vectors that they used to organize the sequence data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chromosomal data and phylogeny</head><p>In addition, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref>, it was shown that the method could also be applied to create phylogenetic trees, which were extremely similar to trees created by NCBI's taxonomy tree making software. In this work, they used chromosomal sequences of arbitrarily chosen organisms (Caenorhabditis elegans, Canis lupus familiaris, Drosophila melanogaster, Mus musculus, Mycoplasma hyorhinis, Oryctolagus cuniculus and Rattus norvegicus) and built a tree that replicated that of NCBI's taxonomy analysis software (available at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/guide/taxonomy/).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HGT</head><p>HGT is the phenomenon where genetic material is shared between unrelated organisms. Evolutionary <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref> and Phylogenetic studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">[73]</ref> have observed common material between unrelated bacterial organisms, which suggests a parallel evolutionary history. The discovery of similar regions of DNA between two enormous genomes is not a trivial task, and therefore alignment-free methods have proven to be helpful in this field. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, the authors present Alignment-Free Local Homology (alfy), a method to determine HGT by an alignment-free approach.</p><p>As determining evolutionary distances from word frequency data is a non-trivial task, the authors report that their method is conveniently able to make this determination. We cite and discuss the method and example presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> where the query sequence, denoted as S Q of Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">3</ref>, is compared with the subject sequence, S 1 . For each position in the query S Q , the alfy algorithm determines the shortest substring that starts in query, which is absent from the subject sequence.</p><p>In Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">4</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_7">5</ref>, this comparison task is shown by a string of numbers (match scores), which show the length of the substring starting in (S Q ) that are absent in (S 1 ). If the consecutive intervals created by these matching scores are wide (e.g. long strings of uninterrupted consecutive integers), then the sequences are closely related (similar); however, if the intervals are generally short, then the sequences are not closely related (dissimilar).</p><p>We cite an example from another study concerning HGT by the same authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. This method is applied to locating regions of common genetic material in Escherichia coli and recombinant HIV-1 strains. This method is similar because it locates local regions in subject sequences that are closely related to the query sequence. In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">6</ref>, sequences S 1 to S 3 are the subjects and S Q is the query. We find which parts of S Q most closely resemble the subject sequences. The sections of sequence material are written in an interval notation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">S Q ½1, 2 ¼ TA matches S 3 ½1, 2, S Q ½3, 4 ¼ GC matches S 2 ½1, 2.</formula><p>By this system, we claim that S Q ½1, 2 is most closely related to S 3 , and S Q ½3, 4 is most closely related to S 2 .</p><p>During the sequence comparison task of query-tosubject, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, the authors denote the length of the To compare sequences, we find the shortest sequence in the query (S Q ), which is absent from a subject.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_59">p jQj À p þ 1. For example, in Table 6, H 1, 1 ¼ T ¼ 1; H 2, 1 ¼ T ¼ 1; H 3, 1 ¼ TAG ¼ 3; and H 1 ¼ max f1, 1, 3g ¼ 3.</formula><p>Conversely, the longest subject subsequences, which start at Q½p are found in a subject sequence, are denoted by S p ¼ fS i 2 Sjh i, p ¼ H p g. Based on these properties, the authors note that the longest sequence from Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">6</ref> is S 3 (the most similar subject to sequence S Q ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ADVANTAGES AND DISADVANTAGES OF METHODS</head><p>The method that an algorithm uses to gain its statistical data for an analysis is an important part of the whole operation. A fault at this stage would travel throughout the comparison task and upset the conclusion. In this section, we describe the generation of the motif frequency distributions, and we discuss how this initial statistical work may not always be appropriate for a particular data set.</p><p>The methods of 'Factor Frequencies' section are powerful methods to use in sequence comparison tasks, as they do not concern the location of the motifs they analyze. Their algorithms are efficient, as they are generally of a linear complexity. They contrast to the general high complexity of the algorithms that are based on dynamic programming. The results of factor frequency methods are adaptable and can be conveniently applied to an analysis by mutual information ('A comparison by frequencies and the Jensen-Shannon Divergence test' section), k-mers ('Suffix trees by k-mer frequencies' section) or by CVs ('Composition vectors based on k-mer frequencies' and 'A revised string composition method sections').</p><p>As the factor frequency methods are generated by word occurrences in a sequence, it important to choose words that are not likely to commonly appear in a sequence. As a general rule in DNA, the shorter the word, then the more likely it will appear randomly in a sequence. In 'BBC by analysis of mutual information' and 'A comparison by frequencies and the Jensen-Shannon Divergence test' section, vectors were created out of pairs of DNA bases. Although this may be an simple way to illustrate the concept, frequencies made up of these short pairs have less meaning than frequencies made up by longer words because any particular DNA pair has a probability of 1  4 2 ¼ 1 16 to occur randomly. We note that for sequences that are largely dissimilar, then shorter words (hence shorter CVs) should be used to create the feature frequency distributions. However, longer words, (hence, longer CVs, assuming an exhaustive list of motifs) may be used when the sequences are known to be similar, such as when they are related, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. The methods of 'Factor Frequencies' section are well suited for this application using both long and short motifs. They also function well when the location of the motif in the sequence is not important, as in the case of synteny.</p><p>Unlike the approaches of 'Factor Frequencies' section where the frequency distributions were generated by user-specified motifs, the methods of 'Data Compression and Dictionaries' section 'choose' their own sizes of words for their sequence comparison task. In the methods proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> (LZ compression based) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> (HGT), the word size is not a parameter set by the researcher. These kinds of algorithms are useful to comparison tasks where it is not clear about the 'correct' kinds of motifs to employ. In the case of factor frequency methods, when designing a list of motifs from which to generate a frequency distribution, an exhaustive list is likely used. As we have previously mentioned, the longer the motif, the larger the exhaustive list. Finding the frequencies of these extra motifs may add additional computational time to the task. Therefore, compression-based methods may be more suitable to comparisons where longer motifs are desirable, such as when the sequences are similar. This might be because the words of varying size and composition will be more similar across related sequences. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p>Comparison of sequence data represents a large problem in computational biology research. Discovery is often frustrated by obstacles such as synteny or other forms of genetic recombination, preventing methods of dynamic programming from working effectively. We provide a summary of the methods that we have discussed in Table <ref type="table">7</ref>, listed by sections, references and authors. When confronted with a large number of comparison tasks, which are unsuitable for traditional forms of alignment from dynamic programming, these alignment-free methods may be the only feasible approach for completing the tasks to permit discovery. This is because the alignment-free methods do not function based on the location of genes or regions in each sequence. When the location of these regions is not important for the analysis, alignment-free methods like the ones included in the present review may accomplish the goal of comparing genetic sequences.</p><p>As there is more sequence data available today than ever before, there are many more projects that depend on sequence comparison. For discovery to be made, this work will have to be done by other technologies such as those based on dynamic programming, which have obvious limitations. Alignment-free methods generally require less computational resources and use algorithms that are typically of linear complexity. These incorporated elements are appropriate for advancing comparative bioinformatics research.</p><p>It is our hope that this review provides useful information for researchers who are studying alignment-free methods and are using them in the analysis of genomic sequences and metagenomes. As the mathematical aspects of the aforementioned tools are themselves an obstacle, it is also our hope that this review helps to introduce the reader to some of the more complicated calculations that are associated with these alignment-free tools for discovery. Furthermore, we envisage that this review will serve as a useful reference in identifying open problems and driving future research in sequence comparison.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key Points</head><p>Dynamic programming methods are inappropriate for the voluminous. Statistical methods from information theory and other areas of mathematics are now used to conveniently differentiate sequence data based on extracted motif distributions. We review popular methods of comparing word distributions between sequences to infer distance. Application of these sequence comparison methods extend to the following: sequence assembly, phylogeny, HGT and many other areas where sequence separation is necessary.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>0</head><label></label><figDesc>The elements of combined vector M by index are also shown. Frequencies of each 2mer are made by normalizing the occurrences of each 2mer in S 1 and S 2 , respectively, by the total number of 2mer occurrences in each sequence.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>g. mutual entropy et al.) are appropriate for frequency analysis. Many of these methods break each sequence for comparison into numeric parts such as frequencies from the occurrence of</figDesc><table /><note><p>types of words or k-mers (substrings of length k) occurring in the sequences. If two sequences are similar, then the derived k-mer frequencies would have similar distributions to reflect this likeness. If the sequences are different, then so are the frequency distributions.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Positions 1 through 16 of the table of vectors for V S 1 from S 1 ¼ ACGTGCTATG and V S 2 from S 2 ¼ ACGCGCTA, aligned with position</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Cs 1 ðWÞ Cs 2 ðWÞ ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi Cs 1 ðWÞ 2 þ Cs 2 ðWÞ 2 , the probability of occurrence of w i for 1 i k and ñi ¼ n i À k þ 1 for i sequences, the centralized count variables, Cs 1 ðWÞ and Cs 2 ðWÞ, are therefore denoted by the following. Cs 1 ðWÞ ¼ C s 1 ðWÞ À ñ1 p W and Cs 2 ðWÞ ¼ C s 2 ðWÞ À ñ2 p W</figDesc><table><row><cell>page 8 of 16</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Bonham-Carter et al.</cell></row><row><cell>For p W ¼</cell><cell>Q t</cell><cell>p w i</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>i¼1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>D S 2 ¼</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>q</cell><cell>ð23Þ</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>W2A k</cell></row></table><note><p>propose a new statistic D S 2 , which is a self-standardized D 2 .</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The similar and different chunks, taken in order from each sequence</figDesc><table><row><cell>Sequence</cell><cell>Same</cell><cell>Different</cell><cell>Same</cell><cell>Different</cell></row><row><cell>S 1</cell><cell>ACG</cell><cell>T</cell><cell>GCTA</cell><cell>TG</cell></row><row><cell>S 2</cell><cell>ACG</cell><cell>C</cell><cell>GCTA</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>The sequences to compare by the alfy method</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>S 1 is compared with S Q to determine the shortest substring in S Q , which is absent from S 1The matching numbers indicate the shortest unique substring starting at this position that is absent from the subject.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Sequences S 1 and S 2 are compared with S Q The matching numbers indicate the shortest unique substring starting at this position that is absent from the subject. The HGT is described by a string of S 1 and S 2 characters to indicate where the subsequences likely originated. page 12 of 16 shortest query sequence prefix by h i, p . The query suffix, Q½p, jQj denotes the sequence starting at position p, which is absent in subject sequences. The length of the longest subsequence starting at Q½p taken over all subject sequences is denoted, H p ¼ max f1 i ng h i, p , where h p is bounded by the query length: H</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>We wish to determine the sequence relations based on common sequence material The query sequence is S Q and subjects are S 1 through S 3 .</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>ß The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com Briefings in Bioinformatics Advance Access published August 23, 2013 at Aston University on January 28, 2014 http://bib.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>at Aston University on January 28, 2014 http://bib.oxfordjournals.org/ Downloaded from</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors thank Joe Fitzpatrick for his work in proof-reading our manuscript. In addition, authors thank Janyl Jumadinova for helping us format the manuscript.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The column 'Alignment' contains the best suggested use of the method.</p><p>page 14 of 16 Bonham-Carter et al.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gusfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Algorithms On Strings, Trees, and Sequences: Computer Science and Computational Biology</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast pattern matching in strings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Knuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pratt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fast string searching algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Boyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="762" to="772" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Practical fast searching in strings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Horspool</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Softw Pract Exp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="501" to="506" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The boyer moore galil string searching strategies revisited</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Apostolico</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Giancarlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SiamJ Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding approximate patterns in strings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ukkonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAlgor</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A guided tour to approximate string matching</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Navarro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J ACM Comp Surv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate string matching in DNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L-L</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Cheung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S-M</forename><surname>Yiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/DASFAA.2003.1192395</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/DASFAA.2003.1192395" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Procceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Database Systems for Advance Applications</title>
		<meeting>ceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Database Systems for Advance Applications</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="310" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The emerging paradigm and open problems in comparative genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Koonin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trends in computational biology: a summary based on a RECOMB plenary lecture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wooley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Comput Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="474" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of sequence alignment algorithms for next-generation sequencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Homer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brief Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="483" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The unimarker (um) method for synteny mapping of large genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B-Y</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y-J</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-M</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3156" to="3165" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free detection of horizontal gene transfer between closely related bacterial genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Domazet-Los ˇo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Haubold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mob Genet Elements</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="230" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequencing wheat chromosome arm 7BS delimits the 7BS/4AL translocation and reveals homoeologous gene conservation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Berkman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Skarshewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Manoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">TheorAppl Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="432" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA shuffling of a family of genes from diverse species accelerates directed evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Crameri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S-A</forename><surname>Raillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bermudez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">391</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="288" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing the scalability of consistency-based progressive multiple sequences alignment applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Orobitg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cores</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Guirado</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Parallel &amp; Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="82" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is dynamic programming?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Eddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="909" to="910" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of common molecular subsequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Waterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general method applicable to the search for similarities in the amino acid sequence of two proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Needleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wunsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="453" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustalw and clustalx version 2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Larkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Blackshields</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2947" to="2948" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gapped blast and psi-blast: a new generation of protein database search programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Altschul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Madden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Scha ¨ffer Aa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3389" to="3402" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grid-enabled blastz: application to comparative genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rajapakse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J VLSI Signal Process Syst Signal Image VideoTechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blatthe blast-like alignment tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="656" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational solutions to large-scale data management and analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schadt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Linderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sorenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="647" to="657" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple sequence alignment with the clustal series of programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chenna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sugawara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Koike</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3497" to="3500" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parallelization of the mafft multiple sequence alignment program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Katoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Toh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1899" to="1900" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abundance of ultramicro inversions within local alignments between human and chimpanzee genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Imanishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Evol Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">308</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free sequence comparison-a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="523" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distance measures for biological sequences: some recent approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mantaci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Restivo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sciortino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Approx Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel feature-based method for whole genome phylogenetic analysis without alignment: application to HEV genotyping and subtyping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">223</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Composition vector method based on maximum entropy principle for sequence comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Yeung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Trans Comput Biol Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-03-03">2011. Mar 3</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved string composition method for sequence comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple statistical algorithm for biological sequence compression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dix</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Allison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Data Compression Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="52" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new sequence distance measure for phylogenetic tree construction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Out</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sayood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2111" to="2130" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The average common substring approach to phylogenomic reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ulitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Burstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Comp Bio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="250" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free detection of local similarity among viral and bacterial genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Domazet-Los ˇo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Haubold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1466" to="1472" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mathematical theory of communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Shannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bell SystTechJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="429" />
			<date type="published" when="1948">1948</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pattern clustering with statistical methods using a DNA-based algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Watada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pedrycz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Nanobioscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison study of virus classification by genome sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics and Bioengineering (BIBE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>IEEE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering DNA methylation expressions using nonparametric beta mixture model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Genomic Signal Processing and Statistics (GENSIPS), 2011 IEEE International Workshop</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="173" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal word sizes for dissimilarity measures and estimation of the degree of dissimilarity between DNA sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T-J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y-H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L-A</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4125" to="4132" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating overlapping structures and background information of words significantly improves biological sequence comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26779</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marı ´n I. Fast comparison of DNA sequences by oligonucleotide profiling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Arnau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gallach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Res Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free genome comparison with feature frequency profiles (ffp) and optimal resolutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sims</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2677" to="2682" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<pubPlace>USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Divergence measures based on the shannon entropy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans InfTheory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confirming the phylogeny of mammals by use of large comparative sequence data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Prasad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Allard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Biol Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1795" to="1808" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequence comparison alignment-free approach based on suffix tree and l-words frequency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Soares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Amorim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SciWorldJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">450124</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prokaryotic phylogeny based on complete genomes without sequence alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mod Phys Lett B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole proteome prokaryote phylogeny without sequence alignment: a k-string composition approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B-I</forename><surname>Hao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic analysis using complete signature information of whole genomes and clustered neighbour-joining method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Bioinform Res Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linguistics of nucleotide sequences: morphology and comparison of vocabularies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Brendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Beckmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Trifonov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biomol Struct Dyn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prokaryote phylogeny without sequence alignment: from avoidance signature to composition distance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Bioinform Comput Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The distribution of the frequency of occurrence of nucleotide subsequences, based on their overlap capability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gentleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mullin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistically significant strings are related to regulatory elements in the promoter regions of saccharomyces cerevisiae</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wanga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">290</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="464" to="474" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogeny of prokaryotes and chloroplasts revealed by a simple composition approach on all protein sequences from complete genomes without sequence alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z-G</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L-Q</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anh</forename><surname>Vv</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Evol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="538" to="545" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing the d2 statistic: word matches in biological sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fore ˆt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat Appl Genet Mol Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Computational Biology: Maps, Sequences and Genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Waterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Chapman and Hall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic behavior of k-word matches between two uniformly distributed sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fore ˆt</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">S21</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kantorovitz</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">S21</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burden</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">S21</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributional regimes for the number of k-word matches between two random sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lippert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Waterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13980" to="13989" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<pubPlace>USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free sequence comparison (i): Statistics and power</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Reinert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Comput Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1615" to="1634" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A statistical method for alignment-free comparison of regulatory sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kantorovitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sinha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="255" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free sequence comparison (ii): theoretical power of comparison statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Reinert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Comput Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1467" to="1490" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free sequence comparison based on next generation sequencing reads</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research in Computational Molecular Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="272" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New powerful statistics for alignment-free sequence comparison under a pattern transfer model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Theor Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A universal algorithm for sequential data compression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ziv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lempel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans InfTheory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deliminate-a fast and efficient method for loss-less compression of genomic sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mohammed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dutta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2527" to="2529" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale compression of genomic sequence databases with the burrows-wheeler transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Jakobi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1415" to="1419" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compressing genomic sequence fragments using slimgene</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kozanitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Saunders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kruglyak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Comput Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="413" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A meta-genome sequencing and assembly preprocessing algorithm inspired by restriction site base composition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Bonham-Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bastola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics and Biomedicine Workshops (BIBMW)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="703" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>IEEE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A meta-genome sequencing and assembly preprocessing algorithm inspired by restriction site base composition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Bonham-Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bastola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributions of palindromic proportional content in bacteria. Short Paper</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Bonham-Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Najjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Thapa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The 8th International Symposium on Bioinformatics Research and Applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Dallas, TX</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ISBRA</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolutionary implications of horizontal gene transfer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Syvanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">&apos;&apos;Parallel evolution and horizontal gene transfer of the pst operon in firmicutes from oligotrophic environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moreno-Letelier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Olmedo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Eguiarte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Evol Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
