<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">HCI, Civic Engagement &amp; Trust</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mike</forename><surname>Harding</surname></persName>
							<email>hardingm@comp.lancs.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Lancaster University Lancaster</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lancashire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bran</forename><surname>Knowles</surname></persName>
							<email>branknowles9@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Lancaster University Lancaster</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lancashire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nigel</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Lancaster University Lancaster</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lancashire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mark</forename><surname>Rouncefield</surname></persName>
							<email>m.rouncefield@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Lancaster University Lancaster</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lancashire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">HCI, Civic Engagement &amp; Trust</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">487E74E3E2CE1C591A5888499BC19F90</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1145/2702123.2702255</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T13:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Civic Engagement</term>
					<term>citizen participation</term>
					<term>crowdsourcing</term>
					<term>trust</term>
					<term>H.4.m Information Systems Applications: Miscellaneous</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>There is a widespread belief that pervasive technologies will encourage and facilitate partnerships between citizens and civic authorities, enabling individuals to play a greater role in civic planning, service delivery and infrastructure management. However, at present sustained use and perceived value of civic engagement technologies remains low because the design space is poorly understood by system developers who focus almost exclusively on empowering citizens rather than adopting an informed, inclusive approach that addresses the needs of both citizens and civic authorities, and helps establish trusted relationships between these different stakeholders. We report on an extensive study of civic engagement in the domain of public infrastructure maintenance and provide insights into the civic management processes to support future design of trusted civic engagement interactions.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>This paper is concerned with understanding and encouraging citizen engagement in civic life, and, consequently, in the design of trusted interactions with civic authorities. Growing populations and increasing demands on ageing civic infrastructure [9] make this a timely topic to explore. Two largely independent streams of research have begun to focus on these issues: (i) smart city programs that attempt to use pervasive sensing to monitor and understand the behaviour of cities as complex systems and (ii) civic engagement tools that provide citizens with technologies that enable them to play a greater role in the management and maintenance of their city.</p><p>Civic crowdsourcing tools have demonstrated the potential to integrate the collective knowledge of citizens <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, empowering users to take an active role in civic decision-making, urban management and service delivery. Maintenance of urban infrastructure <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, monitoring of environmental noise pollution and water management highlight areas of public concern where citizens have been able to collaborate with civic workers. However, interest in long-term civic engagement and use; and the perceived value of civic crowdsourcing applications has remained low, so any vision of civic authorities and citizens acting as partners appears a considerable distance from being realised.</p><p>Here, we consider opportunities, challenges and considerations for the HCI community in developing technologies that facilitate more effective civic engagement by addressing two contributory factors, that we argue represent important issues currently limiting the uptake of civic technology. Firstly, the current focus on a single stakeholder group (i.e. citizens) rather than the adoption of an inclusive design process that addresses the complex inter-relational concerns of both citizens and civic authority stakeholders, and secondly, a lack of appreciation of the high levels of mistrust that exist between citizens and their civic authorities. Why engage with a civic process if you believe nothing is likely to happen as a consequence? Most civic engagement tools tend to be implemented on mobile devices such as smartphones making them relatively easy to prototype. However, and in contrast, designing applications for civic authorities is complex and time-consuming. Civic systems tend to need to integrate with large, bespoke software platforms used to manage city infrastructure and hence are not typically amenable to the type of rapid prototyping and experimental approaches that have proved successful in the domain of the citizen. Such factors also lead to a lack of appreciation of the importance of trusted working relationships between citizens and civic authorities, and that understanding these relationships requires significant effort to involve each stakeholder group in the design process.</p><p>In this paper we investigate two different, but clearly and essentially related, issues: how to design for civic engagement and how to think about trust in ICT design in the domain of civic urban maintenance. We report on an extensive participatory design and iterative prototyping approach involving civic authorities, private contractors and the public. Through a series of formative ethnographic studies (including workshops &amp; in-field observation) we firstly, contribute an in-depth understanding of urban maintenance processes, stakeholder re-lationships and perspectives on trust. Secondly, from this formative analysis of stakeholder perspectives and the domain we identify design considerations to inform the secondary phase of our research, the development and evaluation of a civic engagement prototype system. Finally we provide an analysis of stakeholder experiences with the deployed system prototype, and conclude by discussing future opportunities, challenges and design considerations that we have learnt from this (generally failed) deployment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BACKGROUND AND METHODS</head><p>Our goal in this study was to understand the complex landscape of public infrastructure maintenance from multiple stakeholder perspectives to identify opportunities, challenges and considerations for pervasive technologies that facilitate 'trusted' civic engagement by design. Through our work we consider two main questions:</p><p>1. How do stakeholders rationalise their relationships? and, relatedly, exactly how is trust manifested in civic relationships and operationalised by stakeholders?</p><p>2. How might proposed civic engagement interactions through ICT facilitate trusted relationships? and, relatedly, how might they be integrated and experienced by public individuals, local authorities and private contractor workers?</p><p>We contribute an extensive study of the complexities and inter-dependencies that impact on stakeholder relationships in the public infrastructure maintenance domain and identify pragmatic considerations for researchers developing civic engagement technologies applicable beyond infrastructure maintenance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Related Work</head><p>Civic engagement refers to an individual or collective action designed to identify or address a particular public concern such as urban maintenance that includes activities from refuse collection, upkeep of social housing, flood risk management through to highway repair. To most citizens (and indeed researchers) urban maintenance appears as a 'black box', with civic authorities seeming to make arbitrary decisions concerning which activities to undertake and when. It is probably unreasonable to expect citizens to know or care too much about the fine details of urban maintenance, but this lack of appreciation of a complex culture (where mistrust is commonplace) makes it challenging for citizens to understand or appreciate the activities of civic authorities, and difficult for citizens to form trusted partnerships with government authorities where mistrust and suspicion is the social norm.</p><p>Current efforts to empower citizens in civic life and local authority decision-making have led to a growing number of pervasive technologies that aim to encourage citizen engagement. We believe that current state-of-the-art civic engagement technologies fall short in motivating citizens to effectively contribute information that civic authorities are willing to trust and act upon, and will continue to remain unpopular unless inherent aspects of mistrust that exist are addressed in the design process. This requires considering both citizen and civic authority perspectives.</p><p>Citizen engagement technologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>[24] <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> in the domain of urban maintenance such as FixMyStreet <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, an established commercial civic crowdsourcing mobile application that enables users to exchange non-emergency, street-level issue reports (e.g. potholes, flooded highways), demonstrate a lack of understanding of the domain and interactions they aim to support. King et al.'s analysis of FixMyStreet from the perspective of platform developers, citizens and civic workers highlights that, in the majority of cases the system's design placed expectations on citizens themselves (typically the originator of the report) to update the status after observing that the problem had been resolved in-situ. Overall, citizens positively indicated a preference to using such a pervasive civic reporting application in comparison to traditional reporting channels (e.g. telephone, authority website), citing ease of use and time saving as key benefits. However, civic officials interviewed demonstrated scepticism, highlighting a badly executed design with concerns over accountability (i.e. citizens can post anonymously) and negative impact on existing channels for citizen engagement. Civic customer service workers noted further concern about the impact FixMyStreet could have on public perception of service reliability, citing reported issues that potentially go unresolved for extended periods of time that may have been fixed or are scheduled for completion. Critically for our research, King et al. highlighted a need to further explore requirements across all civic stakeholders in order to better inform the design to support more effective two-way citizen-civic relationships and address underlying institutional and citizen mistrust. Consequently, through an empirical participatory design process, we undergo this exploration and provide insights in the domain from multiple perspectives, whilst providing pragmatic considerations for addressing the inherency of mistrust in citizen and civic authority relationships in the public maintenance domain.</p><p>We have identified few related works in the literature that have attempted to undertake an empirical, participatory design process to understand the complexities of citizen-civic engagement in this domain; or that have taken a nuanced approach in considering trust in the design of ICT; or have been motivated by a need to address issues of trust. Aoki et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> investigated the use of participatory sensing technologies to influence environmental authority decision-making through citizen involvement by examining key stakeholder perspectives, but this understanding was not applied to inform the design or develop implications for design. In our own previous work we have followed an empirical approach to understand the design of a civic system that supports the capture of accurate, 'trusted data' to address domain process inefficiencies. Our work in this paper focuses specifically on facilitating cooperative working relationships between civic authorities and the public, and considers how a broad understanding of citizen and civic relationships can inform the design of ICT to support trusted citizen-civic relationships. Exploring trust relationships between organisations, workers and public individuals through our investigation here has highlighted a need to consider our own perspective on trust in this domain. Moreover, in this work we particularly focus on aspects of human vulnerability, fear and harm as more applicable measures of trust (Rousseau et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and Baier <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>) and provide empirical examples (specifically in relation to knowledge sharing) where levels of trust manifest across both civic workers and citizens rooted predominantly in the acceptability of being vulnerable to another person or organisation's expected positive behaviours (or ill will).</p><p>Parker et al. examined <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> models for developing citizen trust in local civic services and argue that a focus on improving service performance does not necessarily correlate to increased levels of civic trust, referred to as the "performance paradox". They propose a model where trust can be developed in three key areas of interaction with the citizens (i) personal, on-going two-way interaction with civic worker individuals (ii) civic service delivery, and (iii) open and transparent decision-making. Through 'unwrapping' the 'black box' of urban maintenance we demonstrate how considerations for the design of civic engagement technologies can be realised to support similar models of interaction to potentially formulate trust, particularly approaches for supporting sustainable, two-way bidirectional interaction between citizen and civic worker individuals, a requirement highlighted by King et al.</p><p>Studies of trust in the context of mobile crowdsourcing systems have focused primarily on approaches to quantify trust metrics and mechanisms for supporting trust management across distributed devices <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. A number of studies have investigated methods for quantifying trust (e.g. reputation) <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> to support optimised decision-making in pervasive crowdsourcing systems such as Amazon Mechanical Turk <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and GeoTruCrowd <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. While a common feature of systems that aim to provide visualise representations of trust between people, through our investigations we demonstrate findings that highlight concern where such digital representations can act to counterintuitively erode trust in citizen-civic relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Civic Infrastructure Maintenance</head><p>In this section we provide a brief context of urban maintenance describing the complex processes and stakeholder relationships involved. Civic authorities invest significant sums of money in managing the maintenance of our urban areas <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. But to most citizens, urban maintenance appears as a 'black box' with civic authorities seeming to make arbitrary sets of decisions about which activities to undertake leading to difficulties in establishing trusted partnerships. For example, consider the apparently simple case of a citizen reporting a problem with a street light in their neighbourhood. While the citizen may feel that they have performed their civic duty and submitted a reasonable report of the fault, in reality a detailed inspection would be needed to comply with the relevant standards (which currently runs to several hundred pages for the UK). As a result, the civic authority will typically send out a trained inspector which for the average citizen appears to indicate that the authority didn't believe their report. Examples of this kind of disconnect are prominent in highways maintenance, particularly in road resurfacing and road-side drainage management activities. Maintenance activities related to flood risk management such as gully cleansing regimes involve maintenance crews periodically cleaning silt and debris from road-side drains. Over time gullies can become overrun with silt and other environmental waste causing blockages in the drainage network. If left untreated prior to a weather event, blocked gullies can contribute significantly to the development of flooding in urban areas. Therefore, private contractors (common in the UK) are employed by civic authorities to cleanse an agreed number of gullies throughout the year. However, residents often perceive that the civic authority have not performed the necessary maintenance of gullies to mitigate the flood risk prior to a flood event taking place. In earlier work <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> we identified the complex hierarchy of organisation and intra-organisational stakeholders involved in the process of civic highways maintenance. Indeed, citizens are often mistaken in their assumption that their local civic authorities both manage and execute repairs. More commonly, private companies are employed to perform tasks in the field while civic personnel manage requests from citizens and internal inspectors, schedule defects to be fixed and inspect the quality of the repair work once completed. Areas such as highways maintenance have traditionally suffered from high levels of mistrust both externally from citizens dissatisfied with the quality of service, and internally amongst civic authorities and private contractors <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Mistrust is demonstrated in civic working practices through extensive inspections and monitoring of workers and contractors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>In order to undertake an inclusive investigation of the problem domain we adopted a participatory design and iterative prototyping approach, engaging firstly in prior fieldwork with stakeholders through a series of formative ethnographic studies (including stakeholder workshops &amp; one-to-one semistructured interviews), and a subsequent iterative design process of civic engagement technology probes and prototypes that were evaluated through three focus groups and an in-situ user trial over an 8 month period involving local residents, civic authority and private contract workers operating in an urban area of the UK. Our formative work to understand highways maintenance processes, stakeholder relationships and perspectives on trust spanned a one year period involving 70 interviews with over three months of observing and shadowing stakeholders.</p><p>Through a formative analysis of stakeholder perspectives and the domain we identified design considerations to inform the secondary phase of our research, the development and evaluation of a civic engagement prototype system. Analysis of stakeholder experiences with the technologies deployed have allowed us to perform a thematic analysis and provide an insightful discussion around key opportunities, challenges and implications for researchers investigating the design of future civic engagement technologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>UNDERSTANDING STAKEHOLDER PERSPECTIVES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Civic Authorities &amp; Contractors</head><p>Our fieldwork with civic authorities and contractors involved informal, semi-structured interviewing (asking about work and trust incidents) and periods of observation (shadowing highways inspectors or highways maintenance gangs as they went about their everyday work). The fieldwork reported here was carried out by two ethnographers at seven different sites in the UK. Our fieldwork reveals instances of how trust is achieved in everyday work; and what sort of things produce trust and trustability or distrust and suspicion. Of particular interest was the detailed explication of the work of council inspectors and road maintenance gangs and their perception of and by the public.</p><p>The fieldwork provided numerous instances of trust in action, in particular of how trust is part of a developing organisational relationship that needs to be maintained as organisations change, acquire new staff or implement new procedures. However we found tremendous variation, and much suspicion, in the relationships between councils, contractors and the public. There was particular concern shown about how to effectively manage information flow between officials and the public, and how public individuals would perceive feedback (or lack of) from local authorities. One council official when asked about trust in the council amongst the public responded:</p><p>"If asked, most of them would say we don't fully trust the council. The problem is we don't get back to the public, that's changing this year. Or another response from a council official: Ideally Mrs Smith can come into [the council] walk-in centre and ask what's happening on her street."</p><p>When we look for trust in the fieldwork we find it manifested in various ways, some of which may be more consequential for design than others. We find aspects of trust in people; in their interpersonal interactions; shared histories and so on. We find trust too in particular processes: in systems, data, routines and various forms of technology, paperwork and computer work, through which processes are accomplished.</p><p>To gain a greater understanding of stakeholder perspectives in this domain we conducted a two-day workshop with 25 participants from the highways maintenance sector including civic authority, private contractor and industry ICT providers. From this session participants identified a model and visualisation of trust that emphasised the difficulty in gaining trust and the speed and ease with which it can be lost, raising important design challenges for citizen-civic engagement that mediates bidirectional interaction, such as, the challenge of mitigating negative experiences to avoid catastrophic impacts on trust. Overwhelmingly participants agreed openness, and methods to support detection and early warning were essential for maintaining trust relationships to soften the impact and loss of trust if expectations were not met. In terms of factors that decrease trust the group highlighted the issue of inaccurate out-of-date or missing data. In particular, participants felt it was important to have transparency and awareness of the source and ownership of the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Citizens' &amp; Local Communities</head><p>Our understanding of citizen perspectives were shaped by a number of interview and focus group studies which report on in this section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>National Highways Transport Survey</head><p>Our first study featured semi-structured interviews with 31 citizens who had originally taken part in the UK National Highways Transport survey <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The goal of the survey was to understand whether public individuals felt they could trust their local authority, and whether they trusted that services where reliable. Telephone discussions last between 15 and 35 minutes and were framed around the following questions: (i) can you remember any specific incidents that may have caused you to trust or distrust your civic authority?, (ii) is there anything more generally you'd like to say about the highways in your area and how they are maintained, and (iii) can you think of anything your civic authority actively does to make you trust them more?</p><p>Respondents to the first two questions focused primarily on the negative experiences where mistrust in their civic authority was compounded: "Yes, basically [the problem is] potholes around the village where I live. There are hundreds of them but they [the civic authority] don't seem to bother to repair them. I've contacted the council and neighbours have on several occasions. They took the details but did nothing."</p><p>Further respondents highlighted issues around highways maintenance tasks such as salting and gritting roads during adverse weather to address safety concerns. Supporting civic service awareness poses a particular challenge in the design of civic crowdsourcing applications that typically support a unidirectional flow of information from citizens to civic authorities. Traditional crowdsourcing approaches provide means for a requester (i.e. civic authority) to utilise the crowd to perform a task (e.g. report an issue). For civic authorities crowdsourcing can provide a heightened awareness of urban areas they would not typically gain through their internal workforce. However, it is important to consider the reverse whereby citizens are often unable to be in locations where civic authorities are actively performing work. Public awareness of council activities and understanding of civic authority constraints can help mitigate mistrust by managing citizen expectations. Responses to the final question focused around offline 'push' interaction from civic authorities, and the use of promotional news-sheets to help inform the public about civic services. When discussed many respondents either did not read them or believed the information to be inaccurate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Focus Groups &amp; Workshop</head><p>We further explored citizen perspectives of trust through two focus groups and a one day workshop following a similar structure to the civic authority 2-day workshop where we asked about the extent to which they trusted either their local council or contractors; their opinion of the information they were given and whether they were provided sufficient information about the activities of their local council. The results were not inspiring, suggesting a general level of distrust, both for politicians in general and for the ways in which information was presented:</p><p>"the information is too generalised ... its not always easy to find information in detail ... its all manipulated information ... it doesn't mean anything to me ... They give you information that they want you to see and think that's great"</p><p>During the workshop in particular we found the public were much better at generating visions of distrust rather than trust. This focus on the negative somewhat reflects Parker et al. findings <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> that demonstrate the public are more motivated to engage with civic authorities when there is a problem or issue to address. The group discussed the negative impacts of formalising trust in a digitally measurable manner. In particular, participants felt moving away from offline social contracts, which require trust to work, to formal indicators, which require authority and punishment erodes trust and that trust is very hard to gain but very easy to lose. The group also discussed the importance of personalisation and personal interaction when considering factors that impacted on their trust in organisations. Indeed, they highlighted examples of interacting with their council only to be met by an automated process (e.g. telephone IVR systems) or a human following a script. Participations felt less scripted, personal interaction would lead to greater empathy and capabilities to form affective bonds allowing parties to better formulate relational trust.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRUSTED CIVIC ENGAGEMENT THROUGH ICT</head><p>Following our formative analysis of stakeholder perspectives and domain processes in this section we identify key design considerations and describe the implementation of a civic engagement platform.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Design Considerations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification, Capture and Persistence of Evidence</head><p>A common theme identified through our formative studies is a need to provide accurate, attributable evidence of activities.</p><p>At present such evidence is typically created through a mix of electronic workflow systems, paper inspection trails and citizen reports. A shared, trusted repository of evidence that could be accessed by all stakeholders has the potential to significantly improve trust relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Individual and Institutional Entity Representation</head><p>Closely related to the need for evidence is the requirement to be able to accurately attribute the source of evidence. For citizens and institutions accountability is critical to ensure stakeholders act responsibly when performing public activities, accountability also provides a means for stakeholders to assess the reliability of actions by being able to associate the action with the user entity who performed it. Without appropriate representation of real-world entities such as physical objects, citizens, road workers or civic institutions in the digital space, delivering technological capabilities to support attribution, and to allow users to build trust relationships becomes difficult. Indeed, the optional registration of citizen and civic users in engagement tools such as FixMyStreet highlight this problem where information is published through anonymous identities. For civic stakeholders, this limits opportunities to form relationships with citizen contributors and restricts capabilities to validate the reliability of the issues reported.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Explicit Support for Transparency and Trust Management</head><p>Much of our early findings indicate that supporting end-toend bidirectional flow of information between citizen and civic stakeholders is essential in order to mitigate against civic mistrust. The highways maintenance stakeholder workshop further highlighted a need for intelligence in civic engagement platforms that can assess and provide early warning to a trusting entity of potential problems, including features to monitor citizen-civic dialogue exchanges to mediate automated triggering of system-generated information (e.g. detecting a citizen has not received feedback regarding a reported issue and sending reminders to civic stakeholders to provide a response).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Social Communication Channels</head><p>Offline opportunities for explicit social interaction and shared experiences facilitates individuals to form trustworthy relationships. However, traditional online interfaces for citizens to engage with civic authorities often act to depersonalise civic engagement (e.g. digital web forms for reporting problems) and promote relationship formulation with the authority rather than individuals within the civic authority. By allowing citizens and civic individuals to communicate in more freeform social ways increases the opportunity to understand one another, to become familiar with one another, and develop more effective trusted relationships when addressing a particular civic concern. Analysis of the citizen workshop also suggested that a reliance on formalised digital representations of stakeholder trustworthiness has the potential to erode trust (citizens reacted negatively to heavily scripted interactions with authorities).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>System Prototype Overview</head><p>Our system probe comprised three core elements (1) a civic engagement platform providing functionality to support the integration and coordination of 3rd party front-end mobile citizen reporting and back-end civic management tools, (2) a mobile issue reporting application for citizens, and (3) a web based interface for civic authorities to enable civic workers to provide real-time correspondence on citizen reports.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Public Mobile Application</head><p>An initial public mobile application probe was developed to allow participants involved in our early public focus groups to (1) gain an awareness of the types of civic authority information that could be shared and visualised, (2) provide a tangible demonstration of how the public could interact with such information to support further engagement with managing civic authorities, and (3) discuss the interaction design to elicit further user requirements prior to an in-field deployment. The main screen of the prototype (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> left) provided a visualisation of real-time highways maintenance activities plotted on a map. Users of the prototype could view detailed information about the status of an on-going maintenance activity including start times and estimated completion times. Selecting a map icon provided information on specific workers (e.g. council, private contractor workers) involved in the coordination and completion of the work, providing personalised information that is not readily available to the public. Following on from our initial probe we updated the design and implemented a functional prototype named 'Flooder' that supported the reporting of events related to flooding, allowing users to receive &amp; report context-sensitive real-time updates about local flood issues. The public mobile application enabled users to view real-time flood data, including forecasted rainfall and gully silt level data integrated from a gully collection system <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> used by the council overlaid on a map and list view. Accessing information via the map allowed citizens to view flood information near to their current location. Users also had the capability to define areas of interest by providing a location that could be applied to filter the citizen reports they received. This second iteration of the appli- local residents) and store public report information in the platform's open data repository, enabling 3rd party applications (i.e. web interface for civic authorities) to access report information and provide mechanisms to communicate directly with users of the Flooder application. Furthermore, this version of the mobile application included an interaction mechanism to 'witness' problems that had already been reported by other members of the public. This provided a metric civic authorities could use to prioritise issues that impacted on the greatest number of residences but also provided a means for residents to validate information reported by the civic authority to strengthen its trustworthiness. The constraint of only allowing the reporting of flood events and the impact on the perceived usability of the application from users (highlighted in our analysis) led to a 3rd evolution of the public application that enabled users to report about general issues such as potholes and street trash (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Civic Authority Report Management Interface</head><p>A report management web interface component was developed to provide civic operators involved in the management of public complaints and issue reporting with capabilities to view reports and communicate directly with public individuals using the Flooder/StreetSmart mobile application. Our early investigation into existing information workflows and management of public reporting highlighted a reliance on email systems to manage communications between civic operators and public individuals. Indeed, upon receiving a report, typically through telephone communication, contact details and the nature of the report are forwarded onto an operator given the role of handling specific types of report (e.g. street damage, waste management). Depending on the nature of the report it is then scheduled (typically after a physical assessment by a council inspector) as a works order by the managing civic authority. Based on our insights into the reporting process we designed a web interface that could be easily accessed by multiple workers from a computer with a web browser. In particular, the web interface included capabilities to view a list of Flooder/StreetSmart reports updated in realtime, and controls in the interface to allow civic operators to update the status of reports as new information regarding a particular report became available.</p><p>Each report was shown in a list view that included specific details about the report including, the issue description, cause, visual evidence, number of witnesses, the time the report was submitted, status of the report and the location of the issue reported. On receiving a report the civic operator could update the status of a particular report to one of work 'scheduled', 'started' or 'completed'. On a status change instigated by the civic operator the civic interface generated a request to the civic engagement platform to notify citizen users of changes related to reports they were interested in.</p><p>In addition to a notification on the mobile application, the civic interface generated a personalised message (including the name of the civic operator) that gave more detailed information about the status change.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRIALS &amp; EVALUATION</head><p>In order to validate our civic engagement platform design and provide additional insight into the application domain we deployed the system in an area of the UK that commonly experience annual issues related to flooding and highways degradation. In particular we wanted to investigate the ways in which members of the public encounter issues such as damaged pavements, broken streetlights or roads that have become blocked with floodwater. Indeed, it is often assumed that citizens choose not to report such problems -either through a lack of time or because they believe their civic authority is already dealing with the problem. Over time as issues remain unresolved members of the public may begin to question the competency of their civic authority in dealing with issues, and begin to lose trust in their ability to deliver services. In contrast, civic authorities may be unaware of particular issues or are already in the process of scheduling workers to fix reported problems unbeknown to the public. Therefore, through a series of system user focus groups we aimed to gain a deeper understanding of such behaviours in reporting and sharing information through the system. The civic and citizen facing components were trialled over an 8-month period with a 12 participant opportunity sample.</p><p>Qualitative user feedback was gathered throughout using three participant focus groups and an online social networking group. The first focus group took place prior to the application being deployed in order to understand existing attitudes to civic reporting. Subsequently we deployed the application, provided participants with application training and then conducted a further focus group. Based on the feedback from this second focus group, and in response to a change to the needs of the users, we created a new version of the application that we then obtained feedback on from a final focus group. This second version of the application, called StreetSmart included other forms of data than those on the Flooder application such as roadworks and a facility for our user group to post reports. Prior to the deployment of the system, participants were given a demonstration of the application to help inform the design prior to a full user deployment. Participants were asked to consider a range of questions related to information sharing with local authorities and personal opinions about the initial system designs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stakeholder Experiences &amp; Analysis</head><p>In general, participants favoured an application that was multi-functional and offered a range of information sources and functions that could be customised to their own preferences. In particular, participants showed a strong will to become active contributors: "I think you would do. If there was a pot-hole on the road that you kept hitting ... and all you had to do was click on an app and go pothole down our road." However, there was some concern about the consequences of witnessing, especially being labelled a "nosey neighbour".</p><p>We next considered the question of anonymity and asked participants if this was important to them when reporting and witnessing faults. Since the mobile applications depended upon people's willingness to report and witness events we enquired into our participants experiences in this regard -had they ever reported anything to the council: "some yes ... [Interviewer "such as"] ... lights out, pot holes. Online you can report ... I put a request in to look into speed bumps where cars were speeding ... I called the number on the website ... they told me to get other people in the community to make the same request to give it more weighting ... but nothing has been done ... I could call up and follow it up, but I haven't had any letter of why or why they haven't done anything. There is no indication that it is being looked into."</p><p>The issue of feedback seemed important to our focus group and we asked when they would expect feedback: "Within 6 months you would expect some feedback to say what conclusion they had come to (speed bumps), but it would be good to know before ... so there could be some kind of appeal etc. I don't like automated responses, only as some proof to say I did send the email but you didn't reply."</p><p>During deployment, unusually for England, we were blessed with several months of drought. In consequence, most of the social networking group discussions concerned some of the technical and administrative details of the loaned phone and application. For example, there was some concern about the maps on the application, how much information they displayed and how up-to-date they were.</p><p>There was also some concern expressed (repeated in later focus groups) about the sheer practical difficulties of posting or witnessing, in particular the need to accompany a post with a photo, given that our participants were likely to be engaged in driving a car at the time they saw a reportable incident. There were also some issues connected to the amount of information appearing on screen, how useful such information was and the extent to which this merely contributed to an overall sense of clutter. After the trial had run for a couple of months without any significant amount of rain, we held a focus group to share and discuss participant experiences. Unfortunately, and despite our participants enthusiasm for the trial, no flooding had been witnessed.</p><p>Another particularly significant factor that impacted strongly on the trial was the difficulty in recruiting champions within the civic authorities. Despite significant enthusiasm, a series of personnel changes and operational challenges meant that even when our participants witnessed events there was noone in the council to respond. It is clear that this impacted on our participants and the trial, diminishing, to an extent, some of the strong initial enthusiasm. That said there remained a significant level of support for the study and many of the comments at the focus group concerned ways in which particular features of the application could be improved. Although the application was considered easy to use and very user friendly there were some suggestions for improvements:</p><p>"its quite hard if you want to be quick . Reflecting earlier comments on their distrust of politicians in general there was also some discussion concerning the whole subject of trust and whether and how it might be impacted by using the application and the response of the council.</p><p>" ... Im not very political, but if you don't trust the council, just because they're posting on the app it doesn't mean they're trustworthy. The app doesn't make any difference."</p><p>The second half of the trial involved the StreetSmart application. We held a final focus group with our participants who generally considered the application a good idea and an easy method of communicating problems to the council and making the public aware of problems. In particular the variety of topics that were reportable using StreetSmart were considered an advantage over the more limited reporting options of Flooder. Users reported a broad range of issues from the usual flooding, blocked drains and standing water to fly tipping and public disorder. However, much of the focus group discussion was dominated by reports of technical issues such as difficulties of reporting whilst travelling (so that occasionally people would make a report, of standing water or a blocked drain for example, and accompany it with a picture of something entirely unrelated).</p><p>Other technical issues raised by our participants included occasional poor signal issues; that the map would not always provide an accurate indication of their location since it was not always up-to-date with regard to street names (this was explained as an issue with Apple maps) and unnecessarily cluttering the map. Finally, and perhaps most significantly, one persistent and de-motivating gripe from our participants was the lack of any feedback from the council via the system. There was little feedback noted, or indication that issues had been scheduled to reassure participants that someone was listening, and that their efforts were not entirely fruitless.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>Patrick et al. in 'Designing systems that people will trust' <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> argue that 'online users have to develop the knowledge needed to make good trust decisions, and developers must support them by making trustable designs' and give some specific advice, six lessons, to developers who want to build a trusted service. We have considered their advice and the extent to which it might be applicable to citizen engagement services as revealed in our research. Some, such as ease of use characteristics and reducing uncertainty seem important to almost any design; others seem especially relevant to our experiences and interest in 'trust', most obviously that 'external factors or context that may seem to be unrelated to the situation can affect trust' and, most importantly that, 'trust probably develops in stages. In the first stage, superficial interface properties, such as colours and designs, can have a large effect on initial trust decisions. Later, users may make trust decisions based on more reasoned analysis of information' suggesting that our application may ultimately prove successful. In these final sections, we use our broad understanding of stakeholder experiences both within the domain and with our prototype technologies to formulate a number of common themes around key opportunities, challenges and implications for researchers investigating the design of future civic engagement technologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Understanding both citizens and civic authorities fears &amp; vulnerabilities</head><p>While there are a number of current commercial civic engagement applications available <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> [6] <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, we would argue that in most cases such systems do not prioritise trust relationship formulation as a key requirement during design; or evaluate empirically the impact of such technologies on stakeholder perspectives towards trust. What emerged in both our initial field studies and in the evaluation of our prototype engagement technology was the extent of longstanding mistrust, even cynicism, between the stakeholders, with the civic authority fearing litigation and the public anticipating disinterest and inaction from the authorities; and how quickly and easily trust and eager anticipation could change to mistrust and suspicion. As researchers we needed to both understand and manage this difficult situation, hence our emphasis on a holistic approach. Interviews with both citizens and civic workers evinced a general under-current of fear and vulnerability in the sharing of information and knowledge in a civic context. Commonly, civic workers expressed concerns of publicising internal activities because of fear of litigation, while public individuals worried over how their information would be used both by their civic authority and other members of the public. Clearly, understanding such vulnerabilities is essential to ensure stakeholders can reasonably begin to trust each other <ref type="bibr">(Baier [7]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Integrating with corporate I.T solutions</head><p>While citizen applications may be effectively deployed as small mobile applications, systems designed for civic authorities require integration with much larger corporate I.T systems and workflows, and this represents a significant obstacle to innovation. Indeed our integration with two civic platforms (including a works orders platform) was constrained to a unidirectional flow of information from the civic platforms to our civic engagement platform. Clearly, to support greater integration between public facing and civic solutionscivic authorities must consider how such systems are opened to enable the utilisation of new forms of information gathered and shared through public civic engagement tools that deliver more effective civic engagement experiences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supporting feedback, transparency &amp; activity awareness</head><p>All of our stakeholder engagement exercises highlighted the frustration that the different stakeholders felt with the lack of feedback and transparency in most maintenance systems. In our case, even though we recognised its importance in developing and maintaining trusted relationships, the lack of feedback and transparency was largely unrelated to the technology but instead a product of political and organisational factors over which we had no control. A recurring observation from our fieldwork and evaluation study was the lack of appreciation amongst the different stakeholders of the challenges each faces. For example in most cases it was a surprise to several participants that their local civic authority did not actually perform work in the field but outsourced work to several contractors, and therefore their suspicion of 'the council' was often entirely misplaced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>New working practices &amp; civic decision strategies</head><p>Previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> has demonstrated the impact of new technology on working practices in urban maintenance. Our deployment of technology highlighted the challenges civic authorities face in adapting to new levels of citizen interaction with civic processes and suggested the need for a change in working practices -to support such applications. This is not just a concern for the contractor and authority stakeholders since citizens would also need to accustom themselves to changes in everyday working practices. A related common theme through our analysis with citizens is a perceived disconnect between work activities observed in the field (e.g. returning to a particular area multiple times to repair potholes) and a general lack of understanding of internal organisational decision strategies, processes and contractual constraints.</p><p>To date these points have not been considered during the development of civic engagement tools and yet our research suggests that all of these are crucial to the creation of successful systems. Understanding and then operationalising trust in systems or trust in applications is difficult, as Thatcher et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> indicate. Unlike Goncalves et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> we were not especially motivated to explore psychological aspects of citizen engagement or disengagement but note their comment that 'a successful system should allow citizens to easily express the details of the service changes they desire, this is not enough on its own, and citizens require additional motivation to actively participate'.</p><p>In evaluating our civic engagement application, and its relative failure, aspects of Grudin's <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> classic analyses of why applications fail seem appropriate. With the loss of our 'champion' the council's priorities were attuned to more obvious 'political' considerations. As one of our contractors said in regard to 'smart gully services' (where only selected gullies are cleaned) "the problem with the council is that the guy who was most interested has left ... the drainage engineer said, no, we're cleaning them all ... I can understand why ... autumn comes, the leaves fall and we get blocked gullies ... if a gully sucker pulled up in a street and only cleaned one they'd (the public) all be on the phone"</p><p>Success might have been more likely had we recruited a greater number of users -what Grudin terms 'critical mass'and we could have thought more carefully about the adoption and deployment process, (although nobody could have predicted the drought). Certainly it could be suggested that our civic engagement application was a technical success but an organisational failure, that is, there was a need for a clearer understanding of the necessary support within the council for implementing and managing change. As Akamavi et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> suggest, civic engagement presents both organisations and individuals with opportunities for sharing knowledge but any success is dependent on an organisational culture and trust that supports knowledge sharing. The relative failure of civic authorities to actively engage with the system underlines our much broader argument that designing for civic engagement requires a much more complex view of trust, including how it is manifested in everyday interaction and relationships within and between the different stakeholders as well as 'through' the technology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p>This paper considers two different, but clearly and essentially related, issues: how to design for civic engagement and how to think about trust in IT design. There is a clear thread in research and analysis that points to technology as fostering and encouraging social detachment and disengagement, as in Putnam's famous concerns about "bowling alone" <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. This paper has pursued a rather different research agenda to consider the ways in which technology might contribute to increasing citizen engagement. This is based on a reasonable belief that we are heading towards a future that will increasingly involve partnerships between citizens and civic authorities to enable individuals to become more engaged in civic planning, service delivery and infrastructure management. But this application domain is poorly understood by most system designers who focus almost exclusively on empowering citizens rather than considering the needs of both citizens and civic authorities and establishing trusted relationships between these stakeholders. Our analysis of the trust relationship between the different stakeholders highlights issues that appear crucial to fostering civic engagement, issues that are integral to but go well beyond the initial design of the technology to include its deployment and evaluation.</p><p>In this paper we have provided detailed insights into civic management processes that we believe will benefit developers of future civic engagement systems. Based on these insights we have described the design, implementation and evaluation of an open engagement platform to support experiments with two-way dialogues across mobile citizen and back-end civic technologies used to support a civic-engagement tool that has provided further insights into the domain of citizencivic engagement. Olphert et al. suggest that e-government development is typically 'characterised by a techno-centric approach with minimal engagement of citizens' and consequently advocate a participatory approach 'providing citizens with the necessary skills and capabilities to engage effectively offers the key to the successful development of systems such as e-government which impact our lives in the 21st century Information Society' <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</p><p>Our research suggests that part of that participatory approach involves understanding user notions of trust, as part of the design, co-design and re-design of trusted technologies to support civic engagement. This paper has been concerned with exactly this issue of how technology can be designed, developed and utilised to encourage and facilitate active citizen involvement, and how this both impacts on and is impacted by different stakeholders and different manifestations of trust.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Highways maintenance actors and process</figDesc><graphic coords="3,357.48,270.86,170.15,108.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Initial prototype design</figDesc><graphic coords="6,76.92,195.87,97.23,145.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Flooder/SmartStreet application cation integrated with the civic engagement platform, leveraging enhanced features to represent public user entities (i.e.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,76.92,522.64,97.23,145.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>"It would be to a lot of people ... Depends on what it is, if it is related to a person, you wouldn't want that person to know ... But if it is something happening then you wouldn't mind, and if someone knows you are a trusted person, like maybe they see your name they are going to trust it. The council would trust you so they broadcast it. If you attach your name to it then they wont think it was a bogus report. So long as they don't send it out with your name."</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>.. to put an exact location ... By the time you press it you could be 3-4 miles away, you want to do it, especially if you have to stop your car or something like that, it could be a bit away ... so you want a couple of ways of notifying of when there is a flood ... One where you can just press on the location and then write a report and another one where you can't do that because your driving at the time but when you stop further up the road you want to pin point it more accurately" "... or just use ... my location and have a drop down of reports instead of filling it in yourself have an automatic one that is already filled in so you just then go back and edit it later on ... So you could do that and go ... oh theres flooding here with a drain ... and then give a description of what it is when you've stopped the car"</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Wisdom of Crowds: Why the Many Are Smarter Than the Few. James Surowiecki</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge sharing and computer supported collaborative work: the role of organisational culture and trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Akamavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kimble</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 10th Conference of the United Kingdom Academy of Information Systems</title>
		<meeting>the 10th Conference of the United Kingdom Academy of Information Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Citeseer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">22</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Annual local authority road maintenance (alarm) survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Alliance</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.asphaltindustryalliance.com/images/library/files/ALARM_Survey_2014.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Amazon mechanical turk website</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Amazon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.mturk.com/" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A vehicle for research: Using street sweepers to explore the landscape of environmental community action</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Aoki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Honicky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mainwaring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Paulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Subramanian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Woodruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, CHI &apos;09</title>
		<meeting>the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, CHI &apos;09<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="384" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nyc 311 -issue reporting mobile application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Association</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www1.nyc.gov/connect/applications.page" />
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2014" to="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust and antitrust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ethics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="260" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust-based authentication scheme with user rating for low-resource devices in smart environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>El Husseini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>M'hamed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>El Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mokhtari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Personal Ubiquitous Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1013" to="1023" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-06">June 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">for an Urban Future, C. Caution ahead: Overdue nvestments for new york&apos;s aging infrastructure</title>
		<ptr target="http://nhtsurvey2013.econtrack.co.uk" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-03">March 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Citizen motivation on the go: The role of psychological empowerment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gonc alves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kostakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Karapanos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barreto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Camacho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tomasic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zimmerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Interacting with Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>iwt035</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">National highways public satisfaction survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S S</forename><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://nhtsurvey2013.econtrack.co.uk" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why cscw applications fail: problems in the design and evaluationof organizational interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grudin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1988 ACM conference on Computer-supported cooperative work</title>
		<meeting>the 1988 ACM conference on Computer-supported cooperative work</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trustworthy query answering with spatial crowdsourcing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kazemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Shahabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Geotrucrowd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 21st ACM SIGSPATIAL International Conference on Advances in Geographic Information Systems, SIGSPATIAL&apos;13</title>
		<meeting>the 21st ACM SIGSPATIAL International Conference on Advances in Geographic Information Systems, SIGSPATIAL&apos;13<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="323" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trustworthy by design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Knowles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Blair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rouncefield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Walden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 17th ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work Social Computing, CSCW &apos;14</title>
		<meeting>the 17th ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work Social Computing, CSCW &apos;14<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1060" to="1071" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Citizen participation and engagement in the design of e-government services: The missing link in effective ict design and delivery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Olphert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Damodaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. AIS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Open311 civic issue tracking specification</title>
		<ptr target="http://open311.org/" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.fixmystreet.com/" />
		<title level="m">Fix my street website</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Neat streets website</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Org</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>www.neatstreets.com.au</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Spires</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Farook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mean</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">State of Trust -How to Build Better Relationships Between Councils and the Public</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Designing systems that people will trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Patrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Marsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Briggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bowling Alone: The Collapse and Revival of American Community</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Putnam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Simon &amp; Schuster</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Not so different after all: A cross-discipline view of trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Sitkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Burt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Camerer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academy of Management Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A classification and investigation of trustees in b-to-c e-commerce: General vs. specific trust</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Thatcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the Association for Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improvemycity: An open source platform for direct citizen-government communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Tsampoulatidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ververidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tsarchopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nikolopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kompatsiaris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Komninos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 21st ACM International Conference on Multimedia, MM &apos;13</title>
		<meeting>the 21st ACM International Conference on Multimedia, MM &apos;13<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="839" to="842" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A reputation-aware decision-making approach for improving the efficiency of crowdsourcing systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Miao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">An</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2013 International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multi-agent Systems, AAMAS &apos;13</title>
		<meeting>the 2013 International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multi-agent Systems, AAMAS &apos;13<address><addrLine>Richland, SC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1315" to="1316" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
