<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Frame-Based Detection of Opinion Holders and Topics: A Model and a Tool Frame-Based Detection of Opinion Holders and Topics: A Model and a Tool</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Aldo</forename><surname>Gangemi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Valentina</forename><surname>Presutti</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Diego</forename><forename type="middle">Reforgiato</forename><surname>Recupero</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">STLab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">LIPN</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Paris13-CNRS-SorbonneCité</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">FRaNCe</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">ISTC-CNR</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="IT">ITaLY</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">STLab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">ISTC-CNR</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="IT">ITaLY</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Frame-Based Detection of Opinion Holders and Topics: A Model and a Tool Frame-Based Detection of Opinion Holders and Topics: A Model and a Tool</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">241281B74C6E6066025BB870DA026E79</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/MCI.2013.2291688</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T05:04+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Sentilo is a model and a tool to detect holders and topics of opinion sentences. Sentilo implements an approach based on the neo-Davidsonian assumption that events and situations are the primary entities for contextualizing opinions, which makes it able to distinguish holders, main topics, and sub-topics of an opinion. It uses a heuristic graph mining approach that relies on FRED, a machine reader for the Semantic Web that leverages Natural Language Processing (NLP) and Knowledge Representation (KR) components jointly with cognitively-inspired frames. The evaluation results are excellent for holder detection (F1: 95%), very good for subtopic detection (F1: 78%), and good for topic detection (F1: 68%).</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S</head><p>entiment Analysis (SA) aims at identifying and extracting the attitude of a subject i.e., an opinion holder, towards a topic, or the overall tonality of a document. In recent years, the exponential increase of Internet usage and exchange of public opinions on the Web is the driving force behind SA and made it become one of the most studied tasks of Natural Language Processing (NLP). The Web is a huge repository of structured and unstructured data: the analysis of this data in order to extract opinions and sentiments is an opportunity as well as a challenging problem. SA can be document-based, where the sentiment in the entire document is summarized as positive, negative or objective, as well as sentence based, where individual sentences bearing sentiments in the text are classified. Sentence-based SA can be fine-grained when specific contexts within a sentence are considered. We observe that fine grain enables a third variety of SA: aspect-based, where topics are associated to different sentiments according to the considered aspect of a topic.</p><p>SA can be generalized as the analysis of opinions: an opinion is an intentional statement by somebody (holder) on some fact (topic) that is expressed with a possible sentiment. Given a document or a set of documents, they may contain opinions about multiple topics that are interesting to users: in this scenario it is very important to be able to correctly detect topics, and to separate the opinions associated with each topic <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p>One problem that occurs in current SA approaches is the incorrect identification of opinion topics. In many recent SA systems such as <ref type="bibr">[1; 13; 30]</ref>, the user is prompted to just insert a topic in order to obtain a sentiment. Then the system returns a list of opinions on the specified topic. However, some of the returned results are useless to the user because they are out of the domain the user is interested in. For example, one user could look for opinions about Berlusconi, and get several results related to Berlusconi in politics, business, criminal investigations, or football. A different example based on a similar rationale is a user asking about opinions on the Italian Article 18 (Italy's labour code). In this case, opinions and sentiments can be expressed about e.g. its abolition, or in general about the Article itself.</p><p>A SA system should be able to differentiate those possibilities as well. This is practicable only if a system is able to properly distinguish the main topics from the sub-topics of an opinion, together with its holders. For both examples, it would be important to distinguish opinions that are expressed on Berlusconi or on Article 18 as main topics, from those expressed about events or situations involving Berlusconi or Article 18, or other accessory topics. In the latter case, they would be sub-topics, hence the opinion considered indirect. For example, if one expressed a positive opinion on the abolition of Article 18, this would be indirectly a negative opinion on the Article 18. Most existing SA systems would however recognize Article 18 as a topic with a positive opinion, hence providing the wrong analysis for the sentiment, due to the incorrect identification of the main topic.</p><p>In fact, several works <ref type="bibr">[28; 12; 39; 21]</ref> show that considering topics jointly with sentiment features improves the performance of SA systems, although those works do not focus on topic detection as a specific task. A first step toward addressing this issue has been done by sentic computing, defined as <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>: "...A multi-disciplinary approach to sentiment analysis at the cross-roads between affective computing and common sense computing, which exploits both computer and social sciences to better recognize, interpret, and process opinions and sentiments over the Web." One of the goals of sentic computing is to bridge the semantic gap between word-level natural language data and the concept-level opinions conveyed by these so as to provide a more efficient passage from unstructured textual information to structured machine-processable data.</p><p>Following the same direction, this article presents a novel computational intelligence method for SA, focused on representing the semantics of a sentence by modeling the roles played by its elements with respect to a model of opinion sentences. We show, by means of a set of examples and an evaluation, that this representation allows SA to precisely identify opinion holders and topics, hence providing the basis for improving the accuracy of sentence-and aspect-based SA. Our method combines NLP with knowledge representation, but we also envision the application of fuzzy logic, combinatorial optimization, and analogical reasoning to arrive at a full-fledged sentic computing solution.</p><p>Role assignment in our opinion model relies on the exploitation of fine-grained semantics, combined with frame-based lexical and syntactic analysis. It has been proved in <ref type="bibr">[36; 21; 10]</ref> that the quality of SA algorithms improves when considering semantic features. However, in these works (as in many others that focus on the analysis of tweets), topic detection is performed by relying on named entity recognition or by assuming that sentences are topic-based, which can prove efficient only in such specific settings. Existing approaches are mainly based on supervised techniques. Although they prove very effective in many tests, they have three main weaknesses: reliance on manually labelled samples, such as movies and products reviews; need of opinion expressed with explicit sentiment; limited portability, as their performance can change significantly when a same method is applied to a different domain. On the contrary, our method is domain-independent, meaning that it is completely automatic and unsupervised: it does not need a training phase. It performs a semantic interpretation of sentences according to a formal opinion model (cf. Section 3), and is able to identify relevant entities of an opinion regardless of the presence of explicit expressions of sentiment in a text. We show that our method is able to detect opinion holders with an accuracy of 95%, opinion main topics with 68%, and opinion subtopics with 78% (F1 measure).</p><p>Our contribution can be summarized as follows: ❏ a new challenging task: detection of opinion holders, main topics and sub-topics;</p><p>❏ a method based on combining formal knowledge representation, natural language processing, and cognitively-founded frames for opinion mining; ❏ an implementation of this method, named Sentilo<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">1</ref> , which, given an opinion sentence, returns its semantic representation annotated with opinion-relevant concepts; ❏ a model for opinion sentences that we use for annotating their semantic representation. The paper is structured as follows: Section 2 discusses relevant related work; Section 3 presents our method and describes the opinion model; Section 4 describes Sentilo. Results and evaluation of our approach are shown in Section 5 whereas Section 6 drafts the conclusions and discusses future directions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Related Work</head><p>Comprehensive surveys on opinion mining and sentiment analysis are provided in literature by <ref type="bibr">[9; 6; 29; 17; 23]</ref>, hence we do not attempt any additional survey. In this section, we discuss works relevant to our approach, and list some of the most popular lexical resources that are used for supporting opinion mining.</p><p>Most existing SA approaches neglect the topic detection task because they focus on the identification of sentiment features and on the analysis of the tone of an opinion. Several works <ref type="bibr">[28; 12; 39; 21]</ref> have considered the inclusion of topic detection as an important issue for improving SA, however instead of focusing on the topic detection task itself, and evaluating their approaches in this respect, they include topics within their models, assuming that their identification is correct on a statistical basis, and then evaluate the aggregate results from a SA task perspective. Moreover, these approaches rely on the presence of sentiment features for the identification of topics, as their interest is on opinions that bear some explicit sentiment expression, hence they do not consider the identification of opinion topics in general.</p><p>As for opinion holder extraction, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[40]</ref> compares three different methods based on classifiers for holder extraction and proposes a novel method for addressing the less common case of opinion holder playing a patient role. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> uses semantic role labeling based on FrameNet <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[34]</ref> for identifying holder and topic in an opinion sentence focusing on a specific domain.</p><p>In this paper we focus on identifying holder and topics of an opinion independently of the presence of sentiment features and show that our approach is promising with respect to the more general opinion mining task. With regards to popular resources that are used for supporting opinion mining and SA, we have considered (and partly used in the current version of our tool): ❏ SenticNet <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> is a publicly available semantic and a affective resource for concept-level opinion and sentiment analysis.</p><p>SenticNet is built by means of sentic computing, a paradigm that exploits both AI and Semantic Web techniques to better recognize, interpret, and process natural language opinions over the Web. We have integrated SenticNet in our implementation in order to retrieve the polarity scores of terms expressing sentiment, which will be used in the next evolution of Sentilo i.e., polarity classification of opinions associated with their topics and sub-topics. ❏ SentiWordNet <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> is a lexical resource for opinion mining.</p><p>SentiWordNet assigns to each synset of WordNet three sentiment scores: positivity, negativity, objectivity. This resource is integrated in Sentilo with the same aim as the integration of SenticNet. ❏ VerbNet (VN) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> is the largest on-line verb lexicon currently available for English. It is a hierarchical domainindependent, broad-coverage verb lexicon with mappings to other lexical resources such as Word-Net, Xtag and FrameNet. VerbNet is organized into (frame-like) verb classes extending Levin's <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>classes through refinement and addition of subclasses to achieve syntactic and semantic coherence among members of a class. Each verb class is described by "frames" consisting of a syntactic description and semantic predicates, with thematic roles and selectional restrictions on the arguments. We exploit VerbNet in the frame-based semantic representation of opinion sentences. In particular, VerbNet thematic roles are a key reference in our approach for the definition of heuristics that helps in detecting holders and the topics of an opinion (see Section 4).</p><p>FrameNet <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[34]</ref> and LIWC <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> are additional examples of available lexical resources that can be exploited in SA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">A Model for Sentic Computing</head><p>Adapting the definition from <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, we describe an opinion as an intentional statement made by somebody (holder) on some fact (topic), which is expressed with a possible sentiment.</p><p>Opinion sentences can refer to the holder of an opinion either explicitly or implicitly. For example, in the sentence "I believe the issue raised by the President is sufficiently important", the holder of the sentiment is explicit and is denoted by "I". It can be recognized thanks to the verb "believe", which also announces that an opinion (possibly with some sentiment) about a certain topic (i.e. the issue raised by the President) is expressed elsewhere in the sentence. In the sentence "The issue raised by the President is sufficiently important", the holder is implicit (or externally identifiable, e.g. as the author of the text or through other provenance mechanisms).</p><p>Similarly, the sentiment about a topic can be either implicit or explicit. The above mentioned sentences express explicitly a sentiment about the topic, however sometimes this does not happen. For example, consider the sentence "He said that the patient was suffering from tick bite fever". Again, the holder is explicit (i.e. "he"), and the verb "said" announces that an opinion is to be expressed in the sentence, but the fact (i.e., the patient was suffering from tick bite fever) is not associated with an explicit sentiment.</p><p>Special attention has to be given to topics of an opinion. Sentiment analysis is also useful for supporting answers to questions such as: given a topic, what is the trend of opinions about it? For this reason, it is important to correctly identify topics of an opinion, and to distinguish main topics from sub-topics, which sometimes can be complex. For example, the sentence "I appreciate that Berlusconi finally has been condemned", expresses a positive sentiment about the fact: "Berlusconi has been condemned". However, if one is interested in knowing the trend of opinions about Berlusconi, this positive expression should be attributed to the set of negative sentiments about him, as Berlusconi is a subtopic in this opinionated sentence, and the event "condemn" has a negative impact on him.</p><p>In order to handle all these issues, and to be able to recognize holders and topics of an opinion, we use an approach that combines knowledge representation and NLP. We first produce a semantic representation of an opinion sentence (described in Section 3.1), and then we annotate it with a model for opinions (described in Section 3.2) that identifies the opinion holder(s), topic(s), and sub-topic(s).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Frame-Based Semantic Representation of Sentences</head><p>As far as the semantic representation of sentences is concerned, we make an ontological commitment inspired by Davidson's view <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> that the world is primarily described in terms of events and situations (i.e., occurrences of frames), where objects are typically involved in some specific event or situation. Based on this view, we produce an RDF/OWL semantic representation of an opinion sentence as a series of linked events or situations, and their participating objects. We implement this theory as a frame-based knowledge extraction approach (see Section 4). We use DOLCE + DnS [31; 18] as a vocabulary for events and situations 2 , and VerbNet [35] as a reference resource for thematic roles of events. Our commitment has the consequence that we look first for events or situations as main topics, and only when these cannot be extracted, we look for objects or other entities. This will become clearer later in the paper. Events and situations are also typed, and their types are supposed to approximate existing cognitively-inspired frames (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>) as in FrameNet <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[34]</ref>, but also they can bear locally extracted roles, so that appropriate algorithms can discover new frames based on frequency, relevance, or other criteria.</p><p>Let us consider the following example: "Anna says the weather will become beautiful". Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows the semantic representation of this sentence, which follows our ontological assumption. The sentence expresses a main event identified by the verb "says", the agent of which is Anna and the topic role 3 of which is an event identified by the verb "become" (i.e., "the weather will become beautiful"); weather is the agent of such event. Additionally, we represent that "will" expresses a particular modality for the verb, e.g., necessarily, and that weather is qualified by the quality beautiful. 2 prefix dul: stands for http://www.ontologydesignpatterns.org/ont/dul/DUL.owl and prefix rdf: stands for http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#.</p><p>3 "topic" here is a thematic role for the event "say" according to VerbNet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">a Model for Opinion</head><p>Our opinion model defines the main concepts characterizing an opinion, and is used for annotating the semantic representation of a sentence, in order to identify its opinion holder and topic. Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> depicts our opinion model. We define the semantic representation of an opinion sentence as having two parts 4 : (i) opinion trigger context and (ii) opinionated context. The opinion trigger context is optional and identifies concepts that indicate the presence of an opinion expressed in the sentence, and its holder. It is composed of two parts: the entities that allow the identification of the opinion holders (i.e. holders), and the events e.g., think, say, support, etc., that act as triggers of an opinion (i.e., opinion triggers).</p><p>The opinionated context identifies concepts that express an opinion (possibly including sentiments). It is composed of two parts: the entities that identify the opinion topics (i.e., topics), and those expressing the opinion and its possible associated sentiments (i.e., the opinion features). In some cases, terms that activate an opinion can also convey the opinion itself or a possible sentiment, e.g. "approve" or "deny". When this happens, such terms play the role of opinion triggers as well as that of opinion features.</p><p>As for topics, we distinguish between main topics and sub-topics (see Figure <ref type="figure">2 (b)</ref>). In fact, a topic can be a complex structure e.g., an event or a situation, including other complex structure. For the purpose of SA, it is important to distinguish all main topics, that are the direct targets of an opinion, from sub-topics, which could be indirect targets of an opinion. For example, the main topic of the opinion sentence represented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> is the event become, while weather is a sub-topic. The following axioms formalize the concepts of main topic and sub-topic by using a standard description logic syntax, directly translatable into OWL.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(MainTopic SubTopic) Topic . 5<label>(1)</label></formula><p>Topics (of opinion sentences) can be either main topics (direct targets of the opinion) or sub-topics (indirect targets of an opinion). <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Note that an opinion sentence can have nested opinion sentences as its parts: this is represented by the relation hasPartOpinionSentence. Each of them can be represented according to the two-parts model described here. (2)</p><p>When a main topic is a situation, its involved entities are subtopics.</p><p>(Topic ( dependsOn(dul: Event MainTopic) ) )</p><p>SubTopic</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">- - 7 5<label>(3)</label></formula><p>When a main topic is an event, entities that have a dependency relation with it are sub-topics. Examples of dependency relations are: participation in the event (e.g., having a role in it), causality relations, temporal relations e.g., follows, precedes), etc. In order to annotate the semantic representation of an opinion sentence with this model, we rely on three interpretation layers: ❏ Lexical layer: it provides the terms (and possibly a score for them) that act as triggers of an opinion or as opinion features. From an implementation perspective, this layer depends on the lexical resources used jointly with the NLP procedure.</p><p>In our case, we are using Sentic-Net <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, SentiWord-Net <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, and a revision of the Levin's classification of verbs (see Section 4). ❏ Syntactic layer: it provides the syntactic constructs that are relevant in an opinion expression. From an implementation perspective, this layer is addressed by means of part of speech tagging, dependency parsing, and coreference resolution. ❏ Semantic layer: it provides the semantic constructs that are relevant in an opinion model. These are relations, roles, qualities, modalities, negation. From an implementation perspective, this layer is addressed by means of a set of heuristics that map natural language into an event-based logical representation. We use a tool named FRED <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[33]</ref> that produces an event-based RDF/OWL representation of natural language text (see <ref type="bibr">Section 4)</ref>. Following the opinion model, the semantic representation of the sentence "Anna says the weather will become beautiful" presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> is annotated as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>.</p><p>The opinion trigger context is composed of the event say (i.e., opinion trigger) and its agent Anna (i.e., holder). The main topic is identified as the event become (which is not associated with any specific opinion feature). As weather has a dependency relation with the event become (it participates in it with the role of agent), it is identified as a sub-topic. The quality beautiful is annotated as an opinion feature of a sub-topic. The semantic representation of the sentence "anna says the weather will become beautiful" annotated according to the opinion model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Sentilo: Identifying Holders and Topics of an Opinion Sentence</head><p>From an implementation perspective, our approach (named Sentilo) is realized as a pipeline of components depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>, where colored components indicate novel contributions.</p><p>Components in dashed boxes are currently being developed. To the best of our knowledge, Sentilo is the first method for opinion mining that hybridizes formal semantics, NLP and typical computational intelligence techniques.</p><p>In order to explain the pipeline, let us consider the following sentence from the corpus we have used for the evaluation (presented in Section 5): Drug dealers have lost some 3,600 kilos of narcotics, the colonel said.</p><p>The syntactic constructs (cf. Section 3) are provided by C&amp;C <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, a combinatory categorial parser that integrates named entity recognition, a categorial equivalent of dependency relation extraction, and co-reference resolution. The output of C&amp;C for the sample sentence is depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>.</p><p>The output of C&amp;C is processed by Boxer <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, an opensource software that produces event-based, verb-centric, semantic representations of natural language complying with Discourse Representation Theory (DRT) DRT is a  formal theory of meaning originally described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. It provides an event-based model to represent natural language, and is compatible with first-order logic (FOL). DRT uses an explicit semantic structured language called Discourse Representation Structure (DRS). In Boxer, DRS are enriched with the VerbNet [35] inventory of thematic roles. Boxer uses thousands of heuristic rules to transform C&amp;C trees into logical DRS representations. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows the output of Boxer for our sample sentence. The first box introduces a first existential quantification on a variable that is predicated as "colonel", while the second box contains a new event predicated variable ("say(e1)"), and two semantic roles declarations, one of which has an embedded proposition "p2" as arguments. The referent of the p2 variable is a box that contains the bulk of Boxer's representation, with more variables predications, semantic roles, and co-references.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[33]</ref> we have presented FRED,<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">5</ref> a tool that formally maps DRT logical forms (DRS) to RDF/OWL by exploiting framebased design, and by implementing a set of heuristics that address terminology and structure generation according to Semantic Web design practices. FRED enables the semantic representation of opinion sentences according to the frame-based model described in Section 3.1. FRED heuristics are designed to take into account the semantic interpretation of language when transforming it to a formalized form. It addresses, besides sense tagging (to associate a type to a certain entity), sense disambiguation (to identify the correct sense of a term given a certain context), semantic role labeling (to assign a thematic role to an entity, in the context of an event it participates in), terminology extraction and composition, taxonomy induction, named entity resolution, etc., and also issues that are important for opinion and sentiment mining: attribute detection, situation modeling, negation and modality representation. FRED is in charge of processing Boxer output, and of producing its RDF/ OWL representation: Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref> shows the semantic representation of the sample sentence as it is provided by FRED 6 .</p><p>FRED recognizes and represents two main event occurrences in this sentence, i.e. fred:say_1, 7 and fred:lose_1. For each of them it provides a type and identifies its participating entities, e.g. fred:colonel_1 participates in fred:say_1 with the role of agent 8 . Each entity is assigned with a type and aligned, if possible, to an existing Semantic Web entity, e.g. an entity from a Linked Data dataset, e.g. DBpedia, WordNet, etc. In order to obtain a form compliant to Semantic Web modeling from Boxer output we perform a number transformations e.g., the variables from Boxer output are either eliminated, or transformed into new individuals, when they refer to actual entities in discourse representation; the p2 proposition is interpreted as a "situation" that is eventually resolved to its main contained event (fred:lose_1); the "drug" and "dealer" predicates are composed in the new class fred:DrugDealer, with a subclass axiom to fred:Dealer, etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Opinion Model annotator</head><p>On top of FRED, we have developed an opinion model annotator <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[37]</ref>, a component that implements a set of heuristics that extract, from the FRED's graph of a given sentence, information about holders of an opinion sentence, its topics, and its opinion expressing words (i.e., opinion features). Sentilo enriches the RDF/OWL semantic representation of an opinion sentence with annotation triples based on our opinion model (cf. Section 3.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Holder Detection</head><p>To detect opinion holders we rely on Levinopinion (cf. Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>), a revision of Levin's classification of verbs <ref type="bibr">[27; 38]</ref>: we have classified four classes of opinion verbs that imply the presence of an holder; we call them opinion trigger verbs. It is possible to download the four categories of verbs from <ref type="bibr">[32]</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> specifies the relationship between different verb categories (referring to Levin's classification) depending on the presence of an holder which is stating or denying a fact, or if they imply a positive sentiment. When a trigger verb is not present in a sentence, the holder is assumed to be implicit (e.g. the author of the sentence). The four classes of trigger verbs can be described as follows: ❏ Holder activation verbs: verbs such as accept, agree, think, say, tell, cite, claim, recognize, etc. which indicate the presence of an opinion holder who is the subject of the underlying verb; subjects of such verbs are a affirming something expressed in the opinionated context. Verbs in this class appear in the opinion trigger context described in Section 3.2;</p><p>6</p><p>We have removed part of the graph for space reason, the reader is welcome to submit the sentence to FRED or Sentilo online to see the complete output. ❏ Holder activation negated verbs: verbs such as contest, disagree, dismiss, oppose, refuse, reject, etc. which indicate the presence of an opinion holder, who is the subject of the underlying verb; subjects of such verbs have an opinion which is in contrast with whatever is expressed in the opinionated context. Basically, this class of verbs is equivalent to the first class when a negation such as do not, never, etc. is present; ❏ Holder positive polarity verbs: verbs such as love, like, honor, support, etc.. These verbs indicate the presence of an opinion holder expressing a positive sentiment on some topic(s). Verbs in this category appear in the opinion trigger context and have an impact on the opinionated contexts (Section 3.2); ❏ Holder negative polarity verbs: verbs such as dislike, hate, etc..</p><p>These verbs indicate the presence of an opinion holder expressing a negative sentiment on some topic(s). This class of verbs is equivalent to the previous one when a negation occurs. Verbs in this category appear in the opinion trigger context and impact on the opinionated contexts (Section 3.2). Based on our Davidson's theory-based assumption, a verb in a sentence denotes an occurrence of an event, which is participated in by a number of entities, each having a specic role: if a trigger event is detected in a sentence, its participating agent is annotated as the opinion holder.</p><p>In our sample sentence "Drug dealers have lost some 3,600 kilos of narcotics, the colonel said", the verb said is detected as an holder activation verb, hence its associated event instance fred:say_1 is used for identifying the opinion holder that is the entity fred:colonel_1). This is obtained by recognizing the triple pattern: fred:say_1 vn.role:Agent ?holder .</p><p>It might happen that a same verb is classified in more than one category. For example, the verb accept belongs to both Holder activation verbs and Holder positive polarity verbs as it both implies the presence of an holder and the presence of a positive sentiment on a certain topic. This information will influence the computation of sentiment scores associated with the opinion topics, a task that we leave for future development.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>topic Detection</head><p>As for topic detection, Sentilo distinguishes main topics from sub-topics of an opinion. To enable this capability we have defined two equivalent classes of VerbNet thematic roles: a class named AGT, which includes all agentive roles, and a class named PTT, which includes all passive roles. Sentilo annotates as main topics those entities that participate in a trigger event playing a PTT role. If the sentence misses a trigger event, all entities (modulo some exceptions) having only outgoing arcs in the graph (roots) are annotated as main topics.</p><p>Recognizing sub-topics is a more complex and sophisticated task. Given an opinion expressed on an event, such opinion can convey an indirect opinion about some of its participating entities. For example, the sentence: I am happy that Berlusconi has been condemned for fiscal evasion. expresses an opinion (positive) on the condemnation event, and indirectly it conveys an opinion (negative) on Berlusconi, while it does not express an opinion on the specific motivation of the condemnation. Hence, in this case "Berlusconi" should be annotated as a sub-topic, while "fiscal evasion" should not. We say that only entities that play sensitive roles in an event are sub-topics. 9  Establishing if a role is sensitive for an event depends on the specific context. However, we have empirically observed that the roles belonging to AGT and PTT are sensitive in most of the cases. Based on this rationale, our heuristics for annotating sub-topics refines the Formula 3 (cf. Section 3.2) as defined by the following Formula 4.</p><p>(Topic ( (AGT PTT)(dul:Event MainTopic) ) )</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">SubTopic - . - 7 5<label>(4)</label></formula><p>When a main topic is an event, entities that participate in it having either an agentive role or a passive role are sub-topics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>upcoming Extensions</head><p>The following extensions to the system are currently under study: ❏ Sentiment score computation, which uses both the scores provided by SenticNet and SentiWordNet and the semantics of the representation model to assess sentiment scores to the detected topics. ❏ Topic co-reference resolution, which deals with the synonymy between entities or topics, where the goal is to recognize the same situations or events denoted using different expressions, using similarity methods combined with semantic models produced using FRED. 9</p><p>However, future work should take into account contextual effects on sensitivity. For example, the sentence I am happy that Berlusconi has been condemned precisely for fiscal evasion. contains a modifier that shifts sensitivity also to the oblique role filled by "fiscal evasion".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Holder Activation</head><p>Holder Activation, Negated ❏ Topic and opinion models index, which deals with the indexing of the discovered/detected topic associated with their sentiment models. ❏ Fuzzy reasoning, which will be utilized to handle multiple opinion feature scores in a more flexible (natural, humanfriendly) manner. This will be done by using fuzzy varieties of OWL, such as Fuzzy OWL2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, and the related automated reasoners; ❏ Learning mechanisms, sentic pattern discovery, and combinatorial optimization, which will be investigated to further improve the accuracy of the proposed approach. In our case, the graph representations of FRED, and its augmentation with the Sentilo model, provide ordered sets of features that will be reused to train machine learning classifiers, and to perform sentiment patterns discovery, as a variety of knowledge patterns <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. Another interesting direction is in extending combinatorial optimization applied to parsing trees (as e.g. reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>) to FRED's semantic graphs; ❏ Analogical reasoning, which can be used to deal with sarcasm by extending the known or newly discovered sentic patterns to figurative and ironic modalities. Here AffectiveSpace <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> can play an important role as well, once its concepts are associated to frame-based knowledge.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Results and Evaluation</head><p>Sentilo has been evaluated on 50 sentences, including a subset of the MPQA opinion corpus <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, and sentences extracted from the Europarl corpus 10 . MPQA was originally used for the opinion analysis task with training and test cases. Our model does not require training, since it is based on the semantic output of FRED. We can then compare our approach to the original annotations about opinion holders 11  provided in the corpus, incremented with appropriate annotations made by three annotators also for the main topics and subtopics of those opinions. Three annotators have been instructed on our assumptions about events and situations to be taken as preferential main topics, and once they have expressed their choices, they have been allowed to discuss in cases of disagreement.</p><p>They have reached a complete agreement in all cases for holder's identification (modulo the three amendments made to the original benchmark), in 47 cases out of 50 for topic identification (.96 is the average interrater proportional agreement), and in 36 cases out of 50 for subtopic identification (.81 is the average interrater proportional agreement). 12 When annotators did not reach a complete agreement, we accepted the choice of the majority (2 out of 3). We have used proportional agreement because in this case we need an absolute agreement measure, not a relative reliability measure such as Cohen's k. Reliability measures are important when variation within the sample is of interest, e.g. when the research question refers to suitability of a test in a particular setting, cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, which is not the case of simple acceptability of annotations. In such simple cases reliability can even produce paradoxical results, as reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</p><p>The information measures for holder detection and topic detection (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref>) include precision, recall, F1, and accuracy, where the positives and negatives have been calculated locally on each sentence output, i.e. the maximum score for each sentence is 1 for true positives plus false negatives, and for false positives plus true negatives. The reason for this localization is straightforward: each sentence is expected to provide a closed set of holders and topics, and we are interested in the performance of Sentilo for each sentence, not for the joint opinion space of the collection of sentences. The results are very satisfactory for holder detection, where two heuristics provide very high accuracy for most cases, i.e. choosing agentive entities in triggering events, or choosing an implicit holder when all explicit heuristics fail.</p><p>The results are good also for main topic detection, a novel task in the way we perform it here, i.e. by assuming a Davidsonian world, where main entities are assumed to be events or situations, except when purely attributive states of a affairs are referenced. Consider that for this first test, we have applied a few heuristical rules for subgraph mining, without refining them, and without overfitting them after evaluation. Our intent is actually to have a feedback on the validity of our hypotheses, while leaving the optimization of detection methods, and their application to the ranking of opinion features.</p><p>As expected, difficult sentences for main topic detection (14/50) seem to concentrate on unusual syntactic constructions within complex sentences, which require specific rules to enable topic detection. Difficult sentences for topic detection often have an implicit holder (6/14 while the expected distribution should be 4/14), which may indicate an insufficiency in the subgraph extraction heuristics currently used for sentences with implicit holders.</p><p>For subtopics, the results are slightly better than main topics, probably because of the strong connectedness of FRED graphs that allows reaching at subtopics even from wrong main topics. This happens because FRED has been designed to maximize the amount of links between the semantic elements expressed by a sentence: syntactic dependencies, compositional lexical dependencies, automatic typing, robust semantic role labeling even in the absence of a known frame, disambiguation of named entities and word senses. Therefore, the (subjective at the moment) impression is that even when the primary topic attachment is not expected, a correct subtopic can be still reached through one of the paths activated by FRED. Heuristics refinement is however barely due in this case, since we have started only with the rules based on the formal definitions given in 2 and 3 (cf. Section 3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion and Future Work</head><p>As described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, the current state of art in sentiment analysis and opinion mining suffers from simplistic techniques, which leave several challenges, including: (a) compositionality of opinion, (b) opinionated entity disambiguation, (c) contextualization of sentiment, (d) dealing with sarcasm, (e) noise in text, and (f) factual sentiment.</p><p>In this paper we have described a method and a tool for opinion holder and topic detection, which are crucial for (a), (c), and (f). Heuristic graph mining on top of a machine reader that converts sentences into RDF-OWL graphs proves to be a good idea for taking advantage of the relational features existing in the semantic structure of an opinionated text. Results are excellent for holder detection and good for topic/ subtopic detection, and improvement seems easily attainable by incrementally refining heuristics for topic and subtopic detection. Crowdsourcing techniques can be also applied to this task.</p><p>In addition, the use of a semantic-web-aware machine reader like FRED makes it simple to solve (b), at least for public entities and concepts that can be resolved on resources like DBpedia and WordNet. FRED foundation on cognitive frames is also handy for attempting (future work) a resolution of (d), based e.g. on formalizing AffectiveSpace <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> knowledge into frame-based representations.</p><p>Ongoing work concentrates on extracting opinion features from all graph patterns that are generated by Sentilo, and on designing an algorithm to calculate aspect-based opinion scores. The algorithm is being implemented, and will be functionally evaluated by comparison to state-of-art sentiment analysis tools. Moreover, computational intelligence methods (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>), including fuzzy reasoning, combinatorial optimization on graph mining, learning mechanisms, sentic pattern discovery and analogical reasoning, described in Section 4, are being developed on top of Sentilo.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1The semantic representation of the sentence "anna says the weather will become beautiful".</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 AFigure 3</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Figure 2 A model for opinion sentences.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 Figure 5</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Figure 4The pipeline of components in Sentilo.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>7 fred:Figure 6 Figure 7</head><label>767</label><figDesc>Figure 6The output of Boxer for the sentence "Drug dealers have lost some 3,600 kilos of narcotics, the colonel said".</figDesc><graphic coords="7,69.46,72.79,176.18,214.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>10 http://www.statmt.org/europarl/ 11 Our three annotators actually amended three holder annotations, which resulted inaccurate.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="2,120.88,340.27,341.28,178.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Information measures for holder and topic detection.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Measure/</cell><cell>Holder</cell><cell>Topic</cell><cell>subTopic</cell></row><row><cell>Task</cell><cell>deTecTion</cell><cell>deTecTion</cell><cell>deTecTion</cell></row><row><cell>PRECiSion</cell><cell>0.99</cell><cell>0.72</cell><cell>0.77</cell></row><row><cell>RECALL</cell><cell>0.91</cell><cell>0.64</cell><cell>0.77</cell></row><row><cell>F1</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>0.68</cell><cell>0.77</cell></row><row><cell>ACCuRACy</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>0.66</cell><cell>0.80</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>FEbruary 2014 | IEEE ComputatIonal IntEllIgEnCE magazInE 21 © wikimedia commons</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_1"><p>http://wit.istc.cnr.it/stlab-tools/sentilo</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_2"><p>http://wit.istc.cnr.it/stlab-tools/fred</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>The work described in this paper was performed with the support of the PRISMA (PiattafoRme cloud Interoperabili per SMArt-government) project, funded by the MIUR (Ministero dell'Istruzione, dell'Università e della Ricerca).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.sentiment140.com/" />
		<title level="m">Sentiment 140</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SentiWordNet 3.0: An enhanced lexical resource for sentiment analysis and opinion mining</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Esuli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Baccianella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sebastiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 7th conf. Int. Language Resources Evaluation</title>
		<meeting>7th conf. Int. Language Resources Evaluation<address><addrLine>Valletta, Malta</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-05">May 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy ontology representation using OWL 2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bobillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Straccia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1073" to="1094" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-10">Oct. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wide-coverage semantic analysis with Boxer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Conf. Semantics Text Processing</title>
		<meeting>Conf. Semantics Text essing<address><addrLine>Stroudsburg, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="286" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">VerbNet class assignment as a WSD task</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dligach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Ninth Int. Conf. Computational Semantics</title>
		<meeting>Ninth Int. Conf. Computational Semantics<address><addrLine>Stroudsburg, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="94" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cambria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Sentic Computing: Techniques, Tools, and Applications. Dordrecht</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SenticNet 2: A semantic and affective resource for opinion mining and sentiment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cambria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Havasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. FLAIRS Conf</title>
		<meeting>FLAIRS Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of multi-dimensional scaling and artificial neural networks for biologically inspired opinion mining</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cambria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mazzocco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Insp. Cogn. Arch</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-04">Apr. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New avenues in opinion mining and sentiment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cambria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Havasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semantic Web meets computational intelligence: State of the art and perspectives [review article]</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cudr-Mauroux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Comput. Intell. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://mpqa.cs.pitt.edu/corpora/mpqacorpus/" />
		<title level="m">MPQA opinion corpus</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leveraging sentiment analysis for topic detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spangler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Web Intell. Agent Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-08">Aug. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Opinion crawl</title>
		<ptr target="http://opinioncrawl.com/" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The logical form of action sentences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Logic of Decision and Action</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rescher</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Pittsburgh, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Univ. Pittsburgh Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="120" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinicians are right not to like Cohen&apos;s k</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C W</forename><surname>Vet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mokkink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Terwee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hoekstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Knol</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">346</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013-03">Mar. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the efficiency of a widecoverage CCG parser</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Djordjevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Curran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 10th Int. Conf. Parsing Technologies</title>
		<meeting>10th Int. Conf. Parsing Technologies<address><addrLine>Stroudsburg, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="47" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Techniques and applications for sentiment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-04">Apr. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What&apos;s in a schema</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gangemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Ontology and the Lexicon: A Natural Language Processing Perspective</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-R</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Calzolari</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gangemi</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lenci</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Oltramari</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Prevot</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, U.K.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="144" to="182" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a pattern science for the semantic Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gangemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Presutti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semant. web</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-04">Apr. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.liwc.net/" />
		<title level="m">Linguistic inquiry and word count</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relational features in fine-grained opinion analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moschitti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Linguistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="509" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A theory of truth and semantic representation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Formal Methods in the Study of Language</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A G</forename><surname>Groenendijk</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M V</forename><surname>Janssen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Stokhof</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Mathematisch Centrum</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="322" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy logic models for the meaning of emotion words</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kazemzadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Narayanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Comput. Intell. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-05">May 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determining the sentiment of opinions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-M</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hovy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 20th Int. Conf. Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>20th Int. Conf. Computational Linguistics<address><addrLine>Stroudsburg, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting opinions, opinion holders and topics expressed in online news media text</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-M</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hovy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Workshop Sentiment Subjectivity Text</title>
		<meeting>Workshop Sentiment Subjectivity Text<address><addrLine>Stroudsburg, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leveraging alternative grammar extraction strategies using lagrangian relaxation with PCFG-LA product model parsing: A case study with function labels and binarization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Roux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rozenknop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Foster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. EMNLP</title>
		<meeting>EMNLP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">English Verb Classes and Alternations A Preliminary Investigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Univ. Chicago Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Chicago and London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weakly supervised joint sentiment-topic detection from text</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Everson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ruger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Knowl. Data Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1134" to="1145" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthesis lectures on human language technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sentiment Analysis and Opinion Mining</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Rafael, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan and Claypool Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social mention</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.stlab.istc.cnr.it/documents/sentilo/levin-opinion.zip" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Dolce ultra lite ontology</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge extraction based on discourse representation theory and linguistic frames</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Presutti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Draicchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gangemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Knowledge Engineering and Knowledge Management</title>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin Heidelberg, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7603</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="129" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://verbs.colorado.edu/mpalmer/projects/verbnet.html" />
		<title level="m">The FrameNet project</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">The VerbNet project</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semantic sentiment analysis of twitter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Saif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Alani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 11th Int. conf. Semantic Web-Volume Part I</title>
		<meeting>11th Int. conf. Semantic Web-Volume Part I<address><addrLine>Berlin, Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="508" to="524" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sentilo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://wit.istc.cnr.it/stlab-tools/sentilo" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ava: Adjective-verb-adverb combinations for sentiment analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Subrahmanian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Reforgiato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling online reviews with multi-grain topic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Titov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mcdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 17th Int. Conf. World Wide Web</title>
		<meeting>17th Int. Conf. World Wide Web<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="120" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalization methods for in-domain and crossdomain opinion holder extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wiegand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Klakow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 13th Conf. European Chapter Association Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>13th Conf. European Chapter Association Computational Linguistics<address><addrLine>Stroudsburg, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="335" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
