<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Convergence Analysis of the Extended Kalman Filter Used as an Observer for Nonlinear Deterministic Discrete-Time Systems</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Boutayeb</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">CRAN CNRS URA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cosnes et Romain 54400</addrLine>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rafaralahy</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">CRAN CNRS URA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cosnes et Romain 54400</addrLine>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Darouach</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">CRAN CNRS URA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cosnes et Romain 54400</addrLine>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Convergence Analysis of the Extended Kalman Filter Used as an Observer for Nonlinear Deterministic Discrete-Time Systems</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2D4B4B6CE46956B2010CEB59CEA128EE</idno>
					<note type="submission">received June 5, 1995; revised October 17, 1995.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T05:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Convergence analysis</term>
					<term>deterministic nonlinear discretetime systems</term>
					<term>extended Kalman filter</term>
					<term>Lyapunov approach</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this paper, convergence analysis of the extended Kalman filter (EKF), when used as an observer for nonlinear deterministic discrete-time systems, is presented. Based on a new formulation of the first-order linearization technique, sufficient conditions to ensure local asymptotic convergence are established. Furthermore, it is shown that the design of the arbitrary matrix, namely R k in the paper, plays an important role in enlarging the domain of attraction and then improving the convergence of the modified EKF significantly. The efficiency of this approach, compared to the classical version of the EKF, is shown through a nonlinear identification problem as well as a state and parameter estimation of nonlinear discrete-time systems.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Since the 1960's, many research activities have been developed to deal with the problem of state estimation for nonlinear dynamical systems. The main motivation for doing so is that most physical processes are described by nonlinear mathematical models. Thus, several nonlinear state estimation methods have been performed to increase the accuracy and performances of the control system design.</p><p>Generally, we distinguish two approaches for nonlinear observers' design. The first one is based on some nonlinear state transformation using the Lie algebra. This approach brings the original system into a canonical form from which the design of state observers is performed using linear techniques in the new coordinates. Necessary and sufficient conditions for a standard nonlinear system to be state equivalent to the nonlinear canonical form, for both continuous and discrete-time cases, have been established in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[9]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[14]</ref>. We notice that only a few classes of forced nonlinear systems are considered by this nonlinear transformation.</p><p>The second approach is without transformation and is based on the linearized model. In spite of the local convergence of this method, it is widely used in practice and generally gives good results under less restrictive conditions than the first approach <ref type="bibr">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[16]</ref>. One of the most popular estimation techniques largely investigated for state estimation of nonlinear systems is the extended Kalman filter (EKF).</p><p>The EKF consists of using the classical Kalman filter equations to the first-order approximation of the nonlinear model about the last estimate. The literature is vast about this subject, and we refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[16]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[19]</ref> and the references therein. However, few works have been performed to analyze the stability and convergence of the filter. The main difficulty arises from the fact that the EKF equations are only approximate ones. So, the corresponding propagation equations are available only if the estimate belongs to a neighborhood of the actual state.</p><p>An interesting study of asymptotic behavior of the EKF, used for the joint parameter and state estimation of linear time-invariant systems, was developed by Ljung in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[11]</ref>. For this particular case, some modifications, such as coupling between parameters vector and the Kalman gain, were introduced to enhance convergence of the EKF. More recently, in a synthesis work on nonlinear discretetime systems, sufficient conditions of the EKF for noisy systems used as a local asymptotic observer for the deterministic case have been established by Song et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[15]</ref>. They have also shown that conditions needed to ensure the uniform boundedness of certain Riccati equations are related to the observability properties of the considered nonlinear system.</p><p>Recently, Cicarrella et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[18]</ref> have developed a robust observer, which uses n output values and the inverse of the observability matrix at each step, and the local convergence analysis for a multi-input/single-output (MISO) nonlinear discrete-time system was studied.</p><p>Motivated by the identification problem of time-invariant nonlinear systems <ref type="bibr">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>, we address here the problem of stability and the convergence of the EKF when used as a deterministic observer for multi-input/multi-output nonlinear discrete-time systems written in their general form. Based on a new formulation for the exact linearization technique, we introduce instrumental time-varying matrices for the stability and convergence analysis. It is pointed out that, under mild conditions, asymptotic behavior of the EKF may be improved significantly even for bad first-order approximation. To show accuracy and performances of this technique, we use the modified EKF at first as a parameter estimator for the Hammerstein model and secondly as a simultaneous state and parameter estimator of a nonlinear model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PROBLEM FORMULATION</head><p>The nonlinear systems considered here are of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">x k+1 = f (x k ; u k ) (1a) y k = h(x k ; u k ) (1b)</formula><p>where u k 2 R r and y k 2 R p are the input and output vectors at time instant k: We assume that f (x k ; u k ) and h(x k ; u k ) are differentiable on R n : The EKF for the associated noisy system that we use here as an observer of (1a), (1b) is:</p><p>1) measurement update</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">xk+1 = xk+1=k + K k+1 e k+1</formula><p>(2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">K k+1 = P k+1=k H T k+1 (H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 + R k+1 ) 01<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">P k+1 = (I 0 K k+1 H k+1 )P k+1=k<label>(4)</label></formula><p>2) time update</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">xk+1=k = f (x k ; u k )<label>(5)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">P k+1=k = F k P k F T k + Q k (6)</formula><p>0018-9286/97$10.00 © 1997 IEEE where e k+1 = y k+1 0 h(x k+1=k ; u k+1 ) (7)</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">F k = F (x k ; u k ) = @f(x k ; u k ) @x k x =x<label>(8)</label></formula><p>H k+1 = H(x k+1=k ; u k+1 ) = @h(x k+1 ; u k+1 ) @x k+1</p><p>x =x :</p><p>When used as an observer for linear deterministic systems, Q k and R k are arbitrarily chosen, for example, as 0 n and I p , respectively. In the case of linear stochastic systems, optimal filtering in the maximum likelihood sense is obtained when Q k and R k are the covariance matrices of the system and measurement noises, respectively. However, for nonlinear noisy systems, optimality has not been proved, but in general we continue to consider Q k and R k as covariance matrices.</p><p>Hereafter, we will show that the design of R k plays an important role in improving the convergence of the EKF when used as an observer of (1a), (1b). However, since (1a), (1b) is a deterministic system, we set Q k = 0:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. CONVERGENCE ANALYSIS</head><p>In this section we give a simple approach for setting up the convergence analysis of the considered nonlinear systems. It is emphasized that under the local reconstructibility condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[19]</ref>, the asymptotic convergence of the EKF is ensured when the arbitrary matrix R k is adequately chosen.</p><p>Let us note by xk+1 and xk+1=k the state estimation and state prediction error vectors respectively defined by xk+1 = x k+1 0 xk+1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(10)</ref> xk+1=k = x k+1 0 xk+1=k <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(11)</ref> and the candidate Lyapunov function V k+1 as V k+1 = xT k+1 P 01 k+1 xk+1 :</p><p>Our aim here is to determine conditions for which fV k g k=1111 is a decreasing sequence and to show the EKF limitations when the first-order approximation is used. One classical approach consists of using the convergence analysis performed in the linear case when e k+1 and xk+1=k are approximated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">e k+1 H k+1 xk+1=k<label>(13)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">xk+1=k F k xk :<label>(14)</label></formula><p>However, this approximation is available only if xk+1=k and xk belong to a neighborhood of x k+1 and x k , respectively, otherwise the EKF diverges.</p><p>For a rigorous convergence study we have to show that fV k g k=1111 decreases without any approximation. We notice that there always exist residues, due to the first-order linearization technique, of each output error prediction component e ik+1 (i = 1; 111 ; p) of e k+1 and each state error prediction component xjk+1=k (j = 1; 11 1;n) of xk+1=k ; for all k: To take these residues into account, in order to obtain an exact equality, we introduce here unknown diagonal matrices k+1 and k so that</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">H ik+1 xk+1=k = ik+1`eik+1<label>(15)</label></formula><p>xjk+1=k = jk F jk xk :</p><p>H ik+1 and F jk are the ith and jth rows of H k+1 and F k , respectively.</p><p>The exact equality represented here by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">15</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">16</ref>) is the key point of our approach since the convergence study will be performed without any approximation while e ik+1 and xjk+1=k are written in a first-order representation. Now if we introduce the signal vector, we obtain k+1 e k+1 = H k+1 xk+1=k <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(17)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_13">xk+1=k = k F k xk (18)</formula><p>where k+1 2 R p1p and k 2 R n1n are unknown time-varying diagonal matrices k+1 = diagf 1k+1 ; 111; pk+1 g <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(19)</ref> and k = diagf 1 ; 11 1; nk g:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">(20)</formula><p>By subtracting both sides of (2) from x k+1 ; we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">xk+1 = xk+1=k 0 P k+1=k H k+1 (H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 + R k+1 ) 01 e k+1 :<label>(21)</label></formula><p>On the other hand, from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">3</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">4</ref> </p><p>Substituting ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) into ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_15">21</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_15">21</ref>) into ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">12</ref>), the quadratic function becomes V k+1 = (x k+1=k 0 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 e k+1 ) T </p><p>From ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>), (26) becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">V k+1 = V k+1=k + e T k+1 ( k+1 R 01 k+1 k+1 0 k+1 R 01 k+1 0 R 01 k+1 k+1 + R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 )e k+1 :<label>(28)</label></formula><p>On the other hand, V k+1=k may be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">V k+1=k = xT k F T k k (F k P k F T k ) 01 k F k xk :<label>(29)</label></formula><p>A decreasing sequence fV k g k=1111 means that</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">V k+1 0 V k = V k+1 0 V k+1=k + V k+1=k 0 V k 0 (30)</formula><p>or equivalently</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">V k+1 0 V k =e T k+1 ( k+1 R 01 k+1 k+1 0 k+1 R 01 k+1 0 R 01 k+1 k+1 + R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 )e k+1 + xT k (F T k k (F k P k F T k ) 01 k F k 0 P 01 k )x k 0: A sufficient condition to ensure that is k+1 R 01 k+1 k+1 0 k+1 R 01 k+1 0 R 01 k+1 k+1 + R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 0<label>(31)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">F T k k (F k P k F T k ) 01 k F k 0 P 01 k 0: (32)</formula><p>Before we give sufficient conditions to ensure convergence of the EKF, two lemmas are established for intermediate results.</p><p>Lemma 1: If we assume that each ik+1 satisfies the following condition:</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">1 0 1 0 1 k+1 &lt; ik+1 &lt; 1 + 1 0 1 k+1 for i = 1;111;p (33) with k+1 = max(R k+1 )max(R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 1 (H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 + R k+1 ) 01 )<label>(34)</label></formula><p>where max (1) represents the maximum eigenvalue and R k+1 is chosen such that 1 k+1 1; then (31) is verified.</p><p>Proof: As k+1 is a diagonal matrix, its eigenvalues are given by ik+1 and verify k+1 si = ik+1 si (39)</p><p>By using the measure of matrix properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[17]</ref>, corresponding to norm 2, the left side of (39) can be bounded as</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">(( 2 ik+1 0 2 ik+1 )R 01 k+1 + R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 ) (( 2 ik+1 0 2 ik+1 )R 01 k+1 ) + (R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 )<label>(40)</label></formula><p>where (1) is the measure of matrix defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">(A) = max A + A T 2 :</formula><p>As R 01 k+1 and R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 are symmetric matrices and as the interval ]1 0 p 1 0 1 k+1 ;  </p><formula xml:id="formula_26">2 jk F 0T k P 01 k F 01 k 0 F 0T k P 01 k F 01 k 0<label>(49)</label></formula><p>thus under assumption (44), it is easy to show that (32) is also verified. Unfortunately, the convergence of the EKF is not ensured even if fV k g k=1111 is a decreasing sequence. So, some additional conditions in relation to the reconstructibility are needed. For nonlinear systems, the local reconstructibility may be defined in the same way as in the linear case <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[19]</ref>. Let us recall this property, which will be partly investigated in our developments. Under (43), if there exist positive real numbers 1 and 2 so that for all k M and for some finite </p><p>where F k and H k are defined by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">8</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">9</ref>), respectively, then the system (and its associated EKF for xi=i01 and xi sufficiently close to the true state xi) is said to be reconstructible. Thus, we obtain the following lemma.  Now, we propose a simple method to prove local convergence of the EKF applied to deterministic nonlinear systems.</p><p>Theorem: Suppose that (33), (44), and (50) hold, then the EKF (2)-( <ref type="formula">6</ref>), when used as an observer for the nonlinear discrete-time system (1a)-(1b), ensures that lim k!1 (x k 0 xk ) = 0:</p><p>Proof: Under (33) and (44), it has been shown (according to Lemmas 1 and 2) that fV k g k=1111 is a decreasing sequence which converges to a positive scalar V , i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">lim k!1 V k = V:</formula><p>On the other hand, we have  As ik+1 and jk are unknown factors, R k+1 have to be chosen so that the interval ]1 0 p 1 0 1 k+1 ; 1 + p 1 0 1 k+1 [ is large enough to fulfil ( <ref type="formula">33</ref>). An a priori choice of R k+1 is to set it much higher than H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 : Notice that within the maximum limits we have ]1 0 1 0 1 k+1 ; 1 + 1 0 1 k+1 [!]0; 2[: However, setting high values of R k+1 leads to a very slow convergence rate (the gain matrix K k+1 goes to zero). A tradeoff between stability and rate of convergence of the proposed algorithm leads us to set (in our numerical simulations) R k+1 = H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 + Ip where &gt; 0 and &gt; 0 are fixed by the user:</p><p>• For MISO nonlinear systems, R k is a positive scalar, and then (33) becomes 1 k+1 = H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 (H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 + R k+1 ) 01 with 1 0 1 k+1 &gt; 0 for all k:</p><p>• For linear time-varying systems we have k = 1 and k = I n :</p><p>Then (31) and (32) become 01 + H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 (H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 + R k+1 ) 01 0 and</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">F T k (F k P k F T k ) 01 F k 0 P 01 k 0:</formula><p>For R k &gt; 0;fV k g is a decreasing sequence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. NUMERICAL EXAMPLES</head><p>In order to show the efficiency of the proposed approach, we consider two numerical examples.</p><p>Example 1: The first example concerns the identification problem of nonlinear time-invariant systems described by the MISO Hammerstein model. This kind of model is composed by a static nonlinearity followed by a linear dynamic system. Here we consider two interconnected subsystems (high order and high values of g ik ) with the following pulse transfer functions:</p><p>V 1k = g 11 u 1k + g 12 u 2 1k + g 13 u 3 1k + g 14 u 4 1k + g 15 u 5 1k V 2k =g 21 u 2k + g 22 u 2 2k + g 23 u 3 2k + g 24 u 4 2k + g 25 u 5 2k + g 26 u 6</p><p>2k B1 A1 = q 01 + b11q 02 1 + a11q 01 + a12q 02 B 2</p><p>A 2 = q 01 + b 21 q 02 + b 22 q 03 1 + a 21 q 01 + a 22 q 02</p><p>where q 01 is the delay operator and u ik is the ith input of the system at time instant k; i = 1; 2; with a11 = 0:4; a12 = :65; a21 = 0:75; a22 = 0:9 b11 = 0:5; b21 = 00:6; b22 = 0:7 g 11 = 5:2; g 12 = 02:0; g 13 = 5:2; g 14 = 03:5 g 12 = 6:5; g 21 = 6:3; g 22 = 2:8; g 23 = 00:02 g 24 = 3:1; g 25 = 02:3; g 26 = 5:6:</p><p>Parameters of the static nonlinearity V1 and V2 are independent of those of A1; A2; B1; and B2:</p><p>The invariant parameter vector x (i.e., x k+1 = x k ) to be estimated from the input output data (y k ; u 1k ; u 2k ) k=1;111 ; is defined as A nonlinear state-space representation of the input-output Hammerstein model may be written as x k+1 = f(x k ; u 1k ; u 2k ) = x k y k = h(x k ; u 1k ; u 2k ) = 0(a 11 + a 21 )y k01 0 (a 11 a 21 + a 22 + a 12 )y k02 0 (a 11 a 22 + a 21 a 12 )y k03 0 a 12 a 22 y k04 + V 1k01 + (b11 + a21)V 1k02 + (b11a21 + a22)V 1k03 + b11a22V 1k04 + V 2k01 + (b21 + a11)V 2k02 + (b21a11 + a12 + b22)V 2k03 + (a11b22 + b21a12)V 2k04 + a12b22V 2k05 :</p><p>In order to fulfil (33) and ( <ref type="formula">44</ref>) with a good convergence rate, we take R k+1 = 2H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 + 1:</p><p>Owing to a lack of space here, we consider a worst case of very bad initialization. x0 = 100, i.e., all parameters are initialized at 100 with P0 = 10 7 I I I18: The input signals (u 1k ) and (u 2k ) are zero mean white noise sequences with standard deviations 1 = 0:3 and 2 = 0:4, respectively.</p><p>Example 2: The second numerical example, which was worked in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[18]</ref>, consists of a combined parameter and state estimation of the following discrete-time system:</p><p>x 1k+1 x 2k+1 x 3k+1 x 4k+1 x 5k+1 = x 2k 0a0x 1k 0 a1x 2k + bu k x 3k x 4k x 5k y k = x 1k x 2k with a 0 = 0:3 + 0:1 sin(x 3k ) a1 = 1:1 + 0:   We notice that in spite of bad initialization and with a large scale system (example 1), we obtain excellent results with our approach: the actual values of parameters are reached approximately at 800 samples for the first example and at 80 samples for the second one.</p><p>As we expect, the reconstructibility condition for nonlinear systems depends closely on the input signals especially for identification of nonlinear systems. We notice that in the case of parameter estimation, reconstructibility of the system is equivalent to the persistently exciting condition since x i+1 = x i (for time-invariant systems where xi represents the parameters vector to be estimated), and therefore we have F i = F 01 i = I; I is the identity matrix, for all i, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">O e (k 0 M; k) = H k0M F 01 k0M F 01 k0M+1 111F 01 k01 H k0M +1 F k0M +1 1 11F 01 k01 1 1 H k = H k0M H k0M+1 1 1 H k : V. CONCLUSION</formula><p>In this paper, convergence analysis of the EKF used as an observer for nonlinear deterministic discrete-time systems was considered. It is shown, from the theoretical point of view, that under mild conditions and with an appropriate choice of the arbitrary matrix R k ;</p><p>convergence of the EKF may be improved significantly in the sense that the domain of attraction is enlarged. One of the main results in this paper consists of introducing instrumental matrices k and k to evaluate the linearity of the model in order to control both stability and convergence of the EKF.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dynamics and Convergence Rate of Ordinal Comparison of Stochastic Discrete-Event Systems</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Xiaolan Xie</head><p>Abstract-This paper addresses ordinal comparison in the simulation of discrete-event systems. It examines dynamic behaviors of ordinal comparison in a fairly general framework. It proves that for regenerative systems, the probability of obtaining a desired solution using ordinal comparison approaches converges at exponential rate, while the variances of the performance measures converge at best at rate O(1=t 2 ); where t is the simulation time. Heuristic arguments are provided to explain that exponential convergence holds for general systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Optimization in discrete solution space becomes more and more important for discrete-event dynamic systems. The only general tool for evaluating such systems is the simulation. A straightforward and widely used approach consists of simulating all candidate designs to obtain accurate estimation of the performance measures and selecting the best design. Its main drawback is the requirement of a long simulation run to obtain accurate performance estimators. Variances of performance measures converge typically at rate O(1=t) in time t. and these rates are usually unsatisfactory when the number of candidate designs is important.</p><p>Ordinal optimization approaches first proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[10]</ref> (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[11]</ref> for an overview) reduce the computation burden by "combining some mind-set changes" concerning the problem of optimization of discrete-event systems. The primary concern of the ordinal optimization is the rankings of candidate solutions instead of their criterion values. Simulations conducted by various authors for a wide range of problems have shown that the rankings stabilize before the convergence of performance estimates. To achieve further reduction of simulation time, ordinal optimization approaches typically relax the goal of optimization to the isolation of a set of good candidate solutions. Experiments indicate that it is possible to determine whether a solution is good or bad very early in the simulation with high probability. Recent research <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[12]</ref> has demonstrated that impressive improvement in computation efficiency can be achieved using ordinal optimization approaches.</p><p>The purpose of this paper is to provide theoretical evidence of the efficiency of ordinal optimization approaches. It is an extension of a recent work <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref> which considers the convergence of the probability that the best observed design is indeed a "good" design. We consider the following fundamental indicator: the probability that at least k of the observed top-s designs are the actual top-g designs (i.e., satisfactory designs). It is called alignment probability and is meaningful in the perspective of simulation budget allocation. Our contributions include:</p><p>1) monotonicity properties of the alignment probability with respect to s; g; and k are established. They show that goal relaxation improves the computation efficiency; 2) the association, a kind of positive correlation, of simulated systems improves the convergence rate of the probability that the observed best design is the actual best one; 3) informal arguments of the exponential convergence rate of the alignment probability in the general case; </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where s i is the associated eigenvector.Pre-and post-multiplying the left side of (31) by s T i and s i , using relations (35) and (36) in (37) yields to</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(33)  and by the use of (41) and (42), it follows that (31) is satisfied.Lemma 2: If we assume that F k is a bounded nonsingular matrix (43)and each jk satisfies the following condition:01 jk 1 for j = 1;111;n(44)then (32) is verified.Proof: As k is a diagonal matrix, its eigenvalues are given by jk and verify k m j = jk m j where m j is the associated eigenvector.Under assumption (43), (32) is equivalent to post-multiplying the left side of (47) by m T j and m j , ) and (46) in (48) yields</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>0 M; k) =Diag(R 01 k0M ; 111; R 01 k )</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Lemma 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>If we assume that (1a), (1b) is reconstructible (From (23) and under (43) it is easy to show, by induction, that P 01 k+1 = O T e (1;k + 1)&lt;(1;k + 1)Oe(1;k + 1) + 9(0;k) k+1) and &lt;(1;k+1) are defined in (51) and (52), respectively. On a horizon time kM; if the reconstructibility Gramian O T e (1;kM)&lt;(1;kM)Oe(1;kM) is decomposed into k block matrices of horizon M; we obtain e ((i 0 1)M + 1;iM)&lt;((i 0 1)M + 1;iM)Oe((i 0 1)M + 1;iM)] + (0;kM 0 1): (57) Since P 01 kM 0 9(0;kM 0 1) is the sum of k reconstructibility Gramians, then under (50) we obtain the following inequalities: o &lt; k 1 (P 01 kM 0 9(0;kM 0 1)) k 2 :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>kM 0 1)) is bounded by k 1 and k 2 , it is easy to show that (53) and (54) follow from (58), where represents the eigenvalue symbol of P 01 kM 0 9(0;kM 0 1):</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>ik and jk are unknown factors introduced to evaluate the linearity of the model and, consequently, to control the gain matrix K k+1 by an adequate choice of R k in order to ensure stability of the algorithm, particularly when e k+1 6 = H k+1=k xk+1=k and xk+1=k 6 = F k xk : Indeed, the sufficient conditions (33) and(44)   mean that fV k g is a decreasing sequence for all approximations in the form ik+1 e ik+1 = H ik+1 xk+1=k and xjk+1=k = jk F jk xk with</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>x = (a 11 a 12 a 21 a 22 b 11 b 21 b 22 g 11 1 11 g 15 111 g 21 111 g 26 ) T 2 R 18 :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>5 Fig. 1 .</head><label>51</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Rate of convergence of kx k 0 x k k-Example 1.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,306.78,59.58,249.60,148.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Rate of convergence of kx k 0 x k k-Example 2.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,307.50,234.54,248.16,150.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figs. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figs. 1 and 2 show the rate of convergence of the state error norm kx k 0 x k k with respect to samples k when R k is adequately chosen for both examples, while the classical EKF diverges for R k = 1: We</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>), we have</figDesc><table><row><cell>P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 = P k+1=k H T k+1 (H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 + R k+1 ) 01 (22)</cell></row><row><cell>and</cell></row><row><cell>P 01 k+1 = P 01 k+1=k + H T k+1 R 01 k+1 H k+1 :</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1 + p 1 0 1 k+1 []0; 2[; this implies that 2 ik+1 0 2 ik+1 &lt; 0; and (40) yields to</figDesc><table><row><cell>max(( 2 ik+1 0 2 ik+1 )R 01 k+1 + R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 ) 0( 2 ik+1 0 2 ik+1 )max(R 01 k+1 ) + max (R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 ) (41)</cell></row><row><cell>with</cell></row><row><cell>R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1 H T k+1 R 01 k+1 = R 01 k+1 H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 (H k+1 P k+1=k H T k+1 R k+1 ) 01 :</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors wish to thank the anonymous referees for their insightful comments.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A trace inequality for the matrix product</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Lasserre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1500" to="1501" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bounds for the eigenvalues of the solution of the unified algebraic Riccati matrix equation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mrabti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Benseddik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Contr. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="349" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inequalities: Theory of Majorization and Its Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Olkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Orlando, FL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Rockafellar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Convex Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic observers as asymptotic limits of recursive filters: Special cases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Baras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bensoussan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Siam J. Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1147" to="1158" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Canonical form observer design for non linear time-variable systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bestle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zeitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recursive identification method for Hammerstein model-Extension to the nonlinear MISO case</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Boutayeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Darouach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contr. Theory Advanced Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recursive identification method for MISO Wiener-Hammerstein model</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conditions for asymptotic stability of the discrete minimum-variance linear estimator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Deyst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="702" to="705" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied Optimal Estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gelb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Jaswinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Stochastic Processes and Filtering Theory</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linearization by output injection and nonlinear observers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Krener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Isidori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Contr. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear observers with linearizable error dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Krener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Respondek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Siam J. Contr. Optim</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximations to optimal nonlinear filters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kushner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="546" to="556" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic behavior of the extended Kalman filter as a parameter estimator for linear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ljung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
			<publisher>AC-24</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mcgarty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Stochastic Systems and State Estimation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of several nonlinear filters for reentry vehicle tracking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mehra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="319" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observability of autonomous discrete-time nonlinear systems: A geometric approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nijmeijer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="867" to="874" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The extended Kalman filter as a local asymptotic observer for nonlinear discrete-time systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grizzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Amer. Contr. Conf</title>
		<meeting>Amer. Contr. Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3365" to="3369" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Special issue on applications of Kalman filtering</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vidyasagar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Nonlinear Systems Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A robust observer for discrete time nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ciccarella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Dalla</forename><surname>Mora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Germani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Contr. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observer design for nonlinear systems with discrete-time measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Moraal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grizzle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
