<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Wideband Radio Propagation Modeling for Indoor Geolocation Applications</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kaveh</forename><surname>Pahlavan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Prashant</forename><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jacques</forename><surname>Beneat</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Wideband Radio Propagation Modeling for Indoor Geolocation Applications</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6AF1C60E5B97B8AEE4551AE5AA3C851B</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T15:08+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>istics o f t h e frequency-selective f a d i n g m u l t i p a t h indoor radio channel f o r geolocation applications is presented. Multipath characteristics o f the channel are divided into three classes according t o availability and the strength of the direct line of sight (DLOS) path w i t h respect t o the other paths. Statistics o f t h e error in estimating the t i m e o f arrival o f t h e DLOS p a t h i n a b u i l d i n g is related t o t h e receiver's sensitivity and dynamic range. The effects of external walls on estimating t h e location o f the DLOS path are analyzed.</p><p>ndoor radio channels suffer from extremely seri-:s at CWINS, WPI for fruitful discusielp. We also appreciate Yan Xu's coning the R T program for the iario.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>I ous multipath conditions that have to be modeled and analyzed to enable the design of radio equipment for a variety of applications. The objective of wideband radio propagation modeling for telecommunications and geolocation applications are quite different. As a result, available models for radio channel propagation are not adequate for analyzing the performance of geolocation systems. In radio propagation studies for telecommunication applications, the main objective is to determine the relationship between distance and total received power in all paths, and to find out the multipath delay spread of the channel The distancepower relationship is used to determine the coverage of the radio and the multipath delay spread to evaluate the data rate limitations of the receivers [l]. The objective of radio propagation studies for geolocation applications is to determine the relative power and time of arrival (TOA) of the signal arriving from the direct line of sight (DLOS) path versus the signal arriving from other paths. The relative power and TOA of the paths, and the channel noise and interference are used to analyze the error in estimating the distance between the transmitter and the receiver if the DLOS path is not detected correctly.</p><p>With the increased popularity of wireless services in the 1990s new applications in a variety of fields have evolved. These applications were incentives for radio propagation measurement and modeling in indoor and outdoor areas. In the telecommunications industry, indoor radio propagation studies were motivated by voice-oriented wireless private branch exchange (PBX) and personal communications services (PCS) applications as well as data-oriented wireless LANs and wireless ATM services <ref type="bibr">[Z]</ref>. Wideband radio propagation studies were more focused on wideband data applications such as LAN extension, inter-LAN bridges, nomadic access, ad hoc networking, and fusion of computers and communications <ref type="bibr">[3]</ref> Research in wideband indoor radio channel modeling for telecommunications applications in the past decade resulted in numerous measurements, statistical models, and ray tracing software to identify the wideband characteristics of different classes of buildings such as factory floors, office buildings, and residential houses <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref>.</p><p>More recently, applications for indoor geolocation are becoming popular [4]. In mental hospitals and jails there is a growing need to identify the location of specific patients or inmates. In warehouses, laboratories, and hospitals there is a need to identify the location of portable and in-demand pieces of equipment. Public safety departments are thinking of identifying the location of veode at the site of a crime or acci- </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>THREE CLASSES OF LOCATIONS</head><p>In wideband indoor radio propagation studies for telecommunication applications often channel profiles measured in different locations of a building are divided into line of sight and obstructed line of sight because the behavior of the channel in these two classes has substantially different impacts on the performance of a telecommunications system. A logical way to classify channel profiles for geolocation applications is to divide them into three categories. The first category is the dominant direct path (DDP) case, in which the DLOS path is detected by the measurement system and is the strongest path in the channel profile. In this case, traditional GPS (Global Positioning System) receivers [9-111 can lock onto the DLOS path and detect its TOA accurately.</p><p>The second category is the nondominant direct path (NDDP) case, where the DLOS path is detected by the measurement system but is not the dominant path in the channel profile. For these profiles traditional GPS receivers, expected to lock onto the strongest path, will make an erroneous decision on the TOA. The amount of error made by a traditional receiver is the distance associated with the difference between the TOA of the strongest path and the TOA of the DLOS path.</p><p>For the second category, locations with NDDP profiles, a more complex RAKE type receiver [l] can resolve the multipath and make an intelligent decision on the TOA of the DLOS path. The third category of channel profiles are unde- i '</p><p>na passes the signal t that are connected to ning massive simulat exhaustive results fr surement system, whic indoor telecommunic cations <ref type="bibr">[15]</ref>. In gen with results of RT for the particular application. From that point onward, we use results of RT for massive simulations to draw reasonable statistical conclusions <ref type="bibr">[ l , 14, 161.</ref> For telecommunications applications we are interested in the total received power and root mean square (rms) multipath delay spread of the channel. For geolocation applications we have included adequate details of the building to match the power of the DLOS path and to an extent the power in the remaining paths.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows samples for the three classes of profiles obtained from R T and the measurement system on the first floor of t h e Atwater Kent (AK) Laboratories a t Worcester Polytechnic Institute. The floor plan of this building and the location of the transmitter and receivers are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p><p>In the DDP case the transmitter and receiver are in the same area, in the NDDP case a couple of walls separate them, and in the UDP case several walls are between them. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, results of measurement and R T show close agreement in the DDP and NDDP cases. The DLOS path is within 2-4 dB, the range of variations of the paths is within a few dB, and the arriving paths from RT have a reasonable match to the result of measurements. For the UDP case RT accurately predicts the lack of the DLOS path, and the dynamic range is within a few dB, but the rest of the paths follow less accurately compared to the other two cases. As we mentioned earlier, these differences are caused by effects of movement and other details not included in the RT program. However, in geolocation applications we are mainly concerned with statistical behavior of the DLOS path and the dynamic range of the signal. For these purposes R T proves to be a reliable tool for modeling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>STATISTICAL BEHAVIOR OF THE CHANNEL</head><p>T o investigate the statistical behavior of t h e strength of t h e DLOS path, R T simulations were We increase details o the biilding to the extent that res1 Its of empirical data from t h e IT easurement system at selected 1 oints agree T h e transmitter is located at t h e center of t h e building, and the receiver is moved to different points on the grid. The AK building was built in 1906 and had two major remodelings and additions in 1934 and 1981. Therefore, in some areas within the building we have more than one exterior-type wall. The exterior walls of this building are heavy brick, the interior walls are made of aluminum stud and sheet rock, the floors a r e made with metallic beams, t h e doors and windows a r e metallic, and many other metallic objects (such as relatively large electric motors, equipment, and vending machines) are spread over different laboratory areas and corridors of the first floor. The excessive number of metallic objects and heavy and multiple external walls makes this building a very harsh environment for radio propagation.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the classes of channel profiles obtained in different locations of the building. The red, green, and blue areas correspond to the DDP, NDDP, and UDP profiles, respectively. As we discussed earlier, in the red areas traditional geolocation systems work properly, in the green areas more complicated RAKE type receivers are needed to accurately extract the TOA of the DLOS path, and in the blue areas we need additional transmitters to measure the distance accurately. The reader should be reminded that in practice a geolocation system involves at least three transmitters spread over opportunistically selected locations in the building. This figure provides an intuitive understanding of the range of operation of one reference transmitter operating inside a harsh indoor environment.</p><p>We next examine the strength of the DLOS path compared to the combined strength of all other paths and the total received power, including the power in the DLOS path.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> shows the received power (in dBm) versus distance for the DLOS path, all other paths combined, and total power for all locations of the floor plan. The vertical lines on the curves correspond to the one standard deviation of the received signal strength for that distance.</p><p>Over a distance of 45 m in this building, the range of received power in the DLOS path is around 75 dB, while the range of received power in combined other paths and total received power is around 40 dB. The range of received power in the DLOS path is noticeably larger than that of the other paths combined and total received power. An immediate conclusion from this observation is that the receivers designed for transmitter: a) as a function ofdifferent receiver sensitivities and a f i e d dynami: range of 40 dB; b) as a function of different receiver dynamic ranges and a fixed sensitivity of -80 dBm.</p><p>geolocation applications in a frequency-selective fadin; multipath environment should accommodate wider dynamic ranges for the received signal power.</p><p>, and will make an erroneous TOA. This error can easily be suring the distance between the further analyze the behavior of decision on estimati mapped to the error transmitter and recei. and the cumulative d in measurement of th receiver.</p><p>Detection of the ' ture, receiver specifi algorithm used to detl band RAKE-type rei multipath profile of t TOA of the first det path. We identify thir (CDF) of the error the transmitter and 15 dB below the poa conditions are not Si available path that f detects another path error in detection.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">5a</ref> shows tf tion of receiver sensi dB, using the same lo receiver sensitivity fr the probability of cor tance error as a funcdynamic range of 40 in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> peak. Therefore, if a path is more than 13 dB below the strongest path it cannot b e detected, and the dynamic range of this receiver is 13 dB. Using Hanning or other low-sidelobe pulses, we can increase the dynamic range to more than 40 dB. Figure <ref type="figure">5b</ref> shows the effects of the receive r dynamic range on the CDF. of t h e distance error in meters for a receiver with a sensitivity of -80 dBm. A change in dynamic range from 38 dB to 13 dB will reduce the probability of detection of the DLOS path from 86 to 78 percent. For a dynamic range of 13 dB, in more than 90 percent of locations the error in measuring the distance is less than 5 m. Analysis of this sort is useful for receiver designers to evaluate the trade-off among different pulse shapes and relate them to the overall performance of the geolocation system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EFFECTS OF EXTERNAL WALLS</head><p>So far in this article, we have analyzed characteristics of the radio channel for indoor-to-indoor applications, such as geolocation systems for hospitals or manufacturing floors, where the reference transmitters are installed inside the building. There are other indoor applications for which the reference transmitters must be located outside the building. For example, in a military or firefighting operation a warfighter or firefighter could be inside the building while t h e rest of t h e troops a r e outside in nearby locations around the building. In these situations it is expected that the reference transmitters will be located outside the building near the external walls while the receiver is inside the building.</p><p>When we move the transmitter outside the building, characteristics of radio propagation change significantly [ 11. This abrupt change of propagation characteristics is caused due to two major reasons: excessive indoor penetration loss through external walls of the building, and additional paths arriving through windows and doors reflected from neighboring buildings. External walls are usually thicker loadbearing walls made of heavier material which may include concrete and metallic beams. The outside of these walls are covered by external siding that is sometimes metallic, and the insides of these walls are filled with insulation material.</p><p>As a result, in-building penetration loss of external walls is 10-15 dB higher than the loss caused by passing through traditional internal walls [l]. When the transmitter is outside the building, because of this extra power loss due to in-building penetration, the paths that arrive after penetration though several walls become significantly weak and, at IEEE Communications h. agazine April 1998 t certain points, weaker than the signals coming through the windows and doors after bouncing off the neighboring buildings. When both the transmitter and receiver are inside the building we usually neglect the effects of neighboring buildings and the signal penetrations through outside windows and doors because the signal must cross the outside walls twice to come back inside the building. At that stage the signal is assumed to be so weak it can be neglected.</p><p>For telecommunication applications the effects of inbuilding penetration phenomena are reflected in additional and an increase in average rms multipath delay o observe the effects of in-building penetration on geolocation applications, we move the transmitter from the center of the building to the outside location shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> and repeat our previous experiments and analysis. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">6</ref> shows the received power versus distance in meters and the best fit curve for the DLOS path, combined other paths, and total received power. The range of the received signal power for the DLOS path is 90 dB as compared to about 40 dB for the combined other paths and total received power. When compared to the results of Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> for indoor-to-indoor situations, the range of the power of the DLOS path in the outdoor-to-indoor case is significantly larger, while the range of total received power and the combined power in the other paths remains approximately the same. In many locations inside the building, the DLOS path has to pass through many walls, including a heavy outside wall, while other paths can enter the building through open doors and windows. In other words, we may have many locations in the building where we have reasonable power coming through the external windows and doors but the DLOS path is extremely weak.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">7</ref> shows the CDF of the error in predicted distance for a variety of sensitivities and dynamic ranges. When compared with t h e graphs for indoor-to-indoor applications shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>, the curves in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">7</ref> offer two classes of errors, one less than -10 m and the other more than about 30 m. In the first group of profiles, when the DLOS path is not detected, the next detected path has arrived after penetration through the closest wall to the transmitter, so the arrival time is less than 30 ns (10 m) delayed from the arrival time of the DLOS path. In the second group the falsely detected first path arrives through windows and doors from external reflections, so the overall path length is more than 90 ns (30 m). Therefore, the error is either between the paths coming through penetration or those coming through windows and doors, and these two classes provide a distinct behavior in the error caused by the receiver.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Because of the frequency-selective multipath fading characteristics of the indoor radio channel, design of an accurate indoor geolocation system is a challenging task. To provide a foundation for quantitative performance evaluation of such systems a methodology for statistical modeling of this channel for geolocation applications is presented. To relate the performance of traditional GPS receivers to the more complex RAKE-type receivers, the multipath profiles in an indoor area were divided into three classes: DDP, NDDP, and UDP. In the DDP case both RAKE-type and traditional GPS receivers operate properly. In the NDDP case only RAKE receivers function accurately, and in the UDP case neither of the receivers is satisfactory. The statistics of the occurrenceof the three classes of channel profiles in a building with harsh radio propagation characteristics were presented. The statistics of error in measuring the distance as a function of the sensitivity and dynamic range of the receiver as well as effects of outside walls were presented. As we move reference transmitters to the outside of the building, the statistics of the error in estimating the T O A of the DLOS will change significantly. The signal arriving from windows and doors through reflection from neighboring buildings will cause larger errors in prediction of the TOA of the DLOS path.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>W Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Three clas es of channelprofiles: a) DDP, b) NDDP, and c) UDP.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Location of the indoor and outdoor transmitters (small squares) and receivers (X) forthe sample measurements and ray tracing shown in Fig. 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Receivedpoweras afunction of distance inAKL.ab0ratories f i m t m r for the outdoor transmitter location shown in Fig. 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>i W Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>CDF of the error in predicted distance for the outdoor transmitter. a) as a function of different receiver sensitivies and a dynamic range of 40dB; 6 ) with a threshold of -80 d B m and different dynamic ranges.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The authors would like to express their appreciation to DARPA's SUO-SAS program for partial support of this project and approval for public release with unlimited distribution. We are thankful to Dr. Mark McHenry of DARPA for his comments and suggestions. We also thank Paul Creamer and Joseph Pisano, our collaborators at TASC, Reading, Massachusetts, and Dr. James W. Matthews and Ahmad</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">our associa sions and a variety oj tribution in run outdoor-to-indoor S C ~ [I] K. Pahlavan and A</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hatami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Le\ Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">I€ [31 K. Pahlavan, T. Probe works</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pahlavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zahed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Watm</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>41 MicroTRAX trackins harris.com/microtrax</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wi ity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Si</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Report on the New J&apos; of New Jersey</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Bell Labs Tech. 1.. Trueposition Systems</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global Po! formance,&quot; lnt&apos;l. 1. Wir [lo] I. A. Getting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Enge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">DARPA Tactical Techn Review #I and #2: ht [91</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="47" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">less Enhanced 9-1-1 Service -Making It a Realip. 188-202, Autumn 1996. sey Wireless Enhanced 91 1 System Trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ed</forename><surname>Boston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">;</forename><surname>I21</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Indoor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Radio</forename><surname>Channt Meas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">;</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Holt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">;</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="//web-ext2.darpa.mil/tto/sas-docs.htm.ioning" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Trends in Wireless Local Net-Mag., Mar. 1995. and location system Web site</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>State Law and Public Safety</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990-11">1990. Nov. 1997. June 16, 1997. Apr. 1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Networks. &gt;bal Positioning System,&quot; /E€€ Spktrum, Dec. jerstanding GPS: Principles and Applications, 996. &apos;ahlavan, &quot;Measurement and Analysis of the in the Frequency Domain,&quot; /E€€ Trans. lnstr</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Graphical Indoor Radio Channel ay Tracing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. PlMRC &apos;92</title>
		<meeting>PlMRC &apos;92</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-10">Oct. 1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="751" to="755" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sectored Antenna and DFE Modem for High Speed Indoor Radio Communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pahlavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">/€€E Trans. Vehic. Tech</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-11">Nov. 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hasan-Ali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pahlavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Site-Specific Wideband Indoor Channel Modelling Using Ray Tracing Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Transmission Techniques for Wireless LANs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Falsafi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pahlavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-04">Apr. 1996. NOV. 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1983" to="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>/E€€ JSAC</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Massachusetts. His recent research has been focused on indoor radio propagation modeling and analysis of multiple access and transmission methods for wireless local networks. He is editor-in-chief and founder of the lnternational Journal of Wireless lnformation Networks, and has contributed to numerous technical papers and two patents. He has been program chair and organizer of IEEE conferences and workshops including PIMRC</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kaveh Pahlavan [f] (kaveh@wpi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.cwins.wpi.edu" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Wireless lnformation Network Studies (CWINS) at Worcester Polytechnic Institute (WPI)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>98 this year. Additional information is available at</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">i s a research assistant at CWINS at WPI. His recent research has focused on statistical indoor radio propagation modeling for signal coverage and urban geolocation, developing tools for deployment of wireless LANs, and issues in mobile computing and wireless information networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Prashant Krishnamurthy (prashant@wpi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">is a postdoctoral fellow at CWINS at WPI. He has helped in the organization of the Second IEEE Workshop on Wireless LANs held at WPI in 1996, and is currently assisting in the organization of the ninth IEEE Personal Indoor and Mobile Radio Communications conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<publisher>JACQUES 8ENEAT</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>beneat@ece.wpi.edu</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
