<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
							<email>hes-panha@ece.ucsb.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>93106</postCode>
									<settlement>Santa Barbara</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Systems and Robotics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto Superior Técnico</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lisbon</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Control Engineering and Computa-tion</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>93106</postCode>
									<settlement>Santa Barbara</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A45D2F493AABBFDB22FF6E7390DBBF69</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TAC.2007.902731</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T02:54+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Trajectory-Tracking and Path-Following of Underactuated Autonomous Vehicles With Parametric Modeling Uncertainty</head><p>A. Pedro Aguiar, Member, IEEE, and João P. Hespanha, Senior Member, IEEE Abstract-We address the problem of position trajectory-tracking and path-following control design for underactuated autonomous vehicles in the presence of possibly large modeling parametric uncertainty. For a general class of vehicles moving in either 2-or 3-D space, we demonstrate how adaptive switching supervisory control can be combined with a nonlinear Lyapunov-based tracking control law to solve the problem of global boundedness and convergence of the position tracking error to a neighborhood of the origin that can be made arbitrarily small. The desired trajectory does not need to be of a particular type (e.g., trimming trajectories) and can be any sufficiently smooth bounded curve parameterized by time. We also show how these results can be applied to solve the path-following problem, in which the vehicle is required to converge to and follow a path, without a specific temporal specification. We illustrate our design procedures through two vehicle control applications: a hovercraft (moving on a planar surface) and an underwater vehicle (moving in 3-D space). Simulations results are presented and discussed.</p><p>Index Terms-Path-following, supervisory adaptive control, trajectory-tracking, underactuated autonomous vehicles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>T HE past few decades have witnessed an increased research effort in the area of motion control of autonomous vehicles. A typical motion control problem is trajectory-tracking, which is concerned with the design of control laws that force a vehicle to reach and follow a time parameterized reference (i.e., a geometric path with an associated timing law). The degree of difficulty involved in solving this problem is highly dependent on the configuration of the vehicle. For fully actuated systems, the trajectory-tracking problem is now reasonably well understood.</p><p>For underactuated vehicles, i.e., systems with fewer actuators than degrees-of-freedom, 1 trajectory-tracking is still an active research topic. The study of these systems is motivated by the fact that it is usually costly and often not practical to fully actuate autonomous vehicles due to weight, reliability, complexity, and efficiency considerations. Typical examples of underactuated systems include wheeled robots, hovercraft, spacecraft, aircraft, helicopters, missiles, surface vessels, and underwater vehicles. The tracking problem for underactuated vehicles is especially challenging because most of these systems are not fully feedback linearizable and exhibit nonholonomic constraints. The reader is refereed to <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> for a survey of these concepts and to <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> for a framework to study the controllability and the design of motion algorithms for underactuated Lagrangian systems on Lie groups.</p><p>The classical approach for trajectory-tracking of underactuated vehicles utilizes local linearization and decoupling of the multi-variable model to steer the same number of degrees of freedom as the number of available control inputs, which can be done using standard linear (or nonlinear) control methods. Alternative approaches include the linearization of the vehicle error dynamics around trajectories that lead to a time-invariant linear system (also known as trimming trajectories) combined with gain scheduling and/or linear parameter varying (LPV) design methodologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The basic limitation of these approaches is that stability is only guaranteed in a neighborhood of the selected operating points. Moreover, performance can suffer significantly when the vehicle executes maneuvers that emphasize its nonlinearity and cross couplings. A different approach is to use output feedback linearization methods, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. The major challenge in this approach is that a straightforward application of this methodology, which in general involves dynamic inversion, is not always possible because certain involutivity conditions must hold <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. In addition, even when dynamic inversion is possible, the resulting controller may not render the zero-dynamics stable.</p><p>Nonlinear Lyapunov-based designs can overcome some of the limitations mentioned above. Several examples of nonlinear 1 The following definition of underactuated mechanical systems is adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Consider the affine mechanical system described by q = f (q; _ q) + G(q)u</p><p>(1</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">)</formula><p>where q is a vector of independent generalized coordinates, f a vector field that captures the dynamics of the system, G the input matrix, and u the vector of generalized inputs. Equation ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) is underactuated if the rank of G is smaller than the dimension of q, i.e., the generalized inputs are not able to instantaneously set the accelerations in all directions of the configuration space.</p><p>0018-9286/$25.00 © 2007 IEEE trajectory-tracking controllers for marine underactuated vehicles have been reported in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. Typically, tracking problems for autonomous vehicles are solved by designing control laws that make the vehicles track pre-specified feasible "state-space" trajectories, i.e., trajectories that specify the time evolution of the position, orientation, as well as the linear and angular velocities, all consistent with the vehicles' dynamics, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, even through in practical applications one often only needs to track a desired position. This approach suffers from the drawback that usually the vehicles' dynamics exhibit complex nonlinear terms and significant uncertainty, which makes the task of computing a feasible trajectory difficult.</p><p>It is relevant to point out that most of the results mentioned above only solve the problem in the horizontal plane. Only a few authors have tackled this control problems in 3-D space. The reason might be that the vehicle's dynamics become more complex and the number of degree of freedom that are not directly actuated typically increases, making the control design more involved. For example, for an underactuated underwater vehicle, the dynamics include sway and heave velocities that generate nonzero angles of sideslip and attack.</p><p>Motivated by these considerations, we propose a solution to the trajectory-tracking problem for underactuated vehicles in both 2-and 3-D spaces. In this paper, we are especially interested in situations for which there is parametric uncertainty in the model of the vehicle. Typical parameters for which this uncertainty is high, include mass and added mass for underwater vehicles which may be subject to large variations according to the payload configuration, and friction coefficients that are usually strongly dependent on the environmental conditions. The main contribution of the paper is the design of an adaptive supervisory control algorithm that combines logic-based switching <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> with iterative Lyapunov-based techniques such as integrator backstepping <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. The classical approach to adaptive control relies solely on continuous tuning <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. This approach has some inherent limitations that can be overcome by hybrid adaptive algorithms based on switching and logic <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. The basic idea behind supervisory control <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> is to design a suitable family of candidate controllers. Each controller is designed for an admissible nominal model of the process, and a supervision logic orchestrates the switching among the candidate controllers, deciding, at each instant of time, the candidate feedback controller that is more adequate. In order to guarantee stability and avoid chattering, a form of hysteresis is employed. We prove that the adaptive controller solves the problem of global boundedness and convergence of the position tracking error to a neighborhood of the origin that can be made arbitrarily small in the presence of possible large parametric uncertainty. The adaptive supervisory controller does not require persistence of excitation which sets it apart from most parameter estimation algorithms. In the control design, we take into account that the vehicle may have non-negligible dynamics and may undergo complex motions and exhibit large angles of attack and sideslip, which prevents us from using simple extensions of common control designs for wheeled robots where the total velocity vector is aligned with the vehicles main axis. Also, the desired trajectory does not need to be a trimming trajectory and can be any sufficiently smooth time-varying bounded curve, including the degenerate case of a constant trajectory (set-point). The class of vehicles for which the design procedure is applicable is quite general and includes any vehicle modeled as a rigid-body subject to a controlled force and either one controlled torque if it is only moving on a planar surface or two or three independent control torques for a vehicle moving in 3-D space. Furthermore, contrary to most of the approaches described above, the controller proposed does not suffer from geometric singularities due to the parameterization of the vehicle's rotation matrix. This is possible because the attitude control problem is formulated directly in the group of rotations . The literature on designing tracking control laws for underactuated vehicles directly in the configuration manifold (avoiding in this way geometric singularities) is relatively scarce. Noteworthy examples include <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>.</p><p>Another contribution of this paper is the application of these results to solve the path-following motion control problem. In path-following, the vehicle is required to converge to and follow a path that is specified without a temporal law <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. Pioneering work in this area for wheeled mobile robots is described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, Samson addressed the path-following problem for a car pulling several trailers. More recently, Altafini <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> describes a path-following controller for a trailer vehicle that provides local asymptotic stability for a path of nonconstant curvature. Path-following controllers for aircraft and marine vehicles have been reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. Using the approach suggested by Hauser and Hindman <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, an output maneuvering controller was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> for a class of strict feedback nonlinear processes and applied to path-following of fully actuated ships. The underlying assumption in path-following is that the vehicle's forward speed tracks a desired speed profile, while the controller acts on the vehicle's orientation to drive it to the path. Typically, in path-following, smoother convergence to the path is achieved and the control signals are less likely pushed into saturation, when compared to trajectory-tracking. In fact, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, we highlight a fundamental difference between path-following and standard trajectory-tracking by demonstrating that performance limitations due to unstable zero-dynamics can be removed in the path-following problem. Inspired by these ideas, we solve the path-following problem by decomposing it into two subproblems: i) a geometric task, which consists of converging the vehicle to and remaining inside a tube centered around the desired path, and ii) a dynamic assignment task, which assigns a speed profile to the path.</p><p>In Section II, we describe the dynamic model for the class of underactuated autonomous vehicles considered in the paper and formulate the trajectory-tracking and path-following control problems. As a preliminary material for the subsequent sections, Section III presents a nonlinear control law to solve the tracking problem and discusses the stability of the resulting closed-loop. At this point it is assumed that there is no parametric uncertainty. Sections IV and V present the main results of the paper. In Section IV, a solution to the trajectory-tracking is proposed using an estimator-based supervisory controller, and in Section V an extension is made to solve the path-following problem. In Section VI, we illustrate our design methodologies in the context of two vehicle control applications: a hovercraft (moving on a planar surface) and an underwater vehicle (moving in 3-D space). The designs are validated through computer simulations. The paper concludes with a summary of the results and suggestions for further research.</p><p>A subset of the results reported here were presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>.</p><p>Notation: Throughout this paper, given a matrix , denotes its transpose, , are the minimum and maximum eigenvalues of , respectively. Given two vectors , , we denote by the vector . The Euclidean norm is denoted by and the spectral norm by . A piecewise continuous function , is in , being a positive integer, if for some constant .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PROBLEM STATEMENT</head><p>Consider an underactuated vehicle modeled as a rigid body subject to external forces and torques. Let be an inertial coordinate frame and a body-fixed coordinate frame whose origin is located at the center of mass of the vehicle. The configuration of the vehicle is an element of the Special Euclidean group</p><p>, where is a rotation matrix that describes the orientation of the vehicle by mapping body coordinates into inertial coordinates, and is the position of the origin of in . Denoting by and the linear and angular velocities of the vehicle relative to expressed in , respectively, the following kinematic relations apply:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(2a) (2b)</formula><p>where is a function from to the space of skew-symmetric matrices defined by</p><p>We consider here underactuated vehicles with dynamic equations of motion of the following form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(3a) (3b)</formula><p>where and denote constant symmetric positive definite mass and inertia matrices; and denote the control inputs, which act upon the system through a constant nonzero vector and a constant nonsingular matrix 2  , respectively; the terms in (3a) and in (3b) are the rigid-body Coriolis terms, and the functions , represent all the remaining 2 See Remark 4 for the special case of G 2</p><p>.</p><p>forces and torques acting on the body. For the special case of an underwater vehicle, and also include the so-called hydrodynamic added-mass and added-inertia matrices, respectively, i.e., , , where and are the rigid-body mass and inertia matrices, respectively.</p><p>For an underactuated vehicle restricted to moving on a planar surface, the same equations of motion ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>), (3) apply without the first two right-hand side terms in (3b). Also, in this case, , , , , , , with all the other terms in (3) having appropriate dimensions, and the skew-symmetric matrix is given by . For simplicity, in what follows, we restrict our attention to the 3-D case. However, all results are directly applicable to the 2-D case, as will be illustrated in Section VI-A for the control of a Hovercraft. Remark 1: The vehicle dynamic model (3) does not allow to depend on . This was done in part to simplify the analysis and also because in many vehicles this dependance is not present as is the case of the Hovercraft and the AUV described in Section VI. The methodology presented here still applies for the more general case if the dependence on is in the form , provided that is bounded or that a suitable rank condition holds. For details see Property 1 in the Appendix and <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>.</p><p>The problems considered in this paper can be stated as follows:</p><p>Trajectory-tracking problem: Let be a given sufficiently smooth time-varying desired trajectory with its time-derivatives bounded. Design a controller such that all the closed-loop signals are bounded and the tracking error converges to a neighborhood of the origin that can be made arbitrarily small. Path-following problem: Let be a desired path parameterized by and a desired speed 3 assignment. Suppose also that is sufficiently smooth with respect to and its derivatives (with respect to ) are bounded. Design feedback control laws for , , and such that all the closed-loop signals are bounded, the position of the vehicle converges to and remains inside a tube centered around the desired path that can be made arbitrarily thin, i.e., converges to a neighborhood of the origin that can be made arbitrarily small, and the vehicle satisfies a desired speed assignment along the path, i.e., the speed error can be confined to an arbitrarily small ball.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. TRAJECTORY-TRACKING CONTROLLER DESIGN</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Controller Design</head><p>This section proposes a Lyapunov-based control law to solve the trajectory-tracking problem assuming that there is no parametric uncertainty. For the sake of clarity, control-Lyapunov functions are introduced iteratively borrowing from the techniques of backstepping <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. 3 For simplicity of presentation it will be assumed that the speed assignment v () 2 does not depend directly on time t. We can regard as a virtual control that one would use to make negative. This could be achieved, by setting equal to , for some positive constant . To accomplish this we introduce the error variable that we would like to drive to zero, and re-write (4) as <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> Step 3. Backstepping for : After straightforward algebraic manipulations, the dynamic equation of the error can be written as where <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> and</p><p>. It turns out that it will not always be possible to drive to zero. We need to explore the coupling of the translation dynamics with the rotational inputs. To this effect, we will drive to a constant design vector . To achieve this we define as a new error variable that we will drive to zero and consider the augmented control-Lyapunov function</p><p>The time derivative of can be written as <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> In Appendix (cf. Property 1), we show that the matrix B can always be made full-rank by choosing a suitable .</p><p>One can now regard as a virtual control (actually its first component is already a "real" control) that one would like to use to make negative. This could be achieved, by setting equal to where is a symmetric positive definite matrix. To accomplish this we set to be equal to the first entry of , i.e., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> and introduce the error variable that one would like to set to zero. We can now rewrite <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, with given by ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>), as</p><p>Step 4. Backstepping for : Consider now a third control-Lyapunov function given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> Computing its time derivative one obtains</p><p>For simplicity, we did not expand the derivative of . If we then choose <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> where is a symmetric positive matrix, the time derivative of becomes Note that although is not necessarily always negative, this will be sufficient to prove boundedness and convergence of to a neighborhood of the origin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Stability Analysis</head><p>We can now prove that all signals will remain bounded, and that the tracking error converges exponential to an arbitrarily small neighborhood of the origin.</p><p>Theorem 1: Given a sufficiently smooth time-varying desired trajectory with its time-derivatives bounded, consider the nonlinear system described by the underactuated vehicle model ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>), (3) in closed-loop with the feedback controller ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>.</p><p>(i) For every initial condition of , the solution exists globally, all closed-loop signals are bounded, and the tracking error satisfies <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> where , , and are positive constants. From these, only depends on initial conditions. (ii) For a given upper bound on , by appropriate choice of the controller parameters , any desired values for and in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> are possible. Proof: To prove (i) we use Young's inequality <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">4</ref> to conclude that for any <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> Suppose now that we choose sufficiently small so that the matrix is positive definite. In this case we conclude that there is a sufficiently small positive constant such that <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> and, therefore, it is straightforward to conclude from the Comparison Lemma <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> that <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> along solutions to . From here we conclude that all signals remain bounded and therefore the solution exists globally. Moreover, converges to a ball of radius and therefore converges to a ball of radius , because of (10). To prove (ii), we show next that the radius can be made as small as we want by appropriately choosing the con-troller parameters. To this effect, suppose we pick a desired radius and a convergence rate , and we select such that B is full rank. Such value for may depend on the upper bound of (see Property 1). We can then define , provided that we choose sufficiently large so that If we then select , , we conclude from ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) that ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) indeed holds for the prespecified , from which (15) follows. However, now the above choices for the parameters lead to a radius . Remark 2: We did not impose any constraints on the desired trajectory (besides being sufficiently smooth and its derivative being bounded) and we also did not require that the linear velocity of the vehicle be always nonnull. Consequently, can be arbitrary, that is, the desired trajectories do not need to satisfy "dynamic" models, and in particular can be constant for all . In that case, the controller solves the position regulation problem.</p><p>Remark 3: In practice, the vector determines if the vehicle will follow the desired trajectory backward or forward. To observe this, define the following two angles: and , where , , and are the three components of the body-fixed tracking error . Notice that and can be seen as the elevation and azimuth angles, respectively. In steady-state (with , ), from ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>), it follows that . Thus, when the first component of is negative and larger (in absolute value) than the other two components, the vehicle will converge to the trajectory with positive surge velocity, and will stay "behind" the desired trajectory, see examples in Section VI.</p><p>Remark 4: When the vehicle is subject to one controlled force and only two independent control torques, i.e., , but (and consequently ), one can use, e.g., , provided that there exists a symmetric positive definite matrix such that (which is the case for the AUV in Section VI). If we then set the time derivative of becomes where is a disturbance term that depends on the component of the state in the null space of . From the above, one can prove boundedness if this component is bounded. For underwater vehicles, this component typically corresponds to the roll motion which usually is stable due to the restoring forces.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. ESTIMATOR-BASED SUPERVISORY CONTROL</head><p>Using the previous results, this section proposes an estimator-based supervisory control architecture to solve the trajectory-tracking problem in the presence of parametric modeling uncertainty. Let be a vector that contains all the unknown parameters of the dynamic equations of motion <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>, where denotes the number of unknown parameters. The following technical assumption is assumed to hold.</p><p>Assumption 1: Let be a finite set of candidate parameter values</p><p>The actual parameter belongs to . In practice, this assumption can be relaxed to being sufficiently close to an element of , which can be achieved by taking a fine grid, at the price of increased computational burden.</p><p>The supervisory consists of three subsystems (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p><p>multi-estimator-a dynamical system whose inputs are the process input and its output , and whose outputs are , , where each is a suitably defined estimate of which would be asymptotically correct if was equal to . multi-controller-a dynamical system whose inputs are the output estimate and the estimation errors , , and whose outputs are the control signals , , where each is generated by a control law that would be adequate if was equal to . switching logic-a dynamical system whose inputs are the estimation errors and whose output is a switching signal which is used to define the control law .</p><p>The underlying decision-making strategy used by the switching logic basically consists of selecting for , the candidate controller index for which the corresponding performance signal (which is a suitably "normed" value of ) is currently the smallest. This strategy is motivated by the idea that the nominal process model with the smallest performance signal is the one that "best" approximates the actual process, and, thus, the candidate controller associated with that model can be expected to have a better performance of controlling the process.</p><p>In this paper we assume that the whole state of the process is available for feedback. Therefore, , and . Since there is no uncertainty in (2), we can simply pick and . We also restrict our attention to state feedback laws and, therefore, .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Multi-Estimator</head><p>This section addresses the design of a family of estimators parameterized by for the underactuated vehicle model ( <ref type="formula">2</ref> for some positive constants , . The functions and will be defined later (cf. (28a), (28b)). The multi-estimator has the desirable property that the estimator error that corresponds to the actual parameter value converges exponentially to zero and satisfies a -like property.</p><p>Lemma 1: Let be the actual parameter value. There exist , , such that for every initial condition of ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>), ( <ref type="formula">3</ref>), ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>), and continuous signal , there exist positive constants , , that depend on the initial conditions such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(18a) (18b) (18c)</formula><p>for every time in the maximum interval of existence of solution to the closed-loop , . Proof: See the Appendix.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Multi-Controller</head><p>We now design a family of candidate feedback laws such that for each , would solve the tracking problem formulated in Section II for a process model given by ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>), and "sufficiently" small estimation errors , . For a given , we design by constructing control-Lyapunov functions iteratively, following the design procedure proposed in Section III.</p><p>Step 1 and 2: Same as in Section III. However, in this case is redefined as <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> and, therefore</p><p>Step 3: The dynamic equation of the error is now given by where Thus, is redefined as where . The time derivative of can be written as where <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> Following the same line of reason described in Step 3 of Section III, let <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> be a virtual control law for each , where is chosen such that is nonsingular. Let be equal to the first entry of , i.e. ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Then</head><p>Step 4: The third control-Lyapunov function is now given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> Computing its time derivative one obtains where can be decomposed in two terms: . Here, , and is defined to be the same as , but substituting the arguments , by , , respectively. Selecting <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> where for each , is a symmetric positive matrix, the time derivative of becomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> where <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> The last term can be rewritten as , where (28a) (28b) From ( <ref type="formula">26</ref>), although has indefinite terms, it will be verified that they will be dominated by the negative definite terms when the estimator errors , are sufficiently small. This is stated in the following lemma. Lemma 2: Let , denote the maximum interval of existence of solution to the closed-loop and suppose that there exists a time such that for all and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref> where the control law is defined in ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">25</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref> Given a sufficiently smooth time-varying desired trajectory with its time-derivatives bounded and any initial condition of the resulting closed-loop system, the signals , , , and are bounded on . Moreover, if (29) holds with , then, as , the tracking error converges to a neighborhood of the origin that can be made arbitrarily small by appropriate choice of the controller parameters.</p><p>Proof: See the Appendix. Loosely speaking, Lemma 2 states that each candidate controller solves the trajectory-tracking problem formulated in Section II provided that the input disturbances due to the estimation errors have finite energy as defined by the integral <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>. The switching-logic will guarantee that (29) holds by the Scale-Independent Hysteresis Switching Lemma <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> (cf. proof of Theorem 2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Switching-Logic</head><p>Motivated by ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref>, for each , we start by defining the performance signal as the state of the dynamic equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref> with the initial values satisfying . Equation ( <ref type="formula">31</ref>) implies that each performance signal is the sum of an exponentially decaying term that depends on initial conditions and a suitable exponentially weighted "norm" of the corresponding estimation errors. The control parameter acts as a forgetting factor in the evaluation of the performance signals, hence establishing a compromise between adaptation alertness and switching dither.</p><p>The switching logic consider here is the scale-independent hysteresis switching logic proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Let be a positive constant called the hysteresis constant. The operation of the switching logic can be briefly explained as follows: First, we set</p><p>. Suppose that at a certain time the value of has just switched to some . Then, will be kept fixed until a time such that at which point we set to . When the indicated minimum is not unique, a particular value for among those that achieve the minimum can be chosen arbitrarily. Repeating this procedure, a piecewise constant signal is generated that is continuous from right everywhere. Setting for all avoids chattering. The switching signal is used to define the control signal as follows: <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref> where the candidate control laws are defined by ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) and (25).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Stability Analysis</head><p>We are now ready to prove that all closed-loop signals will remain bounded, and that the tracking error converges to an arbitrarily small neighborhood of the origin in the presence of possible large parametric modeling uncertainty.</p><p>Theorem 2: Given a sufficiently smooth time-varying desired trajectory with its time-derivatives bounded, consider the hybrid system described by the underactuated vehicle model ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>), (3) in closed-loop with the switched multi-controller <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>, the multi-estimator <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>, and the switching logic described in Section IV-C. i) For any initial condition of with , , the solution exists globally and all closed-loop signals are bounded. ii) Furthermore, there exists a finite time such that for all (i.e., the switching stops in finite time) and as the tracking error converges to a neighborhood of the origin that can be made arbitrarily small by appropriate choice of the control parameters. Proof: Consider the scaled performance signals , . From <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref> we conclude that</p><p>Because of the scale independence property of the switching logic, replacing by would have no effect on . From <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> we see that each is nondecreasing. This, the finiteness of , and the fact that for each guarantee the existence of a positive number such that , , . It is not hard to conclude from the definition of the switching logic that chattering cannot occur. In fact, there must be an interval of maximal length on which the solution of the system is defined, and can only have a finite number of discontinuities on each proper subinterval of . For details, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. To prove that the switching stops in finite time, observe from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">33</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">30</ref>) that is bounded by virtue of Lemma 1. It follows now that the signals satisfy the hypotheses of the Scale-Independent Hysteresis Switching Lemma <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> which enables us to conclude that the switching stops in finite time. More precisely, there exists a time such that for all . In addition, is bounded on . Using <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>   <ref type="formula">16</ref>), it can be seen that the dynamic equations for the quadratic estimation error , can be expressed (after applying the Comparison Lemma) as an exponential stable linear system with bounded inputs. Therefore, this implies that and are bounded on for each . Since all signals are bounded in the maximal interval of existence of solutions, one conclude that the solutions exist globally, i.e., . The convergence of the tracking error to a neighborhood of the origin now follows from Lemma 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. State-Sharing</head><p>In the previous sections, we have relied on the fact that the set was finite, so that the estimators <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>. If the set is infinite or it has a large number of elements, a different approach is required. One alternative, which leads to a more efficient design, is to replace the individual estimator equations by a single system and use it to generate the estimation errors. In other words, to make the estimators in ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) "share" the same state. The performance signals can be obtained in a similar way. To this effect, suppose that the functions , and are separable on the unknown parameter , i.e, take the form . In that case, we can define and replace the estimators ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(37a) (37b)<label>(37c) (37d)</label></formula><p>with outputs where Note that and satisfy ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) but with possible larger and that still satisfy <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. However, the dimension of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">37</ref>) is now independent of the number of elements in .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. PATH-FOLLOWING CONTROLLER DESIGN</head><p>In this section, inspired by <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>, the results described in Section IV are utilized to solve the path-following problem. Let be a desired geometric path parameterized by a variable and a desired speed assignment. Contrary to trajectory-tracking, in path-following we have the freedom to select a timing law for . In particular, we can regard as an additional control input. In this paper, we actually regard as the additional input, because this will necessarily produce a differentiable . Let us define the position body-fixed path-following error and the speed error . Following the same steps described in Section III and IV-B, and defining [see <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>] as where , we obtain Notice also that where and , . Therefore, using ( <ref type="formula">21</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">23</ref>), we obtain where Notice that can be decomposed as . Thus, if we then choose <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref> the time derivative of becomes closed-loop is still stable, the parameter error affects considerably the closed-loop performance. In contrast, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>(b) shows the closed-loop trajectory for the supervisory controller where, as expected, the hovercraft converges to a small neighborhood of the "virtual" unicycle vehicle, in spite of the uncertainty in . Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2(c</ref>) shows the time evolution of some relevant variables. In steady-state the vehicle is not aligned the direction of the tangent velocity of . Contrary to what happens for wheeled mobile robots (with inherent lateral drag coefficient ) in the hovercraft case we cannot force the orientation to converge to the direction of the tangent velocity .</p><p>To further illustrate the usefulness of the adaptive scheme and test its robustness with respect to sensor noise, a second experiment is described. In this case, all the initial conditions and control parameters are as in the first experiment, but now the "virtual" unicycle vehicle moves with linear velocity and angular velocity such that Zero mean uniform random noise was introduced in every sensed signal: the measured velocities , and ; the orientation angle ; and the and positions. The amplitude was set to (0.05, 0.05), 0.05, 0.1, 0.1, and 0.1, respectively. We also consider the situation where the Hovercraft moves between two surfaces characterized by distinct friction coefficients (e.g., from water to land). To simulate this effect, we set the value of the coefficient of viscous friction to while the Hovercraft is in the region and , otherwise. We can see in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>(b) that the hovercraft still converges to a very small neighborhood of the target unicycle vehicle and its performance is not significantly affected by the switching in .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Trajectory-Tracking and Path-Following of an Underwater Vehicle in 3-D Space</head><p>Consider an ellipsoidal shaped underactuated autonomous underwater vehicle (AUV) not necessarily neutrally buoyant. Let be a body-fixed coordinate frame whose origin is located at the center of mass of the vehicle and suppose that we have available a pure body-fixed control force in the direction, and two independent control torques and about the and axes of the vehicle, respectively. The kinematics and dynamics equations of motion of the vehicle can be written as ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) and (3), where , , , , and The gravitational and buoyant forces are given by and , respectively, where is the mass, is the mass density of the water and is the volume of the displaced water. The numerical values used for the physical parameters match those of the Sirene AUV, described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>. The matrix B defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> takes the form , where , , , , . Two simulation results are included to illustrate the dynamic behavior of the AUV in closed-loop with the trajectory-tracking controller presented in Section III, and the path-following controller in Section V. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>(a) displays the vehicle trajectory using the trajectory-tracking controller in the 3-D-space for the following desired trajectory with , , , and . The initial conditions of the AUV are , , and . The control parameters were selected as follows:</p><p>, , , and . Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>(c) and (e) show the time evolution of the tracking error and the Euler angles (computed from ), respectively. The damped oscillatory behavior of pitch and roll are due to the gravitational and buoyancy forces. Notice that the initial position of the desired position was deliberately chosen to be almost behind the initial position of the vehicle. As we can see, the vehicle turns back in its attempt to be at the given reference position at the prescribed time, requiring significant control effort and consequently inducing a strong oscillatory behavior. The path-following controller in Section V was used to generate the trajectories in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>(b), (d), and (f) where the desired path, the initial conditions and the control gains are the same as in the experiment for the tracking controller. The guidance gain and the speed assignment were set to and , respectively. The initial condition for was chosen to be the one that minimizes the distance between the initial position of the AUV and the desired path. The convergence of the vehicle to the path is now much smoother. From these two experiments one can see that when the primary objective is to steer the vehicle to converge to and move along a geometric path, the path-following controller offers significant performance improvement. For simplicity, in these experiments we did not include model uncertainty.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSION</head><p>We proposed a solution to the trajectory-tracking and path-following problem for underactuated autonomous vehicles in the presence of possibly large modeling parametric uncertainty. For a general class of vehicles moving in either 2or 3-D space, we demonstrated how adaptive switching supervisory control can be combined with a nonlinear Lyapunov-based tracking control law to design a hybrid controller that yields global boundedness and convergence of the position tracking error to a small neighborhood, and robustness to parametric modeling uncertainty. We illustrated our results in the context of two vehicle control applications: a hovercraft (moving on a planar surface) and an underwater vehicle (moving in 3-D space). Simulations show that the control objectives were accomplished.</p><p>An alternative approach to the Lyapunov-based control scheme proposed in Section III consists in choosing an adequate point linked to the vehicle and then utilize output feedback linearization to design a simple controller that drives that point to the reference trajectory. See, for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> for the case of unicycle-like mobile robots. For general underactuated vehicles, the stability of the zero-dynamics would have to be established independently. This is an issue for future research.</p><p>A problem that warrants further research is the control of underactuated vehicles with noise and in the presence of disturbances. Typical disturbances for marine vehicles include the ones induced by wave, wind, and ocean current. small and sufficiently large , such that for all , <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> holds with</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Step 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Coordinate transformation: Consider the global diffeomorphic coordinate transformation which expresses the tracking error in the body-fixed frame. The dynamic equation of the body-fixed tracking error is given by Step 2. Convergence of : We start by defining the control-Lyapunov function and computing its time derivative to obtain (4)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Supervisory control architecture.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,40.62,66.26,246.00,106.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>),<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>. Motivated by Assumption 1 and in view of (3), we consider a family of estimators of the form5   </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. First experiment. Trajectory of the hovercraft in the xy-plane and reference trajectory performed by a unicycle vehicle using the trajectory-tracking controller presented in Section III [diagram (a)] and the estimator-based supervisory controller for trajectory-tracking [diagram (b)]. Time evolution of the tracking error in x-direction, in y-direction, and the switching signal for the estimator-based supervisory controller [diagram (c)].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Second experiment. Trajectory of the hovercraft in the xy-plane and reference trajectory performed by a unicycle vehicle using the trajectory-tracking controller presented in Section III [diagram (a)] and the estimator-based supervisory controller for trajectory-tracking [diagram (b)]. Time evolution of the tracking error in x-direction, in y-direction, and the switching signal for the estimator-based supervisory controller [diagram (c)].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Vehicle trajectory in 3-D space using the trajectory-tracking controller presented in Section III [diagram (a)], and the path-following controller [diagram (b)]. Time evolution of the position error e = (e ; e ; e ), the roll , pitch , and yaw Euler angles for the trajectory-tracking [diagrams (c), (e)], and the path-following [diagrams (d), (f)].</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_0"><p>A special case of the Young's inequality is ab (=2)a + (1=2)b , where a; b 0, and is any positive constant.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_1"><p>When P has a large number of elements, an alternative approach is described in Section IV-E.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_2"><p>The existence of (1) and (1) follows directly from the fact that f (1) and f (1) are C .</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Recommended by Associate Editor A. Garulli. This work was supported in part by the National Science Foundation under Grant ECS-0093762, Project MAYA-Sub of the AdI (PT), project GREX/CEC-IST under Contract 035223, of the Commission of the European Communities, and by the FCT-ISR/IST plurianual funding through the POS_C Program that includes FEDER funds. A. P. Aguiar was with the Center for Control Engineering and Computation,</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>where , , is defined to be the same as , but substituting , by , , and</p><p>Introduce now a forth control Lyapunov function given by Computing its time derivative, we get Selecting the following update law for :</p><p>(39) where is a positive constant, we obtain An extension of Theorem to the path-following then follows. Theorem 3: Given a sufficiently smooth (with respect to ) desired path with its derivatives (with respect to ) bounded, and a desired assignment speed , consider the hybrid system described by the underactuated vehicle model <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref> in closed-loop with the switched multi-controller <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(39)</ref>, the multi-estimator <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>, and the switching logic described in Section IV-C. i) For any initial condition of with , , the solution exists globally and all closed-loop signals are bounded. ii) There exist a finite time such that for all (i.e., the switching stops in finite time). Moreover, as , the position error and the speed error converge to neighborhoods of the origin that can be made arbitrarily small by appropriate choice of the control parameters. Proof: The proof is not given since it is a simple application of the arguments used in the previous theorems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. APPLICATION TO SPECIFIC VEHICLES</head><p>This section illustrates the application of the previous results to two vehicles: a hovercraft (moving on a planar surface) and an underwater vehicle (moving in 3-D space).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Trajectory-Tracking of an Underactuated Hovercraft</head><p>Consider the Caltech MVWT vehicle described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> consisting of a platform mounted on three low-friction, omnidirectional casters, with two attached high-performance ducted fans. Let be the Cartesian coordinates of the vehicle's center of mass and its orientation. Assuming that the friction and moment forces can be modeled by viscous friction, the equations of motion are where is the mass of the vehicle and is the rotational inertia. The starboard and portboard fan forces are denoted and , respectively, and denotes the moment arm of the forces. The geometric and mass centers of the vehicle are assumed to coincide. The coefficient of viscous friction is 5.5 Kg/s and the coefficient of rotational friction is 0.41 Kg m/s. Expressing the equations of motion in the body fixed frame, yields (2) and (</p><p>In this case the matrix B introduced in (8) is given by with . The reader is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> for a detailed coverage of the trajectory-tracking controller with experimental results. We now describe two simulation results that illustrate the performance of the proposed tracking controller with and without supervisory control. The objective of the first experiment is to force the hovercraft to track the "virtual" kinematic unicycle vehicle which starts at and moves with velocities and . The initial conditions for the hovercraft are , ,</p><p>. For simplicity, only the coefficient of viscous friction is unknown, but assumed to belong to the set . The control parameters were selected as follows:</p><p>, , , and for all . The hysteresis constant for the switching logic was set to , the forgetting factor to , and the multi-estimator gains to and . The functions and introduced in ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) are given by . To illustrate the benefits derived from the supervisory control scheme proposed in Section IV, we show in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>(a) the closed-loop trajectory for the (nonadaptive) trajectory-tracking controller presented in Section III when the value of the coefficient of viscous friction assumed by the control system was set to 10% of the real value. It can be seen that although the APPENDIX Property 1: Let be nonzero and uniformly bounded by . Then, there exists a vector that makes defined in (8) full-rank.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proof: Pick</head><p>, where and is a positive constant to be selected shortly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Defining</head><p>, we conclude that <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref> where we used the fact that the rank of a matrix does not change when it is multiplied by a nonsingular matrix. From the definition of [see <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>] we conclude that each element of can be bounded by . Much tighter bounds can be obtained for specific class of vehicles. For example, when then . Assume now that . From (40), we conclude that B has full-rank if one can find at least one minor determinant of nonzero. Consider the one formed by the first, third, and forth columns, i.e. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(41)</ref> where collects all the remaining terms and does not depend on . It follows now from the fact that each can be arbitrarily small by choosing (and consequently ) sufficient large, that (41) can be made nonzero and therefore B full-rank.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>If</head><p>, the same conclusion about the full-rank of B can be made by following the same reasoning but with if , or for the case .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 1:</head><p>Proof: Throughout this proof, to avoid cumbersome notation, we will use , , , to denote , , , and , respectively. Note also that corresponds to the nominal model and therefore is equal to . The same applies for the other model parameters. Consider the following exponentially weighted Lyapunov-like functions:</p><p>where is any positive constant that satisfies <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(42)</ref> Computing the time derivative of and along the solutions of (2b), (3), and ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) for , we obtain</p><p>To prove (18a), consider the Lyapunov function , which is the same as with . From (43) it follows that:</p><p>. Using the Comparison Lemma <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> one concludes that (18a) holds with and . To prove (18b), observe from (43a) and ( <ref type="formula">42</ref> Inequality (18c) can be also concluded by applying the same arguments to (43b). In that case . Lemma 2: Proof: Taking norms to defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> and using (17a) we conclude that Also, from (17b) and (17c), a bound for given in ( <ref type="formula">27</ref>) can be computed as follows:</p><p>Using these two bounds in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> and resorting to Young's inequality it follows that for every positive constant , , satisfies</p><p>where we used the facts that and . Therefore, there exist sufficiently small positive constants , , , and sufficiently large positive constants , such that <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref> where in view of ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">30</ref>), the signals , , , are defined on , and is defined on . Applying the Comparison Lemma to <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref> and using <ref type="bibr">[46,</ref>  <ref type="bibr">Lemma 1]</ref> we conclude that is bounded on . Moreover, when , converges to a ball of radius as . Standard signal chasing arguments can now be applied to conclude that the signals , , and in closed-loop system remain bounded. Furthermore, applying the same arguments described in the proof of item ii) of Theorem 1, one conclude that the tracking error converges to a neighborhood of the origin that can be made arbitrarily small.</p><p>Derivation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>: Using ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) for and the fact that , and , the time-derivative of in <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> can be written as Using the Young's inequality, after a straightforward but messy computations, one can conclude that there exist a sufficiently </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Classical Mechanics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Reading, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">672</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Control of nonholonomic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">-Y</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>The Control Handbook, W. S. Levine</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>CRC and IEEE</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1359" to="1368" />
			<pubPlace>Boca Raton, FL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics and control of a class of underactuated mechanical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reyhanoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Der Schaft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mcclamroch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kolmanovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1663" to="1671" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controllability and motion algorithms for underactuated lagrangian systems on lie groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bullo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Leonard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1437" to="1454" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gain-scheduled missile autopilot design using linear parameter varying transformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shamma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cloutier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Guid. Control Dyn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="263" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trajectory tracking controllers for autonomous vehicles: An integrated approach to guidance and control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kaminer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pascoal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hallberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Silvestre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Guid. Control Dyn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research on gain-scheduling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shamma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1401" to="1425" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Output tracking control design of a helicopter model based on approximate linearization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Koo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 37th Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>37th Conf. Decision Control<address><addrLine>Tampa, FL</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-12">Dec. 1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3635" to="3640" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking and maneuver regulation control for nonlinear nonminimum phase systems: Application to flight control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Al-Hiddabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mcclamroch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Contr. Syst. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="780" to="792" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A decentralized approach to formation maneuvers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R T</forename><surname>Lawton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot. Autom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="933" to="941" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Isidori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Nonlinear Control Systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London, U.K.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear tracking of underactuated surface vessels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Godhavn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 35th Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>35th Conf. Decision Control<address><addrLine>Kobe, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-12">Dec. 1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="975" to="980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global practical stabilization and tracking for an underactuated ship-A combined averaging and backstepping approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Pettersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nijmeijer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IFAC Conf. Syst. Structure Control</title>
		<meeting>IFAC Conf. Syst. Structure Control<address><addrLine>Nantes, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-07">Jul. 1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="64" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trajectory tracking of underactuated underwater vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Alonge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>D'ippolito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Raimondi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 40th Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>40th Conf. Decision Control<address><addrLine>Orlando, FL, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-12">Dec. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global tracking control of underactuated ships by Lyapunov&apos;s direct method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-P</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking and regulation control of an underactuated surface vessel with nonintegrable dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Behal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="495" to="500" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-03">Mar. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Underactuated ship global tracking under relaxed conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1529" to="1536" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-09">Sep. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Universal controllers for stabilization and tracking of underactuated ships</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking control of an underactuated ship</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Pettersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nijmeijer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Contr. Syst. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trajectory tracking control design for autonomous helicopters using a backstepping algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Frazzoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dahleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Feron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 2000 Amer. Contr. Conf</title>
		<meeting>2000 Amer. Contr. Conf<address><addrLine>Chicago, IL</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-06">Jun. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supervision of integralinput-to-state stabilizing controllers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liberzon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1327" to="1335" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krstic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">´</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kanellakopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kokotovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">´</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Nonlinear and Adaptive Control Design</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adaptive Control: Stability, Convergence, and Robustness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bodson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ioannou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Robust Adaptive Control</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overcoming the limitations of adaptive control by means of logic-based switching</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liberzon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Contr. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supervisory control of families of linear set-point controllers part 1: Exact matching</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1413" to="1431" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Certainty equivalence implies detectability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Logic-based switching control of a nonholonomic system with parametric modeling uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liberzon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supervisory field-oriented control of induction motors with uncertain rotor resistance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Netto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ortega</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Adapt. Contr. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lyapunov-based switching supervisory control of nonlinear uncertain systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Angeli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mosca</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="500" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stabilization of relative equilibria for underactuated systems on riemannian manifolds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bullo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1819" to="1834" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path-following and time-varying feedback stabilization of a wheeled mobile robot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Samson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>13.1.1-RO-13.1.5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ICARCV 92</title>
		<meeting>ICARCV 92<address><addrLine>Singapore</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear control design for mobile robots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C D</forename><surname>Wit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Khennouf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Samson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sordalen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Recent Trends in Mobile Robots</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="156" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control of chained systems: Application to path following and time-varying point-stabilization of mobile robots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Samson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A recursive technique for tracking control of nonholonomic systems in chained form</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-P</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nijmeijer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="279" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Following a path of varying curvature as an output regulation problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Altafini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1551" to="1556" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aggressive flight maneuvers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hindman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 36th Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>36th Conf. Decision Control<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-12">Dec. 1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4186" to="4191" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">3D path following control of autonomous underwater vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Encarnaçāao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 39th Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>39th Conf. Decision Control<address><addrLine>Sydney, Australia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-12">Dec. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust output maneuvering for a class of nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Skjetne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Fossen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kokotovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">´</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="383" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path-following or reference-tracking? An answer based on limits of performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Aguiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dačic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">´</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kokotovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">´</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 5th IFAC/EURON Symp</title>
		<meeting>5th IFAC/EURON Symp<address><addrLine>Lisbon, Portugal</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-07">Jul. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path-following for non-minimum phase systems removes performance limitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Aguiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kokotovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">´</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Position tracking of underactuated vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Aguiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 2003 Amer. Contr. Conf</title>
		<meeting>2003 Amer. Contr. Conf<address><addrLine>Denver, CO</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-06">Jun. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Position tracking for a nonlinear underactuated hovercraft: Controller design and experimental results</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Aguiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cremean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 42nd Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>42nd Conf. Decision Control<address><addrLine>HI</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-12">Dec. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Logic-based switching control for trajectory-tracking and path-following of underactuated autonomous vehicles with parametric modeling uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Aguiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hespanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 2004 Amer. Contr. Conf</title>
		<meeting>2004 Amer. Contr. Conf<address><addrLine>Boston, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-06">Jun. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonlinear Systems, 2nd ed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Khalil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a unified theory of parameter adaptive control: Tunability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1002" to="1012" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The caltech multi-vehicle wireless testbed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cremean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dumbar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Van Gogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hickey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Meltzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 41st Conf. Decision Control</title>
		<meeting>41st Conf. Decision Control<address><addrLine>Las Vegas, NV</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-12">Dec. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling and control of an autonomous underwater shuttle for the transport of benthic laboratories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Aguiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Oceans&apos;97 Conf</title>
		<meeting>Oceans&apos;97 Conf<address><addrLine>Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10">Oct. 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear motion control of nonholonomic and underactuated systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Aguiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dep. Elect. Eng., Instituto Superior Técnico (IST)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<pubPlace>Lisbon, Portugal</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
