<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized Adaptive Control of a Class of Large-Scale Interconnected Nonlinear Systems</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Sandeep</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">American Control Conference</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1995</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA, June</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Control/Robotics Research Laboratory (CRRL)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Polytechnic Univer-sity</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>11201</postCode>
									<settlement>Brooklyn</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Senior Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Farshad</forename><surname>Khorrami</surname></persName>
							<email>khorrami@smart.poly.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">American Control Conference</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1995</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA, June</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized Adaptive Control of a Class of Large-Scale Interconnected Nonlinear Systems</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2CA2906FEE20A9828C823083CA3BC3C8</idno>
					<note type="submission">received June 20, 1994; revised February 6, 1995 and February 1, 1996.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T11:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Adaptive</term>
					<term>decentralized control</term>
					<term>large-scale systems</term>
					<term>nonlinear</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Decentralized adaptive control design for a class of large-scale interconnected nonlinear systems with unknown interconnections is considered in this paper. The motivation behind this work is to develop decentralized control for a class of large-scale systems which do not satisfy the matching condition requirement. To this end, large-scale nonlinear systems transformable to the decentralized strict feedback form are considered. Coordinate-free geometric conditions under which any general interconnected nonlinear system can be transformed to this form are obtained. The interconnections are assumed to be bounded by polynomial-type nonlinearities. However, the magnitudes of the nonlinearities are unknown. Global stability and asymptotic regulation are established using classical Lyapunov techniques. The controller is shown to maintain robustness for a wide class of systems obtained by perturbations in the dynamics of the original system. Furthermore, appending additional subsystems does not require controller redesign for the original subsystems. Finally, the scheme is extended to the model reference tracking problem where global uniform boundedness of the tracking error to a compact set is established.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>operating point and possibly degradation in performance and instability over a large domain of operation.</p><p>Most of the literature on decentralized and adaptive control of large-scale nonlinear systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> is focused on systems with first-order bounded interconnections. These results cannot guarantee stability when the interconnections between the subsystems are of higher orders <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, decentralized adaptive controllers for robotic manipulators are designed under the assumption that the nonlinear interconnection terms due to Coriolis and centrifugal effects are slowly time varying. This assumption fails to hold, however, for high-speed trajectory tracking and could possibly result in instability. The first result on global decentralized stabilization of large-scale systems with higher-order interconnections is by Shi and Singh <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. The interconnections are assumed to be bounded by a th order polynomial in states. Adaptation of control gains is utilized to relax the requirement of explicit knowledge of the polynomial.</p><p>A major structural restriction imposed on the system in all these schemes is that the uncertainties and interconnections are in the range space of the input matrix, which is basically the strict matching condition. Global stabilization for systems with mismatched uncertainties is not possible using these schemes. Recent advances in the area of centralized adaptive nonlinear control have resulted in the recursive design of control laws for systems which do not satisfy the strict matching requirement <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Motivated by these advancements in the area of centralized nonlinear control, we seek to investigate the possible extension of the class of large-scale nonlinear systems for which decentralized control laws can be developed.</p><p>In this paper, we extend the strict matching requirement to a class of large-scale nonlinear systems with parametric and nonparametric uncertainties. These are termed as systems of the decentralized strict feedback form. In Section II, we characterize this class of large-scale systems. Geometric conditions are stated under which any interconnected largescale nonlinear system can be transformed into this form via a parameter independent decentralized diffeomorphism. The interconnections are assumed to be bounded by an unknown th-order polynomial in states. In Section III, an adaptive decentralized control is developed using a stepwise design procedure. The design is motivated by the decentralized design in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> and integrator backstepping along with the tuning function design for centralized control <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The scheme is proven to guarantee global stabilization and regulation properties. The developed control is robust to perturbations in the system dynamics. Furthermore, no redesign is required for controllers of the original subsystems if additional subsystems are appended to the system. In Section IV, the scheme is extended to a model reference tracking problem, where uniform boundedness of the tracking error is guaranteed. The effectiveness of the advocated approach is illustrated through simulation examples.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. THE CLASS OF LARGE-SCALE NONLINEAR SYSTEMS</head><p>We consider a large-scale nonlinear system comprised of interconnected subsystems with the interconnections being linear in the unknown parameters. The th subsystem is given as <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> where is the state vector for the th subsystem, is the state vector for the overall system, is the control input, and is a vector of unknown constant parameters for the th subsystem. The vector fields , , and are assumed to be smooth with , , and . We make the following assumption for the isolated subsystems.</p><p>Assumption 2.1: Assume that the isolated subsystems <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> are globally input-to-state linearizable. Equivalently, there exists an output function such that the isolated subsystem has a relative degree with respect to . Sufficient conditions under which this assumption is satisfied are stated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p><p>We now define the notion of the degree of mismatch for interconnected systems.</p><p>Definition 2.1: Assume that the isolated subsystems are exactly externally feedback linearizable. Let denote the smallest integer such that: 1) , ,</p><p>for at least one , where are the vector fields in (1) for the th subsystem corresponding to the interconnections. Then, the degree of mismatch ( ) for the th subsystem is defined as . The decentralized scheme proposed in this paper is applicable to large-scale nonlinear systems which are transformable using a global parameter independent, decentralized transformation to the following decentralized strict feedback form: . . . . . . <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref> with ; , , , . Remark 2.1: Since the primary objective is decentralized control, it is desirable for the transformation for each subsystem to utilize the states local to that subsystem. Assuming that all the states of a subsystem are available for feedback to the controller corresponding to that subsystem, a decentralized control designed in the transformed coordinates still maintains its decentralized structure in the original coordinates. Thus, the terminology decentralized transformation is justified.</p><p>The degree of mismatch defines the separation of the interconnections from the control. The mismatch between the interconnections (and hence uncertainties) and the control is larger for larger , resulting in increased complexity in the control design.</p><p>Remark 2.2: The class of systems (3) illustrates a tradeoff between the degree of mismatch and the complexity of the interconnections. The larger the degree of mismatch for the th subsystem, the fewer are the number of states of that subsystem appearing in the interconnections.</p><p>Given that the isolated subsystem (2) is input-state linearizable, the degree of mismatch of each subsystem stays the same irrespective of the choice of the feedback linearizing coordinate transformation for the isolated subsystem. This is made precise in the following theorem, the proof of which is given in the Appendix.</p><p>Theorem 2.1: The degree of mismatch for each subsystem of a large-scale interconnected system given by ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) is invariant with respect to the choice of the input-state linearizing transformation for the isolated system.</p><p>The necessary and sufficient conditions for the existence of a decentralized diffeomorphism transforming (1)-( <ref type="formula">3</ref>) are stated in the following proposition. Some definitions are stated first.</p><p>Define the following distributions and codistributions for the subsystem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">span (4) span (5)<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where is the output function for which (2) has relative degree .</p><p>We are now ready to state the following proposition. Proposition 2.1: Under Assumption 2.1, a global decentralized diffeomorphism ; , transforming</p><p>(1) into (3), exists if and only if the following two conditions hold globally. 1) , , , , where is the degree of mismatch for the th subsystem. 2) , , , .</p><p>Proof: Refer to the Appendix.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. DECENTRALIZED ADAPTIVE DESIGN</head><p>The decentralized control is designed for (3), obtained from (1) through a decentralized transformation. For notational simplicity, we assume uniform degree of mismatch ( ) and same number of states ( ) for each subsystem. Denoting the first states of the th subsystem by , and the remaining states by , the transformed system is rewritten in terms of as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">. . . . . . . . . . . .<label>(7)</label></formula><p>. . .</p><p>We make a further assumption for the unstructured uncertainties in the interconnections in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">7</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">8</ref>). Assumption 3.1: The nonlinear interconnection terms in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">7</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">8</ref>) are bounded by polynomial-type nonlinearities in , , i.e.,</p><p>with . Note that the parametric uncertainty can be lumped with the unknown coefficients . Remark 3.1: The case where the subsystems have an unequal number of states and a degree of mismatch is notationally more cumbersome than insightful and can be handled, as shown in the sequel, using an example. Moreover, in several practical situations, e.g., power systems, the system is generally comprised of dynamically similar interconnected subsystems.</p><p>The ensuing systematic design procedure is motivated by the decentralized design in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> and integrator backstepping along with the tuning function design for centralized control <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. We first consider the problem of regulating the states to a desired set-point. The extension to the state tracking problem is considered in the next section.</p><p>Step 0: Define <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> Consider the th subsystem given above. Start with the zeroth sub-subsystem, given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">7</ref>), with as the virtual control input. Since is a controllable pair, a symmetric positive definite solution to the algebraic Riccati equation (ARE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> with and a symmetric positive definite matrix. Choose appropriate and to solve <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> for . Following the approach in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, the decentralized control law for the zeroth sub-subsystem of the th subsystem is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> where is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> and is a time-varying adaptation gain. Since is not the control, define Therefore (13) Let be the desired value of the control gain to counteract the effect of the interconnections. Consider the following composite Lyapunov function for the zeroth sub-subsystems of the overall system: <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> where is a positive constant. Differentiating along the trajectories of (13), we obtain Using <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> and bounds from (9), we get <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> where is introduced as a degree of freedom <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Utilizing the inequalities <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> (Cauchy-Schwartz inequality) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> the last term of (15) can be written as  where the last terms can be taken as zero. The following adaptation for is used:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(22)</formula><p>Using ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>), can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">(23)</formula><p>The actual gains and are obtained in the final step. The state equations for and are given as<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> </p><p>(24)</p><p>Step 1: Consider as the virtual control for the subsystem. Let be the estimate of . Since is a function of the bounds on the interconnections, and hence unknown, it needs to be estimated. Likewise, define as an estimate for . Consider the following composite Lyapunov function:</p><p>(25) Differentiating along the trajectories of (24) and combining the term with coefficients of , we obtain</p><p>Using bounds from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">9</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>), the last term in (26) can be written as</p><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">(28)<label>(29)</label></formula><p>and is given by (20). Using (27), is written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">(30)</formula><p>With as the virtual control, we choose</p><p>where . Define</p><p>In terms of ( ), is given as</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">(32)</formula><p>To avoid overparameterization, the adaptation laws for and are obtained in the final step. To this end, we define the following tuning functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">(33) (34)</formula><p>Retaining the relevant terms, the ( ) sub-subsystem can be written as (35)</p><p>Step 2: From now on, the following notation is used unless specified explicitly:</p><p>(36)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consider</head><p>as the virtual control for the ( ) subsystem. Consider the Lyapunov function:</p><p>(37)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Differentiating</head><p>along the trajectories of (35), we obtain</p><p>As in (27), we obtain using ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">9</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>), bounds for with and given by ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>) and (29), respectively. Using these bounds, (38) may be reduced to can be expressed as and can be countered using the control . However, if does not appear in , (44) needs to be upgraded using tuning functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. This is illustrated in Step (</p><p>), where the design procedure is made recursive.</p><p>Step ( ): Consider as the virtual control for the ( ) subsystem, where is given by ( <ref type="formula">45</ref>) and </p><p>Choose the following virtual control for :</p><p>(54)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Define</head><p>Then, is given by (55)</p><p>Step : In the th step, is obtained as a virtual control input [ ] for the subsystem. Define Denoting as the degree of mismatch, we obtain The following decentralized control input is applied for the th subsystem:</p><p>(60)</p><p>with the adaptation laws</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">(61)<label>(62)</label></formula><p>The stability properties of the above designed decentralized adaptive control are stated in the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 3.1: Suppose that (1), with and uniform degree of mismatch for each subsystem, satisfies the conditions of Proposition 2.1. The control input (60) along with the adaptation laws ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>), (61), and (62), obtained from the above systematic design procedure, results in the global uniform stability of the equilibrium Furthermore, regulation of the state is achieved, i.e., for all initial conditions in . Proof of Theorem 3.1: Applying (60) with adaptation laws (61) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_16">62</ref>), ( <ref type="formula">59</ref>) becomes (63)</p><p>The degree of freedom is chosen as (64)</p><p>We need to establish the existence of the gain as a function of the interconnection measure , such that is negative. The first two terms of can be made negative by an appropriate choice of . This can be seen as follows. The coefficients of terms for are negative and are given by The coefficients of terms for are and the coefficients of terms for are given by Therefore, choosing (65) where we have (66) Thus, the solutions , , , , , are bounded for all initial conditions and for all . Thus, , are bounded, ; , implying uniform continuity of and . Moreover, since is a positive, monotonically decreasing function, its limit is well defined and Thus, , . Invoking Barbalat's lemma <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, we have Furthermore, , , , , and are uniformly continuous. Also , where . Therefore Since can be expressed as smooth functions of , using (45), and from the uniqueness of as an equilibrium of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, and (8), we obtain It now follows from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">7</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">8</ref>) that . Finally, since , is a diffeomorphism with , regulation is achieved in the original coordinates, i.e.,</p><p>The above design procedure proceeds independently for each subsystem after Step 0, where the virtual control for the subsystem is obtained. Therefore, as alluded to in Remark 3.1, the degree of mismatch and the number of states for each subsystem need not be the same. Thus, the results of the above theorem are true for the general case of different degrees of mismatch and number of states among the subsystems. Furthermore, for each subsystem, three parameters ( , , ) need to be adapted. However, if , , only the parameters and need to be updated for the th subsystem. These points are illustrated in the example below.</p><p>Remark 3.2: The class of large-scale nonlinear systems can be further extended to systems transformable to the following decentralized pure feedback form: . . .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>. . . (67)</head><p>The decentralized design can be carried out in similar steps as above. However, as discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, the region of attraction in this case is not global, but asymptotic regulation and tracking are guaranteed in regions for which a priori estimates are given.</p><p>Example 3.1: We consider a system comprised of two subsystems with degrees of mismatch , . Subsystem 1:</p><p>(68) Subsystem 2:</p><p>(69</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">)</formula><p>The system is already in the decentralized strict feedback form and hence satisfies the conditions of Theorem 3.1. Identifying with <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> We design a decentralized adaptive control law for the above system following the steps outlined earlier.</p><p>Step 0: Since the interconnections are bounded by quadratic polynomials in the states, from <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> we have . We choose diag Solving the ARE <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, we obtain</p><p>The virtual controls obtained from ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) are given by with adaptation laws obtained from ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) with (70)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Define</head><p>. The terms and in (24) are given by Since , , the unknown parameter can be lumped with the coefficients of the polynomial interconnections, which are also unknown. Thus, only adaptation in is required. Step 1: From the bounds in (27), we obtain Since the degree of mismatch is one, the input appears in this step and is obtained from (31), i.e., (</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">)<label>72</label></formula><p>with adaptation for given by (</p><p>The closed-loop system was simulated for the following initial conditions:</p><p>The nominal values for , were chosen as 1.0. The closed-loop responses for the two subsystems are plotted in Figs. <ref type="figure">1</ref> and<ref type="figure">2</ref>, respectively. The adaptation of parameters , for the two subsystems is shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">4</ref>, respectively.</p><p>Remark 3.3: It is interesting to note that (71) and (72) maintain a robust performance to a wide class of perturbations in the system dynamics, as long as the interconnections are bounded by a quadratic polynomial in . In this sense, the controller guarantees robustness to inaccurately modeled dynamics. Thus, even if the system of (68) and ( <ref type="formula">69</ref>) is modified to the following: Subsystem 1:</p><p>(76) (77) the controller developed above will still maintain a robust performance. The adaptation parameters self-adjust to new (possibly higher) values to incorporate the additional perturbations. Remark 3.4: An important issue in decentralized control design is redesigning decentralized controllers for the original subsystems if more subsystems are appended to the large-scale system. The design methodology proposed here obviates any need for controller redesign for the original subsystems if the order of the nonlinearities in the interconnections, due to the appended subsystem, is less than or equal to that of original system. This is generally true for most practical applications, where the interconnected subsystems are dynamically similar. In any case, defining in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> as the maximum possible order of all current and future interconnections will ensure that the same decentralized controller works for the modified subsystems. For the example considered above, we append a third subsystem to the original system given by ( <ref type="formula">68</ref>) and (69). The new system is given by Subsystem 1:</p><p>(78) Subsystem 2:</p><p>(79) (80)</p><p>The decentralized control laws for the first and second subsystems are given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">71</ref>), (72) with adaptation laws (70) and (73). For the third subsystem</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Defining</head><p>, the control law for is given by (81)</p><p>with adaptation laws (82)</p><p>The initial conditions used for simulations are given by (75) along with</p><p>The closed-loop responses are plotted in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">5</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">6</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7</ref>. The plots validate the fact that the same control laws maintain a robust performance even when more subsystems are appended to the original system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. THE TRACKING FORMULATION</head><p>The objective of the decentralized state tracking problem is to track a given reference model. As before, to avoid notational complexity, we consider the case of uniform degrees of mismatch and number of states among the subsystems. Since the isolated subsystems are in the Brunovsky form, we  choose a similar model for each subsystem of the large-scale system given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">7</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">8</ref>), i.e., . . . <ref type="bibr">(83)</ref> where is an external (reference) input to the th subsystem model. We first define the state tracking errors and . The design procedure in the previous section is applied to tracking error system . . . <ref type="bibr">(84)</ref> with certain distinctions which are outlined below</p><p>Step 0: View as the virtual control for the subsystem in (85). As before we have <ref type="bibr">(85)</ref> with adaptation law for given by (86) where incorporates the " modification" to avoid parameter drift as originally proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. The properties of the virtual control law (85) can be analyzed using the following Lyapunov function:</p><p>(87) with a positive constant. In this case, the interconnection terms can be bounded using the inequality <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> (88) as follows:</p><p>(89) where is now obtained following manipulations parallel to Step 0 in the regulation case with an additional term due to . Since, is only the virtual control, define the error . In Step 1, the dynamics for the error term are formulated, and the virtual control for is obtained. In this case, due to the additional first term in ( <ref type="formula">89</ref> </p><p>The virtual control for at the th step is given by input for each subsystem appears in this step and is obtained from (98) (using ), i.e.,</p><p>with adaptation given by ( <ref type="formula">100</ref>) and (101), i.e.,</p><p>The initial conditions used are given by (75), along with . The closed-loop responses along with the reference model states are plotted in Figs. <ref type="bibr">8-12.</ref> From the plots, we see that the tracking error stays bounded. The adaptation of parameters , , and are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">13</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">14</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">15</ref>, respectively. Remark 4.2: As before, it can be shown that the decentralized tracking control law maintains robustness to perturbations in the system dynamics as long as the order of the interconnections remains the same. Also, the same control law can be used if additional subsystems are appended to the original system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSION</head><p>This paper extends the class of large-scale nonlinear systems for which decentralized controllers can be designed. This class is identified by systems transformable to a decentralized strict feedback form for which the matching condition is not satisfied. Geometric conditions for the existence of a parameter independent, decentralized diffeomorphism are presented. Higher order interconnections bounded by unknown th order polynomials are considered. A constructive, stepwise procedure for decentralized control design is presented. Adaptation      and its effectiveness is shown using a simulation example. Robustness of the developed control laws to perturbations  in the system dynamics is established through simulations. Furthermore, it is shown that no redesign of decentralized controllers is required for the original subsystems if new subsystems are appended to the system. Finally, an adaptive model reference decentralized tracking control design is outlined for the same class of large-scale systems. Global uniform boundedness of the tracking error to a compact set is obtained in this case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX PROOFS OF THEOREM 2.1 AND PROPOSITION 2.1</head><p>To prove Theorem 2.1, we use the following Lemma proved in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>Lemma A1: If is a real valued function, is a vector field, and is a covector field, then for (106)</p><p>Necessity: Given a diffeomorphism that transforms the original system (1)-(3), it is easy to verify that the coordinate-free conditions i) and ii) are satisfied for (3) and hence for (1).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>and<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>, we obtain bounds for Applying these bounds to ,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Subsystem 1 closed-loop response.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Adaptation of 1 and 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Adaptation of &amp;1 and &amp;2 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Subsystem 1 closed-loop response.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Subsystem 2 closed-loop response.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Subsystem 3 closed-loop response.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. States y 11 and y m11 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. States y 12 and y m12 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. States x 11 and x m11 .laws are obtained to update the control gains to counter uncertainties in the interconnections. Global regulation is proved,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. States y 21 and y m21 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. States x 21 and x m21 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13. Adaptation of 1 and 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14. Adaptation of &amp;1 and &amp;2 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 15 .</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Fig. 15. Adaptation of 1 max and 2 max .</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>In the sequel, with a slight abuse of notation, we refer to i as i (y 1 ; 1 1 1 ; y N ; x i1 ; 1 1 1 ; x i ) with the understanding that i0 is i0 (y 1 ; 1 1 1 ; y N ).</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors acknowledge the helpful comments of the anonymous reviewers in rectifying certain technical issues and improving the presentation of this paper.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="bibr">(97)</ref> <p>where the notation used is defined analogously to the regulation case [refer to (36), for example, and also to Example 4.1 below] with the arguments replaced by the error terms. In (97), is the coefficient of in the dynamics of , and and are positive design parameters effecting the magnitude of the tracking error.</p><p>The actual control input appears in the ( )th step. The decentralized tracking control law is given by <ref type="bibr">(98)</ref> with the following adaptation laws:</p><p>(99) (100) <ref type="bibr">(101)</ref> where the tuning functions , , and , are given by ( <ref type="formula">91</ref>)-(93), respectively. In (99)-(101), s are the -modification parameters. The following theorem states the stability and tracking properties of the proposed decentralized tracking control (for proof refer to <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>).</p><p>Theorem 4.1: The control input (98) along with the adaptation laws (86) and ( <ref type="formula">99</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">101</ref>) results in the global uniform boundedness of the error system , , with respect to a compact set around the origin. Furthermore, the error can be made arbitrarily small by choosing the design parameters appropriately.</p><p>Remark 4.1: The control effort at each step ( ) is a function of and . Thus, the choice of , illustrates a tradeoff between the magnitude of the tracking error and the control effort applied. Also, the conclusions of the above theorem are true for the case of nonuniform degrees of mismatch and number of states among the subsystems, as is seen from the example below.</p><p>Example 4.1: We consider the example system given by (68) and (69). The parameters of the reference model (83) are given as</p><p>The reference signals to be tracked are .</p><p>Step 0: Using the same , , and as in Example 3.1, the virtual controls in this step are designed using (85) as For adaptation, we choose the adaptation gains , . The adaptation for given by (86), i.e.,</p><p>Step 1: Define . , , and are the same as in ( <ref type="formula">68</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">69</ref>) with and replaced by and , respectively. Since the degree of mismatch is one, the control Proof of Theorem 2.1: Let and be two outputs for which the isolated subsystem has relative degree . Let the degrees of mismatch with respect to the coordinate transformation corresponding to these two outputs be different. More precisely, , (without loss of generality , so that the degrees of mismatch as defined in <ref type="bibr">Definition</ref>  where is the degree of mismatch for the th subsystem. Hence, the representation of in the transformed coordinates is given by (116) which is the same as given in (3). This completes the proof of sufficiency.</p><p>Sandeep Jain (M'96) received the B.Tech. degree in electrical engineering from the Indian Institute of Technology, New Delhi, in 1990. He received the M.S. degrees in electrical engineering and mathematics in 1992 and 1993, respectively, and the Ph.D. degree in electrical engineering in 1995, all from Polytechnic University, New York.</p><p>He is currently working with Derivatives Ratings at Standard &amp; Poor's, New York, in the area of structured finance and derivative risk modeling and evaluation for financial institutions. He is also an Adjunct Faculty Member in the Financial Engineering Institute at Polytechnic University, where he teaches courses on derivative pricing and bond portfolio management. He has published more than 40 refereed journal and conference papers in the area of robust, adaptive, and decentralized control of nonlinear and large-scale systems and on applications to robotics, flexible structures, and power systems.</p><p>Dr. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized nonlinear adaptive feedback stabilization of large-scale interconnected systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hammamed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Radouane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEE Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized adaptive control of interconnected systems with reduced order models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ioannou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kokotović</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="412" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized adaptive control of interconnected systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ioannou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="1986-04">Apr. 1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized adaptive control: Structural conditions for stability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Gavel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Šiljak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="426" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust control design for interconnected systems with time-varying uncertainties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Leitmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1457" to="1477" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized adaptive controller design for large-scale systems with higher order uncertainties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1106" to="1118" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized adaptive control of robotic manipulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Gavel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hsia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robotics Automat</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robotics Automat</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987-05">May 1987</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1230" to="1235" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized control for interconnected uncertain systems: Extensions to higher-order uncertainties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1453" to="1468" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic design of adaptive controllers for feedback linearizable systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kanellakopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kokotović</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1241" to="1253" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive control of nonlinear systems with a triangular structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Seto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Annaswamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baillieul</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1411" to="1428" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-07">July 1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive nonlinear control without overparameterization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krstić</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kanellakopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kokotović</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Contr. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global transformations of nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hyperstability of Control Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Popov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust redesign of adaptive control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ioannou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kokotović</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automat. Contr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-03">Mar. 1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Rudin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Principles of Mathematical Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adaptive control of nonlinear and large-scale systems with applications to flexible manipulators and power systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-06">June 1995</date>
			<pubPlace>Brooklyn, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Polytechnic University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear control systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Isidori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lecture Notes in Control and Information</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
