<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Maximizing quadratic programs: extending Grothendieck&apos;s inequality</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Moses</forename><surname>Charikar</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Anthony</forename><surname>Wirth</surname></persName>
							<email>awirth@cs.princeton.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Princeton University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Princeton University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Maximizing quadratic programs: extending Grothendieck&apos;s inequality</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">10B59FE8C036E56409225348D66613D6</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T09:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper considers the following type of quadratic programming problem. Given an arbitrary matrix A, whose diagonal elements are zero, find x ∈ {-1, 1} n such that x T Ax is maximized. Our approximation algorithm for this problem uses the canonical semidefinite relaxation and returns a solution whose ratio to the optimum is in Ω(1/ log n). This quadratic programming problem can be seen as an extension to that of maximizing x T Ay (where y's components are also ±1). Grothendieck's inequality states that the ratio of the optimum value of the latter problem to the optimum of its canonical semidefinite relaxation is bounded below by a constant.</p><p>The study of this type of quadratic program arose from a desire to approximate the maximum correlation in correlation clustering. Nothing substantive was known about this problem; we present an Ω(1/ log n) approximation, based on our quadratic programming algorithm.</p><p>We can also guarantee that our quadratic programming algorithm returns a solution to the MAXCUT problem that has a significant advantage over a random assignment.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>In this paper we describe an approximation algorithm for a fairly general type of quadratic programming problem. Given matrix A, with null diagonal entries, maximize</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">n i=1 n j=1 a ij x i x j , s.t. x i ∈ {-1, 1} for all i ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>a problem we call MAXQP. We enforce the a ii = 0 condition because the terms a ii x i x i are equal to a ii and so are just additive constants. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> It is important to note that, for i = j, the a ij terms are arbitrary real values and are not restricted to being nonnegative. The goal is to return a solution that is at least some fraction α of the optimum of (1), OPT QP .</p><p>Our approximation problem is well-defined, for OPT QP is strictly positive unless A is the zero matrix (see <ref type="bibr">Lemma 4)</ref>.</p><p>There exists a body of work that has developed approximation algorithms for maximizing generic quadratic programs. However, they use a slightly different definition of approximation algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, partly because they do not assume that the a ii values are zero. The difficulty of allowing negative a ii values is that the ratio between the semidefinite relaxation and the integral optimum could become arbitrarily large. Therefore, rather than trying to achieve an objective value some fraction α of the optimum, their algorithms achieve relative accuracy µ if the objective value that is returned, val, satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">val -MIN MAX -MIN ≥ µ ,</formula><p>where MAX (MIN) is the maximum (minimum) value of all feasible solutions of the quadratic program. Nesterov <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> presented an SDP-based algorithm with relative accuracy π/2-1 for quadratic programming. Unfortunately these relative accuracy algorithms guarantee nothing in terms of the usual type of approximation factor. For example, a MAXQP instance corresponding to a complete unweighted MAX-CUT problem has MAX ∈ O(n), but MIN ∈ -Ω(n 2 ), and so a constant µ algorithm would not even guarantee returning a positive solution. We note in passing that Nesterov <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> described a 2/π approximation algorithm, in the usual sense, for instances in which A is positive semidefinite.</p><p>Our formulation of MAXQP was partly inspired by a problem in correlation clustering <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, which we detail below. Alon and Naor <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> provided further inspiration with their success in approximating the CUTNORM by trying to maximize m i=1 n j=1 a ij x i y j , s.t. x i , y j ∈ {-1, 1} for all i,j . <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> We can cast (2) as an instance of (1) by letting</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">z = x y and Â = 0 A 0 0 ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>so ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) is now z T Âz. Seeing that MAXQP is an extension of Alon and Naor's problem, we spend some time detailing the similarities and differences between them.</p><p>A quadratic program may be used to model a graph optimization problem in which a ij represents some property of the edge between i and j. One immediate observation from (3) is that if <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> represents the maximization of a function on a bipartite graph, then (1) represents the maximization of the same function on a complete graph.</p><p>Alon and Naor's problem has two key properties that ours does not. Firstly, different rounding techniques can be used for the {x i } and the {y j } in (2), and secondly, (2) has MAX = -MIN (simply replace y with -y in one of the extreme solutions). It turns out that these facts are crucial to their analysis.</p><p>Both (1) and ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) have canonical semidefinite relaxations, respectively,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">max i,j a ij v i • v j s.t. v i • v i = 1 for all i v i ∈ R n ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">max i,j a ij u i • v j s.t. u i • u i = v j • v j = 1 for all i, j u i , v j ∈ R n .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Unfortunately the term-by-term analysis that Goemans and Williamson <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> used in their 0.878 SDP-based approximation algorithm for MAXCUT-which is, in fact, a shifted special case of MAXQP-fails for both (4) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">5</ref>) because some of the terms might be negative. Nevertheless, Megretski <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> showed that the ratio of OPT QP to the optimum of the SDP relaxation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">4</ref>) is in Ω(1/ log n). <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> Grothendieck's inequality <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, a key result in functional analysis, states that the integrality gap between (5) and ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) is in fact a constant. The exact value of this constant is not known, but Alon and Naor converted proofs of the existence of the constant bound <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>-which are also bounds on its sizeinto approximation algorithms for (2).</p><p>Alon and Naor's first algorithm is deterministic: an explicit set of fourwise independent vectors in {-1, 1} n is constructed. They showed that there exists one such vector whose projections onto the optimal SDP solution vectors, truncated to lie in [-1, 1], give a fractional solution no less than 1/27 of optimum (see the beginning of Section 2 to see why a good fractional solution is sufficient). The second algorithm is simply the random hyperplane split of Goemans and Williamson, but with a more involved analysis. This technique treats the x and y variables identically, but the analysis cannot be applied to our problem because it relies on the ratio of MAX to -MIN being at least some constant. The third algorithm shows that there exist two new families of vectors, {u i } and {v j }, so that the expected value of every x i y j term obtained by splitting the u and v vectors with a random hyperplane is some common constant multiple of the corresponding u i • v j value. These u and v vectors are found by maximizing a semidefinite program. None of these techniques seems to apply directly to MAXQP, though we adapt some of the ideas.</p><p>Correlation clustering <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, which we also referred to as clustering with qualitative information in earlier work <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, is a relatively new problem. We are provided with pairwise judgments of the similarity of n data items. In the simplest version of the problem there are three possible inputs for each pair: similar (aka positive), dissimilar (aka negative), or no judgment. We refer to an instance in which a judgment is given for every pair as complete, otherwise it is a general instance.</p><p>In the original paper of Bansal, Blum and Chawla <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, the aim was to partition the items into clusters so that the number of pairs in agreement with the judgments would be maximized (MAXAGREE). A pair is called an agreement if it is a positive pair within one cluster or a negative pair across two distinct clusters. In like manner, we might want to minimize the number of disagreements (MINDIS-AGREE), where a disagreement is a positive pair across two different clusters or a negative pair in one cluster. These two problems are equivalent from an optimization point of view, but rather different from an approximation point of view. For general instances, there exist constant factor algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref> for MAXAGREE, but MINDISAGREE is as hard as the minimum multicut problem and (consequently) only O(log n) algorithms are known <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</p><p>Bansal, Blum and Chawla <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> propose the open problem of maximizing the correlation in correlation clustering (MAXCORR). The correlation is the difference between the number of agreements and the number of disagreements. Their only observation was that the optimal value of this quantity is always in Ω(n) for a complete instance; no nontrivial approximation guarantees were known for MAX-CORR. Based on our approximation algorithm for MAXQP, we obtain an algorithm for MAXCORR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1.">Our results</head><p>Our algorithm for MAXQP is the first approximation algorithm, in the usual sense, for maximizing a generic quadratic program. The algorithm uses a standard semidefinite relaxation <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, bears some similarity to the first algorithm of Alon and Naor <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, and has approximation factor in Ω(1/ log n). Our rounding procedure does not simply assign ±1 values based on a random hyperplane cut of the vectors, but takes into account the sizes of the projections of a random vector onto the solution vectors. If necessary, these projections are truncated to lie in the [-1, 1] interval; from these truncated values an integral solution is obtained using randomized rounding.</p><p>A random assignment of items in a MAXCUT instance will on average result in a cut of 1/2 of the total weight of edges. We say that a cut has gain δ if a 1/2 + δ fraction of the total weight of edges lie across the cut. The gain is analogous to the idea of the advantage over a random assignment <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Our MAXQP algorithm provides an Ω(1/ log(1/δ)) approximation for the optimal MAXCUT gain δ. Since MAXCUT is a shifted special case of MAXQP, it is not difficult to show that it is NP-hard to obtain an approximation algorithm for MAXQP with factor higher than 11/13.</p><p>The MAXCORR problem restricted to two clusters is a special case of MAXQP, in which a ij is 1 for each positive pair ij and a ij is -1 for each negative pair ij. We show that taking the better of the singleton-clusters solution and the best two-cluster solution provides a 1/3 approximation for the general MAXCORR problem. Therefore, we obtain an Ω(1/ log n) approximation for MAXCORR, the first (nontrivial) approximation algorithm known.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2.">Organization</head><p>We present our approximation algorithm for MAXQP in Section 2. Then in Section 3 we explore the relationship between MAXCUT and quadratic programming, and provide some further intuition for our approximation algorithm. In Section 4 we show how our algorithm can be applied to the MAXCORR problem. Finally, we present some open problems in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Maximizing quadratic programs</head><p>We start by showing that the optimum value of MAXQP, modified so that the variables are allowed to take any value in the range [-1, 1], is no larger than that of the original problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Consider the following randomized rounding technique for some fractional solution y ∈ [-1, 1] n :</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">x i = -1, with probability 1-yi 2 +1, with probability 1+yi 2 ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where each x i is rounded independently of the others. A simple calculation shows that, for i = j, E[x i x j ] = y i y j ; since the a ii terms are zero, the expected objective value of the integral solution equals that of the fractional solution. So, to the approximation algorithm. We first solve the semidefinite relaxation (4) of the quadratic program in polynomial time, up to arbitrary precision. We will then round the SDP vector solution {v i } to a fractional solution y. It may be that some y i values fall outside the range [-1, 1]; if so, we will truncate them to ±1. We show that this happens so rarely that the truncation does not alter the expected value of the solution significantly. Finally, we will use the rounding technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> in the previous paragraph to obtain a {-1, 1} solution x. ApproxMaxQP 1. Obtain an optimal solution {v i } to the SDP (4). 2. Create vector r in which the r i are drawn independently from the unit Normal distribution. 3. Let z i = v i • r/T , where T &gt; 0 will be specified later.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">If |z</head><formula xml:id="formula_6">i | &gt; 1, then y i = z i /|z i |, otherwise y i = z i .</formula><p>5. Obtain x i from y i using rounding procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>.</p><p>The solution x is clearly in {-1, 1} n , and it was obtained in polynomial time, so the remainder of this section will show:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theorem 1</head><p>The ratio of the expected value of the solution x returned by ApproxMaxQP to the maximum value of the quadratic program <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">is in Ω(1/ log n), if T = √ 4 log n. Lemma 1 The expected value of z i z j is v i • v j /T 2 .</formula><p>Proof: Since the distribution of the r vector is spherically symmetric, we can assume that v i = e 1 and v j = ae 1 + be 2 . Therefore T z i = v i • r = r 1 and T z j = v j • r = ar 1 + br 2 . Hence</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">T 2 E[z i z j ] = aE[r 2 1 ] + bE[r 1 r 2 ] = aVar[r 1 ] + bE[r 1 ]E[r 2 ] = a = v i • v j .</formula><p>If we were lucky and every |z i | were at most 1, then we would have a 1/T 2 approximation, since the optimum value of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">4</ref>) is at least the optimum of (1). Since this might not happen, we need to analyze the truncated solution y. We show that the expected value of ∆ ij = z i z j -y i y j is small in magnitude.</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Lemma 2 |E[∆ ij ]| is less than 8e -T 2 /2 .</formula><p>Proof: Let us consider the expected value of |∆ ij | on various regions (of r). We assume that n is sufficiently large that T ≥ 1. On the region S = {r :</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">|z i | ≤ 1, |z j | ≤ 1}, y i = z i and y j = z j , so E S [∆ ij ] = 0.</formula><p>Now, due to rotational symmetry, we may again assume that v i = e 1 and v j = ae 1 + be 2 . So the probability that r lies in the region B = {r :</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">z i &gt; 1} is Pr[r 1 &gt; T ] = 1 -Φ(T )</formula><p>, where Φ is the cdf for the Normal distribution. Therefore,</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">E B [|y i y j |] ≤ E B [1] = Pr[r ∈ B] = 1 -Φ(T ) .<label>(7)</label></formula><p>Furthermore,</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">E B [T 2 |z i z j |] = +∞ -∞ +∞ T |s(as + bt)| 1 2π e -s 2 /2 e -t 2 /2 ds dt . (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">)</formula><p>Let us consider each term of (8) one at a time,</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">∞ T s 2 e -s 2 /2 ds = -se -s 2 /2 ∞ T + ∞ T e -s 2 /2 ds = T e -T 2 /2 + √ 2π(1 -Φ(T )) .</formula><p>Also,</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">∞ T |s|e -s 2 /2 ds = e -T 2 /2 and +∞ -∞ |t|e -t 2 /2 dt = 2 .</formula><p>Putting it all together, we see that</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">E B [T 2 |z i z j |] ≤ |a|T √ 2π + |b| π e -T 2 /2 + |a|(1 -Φ(T )) &lt; T e -T 2 /2 + (1 -Φ(T )),<label>(9)</label></formula><p>as |a|, |b| ≤ 1. Since T ≥ 1, combining ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">7</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_17">9</ref>), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">E B [|∆ ij |] ≤ E B [|z i z j |+|y i y j |] &lt; e -T 2 /2 T +2(1-Φ(T )) ,</formula><p>where the first inequality is merely the triangle inequality. By symmetry, we will have the same result on the region {r : z i &lt; -1}. As there was nothing special about i, the same bound also applies for the regions {r : z j &gt; 1} and {r : z j &lt; -1}. The union of these four regions is the complement of the set S. Since the function |∆ ij | is nonnegative, its expectation on S is less than</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">4 T e -T 2 /2 + 8(1 -Φ(T )) . (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">) But E S [∆ ij ] is 0, so (10) is a bound on E[|∆ ij |], and hence on |E[∆ ij ]|.</formula><p>We can bound the second term of (10) by</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">4 ∞ T te -t 2 /2 dt = 4e -T 2 /2 , as T ≥ 1. Therefore, |E[∆ ij ]| &lt; 8e -T 2 /2 .</formula><p>We now show that we are close to obtaining an Ω(1/ log n) approximation. Let OPT SDP stand for the optimum value of (4).</p><p>Lemma 3</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">E[ i,j a ij y i y j ] &gt; OPT SDP T 2 -8e -T 2 /2 i,j |a ij | Proof: E[ i,j a ij y i y j ] = E[ i,j a ij z i z j ] + E[ i,j a ij (-∆ ij )]</formula><p>From Lemma 1, we know that the first term of the right hand side is OPT SDP /T 2 . The second term is</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">-E[ i,j a ij ∆ ij ] = - i,j a ij E[∆ ij ] ≥ - i,j a ij E[∆ ij ] ≥ - i,j |a ij ||E[∆ ij ]| ,</formula><p>which Lemma 2 proves is greater than -8e -T 2 /2 i,j |a ij |.</p><p>The obvious next step is to show that this error term is insignificant. Recall that OPT QP stands for the optimum value of (1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 4</head><formula xml:id="formula_24">OPT QP ≥ 1 n • i,j |a ij |</formula><p>Proof: Consider constructing a random matching on an nvertex complete graph in the following way. Select an edge uniformly at random, remove the endpoints from the graph, and repeat. It is easy to show that the probability of an edge being included in the matching is 1/(n -1) if n is even and 1/n if n is odd. Now, if we assign to each edge the weight |a ij |, then there exists some matching on the n vertices of total weight at least i,j |a ij |/n (the expected value under this random construction). Given a matching, we randomly construct a vector x ∈ {-1, 1} n whose expected QP objective value is the same as the matching weight. For each edge ij in the matching, we independently set x i to ±1 uniformly at random; we let x j equal x i if and only if a ij is nonnegative. The unmatched vertex, if n is odd, is assigned a value independently. For each matched pair ij we score |a ij |, for every other pair the expected score is 0, hence the same total as the matching. Therefore OPT QP is at least i,j |a ij |/n.</p><p>We can now prove Theorem 1.</p><p>Proof: Substituting Lemma 4 into the statement of Lemma 3, with T = √ 4 log n, we see that</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">E[ i,j a ij y i y j ] &gt; OPT QP [ 1 4 log n -8n -2 • n] ,</formula><p>which is in Ω(OPT QP / log n). Finally, note that</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">E[ i,j a ij x i x j ] = E[E[ i,j a ij x i x j | y]] = E[ i,j</formula><p>a ij y i y j ].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Observations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">The relationship with MAXCUT</head><p>Maximizing the gain in the MAXCUT problem can easily be formulated as a quadratic program. Let w stand for the total weight of edges in a MAXCUT instance and δ stand for the gain of the optimal cut-recall that a cut of size w(1/2 + δ) has gain δ. The Goemans-Williamson algorithm guarantees only that its solution will have a cut of at least w(0.439 + 0.878δ), which may have no gain at all. Zwick's outward rotations method <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> or Feige and Langberg's RP R 2 algorithm for LIGHTMAXCUT <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> might approximate the gain well. In fact, our algorithm is an instantiation of Feige and Langberg's rounding scheme, using an s-linear function. These authors do not, however, present any theoretical analysis that applies to our setting.</p><p>We can express MAXCUT as a special case of quadratic programming, by setting A as follows. For all pairs i &lt; j for which there exists an edge of weight w ij , let a ij = -w ij ; for all other values of i and j, let a ij = 0. For a given solution x ∈ {-1, 1} n , the value of the quadratic program q(x), the value of the cut k(x) and the value of its gain g(x), satisfy q(x) = 2k(x) -w = 2w g(x).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 5 If δ * is the optimum gain of a MAXCUT instance, ApproxMaxQP returns a solution whose gain is in</head><formula xml:id="formula_27">Ω δ * log(1/δ * )</formula><p>.</p><p>Proof: Lemma 3 says that ApproxMaxQP will return a solution x for which q(x) is at least</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">OPT QP T 2 -8e -T 2 /2 w ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>as w is the sum of the |a ij | terms. By definition, OPT QP = 2wδ * , so if we set T = 32 log(1/δ * ) then it is not hard to show that ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_28">11</ref>) is greater than</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">OPT QP 64 log(1/δ * )</formula><p>, for all δ * ≤ 1/2 .</p><p>Since the gain, g(x), is a constant multiple of q(x), the result follows.</p><p>Just as we have a reduction to obtain an approximation algorithm for maximizing the gain of a cut, we can also obtain a hardness result for MAXQP from one for MAXCUT.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 6</head><p>It is NP-hard to approximate MAXQP within factor 11/13 + ε.</p><p>Proof: Let α now stand for the hardness factor for MAX-CUT. Since OPT QP = 2OPT CUT -w, distinguishing between the cases OPT CUT ≥ k and OPT CUT &lt; αk is equivalent to distinguishing between OPT QP ≥ 2k -w and OPT QP ≤ 2αk -w. The ratio of these two bounds on</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">OPT QP is 2αk -w 2k -w = α + w α -1 2k -w .</formula><p>The lemma follows from the 16/17 + ε hardness result for MAXCUT <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>, which holds for k = 17w/21.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Correlated random variables and distributions on cuts</head><p>We make some general observations about rounding solutions to the MAXQP SDP relaxation and point out some interesting connections to generating {-1, 1} random variables with given correlations. The value of the SDP solution is i,j a ij v i • v j . Suppose we could generate {-1, 1} random variables X i such that E[X i X j ] = Cv i • v j for all i, j; this would immediately lead to a C-approximation algorithm. In fact, Alon and Naor's third algorithm (based on Krivine's proof) is exactly of this form: they transform the vectors u i , v j to obtain new vectors u i , v j and apply random hyperplane rounding to these new vectors to get a distribution on {-1, 1} random variables with the desired property. We reiterate that, in doing this, they crucially use the fact that they can apply one transformation for the {u i } and a another one for the {v j }; hence this technique does not apply to rounding MAXQP.</p><p>One might wonder whether the existence of an appropriate distribution on {-1, 1} random variables is a lucky coincidence. In fact we demonstrate (the possibly surprising fact) that such a distribution always exists.</p><p>In order to do this, we write an LP formulation for the maximum gap of the SDP for a fixed vector solution. Given a set of vectors v i produced by an optimal SDP solution, consider the problem of finding the A matrix that maximizes the gap between OPT SDP and OPT QP . The problem can be formulated as an LP as follows (note that the a ij are variables here).</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">min c s.t. ij a ij v i • v j = 1 ij a ij x i x j ≤ c for all x ∈ {-1, 1} n</formula><p>The accompanying dual program, below, has one p x variable for every possible setting of x ∈ {-1, 1} n . max b s.t.</p><p>x p x = 1</p><p>x p x x i x j = b v i • v j for all i, j These p x values specify a probability distribution on the x i s. We know that the primal LP has optimal value no lower than the gap of the SDP for MAXQP. By duality, there exists a distribution on {-1, 1} random variables such that E[x i x j ] = b v i • v j , where b, which could be a function of n, is at least the worst case gap of the SDP for MAXQP.</p><p>Our analysis in Section 2 shows that the gap of the MAXQP SDP is in Ω(1/ log n), which has the following interesting interpretation. Given a positive semidefinite matrix K, it is well known that there exist correlated normal random variables X i such that E[X i X j ] = k ij . What if you wanted {-1, 1} random variables instead? Our results show that if we scale the (off-diagonal) entries of the correlation matrix by C ∈ O(1/ log n), then we can guarantee the existence of {-1, 1} random variables with the appropriate correlations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Maximizing correlation in correlation clustering</head><p>We now turn to the correlation clustering application. A series of papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref> resolved many of the issues related to the MAXAGREE and MINDISAGREE problems. Recall that in the MAXCORR problem the aim is to maximize the difference between the number of agreements and disagreements. Until now, no nontrivial approximation algorithm was known for MAXCORR, but we demonstrate that the Ω(1/ log n) approximation for MAXQP can be used to obtain an algorithm with the same asymptotic factor for MAXCORR.</p><p>Let corr(κ) stand for the correlation of clustering κ. There is only one way of placing each item into a singleton cluster: call this clustering κ n and let OPT n = corr(κ n ). In contrast, there are several ways of splitting the items into two clusters, but we let κ OPT 2 stand for one of those with maximal correlation OPT 2 . Finally, κ OPT is some partitioning that has maximum correlation OPT.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 7</head><p>OPT n + 2OPT 2 ≥ OPT .</p><p>Proof: Let the four quantities, w + , a + , w -and a -, stand for the numbers of positive (negative) pairs within (across) clusters in our optimal solution κ OPT . By definition,</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">OPT = w + -a + -w -+ a -.</formula><p>If we split everything up into singletons, we see that</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">OPT n = -w + -a + + w -+ a -.</formula><p>Although we cannot calculate OPT 2 , we can at least provide a lower bound for it. Consider constructing a partitioning by randomly assigning each cluster in κ OPT to one of two new superclusters. The expected correlation of the result of this random procedure is a lower bound for OPT 2 .</p><p>All within-cluster pairs remain within-cluster pairs. With probability 1/2 each across-cluster pair becomes a withincluster pair; consequently its contribution to the expected correlation is zero, and so OPT 2 ≥ w + -w -. We now find that</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">OPT n + 2OPT 2 ≥ w + -a + -w -+ a -= OPT .</formula><p>As mentioned in the introduction, MAXCORR restricted to two clusters is a special case of MAXQP. So Lemma 7 shows that a reasonable approximation to OPT 2 will provide a reasonable approximation algorithm for MAXCORR. This suggests the following algorithm: ApproxMaxCorr 1. Construct the matrix A thus: if i &lt; j and pair ij is similar then a ij = 1, if i &lt; j and pair ij is dissimilar then a ij = -1; otherwise a ij = 0. Theorem 1 tells us that the approximation factor of Ap-proxMaxQP is in Ω(1/ log n), so from Lemma 8 we conclude:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Execute</head><p>Theorem 2 ApproxMaxCorr is an approximation algorithm for MAXCORR with factor in Ω(1/ log n).</p><p>Like the MAXQP problem, this approximation factor for MAXCORR is a long way from the best-known hardness of approximation result.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 9</head><p>It is NP-hard to approximate MAXCORR within a factor of 43/44 + ε.</p><p>Proof: An immediate consequence of our proof of the hardness of approximating MAXAGREE (Theorem 9 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Open problems</head><p>Although Bellare and Rogaway <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> prove various strong inapproximability results for quadratic and polynomial programming, they do not apply to our formulation of MAXQP. The most interesting open problem suggested by our results is whether a constant factor approximation for MAXQP is possible. Certainly, it will not involve the SDP (4), as Alon et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> have recently shown that the integrality gap is in O(1/ log n). In proving this fact, they work with a variant of the dual characterization discussed in Section 3.2.</p><p>It would be interesting to prove hardness results for the problem of maximizing the gain of MAXCUT (the advantage over a random assignment); the hardness results of Håstad and Venkatesh <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> do not apply to this problem. In light of our Ω(log(1/δ)) approximation, obtaining an o(1) hardness of approximation result would be quite challenging.</p><p>Finally, Grothendieck's inequality is a fundamental tool in functional analysis, with several applications. It would be interesting to investigate whether our extension has any functional analysis interpretations and consequences.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ApproxMaxQP on A and obtain solution x. 3. Form partitioning κ 2 by assigning item i to cluster one ifx i = -1 and to cluster two if x i = 1. 4. Calculate OPT n and corr(κ 2 ) and return the clustering with higher correlation. It is easy to verify that maximizing x T Ax subject to |x i | = 1 is equivalent to MAXCORR restricted to just two clusters, both in terms of feasible solutions and objective values. Clearly, max{OPT</figDesc><table><row><cell>≥</cell><cell>α 2 + α α 2 + α</cell><cell>OPT n + OPT ,</cell><cell>2α 2 + α</cell><cell>OPT 2</cell></row><row><cell>by Lemma 7.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p>Lemma 8</p>ApproxMaxCorr achieves an approximation of α/(2 + α), where α is the approximation factor of Approx-MaxQP.</p>Proof: n , corr(κ 2 )} ≥ t OPT n + (1 -t) corr(κ 2 ) ≥ t OPT n + (1 -t) α OPT 2 ,</p>for all t ∈ [0, 1]. If we let t = α/(2 + α), then max{OPT n , corr(κ 2 )} ≥</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Actually it would not harm any of our arguments if we were to allow the a ii values to be nonnegative, but the exposition is simpler if we just ignore these terms.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Our approximation algorithm in Section 2 is an algorithmic version of Megretski's proof.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors would like to thank Noga Alon and Assaf Naor for the reference to Megretski's work and other feedback, Venkatesan Guruswami for an improvement to the hardness of approximation factor for MAXQP, and Amit Chakrabarti, Michael Dinitz, Subhash Khot, Konstantin Makarychev, and Yury Makarychev for several stimulating discussions.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>. Supported by NSF ITR grant CCR-0205594, DOE Early Career Principal Investigator award DE-FG02-02ER25540, NSF CAREER award CCR-0237113 and an Alfred P. Sloan Fellowship. Supported by a Gordon Wu Fellowship and NSF ITR grant CCR-0205594.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quadratic forms on graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Alon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Makarychev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Makarychev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Naor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximating the cut-norm via Grothendieck&apos;s inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Alon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Naor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 36th STOC</title>
		<meeting>of 36th STOC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="80" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bansal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Blum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chawla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 43rd FOCS</title>
		<meeting>43rd FOCS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="247" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bansal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Blum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chawla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Correlation clustering. Machine Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="113" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The complexity of approximating a nonlinear program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bellare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rogaway</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Programming B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering with qualitative information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Charikar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Guruswami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wirth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 44th FOCS</title>
		<meeting>of 44th FOCS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="524" to="533" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation clustering with partial information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Demaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Immorlica</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 6th APPROX</title>
		<meeting>of 6th APPROX</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation clustering-minimizing disagreements on arbitrary weighted graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Emanuel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fiat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 11th ESA</title>
		<meeting>of 11th ESA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="220" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The RP R 2 rounding technique for semidefinite programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Feige</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Langberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 28th ICALP</title>
		<meeting>of 28th ICALP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="224" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved approximation algorithms for maximum cut and satisfiability problems using semidefinite progamming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goemans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1115" to="1145" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Résumé de la théorie métrique des produits tensoriels topologiques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Grothendieck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bol. Soc. Mat. Sao Paulo</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="1953">1953</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some optimal inapproximability results</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Håstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="798" to="859" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the advantage over a random assignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Håstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Venkatesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 34th STOC</title>
		<meeting>of 34th STOC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="52" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sur la constante de Grothendieck</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krivine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C. R. Acad. Sci. Paris Ser. A-B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="446" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relaxation of quadratic programs in operator theory and system analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Megretski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Systems, Approximation, Singular Integral Operators, and Related Topics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bordeaux; Birkhäuser, Basel</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000. 2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="392" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semidefinite relaxation and nonconvex quadratic optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Nesterov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Optimization Methods and Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A proof of the Grothendieck inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Israel J. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="276" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation Clustering: Maximizing agreements via semidefinite programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Swamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 15th SODA</title>
		<meeting>of 15th SODA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="520" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gadgets, approximation, and linear programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trevisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sorkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sudan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Comp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2074" to="2097" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outward rotations: A tool for rounding solutions of semidefinite programming relaxations, with applications to max cut and other problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Zwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 31st STOC</title>
		<meeting>of 31st STOC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="687" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
