<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Research on Intelligent on-line Insulation Monitoring Device of Ship&apos;s AC Power Grid</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xiang-Xin</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
							<email>chengxiangxin@sohu.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Maritime College of Shan Dong Jiaotong University Weihai</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Shuo</surname></persName>
							<email>wushuo84@163.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Maritime College of Shan Dong Jiaotong University Weihai</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Research on Intelligent on-line Insulation Monitoring Device of Ship&apos;s AC Power Grid</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/ISDEA.2010.175</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2022-12-25T13:06+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Ship power grid</term>
					<term>Short circuit</term>
					<term>Insulation resistance</term>
					<term>Insulation monitoring</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The insulation monitoring of ship power system is an important measure to remove faults and hidden troubles. Its condition concerns the security of power system and operation safety of ships. Conventional ship power system insulation monitoring is hard to accurately monitor the insulation resistance decreasing or precisely locate the grounding branch. It takes much time and energy to rule out the insulation failure. This paper introduces the intelligent on-line insulation monitoring device. Based on zero-sequence current detecting method, dual-frequency injection method and SCM control, it can accurately and efficiently monitor the ship power grid and guarantee the operation safety of ships.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>With the development of shipbuilding technology and the increasing tonnage of ship, the modern ship power system capacity has been continually growing.</p><p>Accordingly, its distribution network structure has become more complex and the power grids have become more complex and intensive. Under the harsh condition of high temperature, vibration, shock, oil mist, humidity, salt spray, fungus <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> , the ship power grid has brought a lot of influences to the ship's electrical insulation properties, which results in high incidence of power system insulation failure, thus frequently leads to terrible accidents, as minor as electrical equipment malfunction or damage, as major as fire, collision and sinking disaster. Limited by technical means, it has been difficult to monitor the state of complex branch insulation. Once the monitor failure happens, there is no other way to find out insulation failure points except manual operation, which not only affects operation by supply interruptions, but also hurts crew physical and mental health because of high labor intensity. Thus, the ship's power system insulation real-time monitoring has the extremely vital significance to the security and continuity of power supply system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ⅱ BRIEF INTRODUCTIONS OF THE SHIP POWER GRID</head><p>There are two types of ship power grid, AC power grid and DC power grid. The DC power grid is seldom used, thus will not be analyzed in this paper. Three-phase AC mainly used in the power system on ship has the following three forms: (1)AC three-phase three-wire insulated system (three-phase three-wire system); (2)AC three-phase four-wire system with neutral earthed (three-phase four-wire system); (3)three-wire system with neutral grounding (using the hull as the neutral wire loop).</p><p>What the ship power system regularly uses is AC three-phase insulated system <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> . One of the great advantages of this system is that when short circuit current to earth occurs on one phase it will not cause power outage, thus ensures the continuity and reliability of ship </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Dual-frequency injection method</head><p>Two different-frequency AC signals are injected into the AC power grid. When the power frequency interference is filtrated, the insulation resistance to the earth of each branch can accurately be calculated and the fault branch can be precisely located according to the measured signal current <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> . Dual-frequency injection method has a clear advantage in distinguishing faults with large single-phase insulation resistance or insulation failures existing in all three phases, and can eliminate the impact of grid-to-ground capacitance more effectively, but it is very complex.</p><p>Therefore, the practical device combining the advantages of zero-sequence current detecting method and dual-frequency injection method comprehensively distinguishes the fault branch. When ground fault occurs, the zero-sequence current detecting method should first be utilized to monitor each loaded-branch, and distinguish the fault branch; otherwise, the dual-frequency injection method should be used to locate the fault branch. The following describes the basic principle of dual-frequency injection method.</p><p>The sketch map of dual-frequency injection method is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1 (a)</ref>.</p><p>When power grid insulation failure occurs (such as the insulation resistance of branch i drops to R i ), the device will in turn send out two low-frequency sine-wave signals  </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">i 1 = U ab1 / R +j•2π•f 1 •C•U ab1<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">i 2 = U ab2 / R +j•2π•f 2 •C•U ab2<label>(2)</label></formula><p>In the formula: Insulation resistance values can be obtained by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>) and</p><p>(2):</p><p>(k =f 2 /f 1 )</p><p>In the formula: U ab1m : Amplitude of U ab1 U ab2m : Amplitude of U ab2 I 1m : Amplitude of i 1 I 2m : Amplitude of i 2</p><p>According to measuring the voltage values of U ab1 , U ab2 and the earth leakage current of every loaded branch i 1 , i 2 , which are all corresponding to the frequencies injected into the power grid f 1 , f 2 , the insulation resistance of every loaded branch against earth can be obtained through (3) thus the insulation fault branch can be distinguished. Digital filtering method is also used to eliminate the effect of power frequency in U ab1 , U ab2 and i 1 , i 2 .</p><p>Ⅴ SYSTEM CONFIGURATIONS <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> According to the principle mentioned above, the hardware block-diagram of monitoring device is designed, (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</p><p>When the zero-sequence current detecting method is used, Multiplexer controlled by single chip micyoco (SCM) system collects the power frequency leakage current data of every branch, after comparison with the preset value, the fault branch is distinguished. When the Dual-frequency injection method is used, SCM system gives instruction to the sine wave coder; the sine wave coder will generate a low-frequency sine wave signal f 1 .</p><p>By D/A converting, power amplifying and transformer's isolated boosting, the signal is injected into the power grid.</p><p>Both multiplexer and A / D converter are controlled by SCM system. First the power grid voltage to earth transformed by voltage measurement unit is collected, the leakage current (after amplifying) of every branch also is collected one by one, and then the leakage current i f1 of every branch corresponding to the low frequency f 1 and voltage U f1 is obtained by digital filtering. In the same  Therefore, this device should be widely used.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">2 1 2 2 2 2 2 1 2 2 1 1 ab m ab m m a b m m a bm U U K R K I U I U ⋅ ⋅ − = ⋅ ⋅ − ⋅<label>(3)</label></formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>power supply. Ⅲ INTELLIGENT INSULATION MONITORING DEVICE An advanced intelligent on-line insulation monitoring and warning device that can monitor the insulation and locate the faulty branch is installed in a ship power system. Its high measurement accuracy, accurate positioning and high automation determines its domestic leading level. The main characteristics are as follow: The core of this device consists of microprocessor systems. Highly automated, it has strong expanding function and communication function which makes sure data exchange with other integrated monitor panels. The hardware of insulation monitoring device is modularized according to functions and combined by functional module plug-ins, so the maintainability of the device is enhanced. Through real-time on-line measurement of operating ship power grid insulation resistance, the insulation monitoring device can not only locate the fault branch with decreased single-phase insulation resistance, but also locate the fault branches with decreased two-phase or three-phase insulation resistance and effectively overcome the adverse effects of the capacitance to earth on locating the fault branches. The software of insulation monitoring device also implement modular technology, when we need to improve the function of the device, modifying or adding the corresponding module can achieve the purpose of upgrading on the basis of the original device. Ⅳ THE PRINCIPLE OF LOCATING THE INSULATION FAULT BRANCH The device adopts comprehensive determination principle integrating zero-sequence current detecting method with dual-frequency injection method to detect and locate fault branch, and these two methods have respective advantages in the application scope and technical feasibility. A. Zero-sequence current detecting method Fault branch has two features. First, zero-sequence current of it is far greater than non-fault branch. Second, zero-sequence current of fault branch lags voltage by 90°w hile zero-sequence current of non-fault branch leads voltage by 90°. According to these, the fault branch can be located very precisely. Zero-sequence current method can distinguish single-phase-to-ground fault resistance, but it is difficult to locate the fault branch when insulation failures exist in all three phase or insulation fault resistance is higher.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>f 1 and f 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>to one phase of power grid and ship hull. For the insulation resistance against earth and the capacitive reactance against earth, the internal impedance of generator is negligible; the equivalent circuit can be obtained in Fig. 1 (b) shown. Because of the exist two</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Schematic diagram of dual-frequency injection method</figDesc><graphic url="image-8.png" coords="2,330.29,454.04,207.00,99.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>R: 1 : 1 i 2 :</head><label>112</label><figDesc>Branch insulation resistance value C: Equivalent distributed capacitance value of the branch f 1 , f 2 : Frequency value of the two low-frequency signals i Resulting earth leakage current by the alone action of signal source with the frequency value f Resulting earth leakage current by the alone action of signal source with the frequency value f 2 U ab1 : Resulting voltage-drop of the insulation resistance by the alone action of signal source with the frequency value f 1 ; U ab2 : Resulting voltage-drop of the insulation resistance by the alone action of signal source with the frequency value f 2 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Hardware block-diagram of monitoring device</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="978" xml:id="foot_0">-0-7695-4212-6/10 $26.00 © 2010 IEEE DOI 10.1109/ISDEA.2010.175</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1">Authorized licensed use limited to: Tsinghua University. Downloaded on February 28,2022 at 09:38:39 UTC from IEEE Xplore. Restrictions apply.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Authorized licensed use limited to: Tsinghua University. Downloaded on February 28,2022 at 09:38:39 UTC from IEEE Xplore. Restrictions apply.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Affect of Ship&apos;s Safe Navigate due to the Insulating property of Marine Network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bing-Kang</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JIANSU SHIP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Zhang Chun-Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Ship Electrics</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Dalian</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Dalian Maritime University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Research on Application of Double Frequency Principle to Insulation Fault Locating in earth Free AC System[J], ELECTRIC POWER AUTOMATION EQUIPMENT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Zhuang Jin-Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Xu Guo-Shun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Qi Lian-Suo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Chao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Design and Realization of Ship&apos;s Insulation Monitoring System</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cao Jian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Guo Jian-Ming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
