<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Physical-Layer Security for MISO Visible Light Communication Channels</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Student Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Ayman</forename><surname>Mostafa</surname></persName>
							<email>amostafa@ece.ubc.ca</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Senior Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Lutz</forename><surname>Lampe</surname></persName>
							<email>lampe@ece.ubc.ca</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<postCode>2014</postCode>
									<settlement>Sydney</settlement>
									<region>NSW, June</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of British Colombia</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V6T 1Z4</postCode>
									<settlement>Vancouver</settlement>
									<region>BC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Physical-Layer Security for MISO Visible Light Communication Channels</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D0B7A26B0048674D2161B490AA579075</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/JSAC.2015.2432513</idno>
					<note type="submission">This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSAC.2015.2432513, IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications Manuscript received May 28, 2014; revised November 10, 2014 and March 19, 2015; accepted April 10, 2015. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSAC.2015.2432513, IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T12:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Visible light communication</term>
					<term>intensity modulation</term>
					<term>amplitude constraint</term>
					<term>physical-layer security</term>
					<term>secrecy capacity bounds</term>
					<term>MISO wiretap VLC channel</term>
					<term>robust beamforming</term>
					<term>worst-case secrecy rate</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper considers improving the confidentiality of visible light communication (VLC) links within the framework of physical-layer security. We study a VLC scenario with one transmitter, one legitimate receiver, and one eavesdropper. The transmitter has multiple light sources, while the legitimate and unauthorized receivers have a single photodetector, each. We characterize secrecy rates achievable via transmit beamforming over the multiple-input, single-output (MISO) VLC wiretap channel. For VLC systems, intensity modulation (IM) via lightemitting diodes (LEDs) is the most practical transmission scheme. Because of the limited dynamic range of typical LEDs, the modulating signal must satisfy certain amplitude constraints. Hence, we begin with deriving lower and upper bounds on the secrecy capacity of the scalar Gaussian wiretap channel subject to amplitude constraints. Then, we utilize beamforming to obtain a closed-form secrecy rate expression for the MISO wiretap channel. Finally, we propose a robust beamforming scheme to consider the scenario wherein information about the eavesdropper's channel is imperfect due to location uncertainty. A typical application of the proposed scheme is to secure the communication link when the eavesdropper is expected to exist within a specified area. The performance is measured in terms of the worst-case secrecy rate guaranteed under all admissible realizations of the eavesdropper's channel.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>due to line-of-sight (LoS) propagation and confinement of light waves by opaque surfaces, VLC links cause limited or no internetwork interference. Such advantages qualify VLC links for realizing small-size cells, often referred to as "atto-cells", in fifth generation (5G) networks with coverage ranges on the order of a few meters.</p><p>With the unprecedented increase in traffic volumes over wireless networks, data privacy and confidentiality are becoming a major concern for users as well as network administrators. Typical security mechanisms are implemented at upper layers of the network stack via access control, password protection, and end-to-end encryption. Such schemes are deemed to be secure as long as the storage capacity and computational power of potential eavesdroppers remain within certain limits. During the past few years, however, physical-layer security has emerged as a promising research area to complement conventional encryption techniques and provide a first line of defense against eavesdropping attacks. Physical-layer security refers to the techniques which exploit the channel characteristics in order to hide information from unauthorized receivers, without reliance on upper-layer encryption <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. The fundamental idea behind physical-layer security is to sacrifice a fraction of the communication rate, that otherwise would be used for data transmission, in order to confuse potential eavesdroppers and diminish their capability to infer information, via carefullydesigned signaling and/or coding schemes.</p><p>The framework of information-theoretic security was pioneered by Shannon <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> who proposed a cipher system to achieve perfect secrecy over noiseless channels intercepted by unauthorized users. Almost two decades later, Wyner <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> considered secure transmission over noisy channels via the wiretap channel model. In addition, he proposed a fundamental information-theoretic security measure, termed as the secrecy capacity. Wyner proved that the secrecy capacity is nonzero as long as the eavesdropper's channel is degraded with respect to (w.r.t.) the receiver's channel, regardless of the decoding technology or computational power available to the eavesdropper.</p><p>Motivated by Wyner's work, information theoreticians considered characterizing the secrecy performance of a variety of channel models. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, the secrecy capacity of the scalar, i.e., single-input, single-output (SISO), Gaussian wiretap channel was obtained as the difference between the channel capacities of the source-destination and source-eavesdropper links. A single-letter characterization of the secrecy capacity of the non-degraded wiretap channel was obtained by Csiszár and Körner in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. However, their expression involves stochastic mapping and maximization over an auxiliary random variable whose optimum choice is not straightforward. Therefore, it does not provide much help in obtaining analytical expressions for the secrecy capacity of multiple-antenna systems. The secrecy capacity of the multiple-input, multiple-output (MIMO) Gaussian wiretap channel was considered in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. For the special case of multiple-input, single-output (MISO) channels, it was shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> that beamforming is a secrecy capacity-achieving strategy, and zero-forcing is optimum at asymptotically high signal-to-noise ratio (SNR).</p><p>Despite LoS propagation and better signal confinement, compared to RF channels, the VLC channel, without optical fibers or any sort of wave-guiding, is still of broadcast nature. That makes VLC links inherently susceptible to eavesdropping by unintended or unauthorized users having access to the physical area illuminated by the data transmitters. Typical scenarios include public areas such as classrooms, meeting rooms, libraries, shopping malls, and aircrafts, to name a few.</p><p>Unlike RF channels, conventionally modelled as a Gaussian channel with average power constraint, the most practical communication scheme for VLC systems is intensity modulation (IM) along with direct detection (DD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Typical LEDs exhibit nonlinear current-light characteristics which can be partially compensated via pre-distorters, right before the LED, to mitigate harmonic distortion <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. However, the dynamic range of the LED is inherently limited. Therefore, the modulating signal must satisfy certain amplitude constraints to avoid clipping distortion. Hence, IM/DD channels are typically modelled with amplitude constraints imposed on the channel input, rather than conventional average power constraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</p><p>Compared to the massive body of literature on the average power-constrained Gaussian wiretap channels, literature on the information-theoretic secrecy performance of amplitudeconstrained wiretap channels is rather scarce. In his seminal paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr">Section 26]</ref>, Shannon referred to the difficulty of obtaining an analytical expression for the capacity of peaklimited channels. Instead, he derived a loose lower bound and an asymptotic upper bound which is valid for high peak SNR. Out of his Ph.D. work <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, Smith came up with the rather surprising result that the capacity-achieving distribution for the amplitude-constrained Gaussian channel is discrete with a finite number of mass points. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, Arimoto proposed an iterative numerical algorithm to compute the capacity of arbitrary discrete memoryless channels. Closed-form lower and upper bounds on the capacity of amplitude-constrained Gaussian channels were derived in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, Ozel et al. followed the approach devised in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and proved that the secrecy capacity-achieving distribution for the amplitude-constrained Gaussian wiretap channel is discrete with finite support. To the best of our knowledge, no work in the literature, other than <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, has considered the secrecy performance of amplitudeconstrained Gaussian wiretap channels.</p><p>In this paper, we consider enhancing the confidentiality of VLC links via physical-layer security techniques. In particular, we are interested in characterizing the secrecy rates achievable in a typical VLC scenario consisting of one transmitter, one legitimate receiver, and one eavesdropper, as illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. We begin with deriving lower and upper bounds on the secrecy capacity of the amplitude-constrained Gaussian wiretap channel. Then, we leverage beamforming to derive a closed-form lower bound on the secrecy capacity of the MISO channel. We also characterize secrecy rates achievable via zero-forcing beamformers. Finally, we consider a VLC scenario wherein the eavesdropper is expected to exist within a specified physical area. Thus, the eavesdropper's channel information is not perfectly known to the transmitter. The design problem is to devise a robust beamforming scheme which improves the worst-case secrecy rate guaranteed under all admissible channel realizations of the eavesdropper's link.</p><p>Instead of solving a difficult max-min worst-case maximization problem, we propose a suboptimal, but essentially simple, beamforming scheme based on first-order Taylor's approximation of the LEDs emission pattern. Numerical results show the superior performance of the robust scheme in terms of worstcase secrecy rates. The remainder of the paper is organized as follows. We state the adopted notation in Section II-A, describe the VLC channel model in Section II-B, recall the relevant definitions of beamforming and zero-forcing in Section II-C, and discuss the system model in Section II-D. Lower and upper bounds on the secrecy capacity of the amplitude-constrained Gaussian wiretap channel are provided in Section III-A, while we derive a secrecy rate expression for the MISO case in Section III-B. In Section IV, we formulate the worst-case secrecy rate maximization problem and devise the robust beamforming scheme. Numerical results obtained by simulating a typical VLC scenario are presented in Section V. Finally, we provide concluding remarks in Section VI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PRELIMINARIES A. Notation</head><p>The following notation is adopted throughout the paper. We refer to the transmitter, legitimate receiver, and eavesdropper as "Alice", "Bob", and "Eve", respectively. The set of ndimensional, real-valued numbers is denoted by R n , and the set of n-dimensional, non-negative, real-valued numbers is denoted by R n + . Bold characters denote column vectors, and vector transposition is denoted by the superscript {•} T . The all-ones column vector is denoted by 1, and its dimension will be clear from the context. The curled inequality symbol </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. The VLC Channel Model</head><p>We consider a DC-biased pulse-amplitude modulation (PAM) VLC scheme whose simplified block diagram is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The transmit element is an illumination LED driven by a fixed bias current I DC ∈ R + . The DC bias sets the average radiated optical power and, consequently, adjusts the illumination level. The data signal x(t) ∈ R, t = 1, 2, 3, • • • , is a zero-mean current signal superimposed on I DC , via, e.g., a bias-T circuit, to imperceptibly modulate the instantaneous optical power P TX (t) emitted from the LED. Since E{X(t)} = 0, the data signal does not contribute to the average optical power and, therefore, it does not affect the illumination level. In order to maintain linear currentlight conversion and avoid clipping distortion, the total current I DC +x(t) must be constrained within some range I DC ±αI DC , where α ∈ [0, 1] is termed as the modulation index. Thus, x(t) must satisfy the amplitude constraint |x(t)| ≤ A ∀t, where A = αI DC .</p><p>Then, using an appropriate pre-distorter <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, the electrooptical conversion can be modeled as P TX (t) = η (I DC + x(t)) where η (W/A) is the current-to-light conversion efficiency of the LED. The optical power collected by the receiver is given by P RX (t) = GP TX (t) where G &lt; 1 is the path gain. A PD of responsivity R (A/W) converts the incident optical power into a proportional current RP RX (t). Then, the DC bias is removed, and the signal is amplified via a transimpedance amplifier of gain T (V/A) to produce a voltage signal y(t) ∈ R, which is a scaled, but noisy, version of the transmitted signal x(t). Dominant noise sources are the thermal noise in the receiver electronic circuits, i.e., pre-amplifier noise, and shot noise due to ambient illumination from sunlight and/or other light sources. Both noise processes are well-modelled as signal-independent, zero-mean, additive, white Gaussian noise (AWGN) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>.</p><p>Therefore, the VLC channel in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> can be modelled as x 1 (t)</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">y(t) = hx(t) + w(t),<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">I DC I DC I DC y(t) s(t) w N x 2 (t)</formula><p>x N (t) where h = ηGRT , h ∈ R + , is the channel gain and W (t) ∼ N 0, σ 2 is the noise process.</p><p>Notice that the channel model in (1) considers only LoS propagation and ignores reflections from surrounding surfaces. Such a model is valid for most indoor scenarios wherein light fixtures are attached to the ceiling and facing down, making reflections significantly weaker than LoS components <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>.</p><p>Assuming an LED with a generalized Lambertian emission pattern, the path gain G is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">G = 1 2π (m + 1) cos m (φ) ARX d 2 cos ψ |ψ| ≤ ψ FoV 0 |ψ| &gt; ψ FoV ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where m = -log 2 log cos φ 1 2</p><p>is the order of Lambertian emission with half irradiance at semi-angle φ 1 2 (measured from the optical axis of the LED), φ is the angle of irradiance, A RX is the receiver collection area, d is the LoS distance between the LED and PD, ψ is the angle of incidence (measured from the axis normal to the receiver surface), and ψ FoV is the receiver field-of-view (FoV) semi-angle. The receiver collection area is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">A RX = n 2 sin 2 (ψ FoV ) A PD ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where n is the refractive index of the optical concentrator and A PD is the PD area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Beamforming and Zero-Forcing</head><p>Definition 1 (Transmit Beamforming): Consider a transmitter with N transmit elements. Then, for a transmitted signal vector x(t) ∈ R N , we refer to the transmission scheme as beamforming if x(t) can be factorized as x(t) = ws(t), where w ∈ R N is a fixed vector, termed as the beamformer, while s(t) ∈ R is the transmitted data symbol, i.e., S is a random variable.</p><p>Definition 2 (Zero-Forcing Beamformer): For a transmit beamforming scheme x(t) = ws(t) and a single-element receiver with channel gain vector h ∈ R N , we refer to w as a zero-forcing beamformer, w.r.t. the specified receiver, if w satisfies h T w = 0, i.e., if w is in the null space of h T .</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> depicts a simplified block diagram of a MISO VLC system utilizing transmit beamforming. Notice that, although the VLC channel described in Section II-B utilizes IM, Definitions 1 and 2 are still applicable since the DC bias at the transmitter ensures the non-negativity of the total current driving the LEDs. Notice also that, for a zero-mean signal s(t), beamforming does not affect the illumination level. It is also crucial to notice that a zero-forcing beamformer ensures only that the data signal at the receiver is suppressed to zero. However, the DC component and, consequently, the illumination level at the receiver (or anywhere else) remain unchanged.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. System Model</head><p>We consider the VLC scenario illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The room is illuminated by N A down-facing light fixtures attached to the ceiling, and also utilized by Alice for data transmission. Each fixture consists of multiple LEDs modulated by the same current signal, e.g., the LEDs are connected in series. In addition, the LEDs in a single fixture are sufficiently-close such that their channel gains, to a single receiver, are identical. Bob and Eve have a single PD, each, and their terminals are positioned up-facing.</p><p>Utilizing the VLC channel model in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>), the signals received by Bob and Eve, respectively, are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">y(t) = h T B x(t) + w B (t)<label>(4a)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">z(t) = h T E x(t) + w E (t),<label>(4b)</label></formula><p>where x(t) ∈ R NA is the transmitted signal vector, h B and h E ∈ R NA + are fixed channel gain vectors, and w B (t) and w E (t) are independent and identically-distributed Gaussian noises whose samples are N 0, σ 2 random variables. The transmitted signal x(t) is subject to the amplitude constraint</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">|x(t)| A1 ∀t.<label>(5)</label></formula><p>The fundamental problem addressed in this paper is: Alice shall transmit confidential messages to Bob, and keep the information entirely hidden from Eve, without using secretkey encryption. To formulate the problem properly, we recall relevant definitions from information theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>.</p><p>A 2 nR , n code for a real-valued Gaussian MISO channel subject to an amplitude constraint |x| </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">A1 consists of an index set M = 1, 2, • • • , 2 nR , a stochastic encoder E : M → X n which maps each index m ∈ M into a codeword x(t)| n t=1 , x(t) ∈ R NA ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">lim n→∞ I (M ; Z n ) = 0,<label>(6b)</label></formula><p>where (6a) is the reliability constraint, i.e., reliable connection between Alice and Bob, while (6b) is the strong secrecy constraint. The secrecy capacity is the supremum of all achievable secrecy rates <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p><p>Given the wiretap channel in (4), we are interested in characterizing communication rates between Alice and Bob, subject to the amplitude constraint in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> and reliability and secrecy constraints in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. ACHIEVABLE SECRECY RATES</head><p>We first derive lower and upper bounds on the secrecy capacity of the scalar Gaussian wiretap channel subject to an amplitude constraint. Then, we utilize the lower bound along with beamforming to characterize achievable secrecy rates for the MISO case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Bounds on the Secrecy Capacity for the SISO Channel</head><p>If only a single light fixture is utilized for data transmission, or all the fixtures are modulated by identical current signals, e.g., due to hardware or wiring limitations, the wiretap channel model in (4) simplifies to </p><formula xml:id="formula_9">y(t) = h B x(t) + w B (t) (7a) z(t) = h E x(t) + w E (t). (7b) If h B ≤ h E , then</formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">C SISO s = max p X (I(X; Y ) -I(X; Z)) (8a) s.t. |x| ≤ A. (<label>8b</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">)</formula><p>Because of the amplitude constraint, obtaining a closed-form solution for ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">8</ref>) is a formidable task, if not unfeasible. However, it was shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> that the maximization problem in (8) is convex. Furthermore, it was shown that the optimum distribution p * X , which maximizes I(X; Y ) -I(X; Z), is discrete with a finite number of mass points. Therefore, (8) can be efficiently solved using numerical methods. Nevertheless, closed-form expressions are often of great interest for system design purposes. In the following, we provide closed-form lower and upper bounds on the secrecy capacity of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">8</ref>). Lower bound <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> Lower bound <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> Upper bound <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> h</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">2 E = 10 -3 h 2 B h 2 E = 10 -2 h 2 B h 2 E = 10 -1 h 2 B</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. Secrecy capacity bounds of Theorem 1.</p><p>Theorem 1: The secrecy capacity of the Gaussian wiretap channel in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, subject to the amplitude constraint |x(t)| ≤ A ∀t, is lower-bounded by each of the following two bounds</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">C SISO s ≥ 1 2 log 1 + 2h 2 B A 2 πeσ 2 -1 -2Q δ + h E A σ log 2(h E A + δ) √ 2πσ 2 1 -2Q δ σ -Q δ σ - δ √ 2πσ 2 e -δ 2 2σ 2 + 1 2<label>(9)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">C SISO s ≥ 1 2 log 6h 2 B A 2 + 3πeσ 2 πeh 2 E A 2 + 3πeσ 2 ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>and is upper-bounded by</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">C SISO s ≤ 1 2 log h 2 B A 2 + σ 2 h 2 E A 2 + σ 2 ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where δ in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">9</ref>) is a free parameter such that δ &gt; 0, and Q(•) is the Q-function.</p><p>Proof: See Appendices A and B. Notice that the lower bound in (9) exploits the lower and upper bounds on the capacity of the IM channel studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. Notice also that the upper bound in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> is the secrecy capacity of the Gaussian wiretap channel subject to the average power constraint E{X 2 } ≤ A 2 . Therefore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> can be concluded by relaxing the amplitude constraint |x| ≤ A into the average power constraint E{X 2 } ≤ A 2 . Nevertheless, we provide a rigorous proof for <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> in Appendix B and introduce a general approach for upper-bounding the secrecy capacity of degraded wiretap channels.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> presents the bounds of Theorem 1. Three groups of bounds are shown using 20 log 10 (h B /h E ) = 10, 20, and 30 dB. Lower bound (9) is calculated using δ = σ log (1 + 2h E A/σ) as proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. As can be seen, both <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> along with <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> tightly bound the secrecy capacity at asymptotically low and high SNR B . Notice that (10) incurs a fixed gap of log πe/6 = 0.1765 nats/channel use at asymptotically high SNR B . Nevertheless, since typical VLC links operate at SNR values well below 40 dB (see, e.g., Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_14">10</ref>) is appropriate for VLC scenarios. Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> is more analytically-tractable and, therefore, it will be used to obtain secrecy rate expressions for the MISO channel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Achievable Secrecy Rates for the MISO Case</head><p>A single-letter characterization of the secrecy capacity of the non-degraded wiretap channel was given by Csiszár and Körner as <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> C</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">MISO s = max p UX (I(U; Y ) -I(U; Z)) , (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">)</formula><p>where U is an auxiliary random vector that satisfies the Markov relation U → X → (Y, Z). Unlike the scalar case, the optimization problem in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_16">12</ref>) is, in general, non-convex. Furthermore, the optimum selection of U is not clear. For the Gaussian MISO channel with average power constraint, it was shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> that the secrecy capacity is achieved via beamforming, i.e., the choice U = X = wS is optimum, where w is the beamformer and S is a random variable. An achievable secrecy rate for the MISO channel with amplitude constraint can be obtained by lower-bounding the secrecy capacity in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> as follows.</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">C MISO s (a) ≥ max p X (I (X; Y ) -I (X; Z)) (b) ≥ max w,p S (I (wS; Y ) -I (wS; Z)) (c) ≥ max w 1 2 log 6A 2 w T h B h T B w + 3πeσ 2 πeA 2 w T h E h T E w + 3πeσ 2 ,<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where (a) follows from setting X = U, (b) from choosing X = wS such that |w| 1 and |s| ≤ A, i.e., restricting the transmission scheme to beamforming, and (c) from choosing a uniform distribution p S over the interval [-A, A] and utilizing the lower bound in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</p><p>Although suboptimal, beamforming is preferable as it is a linear operation with low implementation complexity. Furthermore, it reduces the vector channel into a scalar version which enables the use of well-developed scalar channel codes. The lower bound in (13) provides a design equation for the MISO case where the problem is reduced to finding an appropriate beamformer w.</p><p>1) Optimum Beamforming: The optimum beamformer w * which maximizes the secrecy rate in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">w * = arg max w 1 2 log 6A 2 w T h B h T B w + 3πeσ 2 πeA 2 w T h E h T E w + 3πeσ 2 (14a) s.t. |w| 1.<label>(14b)</label></formula><p>Since h B h T B and h E h T E are positive semi-definite matrices (as both are singular), the problem in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">14</ref>) is a maximization of the ratio of two convex quadratic functions with box constraints. Such a problem is non-convex, and obtaining a local maximum has been shown to be NP-hard <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. Nevertheless, several approaches have been proposed, e.g., in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, to obtain suboptimal solutions. A typical algorithm begins with converting the problem into a parametric, non-convex, quadratic problem, as proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. Then, a local maximum is found via active-set or interior methods. 2) Zero-Forcing Beamforming: The secrecy rate in (13) can be further lower-bounded by restricting w to be within Eve's null space. Thus, the optimum zero-forcing beamformer w ZF is obtained by</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">w ZF = arg max w h T B w (15a) s.t. |w| 1 h T E w = 0 .<label>(15b)</label></formula><p>Replacing w in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">13</ref>) with w ZF results in the secrecy rate</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">R ZF s = 1 2 log 1 + 2A 2 w T ZF h B h T B w ZF πeσ 2 . (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">)</formula><p>Unlike the optimum beamforming case in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>, the maximization problem in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">15</ref>) is linear and, therefore, it can be solved with lower computational complexity. Furthermore, the zeroforcing beamformer is sufficient to achieve the secrecy rate in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> without resorting to stochastic encoding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. ROBUST BEAMFORMING</head><p>For the wiretap channel, it is reasonable to assume that Bob's channel is accurately known to Alice, via, e.g., feedback from Bob. On the other hand, Eve is typically a malicious user, and will not feed back her channel information to Alice. Nevertheless, in a typical VLC scenario, with the path gain as given in (2), Alice can map Eve's uncertain location information into an estimate of her channel gain. Thus, an interesting design problem is to secure the connection between Alice and Bob when Eve is expected to exist within a specified area, without knowing her exact location. A relevant practical scenario would be, e.g., a governmental office with certain areas accessible to the public, and among them are potential eavesdroppers.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref> illustrates the scenario with uncertainty about Eve's location. For simplicity, we consider only two-dimensional location uncertainty, and assume that Eve's height is fixed and is accurately known to Alice. Extension to three-dimensional uncertainty should be straightforward. Without loss of generality, we assume that Eve's location is bounded by a square of area 2 × 2 , i.e., Eve is located somewhere at If Alice adopts a beamforming strategy and perfectly knows Bob's channel, then the achievable secrecy rate is given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">13</ref>) as a function of Eve's exact location, i.e., R s (w, ∆ χ , ∆ Υ ). For a fixed beamformer w, there exists a worst-case Eve's location χ E + ∆ * χ (w), Υ E + ∆ * Υ (w) , ∆ * χ (w) ≤ , |∆ * Υ (w)| ≤ , which minimizes the achievable secrecy rate. Such secrecy rate is termed as the worst-case secrecy rate R wc s (w), and is a function of w. By definition, achieving R wc s (w) is guaranteed regardless of Eve's exact location (χ E + ∆ χ , Υ E + ∆ Υ ). Then, the design problem is to find the beamformer w RB which maximizes the worst-case secrecy rate over all admissible beamformers |w| 1. Such a transmission strategy will be termed as robust beamforming.</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">(χ E + ∆ χ , Υ E + ∆ Υ ),</formula><p>To simplify the problem formulation, we rewrite Eve's channel gain as a function of her location. Assume that the ith light fixture is located at (χ A,i , Υ A,i , Z), where χ A,i and Υ A,i are measured w.r.t. the reference point, while Z is the vertical distance between the light fixtures and Eve. Then, for i ∈ {1, 2, • • • , N A }, the channel gain h E,i , when |ψ i | ≤ ψ FoV , i.e., when the ith light fixture is within Eve's FoV, can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">h E,i = η 2π (m + 1) Z d i m A RX d 2 i Z d i RT = Kd -(m+3) i = K (χ i + ∆ χ ) 2 + (Υ i + ∆ Υ ) 2 + Z 2 -m+3 2 ,<label>(17)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">χ i = χ E -χ A,i , Υ i = Υ E -Υ A,i , and K = η 2π (m + 1)Z m+1 A RX RT is a constant.</formula><p>Thus, the worst-case secrecy rate maximization problem can be formulated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">R wc s * = max w min ∆χ,∆Υ 1 2 log 6A 2 w T h B h T B w + 3πeσ 2 πeA 2 w T h E h T E w + 3πeσ 2 (18a) s.t.      |w| 1 |∆ χ | ≤ |∆ Υ | ≤ ,<label>(18b)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">, for i ∈ {1, 2, • • • , N A }, h E,i = K (χ i + ∆ χ ) 2 + (Υ i + ∆ Υ ) 2 + Z 2 -m+3 2 .<label>(18c)</label></formula><p>The max-min problem in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> involves two optimization problems. The inner problem is to find the worst-case location for Eve ∆ * χ (w), ∆ * Υ (w) which minimizes R s for a fixed w. The outer problem is similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> and involves finding the optimal beamformer w * (∆ χ , ∆ Υ ) that maximizes R s for a given location (∆ χ , ∆ Υ ). Solving ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">18</ref>) is difficult mainly due to the mutual dependence between the optimization parameters in the inner and outer problems. In the following, we simplify (18) by considering the first-order Taylor series approximation of the channel gain in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">17</ref>) at (∆ χ , ∆ Υ ) = (0, 0).</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">Define D i = (χ 2 i + Υ 2 i + Z 2 ), then, for i ∈ {1, 2, • • • , N A }, Taylor's expansion of h E,i at (∆ χ , ∆ Υ ) = (0, 0) is given by h E,i (∆ χ , ∆ Υ ) = K D -(m+3) i -(m + 3)χ i D -(m+5) i ∆ χ -(m + 3)Υ i D -(m+5) i ∆ Υ + m + 3 2 (m + 5)χ 2 i D -(m+7) i -D -(m+5) i ∆ 2 χ + m + 3 2 (m + 5)Υ 2 i D -(m+7) i -D -(m+5) i ∆ 2 Υ +(m + 3)(m + 5)χ i Υ i D -(m+7) i ∆ χ ∆ Υ + • • • . (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">)</formula><p>For sufficiently small , h E,i can be approximated by the first three terms in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> as</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">hE,i (∆ χ , ∆ Υ ) = K D -(m+3) i -(m + 3)χ i D -(m+5) i ∆ χ -(m + 3)Υ i D -(m+5) i ∆ Υ = K (α i + β i ∆ χ + Γ i ∆ Υ ) ,<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">α i = D -(m+3) i , β i = -(m + 3)χ i D -(m+5) i</formula><p>, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">Γ i = -(m + 3)Υ i D -(m+5) i . We define the matrix HE ∈ R NA×3 as HE =      α 1 β 1 Γ 1 α 2 β 2 Γ 2 . . . . . . . . . α NA β NA Γ NA      . (<label>21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">)</formula><p>Then, for sufficiently small , h E (∆ χ , ∆ Υ ) can be approximated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">hE = K HE   1 ∆ χ ∆ Υ   . (<label>22</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">)</formula><p>The columns of HE span a three-dimensional vector space HE . If Alice has more than three transmit elements, i.e., N A ≥ 4, we propose restricting the transmit beamformer w into the null space of HE . Such a beamformer would significantly degrade the received signal at Eve provided that her actual location is fairly close to (χ E , Υ E ).</p><p>The approximation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>, along with restricting w within the null space of HE , lead to a considerable simplification of <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> and allow decoupling the optimization variables in order to solve two disjoint maximization problems. In particular, the robust beamforming problem can be reformulated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">w RB = arg max w h T B w (23a) s.t. |w| 1 HT E w = 0 , (<label>23b</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_38">(∆ wc χ , ∆ wc Υ ) = arg max ∆χ,∆Υ w T RB h E (24a) s.t. |∆ χ | ≤ |∆ Υ | ≤ , (<label>24b</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">)</formula><p>and the resulting worst-case secrecy rate is obtained by</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">R wc s = 1 2 log 6A 2 w T RB h B h T B w RB + 3πeσ 2 πeA 2 w T RB h wc E (h wc E ) T w RB + 3πeσ 2 , (<label>25</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">)</formula><p>where h wc E ≡ h E ∆ wc χ , ∆ wc Υ . Notice that the maximization in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref>, which is the design equation for the robust beamformer, is a linear problem. On the other hand, the maximization in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>, with h E as given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, is a non-convex problem, and is used to find Eve's location corresponding to the worst-case secrecy rate. Nevertheless, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> can be simplified by approximating h E using the secondorder terms of Taylor's expansion provided in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">hE = K      a 1 b 1 c 1 a 2 b 2 c 2 . . . . . . . . . a NA b NA c NA        ∆ 2 χ ∆ 2 Υ ∆ χ ∆ Υ   ,<label>(26)</label></formula><p>where, for i ∈ {1, 2, • • • , N A },</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">a i = m + 3 2 (m + 5)χ 2 i D -(m+7) i -D -(m+5) i , b i = m + 3 2 (m + 5)Υ 2 i D -(m+7) i -D -(m+5) i , c i = (m + 3)(m + 5)χ i Υ i D -(m+7) i</formula><p>.</p><p>Such an approximation results in a quadratic maximization problem, which is still non-convex, but is easier to solve.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. NUMERICAL RESULTS</head><p>To validate the proposed schemes, we have numerically simulated a typical indoor VLC scenario. The problem geometry is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>, and simulation parameters are provided in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">I</ref>. The room dimensions (5 × 5 × 3 m 3 ) and the number of light fixtures and their locations are quite similar to those in Room 5505, Fred Kaiser Building, Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, The University of British Columbia, Vancouver Campus. There exist 16 down-facing light fixtures attached to the ceiling. Each fixture consists of four LEDs, and each LED radiates one Watt optical power. The half-illuminance semi-angle is 60 • , which is a typical value for commercially-available high-brightness LEDs. Notice that LEDs with wide half-illuminance angles, e.g., 60 • , are preferred for general-purpose lighting to provide uniform illumination. The LEDs modulation index is set to 10%. Bob and Eve are located at height 0.85 m above the floor level, e.g., on desks, and their receivers have a 60 • FoV (semi-angle). We use a Cartesian coordinate system (x, y) at the receivers height to identify their locations. The origin (0, 0) corresponds to the room center, and all distances are measured in meters. Noise power is calculated using [32, eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">6</ref>) and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">I</ref>] with a 70 MHz receiver bandwidth, and the result is averaged over the entire room area. The average electrical noise power is -98.82 dBm. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref> shows the spatial distribution of the SNR at the receivers height without beamforming, i.e., w = 1. As can be seen, the SNR reaches its maximum value, 39.40 dB, at the room center, and decays to 24.97 dB at the corners.  -98.82 dBm Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8</ref> shows the achievable communication rate R B , between Alice and Bob, as a function of Bob's location, without secrecy constraints. This rate is obtained using (16) after setting w ZF = 1.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref> shows the secrecy rates achievable via the optimal beamformer (14a) and zero-forcing beamformer (15a) as functions of A. Bob and Eve are located at (-0.9, -2.0) and (1.6, -0.7), respectively. Their channel gain vectors are provided in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">II</ref> with fixture indices corresponding to those illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>. As can be seen, the improvement in secrecy rate via optimal beamforming, compared to zero-   forcing, is negligible and does not outweigh the simplicity of the zero-forcing scheme.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10</ref>, Bob's location is fixed at (-0.9, -2.0) and the secrecy rate in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">16</ref>) is shown as a function of Eve's location within the entire room area. As expected, the secrecy rate significantly decreases when Eve is close to Bob. Once Eve is relatively far, e.g., more than about 2.5 m, the secrecy rate is almost independent of Eve's exact location. It is also interesting to characterize the loss in transmission rate caused by the secrecy constraint, i.e., R B -R s , by comparing the secrecy rates in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10</ref> with R B (-0.9, -2.0) = 3.2256 nats/channel use from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8</ref>.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11</ref>, Eve's location is fixed at (1.6, -0.7) and the secrecy rate ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">16</ref>) is shown as a function of Bob's location. Even when Bob is relatively far from Eve, the secrecy rate still depends on Bob's location due to the dependence of R ZF Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>. Secrecy rates achievable via optimal beamforming (13) and zeroforcing beamforming <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> versus the amplitude constraint A in dBm. Bob and Eve are located at (-0.9, -2.0) and (1.6, -0.7), respectively, and their channel gains are provided in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">II</ref>. Noise power is -98.82 dBm.  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">16</ref>) as a function of Eve's location. Bob is located at (-0.9, -2.0). on h B . Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">12</ref> highlights the error in estimating the channel gain caused by truncating Taylor's expansion after the firstorder terms. The spatial distribution of the channel gain from Fixture 8 is shown within the square area bounded by (1.6±0.25, -0.7±0.25). As expected, Taylor's approximation exhibits maximum error at the corners. The maximum relative error is 5.45% at (1.85, -0.45).</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">13</ref> considers the robust beamforming problem and shows the improvement in the worst-case secrecy rate attained by applying the robust beamformer in (23a). Bob is located at (-0.9, -2.0), and his channel gain is perfectly known to Alice. Eve is located somewhere within the square area (1.6 ± , -0.7 ± ). For relatively small , i.e., when Alice is quite certain about Eve's location, the non-robust beamformer exhibits a slightly-better performance. The reason is that two  degrees of freedom are unnecessarily exploited with the robust beamformer to null out the signal at the directions of the second and third columns of HE in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>. As increases, the robust beamformer is clearly superior, and it slows down the decay in R wc s with increasing . Finally, we validate the robust beamforming scheme over the entire room area, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">14</ref>. We divide the room into 25 squares. Each square has an area of 1 m 2 , and outlines possible locations for Eve. Bob is located at (-0.9, -2.0), and his channel gain is perfectly known to Alice. Alice also knows which square bounds Eve's location, without knowing her exact location. From such information, Alice applies the robust beamformer in (23a). The resulting secrecy rate is shown as a function of Eve's location within each square. Worst-case secrecy rates R wc s are also shown. Notice that R wc s is zero when Bob and Eve are located within the same square, and it increases as Eve moves far away from Bob.  Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">14</ref>. Secrecy rate as a function of Eve's location when the robust beamformer (23a) is applied. Eve's location information is quantized into 25 squares, each of area 1 m 2 , and the quantized location information is available to Alice. Bob is located at (-0.9, -2.0). Worst-case secrecy rates (nats/channel use) are also shown inside each square.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>In this work, we proposed the use of physical-layer security techniques to enhance the confidentiality of VLC links. So far, there have been very few deployments of physical-layer security systems. One major shortcoming of such security schemes is performance sensitivity to channel information assumptions, especially for the eavesdropper's link. We believe, however, that VLC networks have a potential for the deployment of physical-layer security prototypes since realistic assumptions about the eavesdropper's channel can be made.</p><p>Unlike RF channels, the VLC channel is well-modelled with amplitude constraints imposed on the channel input, making it difficult to obtain analytical expressions for the secrecy capacity, even for the simple SISO case. Therefore, we derived closed-form lower and upper bounds on the secrecy capacity of the amplitude-constrained wiretap channel. Then, we utilized beamforming to obtain achievable secrecy rates for the MISO channel. We have shown that zero-forcing is an appropriate strategy for secure transmission over MISO VLC channels. Although suboptimal, zero-forcing is preferable as it is an achievability strategy that eliminates the need to use secrecy codes which involve stochastic encoding. We have also proposed a practical robust beamforming scheme which considerably improves worst-case secrecy rates when information about the eavesdropper's channel is imperfect due to location uncertainty. The robust scheme directly addresses the aforementioned problem of performance sensitivity to channel assumptions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A DERIVATION OF THE LOWER BOUNDS ON SECRECY CAPACITY</head><p>A. Lower Bound (9) of Theorem 1</p><p>The secrecy capacity in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">8</ref>) can be lower-bounded by the difference between the channel capacities of Alice-Bob and Alice-Eve links as follows.</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">C SISO s = max p X (I(X; Y ) -I(X; Z)) (a) ≥ max p X I(X; Y ) -max p X I(X; Z) = C B -C E ,<label>(27)</label></formula><p>where (a) follows from the inequality</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">max u (f 1 (u) -f 2 (u)) ≥ max u f 1 (u) -max u f 2 (u)</formula><p>for arbitrary functions f 1 and f 2 . Then, C B and C E , respectively, can be lower-and upper-bounded by [24, Theorem 5]</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">C B ≥ 1 2 log 1 + 2h 2 B A 2 πeσ 2 , (<label>28a</label></formula><p>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">C E ≤ 1 -2Q δ + h E A σ log 2(h E A + δ) √ 2πσ 2 1 -2Q δ σ + Q δ σ + δ √ 2πσ 2 e -δ 2 2σ 2 - 1 2 ,<label>(28b)</label></formula><p>where δ &gt; 0 is a free parameter. Finally, plugging ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_46">28</ref>) into ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_44">27</ref>) results in the lower bound in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</p><p>B. Lower Bound (10) of Theorem 1</p><p>Another lower bound on the secrecy capacity of (8) can be obtained as follows.</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">C SISO s = max p X (I(X; Y ) -I(X; Z)) = max p X (h(Y ) -h(Y |X) -h(Z) + h(Z|X)) = max p X (h(Y ) -h(Z)) = max p X (h(h B X + W B ) -h(Z)) (a) ≥ max p X 1 2 log e 2h(hBX) + e 2h(WB) - 1 2 log 2πe × var {Z} (b) ≥ 1 2 log 4h 2 B A 2 + 2πeσ 2 - 1 2 log 2πe 4h 2 E A 2 12 + σ 2 = 1 2 log 6h 2 B A 2 + 3πeσ 2 πeh 2 E A 2 + 3πeσ 2 ,<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where (a) follows from lower-bounding h(h B X + W B ) using the entropy-power inequality [34, Theorem 17. </p><formula xml:id="formula_49">= var{h E X} + var{W E } = (2h E A) 2 /12 + σ 2 .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX B DERIVATION OF THE UPPER BOUND ON SECRECY CAPACITY</head><p>We follow the approach proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> to derive an upper bound on the secrecy capacity of the degraded wiretap channel using a dual expression for the secrecy capacity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Duality-Based Upper Bound on Conditional Mutual Information</head><p>Theorem 2: The conditional mutual information I(X; Y |Z) is upper-bounded by</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">I(X; Y |Z) ≤ E p XZ D p Y |XZ (y|X, Z) q Y |Z (y|Z) ,<label>(30)</label></formula><p>where p Y |XZ is uniquely determined by the conditional distributions of the degraded wiretap channel, i.e., p Y |X and p Z|Y , while q Y |Z is an arbitrary conditional distribution of Y given Z.</p><p>Proof: We begin with </p><p>Then, the inequality in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref> follows by noting that the integral in ( <ref type="formula">32</ref>) is always non-negative. Equality holds in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref> when D p Y |Z q Y |Z = 0, i.e., when q Y |Z = p Y |Z ∀Z ∈ Z. Therefore, (30) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">I(X; Y |Z) = min q Y |Z E p X p Z|X D p Y |XZ (y|X, Z) q Y |Z (y|Z) .</formula><p>(34) Notice that the input distribution p X in (34) is arbitrary, and there exists a unique distribution p * X that maximizes I(X; Y |Z), subject to the channel input constraints, resulting in the secrecy capacity C s , i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">C s = min q Y |Z max p X E p X p Z|X D p Y |XZ (y|X, Z) q Y |Z (y|Z) .</formula><p>(35) Then, by dropping the minimization and choosing an arbitrary conditional distribution q Y |Z , we obtain the following upper bound on the secrecy capacity.</p><p>Lemma 1: An upper bound on the secrecy capacity of the degraded wiretap channel is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">C s ≤ E p * X p Z|X D p Y |XZ (y|X, Z) q Y |Z (y|Z)<label>(36)</label></formula><p>for an arbitrary conditional distribution q Y |Z . </p><p>We define γ 2 B = σ 2 /h 2 B and γ 2 E = σ 2 /h 2 E . Thus, ) .</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">I 1 = E p * X p Y Z|X log p Y |XZ (Y |X, Z) = -h(Y |X, Z) = -(h(Y |X) + h(Z|X, Y ) -h(Z|X)) = - 1 2 log 2πe γ 2 B (γ 2 E -γ 2 B ) γ 2 E . (<label>38</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_57">)</formula><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">)<label>40</label></formula><p>Therefore, </p><formula xml:id="formula_59">I 2 = -E p * X    1 2πγ 2 B ∞ -∞ e - (y-X) 2 2γ 2 B ∞ -∞<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_60">)</formula><p>where the last inequality follows from E p * X {X 2 } ≤ A 2 . To minimize the expression in (41), we choose</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">µ = A 2 + γ 2 B A 2 + γ 2 E ,<label>(42a)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_62">s 2 = (A 2 + γ 2 B )(γ 2 E -γ 2 B ) A 2 + γ 2 E .<label>(42b)</label></formula><p>Plugging (42) into (41) and adding the result to <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref>, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">C s ≤ 1 2 log (A 2 + γ 2 B )γ 2 E (A 2 + γ 2 E )γ 2 B = 1 2 log h 2 B A 2 + σ 2 h 2 E A 2 + σ 2 . (<label>43</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_64">)</formula><p>Notice that the upper bound in (43) can be obtained by relaxing the amplitude constraint into the average power constraint E{X 2 } ≤ A 2 and calculating the secrecy capacity of the resulting channel. Nevertheless, the proposed framework is useful for deriving upper bounds on the secrecy capacity of arbitrary degraded channels since Lemma 1 holds for arbitrary distributions p Y |X and p Z|Y , i.e., the main and degraded channels need not be Gaussian.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. A VLC network consisting of one sender (Alice), who utilizes the light sources for data transmission, one legitimate receiver (Bob), and one eavesdropper (Eve).</figDesc><graphic coords="2,239.39,78.00,397.66,91.37" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>w 2 w 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Transmit beamforming over a MISO PAM VLC channel.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(h B A/σ) (dB) Secrecy capacity bounds (nats/channel use)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Geometry for the robust beamforming problem. The highlighted area identifies possible locations for Eve.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where χ E and Υ E are measured w.r.t. some reference point at Eve's height, e.g., the room center, while |∆ χ | and |∆ Υ | are bounded as |∆ χ | ≤ and |∆ Υ | ≤ . From this location information, Alice can estimate Eve's channel with some bounded error.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Geometry of a VLC scenario with 16 light fixtures.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Spatial distribution of the SNR at the receivers level (0.85 m above the floor level) without beamforming.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Achievable communication rate, between Alice and Bob, as a function of Bob's location, without secrecy constraints.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig.10. Secrecy rate achievable via zero-forcing beamforming<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> as a function of Eve's location. Bob is located at (-0.9, -2.0).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Secrecy rate achievable via zero-forcing beamforming (16) as a function of Bob's location. Eve is located at (1.6, -0.7).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Spatial distribution of the channel gain from Fixture 8 (see Fig. 6 for fixture indices) within a square of area (0.5 × 0.5 m 2 ) centered at (1.6, -0.7).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig.13. Worst-case secrecy rate (25) versus , half the side length of the square outlining possible locations of Eve. Bob is located at (-0.9, -2.0) and Eve's location is bounded by (1.6 ± , -0.7 ± ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>7.3], and upperbounding h(Z) by the differential entropy of a Gaussian random variable with variance var{Z}, and (b) from dropping the maximization, choosing a uniform distribution p X over the interval [-A, A], and substituting h(h B X) = log (2h B A) and var{Z}</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>B. Upper Bound ( 11 )</head><label>11</label><figDesc>of Theorem 1 Substituting for D(• •) in<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref>, we obtainC s ≤ E p * X p Z|X    Y p Y |XZ (y|X, Z) log p Y |XZ (y|X, Z) q Y |Z (y|Z)dy (y, z|X) log p Y |XZ (y|X, z) dy dz (y, z|X) log q Y |Z (y|z) dy dz</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>according to transition probabilities p χ n |M , and a deterministic decoder D : Y n → M which maps the received sequence y(t)| n R s is an achievable secrecy rate, if there exists a 2 nRs , n code such that</figDesc><table><row><cell>lim n→∞</cell><cell>P n e = 0</cell><cell>(6a)</cell></row></table><note><p>t=1 , y(t) ∈ R, to an estimate m = D (y(t)| n t=1 ), m ∈ M. Each codeword x(t)| n t=1 must satisfy the amplitude constraint |x(t)| A1 ∀t. The rate of information transmission is R (bits/channel use). An error event occurs when m = m, and the communication reliability is measured in terms of the average error probability P n e . By considering the wiretap channel in (4), I(M; Y n ) measures the amount of information attainable by Bob within n channel uses, while I(M; Z n ) measures the amount of information leaked to Eve. A communication rate R s is said to be achievable and fully secure, i.e.,</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE I</head><label>I</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>SIMULATION PARAMETERS.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Problem geometry</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Room dimensions (W × L × H)</cell><cell>5 × 5 × 3 m 3</cell></row><row><cell>Light fixtures (Alice) height</cell><cell>3 m</cell></row><row><cell>Receivers (Bob and Eve) height</cell><cell>0.85 m</cell></row><row><cell>Number of light fixtures NA</cell><cell>16</cell></row><row><cell>Number of LEDs per fixture</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Transmitter characteristics</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Average optical power per LED</cell><cell>1 W</cell></row><row><cell>Modulation index α</cell><cell>10%</cell></row><row><cell>LED half luminous intensity semi-angle φ 1</cell><cell>60 •</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Receiver characteristics</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Receiver FoV ψFoV</cell><cell>60 •</cell></row><row><cell>Lens refractive index n</cell><cell>1.5</cell></row><row><cell>PD responsivity R</cell><cell>0.54 (A/W)</cell></row><row><cell>PD geometrical area APD</cell><cell>1 cm 2</cell></row><row><cell>Average electrical noise power σ 2</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Y, and Z are the support sets of X, Y , and Z, respectively. Adding<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref> to<ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>, we obtainI(X; Y |Z) + E p XZ D p Y |Z (y|Z) q Y |Z (y|Z) = XZ D p Y |XZ (y|X, Z) q Y |Z (y|Z) .</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">p XY Z (x, y, z) log</cell><cell>p Y |XZ (y|x, z) q Y |Z (y|z)</cell><cell>dx dy dz</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">X Y Z</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>= E p XZ</cell><cell>  Y</cell><cell cols="2">p Y |XZ (y|X, Z) log</cell><cell>p Y |XZ (y|X, Z) q Y |Z (y|Z)</cell><cell>dy</cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>= E p</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>I(X; Y |Z)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>=</cell><cell>p XY Z (x, y, z) log</cell><cell>p Y |XZ (y|x, z) p Y |Z (y|z)</cell><cell>dx dy dz (31)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>X Y Z</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p>and</p>E p XZ D p Y |Z (y|Z) q Y |Z (y|Z) = X Y Z p XY Z (x, y, z) log p Y |Z (y|z) q Y |Z (y|z) dx dy dz,</p>(32)</p>where X ,</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>IEEE JOURNAL ON SELECTED AREAS IN COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 33, NO. X, MONTH 2015 To calculate I 2 , we choose q Y |Z as where µ and s 2 are constants to be determined in (42). For a degraded Gaussian wiretap channel, we have p Y Z|X (y, z|x) = p Y |X (y|x) p Z|XY (z|x, y) = p Y |X (y|x) p Z|Y (z|y)</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">q Y |Z (y|z) =</cell><cell>√</cell><cell>1 2πs 2</cell><cell>e -(y-µz) 2 2s 2</cell><cell>,</cell><cell></cell><cell>(39)</cell></row><row><cell>=</cell><cell>1 2πγ 2 B</cell><cell>e</cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">(y-x) 2 2γ 2 B</cell><cell cols="2">1 2π(γ 2 E -γ 2 B )</cell><cell>e</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>(z-y) 2 2(γ 2 E -γ 2 B</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors would like to thank Prof. Steve Hranilovic at McMaster University for insightful comments and suggestions.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported by the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC). The material in this paper was presented in part at the 2014 IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC),</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Short-Range Wireless Optical Communication Using Visible Light</title>
		<idno>802.15.7-2011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area Networks-Part</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">IEEE Std</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lenk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lenk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Practical Lighting Design With LEDs</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Theoretic Security, ser. Foundations and Trends R in Communications and Information Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Poor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shamai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Shitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Now Publishers</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Physical-Layer Security: From Information Theory to Security Engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-10">October 2011</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Securing Wireless Communications at the Physical Layer</title>
		<editor>R. Liu and W. Trappe</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Physical Layer Approaches for Securing Wireless Communication Systems, ser. SpringerBriefs in Computer Science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Physical Layer Security in Wireless Communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Signal Processing Approaches to Secure Physical Layer Communications in Multi-Antenna Wireless Systems, ser</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-C</forename><surname>Lan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">SpringerBriefs in Electrical and Computer Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principles of physical layer security in multiuser wireless networks: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mukherjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fakoorian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Swindlehurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Communications Surveys &amp; Tutorials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1550" to="1573" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Third quarter</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Communication theory of secrecy systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bell System Technical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="656" to="715" />
			<date type="published" when="1949">1949</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The wire-tap channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wyner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bell System Technical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1355" to="1387" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Gaussian wire-tap channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Leung-Yan-Cheong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hellman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="456" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Broadcast channels with confidential messages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Csiszár</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Körner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards the secrecy capacity of the Gaussian MIMO wire-tap channel: The 2-2-1 channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shafiee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ulukus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4033" to="4039" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-09">Sept 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secrecy capacity region of a multiple-antenna Gaussian broadcast channel with confidential messages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Poor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1235" to="1249" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-03">March 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on the secrecy capacity of the multipleantenna wiretap channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shamai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2547" to="2553" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-06">June 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secure transmission with multiple antennas-part II: The MIMOME wiretap channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Khisti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5515" to="5532" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The secrecy capacity of the MIMO wiretap channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Oggier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hassibi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4961" to="4972" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-08">Aug 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secure transmission with multiple antennas I: The MISOME wiretap channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Khisti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wornell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3088" to="3104" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visible-light communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tae-Gyu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">;</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Arnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Barry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Karagiannidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advanced Optical Wireless Communication Systems</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schober</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Uysal</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="368" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visible light communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ghassemlooy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Popoola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rajbhandari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Optical Wireless Communications: System and Channel Modelling with MATLAB R</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="496" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predistortion in optical wireless transmission using OFDM</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Elgala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mesleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Ninth International Conference on Hybrid Intelligent Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-08">Aug 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="189" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optical intensity-modulated direct detection channels: signal space and lattice codes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hranilovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kschischang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1385" to="1399" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-06">June 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the capacity of free-space optical intensity channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lapidoth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wigger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4449" to="4461" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-10">Oct 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mathematical theory of communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bell System Technical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1948-10">July/October 1948</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the Information Capacity of Peak and Average Power Constrained Gaussian Channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
			<pubPlace>Berkeley, California</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Electrical Engineering, University of California</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The information capacity of amplitude-and variance-constrained scalar Gaussian channels</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information and Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An algorithm for computing the capacity of arbitrary discrete memoryless channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="1972-01">Jan 1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gaussian wiretap channel with an amplitude constraint</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Ozel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ekrem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ulukus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2012 IEEE Information Theory Workshop (ITW)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-09">Sept 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="143" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fundamental analysis for visible-light communication system using LED lights</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Komine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nakagawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Consumer Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Broadband information broadcasting using LED-based interior lighting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grubor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Randel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-D</forename><surname>Langer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Walewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Lightwave Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3883" to="3892" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-12">Dec 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High data rate multiple input multiple output (MIMO) optical wireless communications using white LED lighting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1654" to="1662" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wireless infrared communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-02">Feb 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Elements of Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Active-Set Methods for Quadratic Programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of California, San Diego</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximization of the ratio of two convex quadratic functions over a polytope</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-Y</forename><surname>Gotoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Konno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational Optimization and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fractional programming with convex quadratic forms and functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Benson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Operational Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">173</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On nonlinear fractional programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dinkelbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="492" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capacity bounds via duality with applications to multiple-antenna systems on flat-fading channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lapidoth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2426" to="2467" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-10">Oct 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Duality-Based Bounds on Channel Capacity</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Swiss Federal Institute of Technology, Zürich</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
