<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Event-Triggered Schemes on Leader-Following Consensus of General Linear Multiagent Systems Under Different Topologies</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wenying</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">City University of Hong Kong</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>211189</postCode>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">City University of Hong Kong</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>211189</postCode>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Senior Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">W C</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
							<email>madaniel@cityu.edu.hk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">City University of Hong Kong</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>211189</postCode>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210096</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lulu</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<email>lilulu01@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">City University of Hong Kong</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>211189</postCode>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hefei University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>230009</postCode>
									<settlement>Hefei</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Jinde</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
							<email>jdcao@seu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">City University of Hong Kong</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>211189</postCode>
									<settlement>Hong Kong</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Research Center for Complex Systems and Network Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210096</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Event-Triggered Schemes on Leader-Following Consensus of General Linear Multiagent Systems Under Different Topologies</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B14B0F5A336B02F4F00D81818A01E21D</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TCYB.2015.2510746</idno>
					<note type="submission">Manuscript received August 5, 2015; revised October 25, 2015; accepted December 17, 2015.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T10:54+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Consensus</term>
					<term>event-triggered</term>
					<term>leader-following</term>
					<term>multiagent system</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper investigates the leader-following consensus for multiagent systems with general linear dynamics by means of event-triggered scheme (ETS). We propose three types of schemes, namely, distributed ETS (distributed-ETS), centralized ETS (centralized-ETS), and clustered ETS (clustered-ETS) for different network topologies. All these schemes guarantee that all followers can track the leader eventually. It should be emphasized that all event-triggered protocols in this paper depend on local information and their executions are distributed. Moreover, it is shown that such event-triggered mechanism can significantly reduce the frequency of control's update. Further, positive inner-event time intervals are assured for those cases of distributed-ETS, centralized-ETS, and clustered-ETS. In addition, two methods are proposed to avoid continuous communication between agents for event detection. Finally, numerical examples are provided to illustrate the effectiveness of the ETSs.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>communication and control of agents so that all members agree upon the same final state <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p>Numerous research works have contributed to consensus problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Most of these works assume that either agents get continuous access to the states of their neighbors or the controllers update themselves continuously via current states of agents. Actually, this phenomenon is far from realistic and requires high communication cost and expensive control action. In order to lower the cost, a sample-data approach was proposed <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Sampled-data control is essentially time-driven and generally needs to estimate a conservative sampling period or average sampling period. Recently, a new approach was developed based on an event-triggered scheme. It has provided an alternative mechanism where agents broadcast their states or update controller only when they need, which is unknown in advance. That is, only when the condition is triggered, the agents will then take the sample of information or controllers take the corresponding action, respectively. Compared with traditional control methods, evendriven controller has the advantages of lowering cost and saving energy.</p><p>Event-based control is a very appealing topic in networked control systems (NCSs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, a simple eventtriggered scheduler is proposed to stabilize control tasks, which leads to guaranteed performance and relax traditional periodic execution. Then a distributed event-based feedback scheme is introduced to NCS <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and their analysis can be applied to linear or nonlinear system. Event-triggered idea is also applied to stochastic systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and deal with state estimation <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. Moreover, it is a basic, yet challenging issue to avoid the Zeno behavior, that is to avoid an infinite number of event-triggered time instants in a finite amount of time.</p><p>There have been some recent papers on applying eventtriggered scheme (ETS) to cooperation of multiagent systems, such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> for discrete-time systems or <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> for continuous-time systems. A key issue of the event-trigged control is how to design and optimize event-based conditions. In order to cater for different needs of network topologies, various ETSs are springing up. To be specific, if the eventbased condition depends on all agents' information and thus all agents will update their information together. It is called centralized ETS (centralized-ETS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. On the other hand, if event-triggered conditions are distributed and mutual independent, they are considered as distributed ETS (distributed-ETS).</p><p>In this paper, we introduce a new kind of ETS-clustered ETS (clustered-ETS).</p><p>In addition, hybrid triggered mechanism combined with time-driven and event-driven is also proposed to reduce the frequency of event detection <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. However, most of the developed ETSs only focus on a kind of simple multiagent systems. Although a small number of recent papers on event-triggered control based on more general systems have been reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, they generally require network topology of systems to be connected. In this paper, we design various types of event-triggered controllers over different kinds of network topologies.</p><p>The contributions of this paper are fourfold. First, compared with <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, our system is of general linear dynamics with a leader. Thus our goal is to make all followers track this leader, thus our final trajectory is a dynamic orbit based on the leader instead of a static point in average consensus problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. In addition, it is hard to obtain an appropriate event-triggered condition to achieve the leader-following consensus in multiagent system with general linear dynamics by event-triggered controllers presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. However, in this paper, we introduce a novel updated scheme of tracking control based on event-triggered mechanism, which can successfully reach leader-following consensus. Based on this new updated scheme, we proposed three types of ETSs for different network topologies.</p><p>Second, a distributed-ETS is first designed to guarantee all followers to track the leader. In this case, the topology has a spanning tree with the leader as the root vertex.</p><p>Here "distributed" means that event detection for each agent is independent and it just receives its neighbors' information to determine its own next event instant. Note that our distributed event-triggered protocol not only guarantees the leader-following consensus but excludes Zeno behavior. Moreover, it is interesting to note that a leader only needs to transmit its information to its neighbors once initially, the follower can track the leader eventually by following the dynamic path.</p><p>Third, we proposed a centralized-ETS to reach leaderfollowing consensus over jointly connected topology. Here "centralized" denotes that all agents share a common event condition and thus they will update their information together when it is necessary. In this section, we weaken the requirement on communication topology in the existing related research. Here our topology switches among different modes instead of a fixed one, and each topology is allowed to be disconnected. Thus some interesting questions may be asked. For instance, how to design an appropriate ETS under switching communication topology? How to determine the topology switching time sequence and event-triggered time sequence? Are they the same or do they have intersection? All of these issues will be studied in this section. Note that in this scenario the consensus protocol depends on local information.</p><p>Fourth, a novel ETS is proposed in this paper-clustered-ETS. Here, the communication topology G among followers is disconnected, thus all followers are divided into several clusters (families or groups). Based on this topology, a new triggering scheme is designed, which fuses characteristics of the distributed-and centralized-ETS but is different from them. The clustered ETS means that all members in the same cluster share a common event condition and thus they will update their information together without the impact of other clusters. Therefore, clustered-ETS has the following advantages: 1) event detection in this scheme is decentralized and hence it may mitigate risk of information congestion as compared with centralized-ETS and 2) the process of event detection is not independently carried out for each agent. Instead, it receives the information of members in the same cluster to determine their common next event instant. In other words, the detection aims at each cluster not each agent. Thus it may reduce the cost of event detection to some extent as compared with distributed-ETS. To sum up, the clustered ETS is different from distributed-and centralized-ETSs, but have the advantages of both ETSs. Finally, two methods are proposed to avoid continuous communication between agents for event detection.</p><p>The rest of this paper is organized as follows. Section II gives some basic theory on graphs and matrices. Three different types of event-triggered controllers are presented, respectively, in Sections III-V. Some numerical examples are given in Section VII to verify the effectiveness of our ETSs. Finally, Section VIII concludes this paper.</p><p>The following notations will be used throughout this paper: R n and R n×m represent the set of all n dimensional real column vectors and the set of all n×m dimensional real matrices. Similarly, I n denotes (1, 1, . . . , 1) T with dimension n. I n×n means n-dimension unit matrix and I denotes unit matrix with proper dimension. Besides, ||•|| refers to two-norm for vectors or the induced two-norm for matrices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PRELIMINARIES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Basic Theory on Graphs and Matrices</head><p>A directed graph Ḡ consists of nodes {0, 1, 2, . . . , N} and a set of edges Ē. Its subgraph G consisting of nodes {1, 2, . . . , N} and a edge set E is a undirected graph. If there is a edge between nodes i and j, then (i, j) ∈ E and node j is called the neighbor of node i and vice versa. The set N i includes all neighbors of node i. The Laplacian matrix L is defined as: when i = j, l ij = -1, if (i, j) ∈ E, otherwise, l ij = 0; l ii = -j∈N i l ij . A diagonal matrix D is defined as: d i = 1 if node i can receive the information of the leader (node 0); otherwise, d i = 0. Let H = L + D and its eigenvalues can be set in increasing order 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">≤ λ 1 ≤ λ 2 ≤ • • • ≤ λ N .</formula><p>For each graph Ḡp , the eigenvalues of its corresponding matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">H p is denoted as 0 ≤ λ p 1 ≤ λ p 2 ≤ • • • ≤ λ p N . Definition 1: The graph Ḡ(t) is called jointly-connected on the time interval [a, b] if the union ∪ t∈[a,b] Ḡσ(t) is connected.</formula><p>Note that the union ∪ t∈[a,b] Ḡσ(t) means that the union of all nodes and edges of the activated graphs over <ref type="bibr">[a, b]</ref>.</p><p>Lemma 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>: Some properties of H are given as follows.</p><p>1) The matrix H is positive definite if and only if the graph Ḡ is connected.</p><p>2) Let matrices H 1 , . . . , H m be associated with the graphs Ḡ1 , . . . , Ḡm , respectively. If these graphs are jointly connected, then m i=1 H i is positive definite.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Problem Statement</head><p>Consider leader-following multiagent systems including N followers and a leader, which are equipped with general linear dynamics. The leader is labeled as node 0 and its dynamics can be described as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">ẋ0 (t) = Ax 0 (t), x 0 (t) ∈ R n (1)</formula><p>and the dynamics of followers can be described by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">ẋi (t) = Ax i (t) + Bu i (t), i = 1, 2, . . . , N<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">x i (t) ∈ R n , A ∈ R n×n , B ∈ R n×m , and u i (t) ∈ R m is the control input of agent i.</formula><p>Obviously, the trajectory of the leader cannot be affected by followers.</p><p>In this paper, for different topological structures, we design appropriate event-triggered information transmission and protocols u i (t) such that leader-following consensus can be achieved, i.e., x i (t)x 0 (t) = 0 as t → ∞ (i = 1, 2, . . . , N) for any initial conditions.</p><p>Assumption 1: The pair (A, B) is stabilizable. Under Assumption 1, for any α &gt; 0, there exists a positive definite solution P &gt; 0 to the following Riccati inequality holds <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">A T P + PA -2αPBB T P + αI &lt; 0.<label>(3)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. DISTRIBUTED EVENT-TRIGGERED CONTROL OVER CONNECTED TOPOLOGY</head><p>The topology Ḡ is assumed to contain a spanning tree with the leader as the root vertex in this section. Our goal is to design a distributed-ETS to guarantee all followers to track the leader finally.</p><p>First, the measurement error for agent i's state can be defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">e i (t) = exp A t -t i k x i t i k -x i (t), t ∈ t i k , t i k+1 (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">)</formula><p>where t i k is the kth event-triggered instant for agent i. Besides, we define e(t) = (e T 1 (t), e T 2 (t), . . . , e T N (t)) T . Note that the error e i (t) exists due to its control input u i (t), hence the error will decrease (or even vanish) as the followers approach to the leader. It should be emphasized that the trajectory of the leader cannot be affected by the followers, thus it has no control input. Therefore, e 0 (t) = 0 all the time.</p><p>Then we define</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">xi (t) = exp A t -t i k x i t i k , t ∈ t i k , t i k+1 . (<label>5</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">)</formula><p>The distributed event-triggered consensus protocol is</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">u i (t) = K j∈N i a ij xj (t) -xi (t) + d i x0 (t) -xi (t)<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where K = B T P and P is a positive definite matrix to be designed later.</p><p>The triggering time sequence {t i k } for every agent i is determined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">t i k+1 = max ⎧ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ t i k + τ i , inf ⎧ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ t : t &gt; t i k and ||Ke i (t)|| 2 &gt; κ i K ⎡ ⎣ j∈N i x j (t) -x i (t) + d i (x 0 (t) -x i (t)) ⎤ ⎦ 2 ⎫ ⎪ ⎬ ⎪ ⎭ ⎫ ⎪ ⎬ ⎪ ⎭<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where τ i &gt; 0 is a constant and will be determined subsequently. Here if node i can receive the information of the leader, then d i = 1; otherwise, d i = 0. Note that, agent i will transmit its current state to its neighbors and update its control protocol only when t = t i k . Then, e i (t) is reset to zero. When t ∈ (t i k , t i k+1 ), no further action is required. Remark 1: As is well known, consensus issue in multiagent systems involves two concerns: 1) information transmission and 2) control protocol update. In conventional continuous multiagent systems, these two activities are executed continuously such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. In this section, we propose a distributed-ETS <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, which reduces the energy and cost of control protocol's update. However, based on this scheme, agent i needs to use the information of its neighbor x j (t) for its own event detection, which implies that continuous information transmission may be required for event detection. Therefore, we will propose two methods to avoid continuous communication for event detection between agents in Section VI.</p><p>In this section, every agent i has its event-triggered time sequence, which is determined by its neighbors' information. Hence this ETS ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">7</ref>) is considered to be distributed.</p><p>Let</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">δ i (t) = x i (t) -x 0 (t) and δi (t) = xi (t) -x0 (t), then δi (t) = Aδ i (t) + BK j∈N i a ij xj (t) -xi (t) + d i x0 (t) -xi (t) = Aδ i (t) + BK j∈N i a ij δj (t) -δi (t) -d i δi (t). (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">) Note that x 0 (t) = x0 (t), thus δi (t) = δ i (t) + e i (t). By setting δ(t) = (δ T 1 (t), δ T 2 (t), . . . , δ T N (t)) T , we have δ(t) = (I N×N ⊗ A)δ(t) + (H ⊗ BK)(e(t) + δ(t)). (<label>9</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">)</formula><p>Now we present our main result in this section. Theorem 1: Consider the leader-following multiagent system (1), (2), we assume that the communication topology Ḡ has a spanning tree with the leader as the root vertex. Assumption 1 holds and there exists 0 &lt; ρ 1 , ρ 2 &lt; 1 so that ρ 1 + ρ 2 ≤ ρ &lt; 1. Then the leader-following consensus can be achieved under the distributed event-triggered protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> and the event condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> with</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">κ i ≤ ρ 1 /λ 2 N , c = ρ 2 /(λ 2 N N),</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">τ i &lt; τ satisfying τ = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ √ cp 1 √ cp 0 p 1 + p 2 1 if p 2 1 = p 0 p 2 1 √ ιp 0 arctan √ c √ ι + p 1 p 0 √ ι -arctan p 1 p 0 √ ι if p 2 1 &lt; p 0 p 2 1 2p 0 √ -ι ln √ cp 0 + p 1 -p 0 √ -ι p 1 + p 0 √ -ι √ cp 0 + p 1 + p 0 √ -ι p 1 -p 0 √ -ι if p 2 1 &gt; p 0 p 2<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where Proof: Consider the following Lyapunov function</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">ι = (p 2 p 0 -p 2 1 )/p 0 , p 0 = ||H 2 ⊗ (KB)||, p 1 = ||I N×N ⊗ A|| + ||H ⊗ (BK)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_18">V(t) = N i=1 δ T i (t)Pδ i (t)</formula><p>, where P is positive definite matrix and satisfies <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_19">with α = (1 -ρ)λ 1 /2. Then V(t) = N i=1 δ T i (t) A T P + PA δ i (t) + ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ N i=1 δ T i (t)2PBK j∈N i a ij xj (t) -xi (t) + d i x0 (t) -xi (t) ⎫ ⎬ ⎭ = N i=1 δ T i (t) A T P + PA δ i (t) + ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ N i=1 δ i (t)2PBK j∈N i a ij δ j (t) -δ i (t) + e j (t) -e i (t) -d i (δ i (t) + e i (t)) ⎫ ⎬ ⎭ = δ T (t) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA -H ⊗ 2PBB T P δ(t) -δ T (t) H ⊗ 2PB T BP e(t) ≤ δ T (t) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA -H ⊗ PBB T P δ(t)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>+ e T (t) H ⊗ PBB T P e(t).</head><p>If we can guarantee that e T (t) H ⊗ PBB T P e(t) ≤ ρδ T (t) H ⊗ PBB T P δ(t) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> with 0 &lt; ρ &lt; 1, then one has</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">V ≤ N i=1 δ T i (t) A T P + PA -(1 -ρ)λ 1 PBB T P δ i (t) ≤ - 1 -ρ 2 λ 1 N i=1 δ T i (t)δ i (t). (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">)</formula><p>Denote the node sets M 1 (t) and M 2 (t) consisting of agents which are triggered by conditions (1) or (2) in the latest event instant, respectively. Thus</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">M 1 (t) ∪ M 2 (t) = {1, 2, . . . N} and M 1 (t) ∩ M 2 (t) = Ø. A sufficient condition for (11) is that i∈M 1 ||Ke i (t)|| 2 ≤ i∈M 1 ρ 1 λ 2 N K ⎡ ⎣ j∈N i δ j (t) -δ i (t) -d i δ i (t) ⎤ ⎦ 2 ≤ ρ 1 λ 2 N N i=1 K ⎡ ⎣ j∈N i δ j (t) -δ i (t) -d i δ i (t) ⎤ ⎦ 2 (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">)</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">i∈M 2 ||Ke i (t)|| 2 ≤ ρ 2 λ 2 N N i=1 K ⎡ ⎣ j∈N i δ j (t) -δ i (t) -d i δ i (t) ⎤ ⎦ 2<label>(14)</label></formula><p>with <ref type="formula">15</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">ρ 1 + ρ 2 ≤ ρ and 0 &lt; ρ 1 , ρ 2 &lt; 1. For agents in M 1 , (13) is obviously satisfied if κ i ≤ ρ 1 /λ 2 N . For agents in M 2 , a sufficient condition is ||Ke i (t)|| 2 ≤ ρ 2 λ 2 N N N i=1 K ⎡ ⎣ j∈N i δ j (t) -δ i (t) -d i δ i (t) ⎤ ⎦ 2 = c (H ⊗ K)δ(t) 2 (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">with c = ρ 2 /(λ 2 N N). The evolution time of Ke i (t) / H ⊗ Kδ(t) from 0 to √ c is lower bounded by that of (I N×N ⊗ K)e(t) / H ⊗ Kδ(t) from 0 to √ c. Then one has d dt ||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t)|| ||(H ⊗ K)δ(t)|| = e T (t) I N×N ⊗ K T K ė(t) ||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t)||||(H ⊗ K)δ(t)|| - ||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t)|| δ T (t) H T H ⊗ K T K δ(t) ||(H ⊗ K)δ(t)|| 3 ≤ (||I N×N ⊗ A|| + ||H ⊗ (BK)||) ||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t)|| ||(H ⊗ K)δ(t)|| + ||I N×N ⊗ (KB)|| + (||I N×N ⊗ A|| + ||H ⊗ (BK)||) ||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t)|| ||(H ⊗ K)δ(t)|| + H 2 ⊗ (KB) ||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t)|| 2 ||(H ⊗ K)δ(t)|| 2 = H 2 ⊗ (KB) ||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t)|| 2 ||(H ⊗ K)δ(t)|| 2 + 2(||I N×N ⊗ A|| + ||H ⊗ (BK)||) ||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t)|| ||(H ⊗ K)δ(t)|| + ||I N×N ⊗ (KB)||. (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">) Let φ(t) = (||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t))||/||(H ⊗ K)δ(t)||), we obtain φ(t) ≤ ψ(t, ψ 0 )</formula><p>which is the solution of the following equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">dψ dt = p 0 ψ 2 + 2p 1 ψ + p 2 ; ψ(t, ψ 0 ) = ψ 0 (<label>17</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">)</formula><p>where </p><formula xml:id="formula_30">p 0 = ||H 2 ⊗ (KB)||, p 1 = ||I N×N ⊗ A|| + ||H ⊗ (BK)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_31">√ c, that implies ψ(τ, 0) = √ c and t i k+1 -t i k ≥ τ. Case 1: If p 2 1 = p 0 p 2 , then τ = ( √ cp 1 / √ cp 0 p 1 + p 2 1 ). Case 2: If p 2 1 &lt; p 0 p 2 , then τ = (1/ √ ιp 0 ) [arctan (( √ c/ √ ι) + (p 1 /p 0 √ ι))-arctan ((p 1 /p 0 √ ι))] with ι = (p 2 p 0 -p 2 1 )/p 0 . Case 3: If p 2 1 &gt; p 0 p 2 , then τ = (1/2p 0 √ -ι) ln |( √ cp 0 + p 1 -p 0 √ -ι)(p 1 + p 0 √ -ι)/( √ cp 0 + p 1 + p 0 √ -ι)(p 1 -p 0 √ -ι)|.</formula><p>Hence, for agents in M 2 (t), the event time interval can be chosen as τ i ≤ τ , which leads to (15) can be guaranteed.</p><p>Thus it can be concluded that V(t) &lt; 0 if δ i (t) = 0. That implies all followers x i (t) → x 0 (t) (i = 1, 2, . . . , N) as t goes to infinity. Therefore, the leader-following consensus can be achieved.</p><p>Remark 2: Comparing with the static consensus law in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, the protocol in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">6</ref>) is considered to be a dynamic one. To be specific, the static consensus control in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> is chosen to be a constant based</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">on xi (t) = x i (t i k ), i = 1, . . . , N until a new updated sig- nal is received. Despite the protocol in (6) depends on x i (t i k ) when t ∈ [t i k , t i k+1 ), it varies with xi (t) = exp(A(t -t i k ))x i (t i k ).</formula><p>In fact, previous static control laws are not suitable for our issue. In this section, the matrix A in systems ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">2</ref>) may allow to have roots with positive real parts, which means that the system could be unstable even diverging. Thus if ẽi = x i (t)x i (t i k ) is chosen instead of (4), then it will lead to a great increase in number of event triggered due to that <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> is much easier to satisfy. Furthermore, it is noted that when our system degenerate to a special case with A = 0, our control scheme will be similar to those in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. Therefore, our control scheme has a wide range of application.</p><p>Remark 3: This ETS is built to lower significant the frequency of control update. Moreover, we find a very interesting phenomenon that the leader only needs to transmit its information to its neighbors once to guarantee the leaderfollowing consensus. Actually, the followers linked with the leader can estimate accurately the leader's all states x 0 (t) = exp(A(tt 0 ))x(t 0 ) based on its some state x(t 0 ) since the leader has no control input. In this scenario, the ETS (5), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">7</ref>) is effective to guarantee all followers to track the leader.</p><p>Remark 4: Inspired by Fan et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, we design a distributed-ETS for general linear multiagent system to reduce the energy and cost of control update, where both event-based condition and consensus protocol are distributed. Note that our designed distributed-ETS not only guarantees asymptotical leader-following consensus, but excludes Zeno behavior. As compared with <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, our system is more general and involves a leader, which leads to a more challenging theoretical analysis. Moreover, we will propose two other kinds of ETSs with weak restrictions on topology in the following sections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CENTRALIZED EVENT-TRIGGERED CONTROL OVER JOINTLY-CONNECTED TOPOLOGY</head><p>In the previous section, we have designed a distributed-ETS for a special topology including a spanning tree with the leader as the root vertex. In this section, leader-following system over switching topologies will be considered where each topology may be disconnected. In this scenario, a diverse controller will be proposed.</p><p>In this section, the topology here is switching, to be specific, the topologies of the considered leader-following system vary with time. Let { Ḡp |p ∈ P} to be all possible topologies on nodes which include the leader node 0 and all follower nodes 1, 2, . . . , n. Correspondingly, the set {G p |p ∈ P} means all topologies over all follower nodes 1, 2, . . . , n. The switching signal is defined as σ (t) : [0, ∞) → P to determine the topology Ḡσ(t) at t. Obviously, σ (t) is a piece-wise function, which implies that matrices L σ (t) and D σ (t) are time-varying.</p><p>For clear discussion, we further specify the switching topology. Consider an infinite sequence of bounded, nonoverlapping and continuous time intervals [T m , T m+1 ), (m = 0, 1, 2, . . .), and T 0 = 0. Let T m+1 -T m ≤ α m with some positive constant α m . Assume that for each pair of [T m , T m+1 ), there exists a sequence of nonoverlapping, continuous subintervals</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">T 0 m , T 1 m , . . . , T i m , T i+1 m , . . . , T s m -1 m , T s m m</formula><p>with T m = T 0 m and T m+1 = T s m m for some positive integer s m . We suppose that there exists a dwell time τ &gt; 0 satisfying T i+1 m -T i m ≥ τ , m = 0, 1, 2, . . . , and i = 0, 1, . . . , s m -1. The topology only switches at time instants {T 0 0 , T 1 0 , . . . , T i m , T i+1 m , . . .}, namely, the switching topology is fixed in each time subinterval [T i m , T i+1 m ). Here, each graph Ḡσ(t) could be disconnected.</p><p>Assumption 2: All the eigenvalues of A have no positive real part eigenvalues.</p><p>Assumption 3: There exists a positive matrix P satisfying (3) and A T P + PA ≤ 0 with α = (1 -λ 2 max β)η/2, β &lt; 1/(λ max ) 2 and λ max = max{λ p N |p ∈ P} and η = min{the smallest eigenvalue of s i=1 H p s |∪ i=1,...,s Ḡp i is connected and p i ∈ P}. Note that the parameter η can be determined by using an exhaustive search method <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>.</p><p>A centralized event-triggered consensus protocol is designed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">u i (t) = K N j=1 a ij (t) xj (t) -xi (t) + d i (t) x0 (t) -xi (t) (<label>18</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">)</formula><p>where K = B T P and P is a positive definite matrix to be designed in the following. Thus</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">δ(t) = (I N×N ⊗ A)δ(t) + H σ (t) ⊗ BK (e(t) + δ(t)). (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">)</formula><p>Besides, the triggering time sequence {t k } is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">t k+1 = inf t &gt; t k : ||(I N×N ⊗ K)e(t)|| 2 &gt; β|| H σ (t) ⊗ K x(t) -D σ (t) ⊗ K (I N ⊗ x 0 (t))|| 2 . (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">)</formula><p>Remark 5: It should be noted that the centralized eventtriggered protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> depends on the local information. Here centralized means all agents share a common event-triggered time sequence, that is, all followers update their information together. IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON CYBERNETICS Theorem 2: Consider the leader-following multiagent system (1), (2), we assume that the communication topology is jointly-connected during every time interval [T m , T m+1 ), (m = 0, 1, 2, . . .), under the centralized event-triggered protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> and event-based condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>, the leader-following consensus can be achieved if Assumptions 1-3 hold. In addition, Zeno behavior can be excluded.</p><p>Proof: Consider a common Lyapunov function</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">V(t) = N i=1 δ T i (t)Pδ i (t). During t ∈ [t k , t k+1</formula><p>), the following cases occur.</p><p>Case A: If the topology keeps fixed during [t k , t k+1 ), we assume that the subgraph p ∈ P is activated at a time t, then m , t k+1 ), when the corresponding topologies are Ḡp and Ḡp+1 . The topology changes before the next event time, hence there are two cases that may happen.</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">V(t) = N i=1 δ T i (t) A T P + PA δ i (t) + ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ N i=1 δ T i (t)2PBK j∈N i a ij (t) xj (t k ) -xi (t k ) + d i (t) x0 (t k ) -xi (t k ) ⎫ ⎬ ⎭ = δ T (t) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA -H p ⊗ 2PBB T P δ(t) -δ T (t) H p ⊗ 2PBB T P e(t) ≤ δ T (t) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA -H p ⊗ PBB T P δ(t) + e T (t) H p ⊗ PBB T P e(t) ≤ δ T (t) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA -H p ⊗ PBB T P δ(t) + δ T (t) λ p N 2 βH p ⊗ PBB T P δ(t) ≤ δ T (t) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA -1 -λ p N 2 β H p ⊗ PBB T P δ(t) ≤ δ T (t) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA -1 -(λ max ) 2 β H p ⊗ PBB T P δ(t) ≤ 0.</formula><p>1) "Asynchronous event-trigger and switching," when the topology switches from Ḡp to a new graph Ḡp+1 , the event condition also holds, then no further action is required. In this case, we study</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">V(t) during [t k , T j 0 m ) and [T j 0 m , t k+1 ), respectively. Obviously, V(t) ≤ 0 holds when t ∈ [t k , T j 0 m ) and [T j 0 m , t k+1 ).</formula><p>2) "Synchronous event-trigger and switching," the change of topology leads to that event-triggered condition is violated, then the event condition is triggered, and also this switching time instant will be a new event time, namely t k+1 = T j 0 m , thus it turns to case A. Moreover, the discussion is similar when the topology switches finite times at time interval [t k , t k+1 ).</p><p>Hence V(t) is nonincreasing and lower bounded, which implies that V(t) exists as t → ∞. By the Cauchy's convergence criteria, for any ε &gt; 0, there exists T(ε) &gt; 0 such that |V(T m+1 ) -V(T m )| &lt; ε for all T m &gt; T(ε). In other words</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">T m+1 T m V(s)ds &gt; -ε<label>(21)</label></formula><p>which can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">T 1 m T 0 m V(s) ds + T 2 m T 1 m V(s) ds + • • • + T s k m T sm-1 m V(s) ds &gt; -ε namely, T i+1 m T i m V(s) ds &gt; -ε since s k is finite.</formula><p>According to Theorem 1, we can conclude that the eventtriggered condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> is at most triggered finite times during every time interval [T i m , T i+1 m ), by additivity of integration on intervals, thus</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">-ε &lt; T i+1 m T i m V(s) ds &lt; T i+1 m T i m δ T (s) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA -1 -(λ max ) 2 β H σ (T i m ) ⊗ PBB T P δ(s) ds &lt; T i m + τ T i m δ T (s) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA -1 -(λ max ) 2 β H σ (T i m ) ⊗ PBB T P δ(s) ds, i = 0, 1, 2, . . . , s m -1. Hence lim t→∞ t+ τ t δ T (s) I n×n ⊗ A T P + PA -1 -(λ max ) 2 β H σ (T i m ) ⊗ PBB T P δ(s) ds = 0 i = 1, 2, . . . , s m -1. One has lim t→∞ t+ τ t δ T (s) I N×N ⊗ (A T P + PA) δ(s) ds -lim t→∞ t+ τ t δ(s) 1 -(λ max ) 2 β × H σ (T 0 m ) ⊗ PBB T P δ(s) ds + • • • + • • • + lim t→∞ t+ τ t δ T (s) I N×N ⊗ (A T P + PA) δ(s) ds + lim t→∞ t+ τ t δ(s) 1 -(λ max ) 2 β × H σ T sm-1 m ⊗ PBB T P δ(s) ds = 0.</formula><p>Since the graphs are jointly-connected during [T m , T m+1 ) for m = 0, 1, . . . , then</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">H σ (T 0 m ) + H σ (T 1 m ) + • • • + H σ T sm-1 m &gt; 0. Thus 0 = lim t→∞ t+ τ t s m δ T (s) I N×N ⊗ A T P + PA δ(s) ds -lim t→∞ t+ τ t δ T (s) 1 -(λ max ) 2 β × H σ (T 0 m ) + H σ (T 1 m ) + • • • + H σ T sm-1 m ⊗ PBB T P δ(s) ds ≤ lim t→∞ t+ τ t s m n i=1 δ T i (s)(A T P + PA)δ i (s) - n i=1 δ T i (s) 1 -λ 2 max β ηPB T BPδ i (s) ds = lim t→∞ t+ τ t s m n i=1 δ T i (s) A T P + PA -1 -λ 2 max β ηPB T BP δ i (s) ds (22) ≤ -1 -λ 2 max β η/2 lim t→∞ t+ τ t N i=1 δ T i (s)δ i (s) ds (23) ≤ 0. (<label>24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_47">)</formula><p>Due to the fact that lim t→+∞ V(t) exists, δ(t) is bounded and so is δ(t) by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_36">19</ref>). Therefore, one has lim t→∞ N i=1 δ T i (t)δ i (t) = 0, which implies lim t→∞ δ i (t) = 0. Furthermore, due to the fact that the switching topology may lead to event triggering, there is no lower bound for event intervals. However, we also can conclude that Zeno behavior can be excluded due to the switching dwell time of topology τ &gt; 0.</p><p>Remark 6: It is noted that the set { Ḡp |p ∈ P} is a known finite set, thus it implies that λ max exists. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40,</ref><ref type="bibr">Lemma 2]</ref>, the upper bound of λ max can be estimated.</p><p>Remark 7: In general, the event-triggered frequency are dependent on λ N . If λ N is very large, then β will be very small. As a result, (20) may be much easier to satisfy so that the frequency of event trigger will increases. On the contrary, a sufficient small λ N will lead to the low frequency of event trigger.</p><p>Remark 8: This section studies a switching topology, and the switching frequency is not allowed to be too fast since we require T j+1 m -T j m &gt; τ for i = 0, 1, . . . , s m -1, m = 0, 1, . . . . Another condition for the switching frequency is T m+1 -T m &lt; α m . In practice, τ and α m can be chosen and adjusted in accordance with the practical need and no further requirement is imposed in this paper.</p><p>Remark 9: Theorem 2 studies that how to trigger the event condition over switching topology. As shown in the above discussion, the topology variation is time-based and no other event is assigned to it. However, when to update control information depends on event condition, thus this will lead to two time sequence: 1) topology switching time sequence and 2) event-triggered time sequence. One may ask whether both time sequences are the same or they have different time instances of occurrences. In fact, the issues have been solved in the proof of Theorem 2. In this section, we do not have any requirement for the relation between these two time sequences. The topology variation is arbitrary but its rate is not allowed to be too quick (the switching interval is less than an upper bound, see Remark 8) and be too slow (a lower bound is set). In addition, the event-triggered time sequence is a set of time points when the event condition is violated. If the change of the topology leads to that the event condition is violated, then this switching time instant will be event time point. If not, topology switching has no effect on event triggers.</p><p>Remark 10: In <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, the general switching network case for a system has been investigated. However, two kinds of significant improvement have been made in this paper. First, event-triggered consensus protocol is used in this paper while continuous information transmission and control updated is needed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. Thus our control scheme can lower the cost and save more energy. Second, an assumption was imposed for the system in <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> that the matrix A has no positive real part eigenvalues, but there is no such requirement in this paper and covers a more general systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CLUSTERED EVENT-TRIGGERED CONTROLLER OVER TOPOLOGY WITH DISCONNECTED SUBGRAPH</head><p>Distributed-and centralized-ETSs have been discussed, respectively, in Sections III and IV based on two different network topologies. In this section, we will propose a novel ETS, which neither require that each follower independently determines its own event-triggered time sequence nor need that all followers share common event-triggered signals. Thus clustered-ETS is considered as an excellent approach which has mixed features of distributed-and centralized-ETS.</p><p>In this section, graph Ḡ is fixed and subgraph G among followers is assumed to be disconnected. Thus they can classified as several connected components and each component is considered as a cluster (group or family).</p><p>For convenient discussion, we suppose that N followers have been classified into m independent clusters, namely, there is no information exchange between two different clusters.</p><p>Then we reorder the followers by using elementary matrix U to</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">U -1 LU = ⎛ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎝ L 1 0 0 • • • 0 0 L 2 0 • • • 0 . . . . . . . . . • • • . . . 0 0 0 • • • L m ⎞ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ ⎠ . (<label>25</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">)</formula><p>The graph G among followers has m connected components and L i is the Laplace matrix of the i connected component. Correspondingly, we let y(t) = Ux(t) with y(t) = (y T  11 , y T 12 , . . . , y T 1l 1 , y T 21 , . . . , y T 2l 2 , . . . , y T ml m ) T and</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">l 1 + l 2 +• • •+ l m = N.</formula><p>When follower i belongs to cluster c, c = 1, 2, . . . , m, then we define</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">e i (t) = exp A(t -t c k ) y i (t c k ) -y i (t). (<label>26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">) IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON CYBERNETICS</formula><p>Then a new event-triggered condition is presented which is of the following form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">e c (t) 2 ≤ β c (H c ⊗ K c )Y c (t) -(D c ⊗ K c ) I l c ⊗ x 0 (t) 2<label>(27)</label></formula><p>where e c = (e T c1 , e T l c2 , . . . , e T cl c ) T with</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">H c = L c + D c , Y c = (y T c1 , y T c2 , . . . , y T cl c ) T , and D c = diag{d c1 , d c2 , . . . , d cl c }.</formula><p>If follower i can receive the information of the leader,</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">d i = 1, otherwise d i = 0.</formula><p>Similarly, we define</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">ŷi (t) = exp A t -t c k y i t c k , y ∈ t c k , t c k+1 .<label>(28)</label></formula><p>Moreover, the clustered event-triggered consensus protocol is designed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">u i (t) = K c j∈N i a ij ŷj (t) -ŷi (t) + d i ŷ0 (t) -ŷi (t)<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where K c = B T P c with a positive definite matrix P c to be designed later.</p><p>Remark 11: This clustered-ETS is a novel information transmission and control scheme and could be regarded as a mixed feature among distributed and centralized schemes in some specific situations. That controller implies that followers in the same cluster share a common event-triggered conditions and they will update their information together, but will not be affected by agents in other clusters.</p><p>Theorem 3: Consider the leader-following multiagent system (1), (2), we assume that there is at least a follower in each cluster that can received the information from the leader. Under the clustered event-triggered protocol (29) and clustered event-based condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>, the leader-following consensus can be achieved if Assumption 1 and β c &lt; 1/(λ c N ) 2 for all c = 1, 2 . . . , m. In addition, Zeno behavior can be avoided under cluster-ETS <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>.</p><p>Proof:</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">Let δ i (t) = y i (t) -x 0 (t). Consider the Lyapunov function V(t) = n i=1 δ T i (t)P c δ i (t), P c satisfies (3) with α = (1 -(λ c N ) 2 β c )λ c 1 /2 c = 1, 2, . . . , m. Let c = (δ T l c-1 +1 , δ T l c-1 +2 , . . . , δ T l c ) T , c = 1, 2, . . . , m. Then V(t) = N i=1 δ T i (t) A T P c + P c A δ i (t) + ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ N i=1 δ i (t)2P c BK c j∈N i a ij δ j (t) -δ i (t) + e j (t) -e i (t) -d i (δ i (t) + e i (t)) ⎫ ⎬ ⎭ ≤ m c=1 T c (t) I l c ×l c ⊗ A T P c + P c A -H c ⊗ P c BB T P c c (t) + m c=1 e T c (t) H c ⊗ P c BB T P c e c (t) ≤ - m c=1 1 -λ c N 2 β c λ c 1 /2 T c (t) c (t).</formula><p>Thus V(t) &lt; 0 if c (t) = 0, which implies that as t goes to infinity, c (t) → 0 for all c = 1, 2, . . . , m. In other words, lim t→∞ (y i (t)x 0 (t)) = 0, i = 1, 2, . . . , N. Moreover, similar to Theorem 1, we conclude that for each cluster c, there exists τ c &gt; 0 such that t c k+1 -t c k &gt; τ c . Therefore, for all agents, Zeno behavior can be excluded. The proof is completed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. EXCLUDE CONTINUOUS COMMUNICATION</head><p>In this section, we will propose two methods to avoid continuous communication between agents for event detection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Method I</head><p>In order to determine the next event instant t i k+1 of agent i, the event detector of agent i needs to acquire its neighbors' information when their control protocols are updated. Hence, for agent j ∈ N i , only the information of {t j k , x j (t j k ), q j (t j k )} and {t l k , x j (t l k ), q j (t l k )} (l ∈ N j ) are sent to detect the event condition of agent i, which can avoid continuous communication between agents for event detection. Here q j (t j k ) is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">q j t j k = p∈N j xp t j k -xj t j k + d j x0 t j k -xj t j k . (<label>30</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_60">)</formula><p>To better illustrate this point, we will explain: 1) when the control protocol of agent j is updated and 2) how to use information of {t j k , x j (t j k ), q j (t j k )} and {t l k , x j (t l k ), q j (t l k )} to avoid continuous communication between agents for event detection.</p><p>The control protocol of agent j is updated in the following two cases.</p><p>Case (a): The control protocol of agent j is updated at its own triggering instants.</p><p>Step 1: Suppose that agent j triggers at time t j k , it means that agent j updates the value of its control protocol at time t j k and sends {t j k , x j (t j k ), q j (t k j )} to all its neighbors immediately.</p><p>Step 2: From step 1, each agent j ∈ N i sends trigger information to agent i whenever agent j triggers at time t j k , then agent i collects these information x j (t j k ) and q j (t j k ) at time t j k . Hence agent i can compute agent j's state at time t &gt; t j k (without continuous communication between agents i and j) by <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref> until agent i receives information of agent j. Note that t j k is the triggering instant of agent j in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">x j (t) = exp A t -t j k x j t j k + exp(At) t t j k exp(-As)BK exp A s -t j k q j t j k</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case (b):</head><p>The control protocol of agent j will be updated at its neighbors' triggering instants as well.</p><p>Step 1: Suppose that agent l( = i) is a neighbor of agent j. It triggers at time t l k and sends {t l k , x l (t l k ), q l (t l k )} to agent j so that the control protocol of agent j is updated by using the newest information of agent l according to the definition of q j . Then agent j sends the newest information of {t l k , x j (t l k ), q j (t l k )} to its neighbors' event detectors.</p><p>Step 2: From step 1, each agent j ∈ N i sends information to the event detector of agent i whenever agent j's control protocol updates at time t l k , (l ∈ N j ), then agent i's detector collects these information x j (t l k ) and q j (t l k ) at time t l k . Hence agent i can compute agent j's state at time t &gt; t l k (without continuous communication between agents i and j) by</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">x j (t) = exp A t -t l k x j t l k + exp(At) t t l k exp(-As)BK exp A s -t l k q j t l k (32)</formula><p>until agent i receives information of agent j. Note that t l k (l ∈ N j ) is the triggering instant of agent j's neighbors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>. Remark 12: From method I, the control protocol of agent j will be updated at its own triggering instants and its neighbors' triggering instants. Note that, the triggering of agent l's neighbors will have no effect on the control protocol of agent j. Thus, the triggering of neighbors' neighbors of agent j will not have further effect on the control protocol of agent j. In conclusion, it is impossible that all agents will update their own control protocols when one agent triggers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Method II</head><p>According to distributed event time instants determined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, the event detection is not required to continuously execute.</p><p>To be specific, assume that agent i triggers its information at t i k , then the event detection is not required during time interval (t i k , t i k + τ i ] according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. Thus agent i does not need to receive its neighbors' information during (t i k , t i k + τ i ]. The activity of event detection starts from time t i k + τ i until agent i's next triggering instant t i k+1 . Therefore, agent i does not get continuous access to its neighbor j's state and the frequency of information transmission also has been reduced by this algorithm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. SIMULATIONS</head><p>In this section, some examples will be given to illustrate the effectiveness of our designed ETSs over different network topologies.</p><p>Example 1: Consider a system with a leader and four followers where</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">A = ⎡ ⎣ 0.003 1 0 -1 0.001 0 0 0 -2 ⎤ ⎦ ; B = ⎡ ⎣ 0.1 0.2 0.1 ⎤ ⎦<label>(33)</label></formula><p>where the eigenvalues of A are -2, 0.002 + 0.9999i, and 0.002 -0.9999i, which implies that they are not required to be in the closed left plane. The topology is fixed and has a spanning tree with the leader as the root vertex (see Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>). We choose κ 1 = 0.060, κ 2 = 0.055, κ 3 = 0.050, κ 4 = 0.045, γ 1 = 0.8, γ 1 = 0.1, τ 1 = 0.05, τ 2 = 0.04, τ 3 = 0.03, and τ 4 = 0.02. From Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, under our distributed-ETS ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">6</ref>), all followers can asymptotically track the leader. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TABLE I EVENT TIME INTERVALS FOR EACH FOLLOWER</head><p>Moreover, Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows event-triggered time instant for each follower during [6 s, 9 s]. The numbers of event trigger are totally 847, 925, 1043, and 1137 times, respectively, during [0 s, 50 s] and the mean time interval (s) is 0.0590, 0.0541, 0.0479, and 0.0440, which are presented in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>. The distributed-ETS reduces substantially the frequency of information transmission and control updated compared with that without event-triggered case (see Table <ref type="table">I</ref>).</p><p>Example 2: Consider a system</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">A = ⎡ ⎣ 0 1 0 -1 0 0 0 0 -2 ⎤ ⎦ ; B = ⎡ ⎣ 0.1 0.2 0.1 ⎤ ⎦<label>(34)</label></formula><p>with a switching topology, where the system dynamics is same with that in Example 1. The topology switches among graphs IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON CYBERNETICS { Ḡ1 , Ḡ2 , Ḡ3 } and obviously, Ḡ1 , Ḡ2 , and Ḡ3 are not connected, but Ḡ1 ∪ Ḡ2 ∪ Ḡ3 has a spanning tree (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). The switching signal is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">σ (t) = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ 1 if 3k ≤ t &lt; 3k + 1 2 if 3k + 1 ≤ t &lt; 3k + 2 3 if 3k + 2 ≤ t &lt; 3k + 3.<label>(35)</label></formula><p>In this case, we design a centralized-ETS <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. Under this controller, all followers can reach the same state with leader, i.e., followers can track the leader finally (see Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</p><p>In this example, all followers share an event-triggered condition and the event-triggered time during [40 s, 45 s] is displayed in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>. The number of event trigger is 250 times during time interval [0 s, 100 s] and the mean time interval (s) is 0.4. Hence, this centralized event trigger protocol is effective to reach leader-following consensus with switching and jointly connected topologies. Moreover, the centralized-ETS lowers significantly the cost of information transmission and control protocol's update as compared with that without event-triggered case (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>). Example 3: An example with a leader and five followers is considered here, whose dynamics is defined as <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref>. The system topology is shown as Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">7</ref>, moreover, we can see its subgraph G among followers is disconnected and thus it can be divided into two connected components which are called clusters I and II. Cluster I contains followers 1 and 2 and cluster II includes followers 3-5.    In addition, we choose β 1 = 0.0208 and β 2 = 0.05. In this case, each cluster shares a common event condition, hence two different event-triggered protocols (29) are used here. From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref>, the leader-following consensus can be reached under the clustered-ETS. In addition, event conditions are triggered 92 times for followers in cluster I and 326 times for followers in cluster II during [0 s, 30 s]. Their mean time intervals are 0.326 and 0.092 respectively. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9</ref> presents the event time for each cluster during the time interval [4 s, 9 s]. It is clearly displayed that the clustered-ETS has significantly low number of event trigger for information transmission and control update compared with that without event-triggered case. Remark 13: In Example 3, if we use distributed-ETS, then each agent is assigned one detector, consequently it may lead to rather high cost to verify conditions. Its advantage lies in the fact that each agent independently determines its event time sequence by receiving its neighbors' information. If the centralized-ETS is used, only one detector is needed and hence the cost is low. However, in this case, it is necessary for the detector to receive all agents' information to determine the next event instant. This may lead to information congestion or information overload especially in large-scale networks. As for clustered-ETS, each cluster share a common detector and the event detection requires the information of followers in a cluster. It has a lower cost for detector as compared with distributed-ETS, and mitigate the risk of information congestion as compared with centralized-ETS. In general, we prefer to use the clustered ETS which is a mixture of distributedand centralized-ETSs, and have the advantages of both ETSs. To better present the features of three kinds of ETSs, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">II</ref> is provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VIII. CONCLUSION</head><p>This paper has studied a leader-following consensus problem in multiagent systems with general linear dynamics. Three different types of ETSs, namely distributed-, centralized-, and clustered-ETS, form a framework and have been investigated over different network topologies. They are effective to guarantee that all followers can track the leader ultimately on the one hand and reduce the frequency of information transmission and control updating on the other hand. Moreover, the positive inner-event time intervals have been assured for these three kinds of ETSs. Furthermore, we propose two methods to avoid continuous communication between agents for event detection.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>||, and p 2 = ||I N×N ⊗ (KB)||. Furthermore, Zeno behavior can be avoided.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Case B: If the topology switches at T j 0 m</head><label>0</label><figDesc>, whereT j 0 m ∈ [t k , t k+1 ) and keeps fixed during [t k , T j 0 m ) and [T j 0</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .Fig. 3 .</head><label>123</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Fixed topology.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .Fig. 5 .</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Switching topology.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Event time for all followers under centralized-ETS.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Fix topology that has a disconnect subgraph among followers.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. States trajectory of a leader and five followers under clustered-ETS.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Event time for each cluster under clustered-ETS.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE II CHARACTERISTICS</head><label>II</label><figDesc>OF DISTRIBUTED-, CENTRALIZED-,</figDesc><table /><note><p>AND CLUSTERED-ETSS</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the Research Grants Council of Hong Kong Special Administrative Region under Grant GRF CityU 11204514, in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under Grant no. 61573096 and 61503115, and in part by the 333 Engineering Foundation of Jiangsu Province of China under Grant no. BRA2015286. This paper was recommended by Associate Editor X.-M. Sun.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Wenying Xu received the M.S. degree in applied mathematics from Southeast University, Nanjing, China, in 2014. She is currently pursuing the Ph.D. degree with the Department of Mathematics, City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong.</p><p>Her current research interests include eventtriggered control, multiagent systems, and bifurcation analysis.</p><p>Ms. Xu was a recipient of the Outstanding Master Degree Thesis Award from Jiangsu Province, China, in 2015. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus and cooperation in networked multi-agent systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Olfati-Saber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fax</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-01">Jan. 2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="233" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed synchronization in networks of agent systems with nonlinearities and random switchings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kurths</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="370" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-02">Feb. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On controllability of neuronal networks with constraints on the average of control gains</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kurths</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2670" to="2681" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pinning impulsive stabilization of nonlinear dynamical networks with time-varying delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W C</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kurths</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Bifurcat. Chaos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 1250176</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new framework for analysis on stability and bifurcation in a class of neural networks with discrete and distributed delays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W C</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2224" to="2236" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-10">Oct. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed coordination architecture for multi-robot formation control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Robot. Auton. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="324" to="333" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A bridging model for parallel computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Valiant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new protocol for finite-time consensus of detail-balanced multi-agent networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ID 043134</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chaos Interdiscipl. J. Nonlin. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus tracking of multi-agent systems with Lipschitz-type node dynamics and switching topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Circuits Syst. I, Reg. Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-02">Feb. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some necessary and sufficient conditions for second-order consensus in multi-agent dynamical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1089" to="1095" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus in multi-agent systems with communication constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robust Nonlin. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leader-following consensus of nonlinear multi-agent systems with jointly connected topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Control Theory Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="432" to="440" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A unified approach to practical consensus with quantized data and time delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W C</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Circuits Syst. I, Reg. Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2668" to="2678" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-10">Oct. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantized h ∞ control for nonlinear stochastic time-delay systems with missing measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1431" to="1444" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">Jun. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synchronization of coupled neutral-type neural networks with jumping-mode-dependent discrete and unbounded distributed delays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-02">Feb. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">M-matrix strategies for pinningcontrolled leader-following consensus in multiagent systems with nonlinear dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1688" to="1697" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-12">Dec. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust synchronization of multiple memristive neural networks with uncertain parameters via nonlinear coupling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst., Man, Cybern., Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1077" to="1086" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-07">Jul. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Second-order consensus in multi-agent dynamical systems with sampled position data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1496" to="1503" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sampled-data based consensus of continuous-time multi-agent systems with time-varying topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1226" to="1231" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-05">May 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus of multi-agent systems with nonlinear dynamics and sampled data information: A delayed-input approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robust Nonlin. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="602" to="619" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-triggered real-time scheduling of stabilizing control tasks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tabuada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1680" to="1685" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-09">Sep. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-triggering in distributed networked control systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lemmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="586" to="601" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-03">Mar. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event based pulse-modulated control of linear stochastic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2144" to="2150" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-08">Aug. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-triggered output feedback control for networked control systems using passivity: Achieving L2 stability in the presence of communication delays and signal quantization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Antsaklis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Event-Triggered Feedback in Control, Estimation, and Optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lemmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London, U.K.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-triggered state estimation for complex networks with mixed time delays via sampled data information: The continuous-time case</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2804" to="2815" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">Dec. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-triggered robust distributed state estimation for sensor networks with state-dependent noises</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Alsaadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Gen. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="254" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A distributed event-triggered scheme for discrete-time multi-agent consensus with communication delays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W C</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Control Theory Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="830" to="837" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-07">Jul. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed event-triggered control of multi-agent systems with combinational measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="675" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-based broadcasting for multi-agent average consensus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Seyboth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Dimarogonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="252" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event based agreement protocols for multi-agent networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2125" to="2132" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed event-triggered control for multi-agent systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Dimarogonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Frazzoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1291" to="1297" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-05">May 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Average sampled-data consensus driven by edge events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 31th Chin</title>
		<meeting>31th Chin<address><addrLine>Hefei, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-07">Jul. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6239" to="6244" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Output synchronization of networked passive systems with event-driven communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Antsaklis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="750" to="756" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-03">Mar. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized event-triggered consensus with general linear dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Casbeer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2633" to="2640" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semi-global leader-following consensus of linear multi-agent systems with input saturation via low gain feedback</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Z Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Circuits Syst. I, Reg. Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1881" to="1889" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-07">Jul. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leader-following consensus of multi-agent systems under fixed and switching topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="217" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-triggered consensus for multi-agent systems with Zeno-free triggers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2779" to="2784" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-10">Oct. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extreme properties of eigenvalues of a hermitian transformation and singular values of the sum and product of linear transformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Amir-Moéz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Duke Math. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="463" to="476" />
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive second-order consensus of networked mobile agents with nonlinear dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="368" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
