<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Integrating Culture into Interface Design</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Julie</forename><surname>Khaslavsky</surname></persName>
							<email>dgatsby@leland.stanford.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Communications Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Integrating Culture into Interface Design</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BAF1596AB5922A3A13EB2B55F7825E02</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T02:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>international interfaces</term>
					<term>localization</term>
					<term>mental models</term>
					<term>user models</term>
					<term>conceptual design</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this paper, I describe how culture impacts usability and design, present a package of variables for identifying cultural differences, and give localization suggestions. I also present ideas for research leading to specific guidelines for integrating culture into design KEYWORDS</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>In today's increasingly global market, many designers are faced with the task of insuring that their products are equally as usable in foreign countries as in the United States.</p><p>Given the impact that culture has on people's behavior, truly intuitive international software should reflect the cultural orientation of its users and not just be a translation of an American interface. Conceptual localization that snugly fits a user's culturally specific mental model of the software with its functionality, feedback, and support for learning is a much more effective way to design software for international use.</p><p>While the concept of mental modeling has become a standard buzz word for interfacedesign, it is unclear how culture impacts the user's mental model and learning process. Further research is needed to determine the impact of culture on interface perception and modeling to set a standard practice for software design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Past Research</head><p>Although there have been many formal studies illustrating the success of conceptual design and mental models, none of them have been cross-cultural. Most previous crosscultural computer research has focused on questionnaires about technology attitudes and anxiety levels and hasn't provided any behavioral data. So far, there has been only one study, conducted recently in Australia, that evaluated culturally motivated design preferences, beliefs about system usefulness, perception of system ease of use, attitude of satisfaction using, and overall acceptance through a questionnaire survey of Australian versus Asian users.</p><p>Preliminary findings of this first pilot study revealed differences between several intercultural groups. For example, Chinese users heavily based software acceptance on beliefs about its usefulness, Indonesians were more motivated by perceptions of the system's ease of use, and Australians were most satisfied by interfaces that fit their overall design preferences.This suggests that the Chinese are more willing to work with a useful yet difficult interface, Indonesians have lower tolerance for usability problems, and for Australians appearance is a big factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[2]</ref>.</p><p>Most commercial international interface design literature outlines very limited culturally oriented techniques for improving localization and focuses on techniques for simplifying translation and insuring culturally appropriate icons. Literature that does recommend more in-depth cultural study for successful localization [ 1,4, 81 does not provide extensive information about how cultural models can be applied in a meaningful way to a product's design. Furthermore, while there is substantial literature detailing localization practices for Asian countries, there is no literature detailing software design guidelines for Europe, a major software market. This research would suggest that misunderstandings which occur in intercultural communication between two people are indicative of related misunderstandings between foreign computer users and American designed programs. Even within the U.S., an interfacedesigner's perspective can be very different from the user's due to a vastly differentwork culture, social class, and level of techno-saviness. One can imagine how much wider this perspective gap grows when the culture of another country is thrown into the picture.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CREATING A CULTURE BASED MENTAL MODEL</head><p>I have leveraged the three existing schemas of cultural differentiation <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">9]</ref> to create a package of nine descriptive variables useful for assessing culture and design. These terms are: . Speed of message -speed at which people decode and act on messages <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[5]</ref> .</p><p>Context -amount of information that is in a given communication as a function of the context in which it occurs [S] .</p><p>Personal space <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[5]</ref> .</p><p>Time -linear, one thing at a time (monochronic) or simultaneous, concurrent (polychronic) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[5]</ref> l Power distance -how subordinates respond to power and authority <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[6]</ref> .</p><p>Collectivism (loyalties to group, strong interpersonal ties) vs. Individualism (emphasis on looking out for yourself) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[6]</ref> .</p><p>Uncertaintyavoidance <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[6]</ref> l Diffuse vs. Specific -separation of business and personal relationships <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[9]</ref> .</p><p>Particularism vs. Universalism -rule-based VS. relationship based behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[9]</ref> Design for the European Market</p><p>Most of the past work with cultural models has focused on extending these variables to Asian cultures where communication differences with America are readily apparent. There has not been much work comparing Europe and America due to the presumed similarities between western nations. However, there is good reason to believe that sufficient differencesexist between European nations, such that users from each country will display different culturally motivated problems when interacting with the same application localized only through translation. The table below roughly reflects how America scores on the above variables as opposed to France <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[5]</ref>. It reveals that the culturaldifferences are perhaps much greater than expected.</p><p>Only two of the variables, speed of message and individualism are the same: A comparative study of French and American culture and mental models should reveal many more surprising and significant differences between the two groups that will prove instrumental to understanding the impact of culture on interface design. 2) Culture specific localization is necessary for every country, not just Asia. Hall's Understanding Cultural Differences is especially useful when localizing for Germany and France. A product that looks and acts like it was developed by people from the user's culture can make thedifferencebetweenjust a good product and a really hot seller in the overseas market.</p><p>3) Use the package of variables outlined on the left to drive your search for more information from users. Informal discussions with people from that culture can quickly answer many questions and influence your design. Refer to Heft's article in International User Interfaces[ l] for a good overview of most of these variables. 4) Keep your eye out for emerging studies on intercultural usability that outline specific design implications and fill in the gaps in current research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NEXT STEPS</head><p>The next phase of this project calls for an empirical study in which usability and mental modeling is measured for American vs. French users on a software application. The idea is to select inexperienced users from both countries, videotape them performing specific tasks on a version of the software localized only through translation, follow-up with an interview and a questionnaire, and quantitatively content analyze the videos. Comparison of cross-cultural subjects will be difficult amidst all of the other confounding variables. However, this issue is part of the continuing research in this fairly new and important area.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Culture is a system of shared meanings that form a framework for problem solving and behavior in everyday life. Individuals communicate with each other by assigning meaning to messages based on their prior beliefs, attitudes, and values. Since people from differentcultures often have different beliefs, attitudes, and values, normal human misunderstandings which occur in interactions between people of the same culture are magnified by the wider differences in intercultural interaction. Knowing what kind of information people from other cultures require and in what form is the key to effective communication<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[5]</ref>.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>more in depth conceptual problems with your design when localizing. A much needed feature might be missing for that population. See Nielsen's<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[8]</ref> description of the French LYRE program for a good example of this. Imagine how a program such as Intuit's Quicken which is driven by American individualistic financial values might fare in a collectivist oriented country.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>I would like to thank BJ Fogg, Donald Day, Cliff Nass, and Marina and Ilia Khaslavsky for their invaluable time andencouragement.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of culture in interface acceptance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Evers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Day</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings, 6th IFIP Conference on Human Computer Znteraction</title>
		<meeting>6th IFIP Conference on Human Computer Znteraction<address><addrLine>Sydney, Australia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-07-14">1997. July 14-18</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Femandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Global Interface Design</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Diego</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AP Professional</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Understanding Cultural Differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<publisher>Intercultural Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Maine</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cultures and Organizations. Software of the Mind</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hofstede</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Testing of International User Interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Designing User Interfaces</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jakob</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="45" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Riding the Waves of Culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Trompenaarq</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Understanding the Cultural Diversity in Business</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Nicholas Brealey</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
