<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">An improved edge-based level set method combining local regional fitting information for noisy image segmentation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-06-15">15 June 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cheng</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Beijing Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100044</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Weibin</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<email>wbliu@bjtu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Beijing Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100044</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Weiwei</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Software Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Beijing Jiaotong University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100044</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">An improved edge-based level set method combining local regional fitting information for noisy image segmentation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-06-15">15 June 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FD050841DFAC2023F3B8BC266ABDF2E6</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.sigpro.2016.06.013</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 27 October 2015 Received in revised form 9 March 2016 Accepted 13 June 2016</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T12:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Level set method Image segmentation Variable regional coefficient Edge stop function</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Level set methods (LSMs) have been widely used in image segmentation because of their good properties which provide more smooth and accurate segmentation results. The edge-based LSMs use the gradient information of images through edge stop functions (ESFs) to guide the contour curve approaching to object edges. The traditional edge-based LSMs cannot obtain satisfactory segmentation results for noisy images because their regional coefficients are constant and their ESFs are easily influenced by noises. To solve the problems, this paper analyzes the different properties between noise points and object edge points and uses the local regional properties of images points to distinguish noises and object edge points. Based on the local regional properties, we introduce a variable regional coefficient and an improved ESF to overcome shortcomings of the constant regional coefficient and the traditional ESFs. Then we propose an improved edge-based level set method combining local regional fitting information by applying the proposed variable regional coefficient and the improved ESF to the energy function of level set function. The experimental results show that our method obtains accurate segmentation results for noisy images with insensitive to noises and without missing object edges and prove that the method is efficient and robust.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Image segmentation is of great significance in image processing and computer vision. Various methods have been proposed to solve this problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. In these methods, active contour models (ACMs, also named snake or deformable models) are widely used because of their excellent properties which can provide smooth and accurate segmentation results <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>Kass et al propose the original ACM in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, which is also named parametric ACM. However, it is difficult in handling the topological changes of contour curve since it implements the explicit curve to extract object edges. Osher and Sethian propose the level set method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, in which a contour curve is implicitly represented as the zero level set of a high dimensional function (also called level set function, LSF), and easily handle the topological changes of contour curve in the level set evolution.</p><p>Existing level set methods for image segmentation can be categorized into two groups: edge-based level set methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and region-based level set methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</p><p>Through edge stop functions, edge-based level set methods use the gradient information of images to guarantee the contour curve locating at object edges. Due to using the gradient information as stopping criteria, edge-based level set methods can segment images without any priority of the number of heterogeneous objects. However, the gradient information is sensitive to noises, thus the traditional edge-based level set methods are sensitive to noises. Geodesic active contour (GAC) model proposed by Caselles et al. in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> is a classical edge-based level set method, which uses the intrinsic geometric measure of images to drive the contour curve toward object edges in its segmentation. Distance regularized level set evolution (DRLSE) method proposed by Li et al. in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref> is another classical edge-based level set method, which uses the external energy term to drive the contour curve toward object edges during its evolution.</p><p>Through regional descriptors, region-based level set methods use the regional information of images to guarantee the contour curve locating at object edges. Due to using the regional information as stopping criteria, the region-based level set methods can be insensitive to noises.</p><p>C-V model proposed by Chan and Vese in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> is a classical region-based model, which uses the global regional information to segment images. It can segment the images whose object and background regions have homogeneous intensity but cannot Contents lists available at ScienceDirect journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/sigpro segment the images whose object and background regions have heterogeneous intensity. Local binary fitting (LBF) model proposed by <ref type="bibr">Li et al.</ref> in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> is another classical region-based model, which uses the local region information to segment images. It can segment the images with heterogeneous intensity but is very sensitive to initialization and easily gets stuck into local minima.</p><p>Noise is always inevitably introduced into images through a variety of ways and brings great challenges in image segmentation <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. The major problem of edge-based level set methods for noisy images is that noise may make the contour curve prone to passing through object edges or falling into local minima which lead to unsatisfactory segmentation results.</p><p>When the initialization of contour curve is far away from object edges, it is necessary for edge-based level set methods to use the external force term to guarantee the contour curve converging at object edges <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. For this end, the GAC model introduces a balloon force term to shrink and expand the contour curve <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. And the DRLSE method uses an external energy term including a length energy term and an area energy term to solve it <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. Based on the edge stop function, the length energy term ensures the contour curve has the shortest length, which regularizes the contour curve and makes it smooth; and the area energy term ensures the contour curve has the smallest area, which controls the speed of the contour curve converging to object edges.</p><p>Edge stop functions are essential for edge-based level set methods which guarantee the contour curve locating at object edges; however, the traditional edge stop functions are sensitive to noises since they are merely based on the gradient information. In addition, since the area energy term controls the convergence properties of contour curve, it is not suitable to set its coefficient as a constant in noisy image segmentation, which we will offer a detailed analysis in Section 3.2. Therefore, the traditional edgebased level set methods usually cannot obtain satisfactory segmentation results for noisy images.</p><p>In this paper, we analyze the properties of noise points and object edge points, and use the local regional property to distinguish them. Based on the different local regional properties between them, we propose a variable regional coefficient and an improved edge stop function. The variable regional coefficient solves the problem that the constant regional coefficient may lead the contour curve easily falling into local minima or missing object edges in segmentation of noisy image. The improved edge stop function overcomes the shortcoming that the traditional edge stop functions are easily influenced by noises. By applying the variable regional coefficient and the improved edge stop function to the energy function of level set function, we propose an improved edge-based level set method combining local regional fitting information to better segment noisy images. The experimental results show that our method obtains accurate segmentation results for noisy images with insensitive to noises and without missing object edges, which prove the robustness and the effectiveness of our method to noises.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Principle of level set method</head><p>Based on the curve evolution theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, the evolution equation of curve can be expressed as ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">( ) ∂ ∂ = → = = ( ) ( ) ⎧ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ ⎪ C p t t FN C p t C p , , 0 1 0 where ∈ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ p 0, 1 is the spatial parametric, ∈ ∞ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ t 0,</formula><p>is the temporal parametric, ( ) </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">C</formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">φ φ ∂ ∂ + ∇ ⋅ ∂ ∂ = ( ) ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ t C t 0 3</formula><p>where ∇ is the gradient operator.</p><p>Assuming that the values outside contour curve are positive and the values inside are negative, the inner normal vector is</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">φ φ → = - ∇ ∇ ( ) N 4</formula><p>and the level set evolution equation of contour curve <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">( ) φ φ φ φ ∂ ∂ = ∇ = = ( ) ( ) ⎧ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ ⎪ t F x y t x y , ,<label>0 , 5 0</label></formula><p>The level set evolution equation of the classical GAC method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">φ φ φ φ υ ∂ ∂ = ∇ ∇ ∇ + ( ) ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ t div g g 6</formula><p>where υ is a constant coefficient, (•) div is the divergence operator, g is an edge stop function which is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">= + = + ∇ * ( ) σ g f G I 1 1 1 1 7 2</formula><p>where f is the gradient information of the given image I, σ G is the Gaussian kernel function with standard deviation σ .</p><p>In the variational level set methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, the evolution problems of contour curve are converted to the minimization problem of the energy functions including different image feature information, and then are solved by the gradient descent flow method and the variational method. Therefore, the level set evolution equation of contour curve can be obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">φ φ ∂ ∂ = - ∂ ∂ ( ) t E 8</formula><p>The energy function ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">φ ( ) E</formula><p>x of the classical DRLSE method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref> is defined as  </p><formula xml:id="formula_9">( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ∫ ∫ ∫ ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) φ μ φ λ φ υ φ μ φ λ δ φ φ υ φ = + + = ∇ + ∇ () + - ( ) ε ε Ω Ω Ω E R L A p d</formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) φ π π φ φ φ φ ∇ ( ) = - ∇ ( ) ∇ ( ) ≤ ∇ ( ) - ∇ ( ) ≥ ( ) ⎧ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ ⎪ ⎪ p x 1 2 1 cos 2 x , if x 1 1 2 x 1 , if x 1 10</formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">( ) = + ≤ &gt; ( ) ε ⎜ ⎟ ⎧ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ ⎪ ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎛ ⎝ ⎞ ⎠ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥ x x x x 1 2 1 cos , 0, 11 ε π π ε ε ε ε ( ) = + + ≤ &gt; &lt; - ( ) ε ⎜ ⎟ ⎧ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ ⎪ ⎪ ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎛ ⎝ ⎞ ⎠ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥ H x x x x x x 1 2 1 1 sin , 1, 0,<label>12</label></formula><p>Minimizing the energy function φ ( ( )) E</p><p>x by calculus of varia- tions with <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>, the level set evolution equation of the DRLSE method is obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">( ) ( ) φ μ φ φ λ δ φ φ φ υδ φ ∂ ∂ = ∇ ∇ + ( ) ∇ ∇ + ( ) ( ) ε ε ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ t div d div g g 13 p where (•) d p</formula><p>is a function defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">( ) = ′( ) ( ) d s p s s 14 p</formula><p>Since the energy functions in variational level set methods can be constructed by the different energy terms which represent different image feature information, the models of variational level sets can be formed flexibly for different segmentation purposes <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</p><p>In the variational level set methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, the temporal partial derivatives are approximated by the forward difference equation and the spatial partial derivatives are approximated by the central difference equation, thus the level set evolution equations of ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>) can be discretized as ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">φ φ φ - Δ = ( ) + t L 15 i j k i j k i j k , 1 , ,</formula><p>where ( ) i j , is the spatial index, k is the temporal index, Δt is the time step, and φ ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">L i j k</formula><p>, is the approximation of the right side of <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>. In order to calculate the level set evolution function of (15) conveniently, the iterative equation of ( <ref type="formula">15</ref>) is expressed as ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">φ φ φ = +Δ ( ) + tL 16 i j k i j k i j k , 1 , ,</formula><p>3. Improved edge-based level set method combining local regional fitting information</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Different properties between noise points and object edge points</head><p>Noises in images usually change some pixels' gray value and lead these pixels having larger gray difference compared with their neighbor pixels, so these pixels have large gradient values <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Therefore, the gradient information of images is easily influenced by noises. Since the traditional edge stop functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> are defined as the decreasing functions merely relating with the gradient information of images, they are also easily influenced by noises. Therefore, the edge-based level set methods which use the traditional edge stop functions to guarantee the contour curve locating at object edges cannot distinguish the points with large gradient values are noise points or object edge points correctly and lead to unsatisfactory segmentation results.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> is a noisy synthetic image which can show the different properties between noise points and object edge points. Inspired by the region-based level set methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31]</ref> which regard objects and background as heterogeneously regions and assume each region has homogeneously property, we think a different property between noise points and object edge points is that the local neighborhoods of noise points have one homogeneously regional property while the local neighborhoods of object edge points have two heterogeneously regional properties. Therefore, we implement the local regional property of image points to distinguish the points with large gradient values are noise points or object edge points. If their local neighborhoods have two heterogeneously regional properties, the points will be regarded as object edge points; if their local neighborhoods have one homogeneously regional property, the points will be regarded as noise points.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Variable regional coefficient combining local regional fitting means</head><p>When the initialization of contour curve is away from object edges, the area energy term which controls the convergence properties of contour curve is necessary for level set evolution <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. In the traditional edge-based level set methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>, the coefficient of area energy term is usually set as a constant. A large constant coefficient can lead the contour curve evolving to object edges rapidly but may lead the contour curve missing object edges. A small constant coefficient can ensure the contour curve does not miss object edges but may lead the contour curve falling into local minima. So it is difficult to choose a suitable constant coefficient for the area energy term.</p><p>Influenced by noises, a large constant coefficient is more likely to lead the contour curve missing object edges while a small constant coefficient is more likely to lead the contour curve falling into local minima. On one hand, a large constant coefficient shall be selected in order to ensure the contour curve does not fall into local minima; on the other hand, a small constant coefficient shall be selected in order to ensure the contour curve does not miss object edges. Therefore, it is not suitable to set the coefficient of area energy term as a constant in noisy image segmentation, which can be validated by the experimental results in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>.</p><p>To solve the problem, based on the analysis in Section 3.1, we introduce local regional fitting <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> means to regional coefficient and propose a variable regional coefficient, which is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">υ α ( ) = + ( ) β - ( ) - ( ) e k x 17 f f x x in out</formula><p>where α&gt;0 is a linear coefficient, β&gt;0 is a nonlinear coefficient,  ( 
)</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">φ φ ( ) = ( -)* ( ) ( ) ( -)* ( ) ( ) σ σ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ f k I H k H x x y y y x y y 18 in ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) φ φ ( ) = ( -)* ( ) - ( ) ( -)* - ( ) ( ) σ σ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ f k I H k H x</formula><p>x y y 1 y</p><p>x y 1 y 19 out where ( -) σ k x y is the Gaussian kernel function with standard deviation σ and center x, ( ) I y is the intensity of point y, φ ( ) y is the level set function of point y, and (•) H is the Heaviside function. The proposed variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x is controlled by following parameters: the linear coefficient α, the nonlinear coefficient β, the constant coefficient k and the scale factor σ of Gaussian kernel function. The linear coefficient α is a relatively large constant, which guarantees υ ( )</p><p>x has large values in smooth regions; the nonlinear coefficient β is a constant, which controls the sensitivity of υ ( )</p><p>x to noises and object edges; the constant coefficient k is a relatively small constant, which ensures υ ( )</p><p>x has value k near object edges; the scale factor σ of Gaussian kernel function is an indirect parameter for υ ( )</p><p>x because it controls the amount of local regional information introduced to the local regional fitting means using in υ ( )</p><p>x . Because of the above parameters, the variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x has following properties: (1) when the image point x is in smooth region, the absolute</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">( )- ( ) f f x x in out</formula><p>is small, so the variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x can be guaranteed to have a re- latively large value; (2) when the image point x is near object edge, the absolute</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">( )- ( ) f f x x in out</formula><p>is relatively large, so the variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x can be guaranteed to have a small value. Therefore, the variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x has large values in smooth regions while small values near object edges. So the level set evolution equation can have fast convergence speed in smooth regions which ensures the contour curve moves to object edges rapidly and is robust to noises, while it can have slow convergence speed near object edges which ensures the contour curve does not miss object edges and stop its evolution prematurely.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Improved edge stop function combining local regional fitting variances</head><p>Edge stop function is a decreasing function relating with the gradient information of images, which can guarantee the contour curve locating at object edges <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. At present, the form of edge stop function has no uniform regulation. Different forms of edge stop function <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref> will lead level set function producing different segmentation results for images. Thus choosing a relatively good edge stop function is very helpful to improve the segmentation results.</p><p>To improve the properties of edge stop function, based on the analysis in Section 3.1, we introduce local regional fitting <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> variances to edge stop function and propose an improved edge stop function, which is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">( ) σ σ ( ) = + ( )+ ( )+ ( ) g f x 1 1 / x x 1<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">in out 2 2</formula><p>where f is the gradient information of given image, σ ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">x in 2</formula><p>and σ ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">x out 2</formula><p>are the local regional fitting variances of image point x inside and outside the contour curve respectively when the center of Gaussian kernel function locates at x, which are defined as ( ) ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">σ φ ( ) = ( -)* ( ) -( ) ( ) ( ) σ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ k I f H x x y y x y 21 in in 2 2 ( ) ( ) ( ) σ φ ( ) = ( -)* ( ) - ( ) - ( ) ( ) σ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ k I f H x x y y x 1 y 22 out out 2 2</formula><p>where ( -) σ k x y is the Gaussian kernel function with standard deviation σ and center x, ( ) I y is the intensity of point y, φ ( ) y is the level set function of point y, and (•) H is the Heaviside function. Since the scale factor σ of Gaussian kernel function controls the Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The segmentation results by DRLSE method. From right to left are the different regional coefficients which are set 0.5, 0.6, 0.8 and 1.0 respectively. From top to bottom are the weak-edge images which randomly added salt and pepper noise, Gaussian noise, speckle noise with noise density 0.01.</p><p>amount of the local regional information introduced to the local regional fitting variances, it is an indirect parameter for the improved edge stop function ( ) g x . Because of the local regional fitting variances, the improved edge stop function ( ) g x has following properties: (1) when the image point x is in smooth region and its local neighborhood has no noise points, both the gradient f and the sum σ σ ( )+ ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">x x in out 2 2</formula><p>have small values, so the improved edge stop function satisfies ( )→ g x 1;</p><p>(2) when the image point x is in smooth region and its local neighborhood has noise points, the sum σ σ ( )+ ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">x x in out 2 2</formula><p>have relatively large values, so the improved edge stop function is no longer close to zero; (3) when the image point x is near object edge, the gradient f is large but the sum σ σ ( )+ ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">x x in out 2 2</formula><p>is small, so the improved edge stop function satisfies ( )→ g x 0. Both the im- proved edge stop function ( ) g x and the traditional edge stop functions have the first and the third properties. The second property is the great advantage of the improved edge stop function ( ) g x over the traditional edge stop functions, and ensures the improved edge stop function ( ) g x is insensitive to noises.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Improved edge-based level set model combining local regional fitting information</head><p>Inspired by the work of Li et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, and by applying the proposed variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x and the improved edge stop function ( ) g x to energy function φ ( ( )) E</p><p>x , we propose an improved edge-based level set method combining local regional fitting information for better segmentation of noisy images, which is obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ∫ ∫ ∫ ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) φ υ μ φ λ φ υ φ μ φ λ δ φ φ υ φ = + + = ∇ + ∇ + - ( ) ε ε Ω Ω Ω E g R L A p d g d g H d x , x , x x x x x x x x x x x x x x x 23 p g g x x</formula><p>Keeping υ ( ) x and ( ) g x fixed, we minimize the energy function φ υ ( ( ) ( ) ( )) E g x , x , x by calculus of variations with (8), thus the level set evolution equation of ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>) is obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">( ) ( ) φ μ φ φ λ δ φ φ φ δ φ υ ∂ ∂ = ∇ ∇ + ( ) ( ) ∇ ∇ + ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ε ε ⎛ ⎝ ⎜ ⎞ ⎠ ⎟ t div d div g g x x x 24 p</formula><p>The first term μ φ φ ( (∇ )∇ ) div d p is associated with the penalty energy term μ φ</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">( ( )) R x p</formula><p>. It ensures the level set function is automatically approximated as a signed distance function and avoids the re-initialization of level set function. The second term ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">λδ φ ( ) ( ) ε φ φ ∇ ∇ div g x and the third term δ φ υ ( ) ( ) ( ) ε g x</formula><p>x are asso- ciated with the length energy term ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">λ φ ( ) ( ) L x g x</formula><p>and the area energy term υ φ ( ) ( ( ))</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">( ) A x x g x</formula><p>respectively. Because of using the proposed variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x and the improved edge stop function ( ) g x in the calculation of level set function, the second term can ensure the contour curve precisely convergences at object edges and the third term can ensure the contour curve moves to and does not miss object edges.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Numerical implementation</head><p>Before the iteration of level set evolution, the level set function should be initialized. In this paper, the level set function is initialized as , Ω 0 is a region of image domain Ω. Therefore, the numerical implementation of our method can be summarized as following steps: Algorithm 1. Improved edge-based level set method combining local regional fitting information.</p><p>Step 1: initialize level set function by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>;</p><p>Step 2: calculate</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">( ) ( ) f f x ,</formula><p>x in out by ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>) respectively;</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">Step 3: calculate σ σ ( ) ( ) x ,</formula><p>x in out by ( <ref type="formula">21</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) respectively; Step 4: calculate υ ( ) ( ) g x ,</p><p>x by ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">20</ref>) respectively;</p><p>Step 5: update level set function by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>;</p><p>Step 6: repeat step 2-5 until level set function is stable or total iteration steps reach limit</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Experimental results</head><p>The performance of our method has been validated in segmentation experiments on a variety of noisy images. All experiments are performed on a computer with 2.00 GHz Intel Core i7 CPU and 8 GB RAM. The two classical edge-based level set methods, the GAC method and the DRLSE method, are taken as the comparison methods which provide an effective performance evaluation of our method. All the comparison experiments of our method and the two classical methods are pure data-driven, take no shape prior and use the same initialization of contour curves.</p><p>To evaluate the performances of our method more objectively, the segmentation experiments are first performed on a synthetic image and three objective metrics (the jaccard similarity (JS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, the dice similarity coefficient (DSC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, and the ratio of segmentation error (RSE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>) are used to evaluate the performances of our method. Let S1 represents the true foreground of images and let S2 represents the foreground obtained by the experimental methods, the three objective metrics are defined as below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) = ∩ ∪ = ∩ + = + Ω N S S N S S N S S N S N S N S S N S S N JS , D S C 2 , RSE / / . 1 2 1 2 1 2 1 2 2 1 1 2</formula><p>where (•) N indicates the number of pixels in the enclosed region, and Ω is the image domain. The closer the JS, DSC values to 1 and RSE values to 0, the better the segmentation results. For a picture, a perfect segmentation will give</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">= = JS DSC 1, = RSE 0.</formula><p>To test the robustness of our method against noises, three sorts of noises (salt and pepper noise, Gaussian noise and speckle noise) are independently and randomly added to the synthetic image.</p><p>In the segmentation experiments on the synthetic image, the parameters of our method are set as following: penalty term coefficient μ=0. 2, length term coefficient λ=1, time step Δ = t 5, total iteration steps = N 1500, linear coefficient α = 15, constant coefficient = k 0.25 and nonlinear coefficient β = 3. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> is the segmentation results of our method for the synthetic image which is randomly added the three sorts of noises with increasing noise density. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref> is the JS, DSC and RSE values for the segmentation results in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>. It is easily to see that the JS and DSC values of the segmentation results are very close to 1 and the RSE values of the segmentation results are very close to 0. Therefore, the segmentation results of our method are accurate. It also can see that although the segmentation results of our method become worse when the noise density increases, they are still relatively accurate.</p><p>To evaluate the effectiveness of our method for noisy image segmentation more comprehensive, the segmentation experiments are then performed on real images (strong-edge images and weak-edge images) and the three sorts of noises are also independently and randomly added to them. Due to having no priority of the accurate edges of real images, the segmentation results are mainly measured by the subjective judgment.</p><p>In the segmentation experiments on the real images, the parameters of the comparison methods and our method are set as following: for the GAC method, time step Δ = t 0. 1, total iteration steps = N 5000; for the DRLSE method, penalty term coefficient μ=0. 2, length term coefficient λ=1, time step Δ = t 5, total iteration steps = N 2500 for strong-edge images and = N 2000 for weak-edge images; for our method, penalty term coefficient μ=0. 2, length term coefficient λ=1, time step Δ = t 5, total iteration steps = N 2000 for strong-edge images and = N 1500 for weak-edge images.</p><p>Since the weak object edges are more easily missed in noisy image segmentation, the regional coefficient of area energy term for the weak-edge images shall not be as large as it for the strongedge images. So we select two sets values of regional coefficient for the weak-edge and the strong-edge images respectively in the comparison experiments: one set values are small for the weakedge images, and the other are large for the strong-edges images. For the GAC method, the small coefficient of balloon force for the weak-edge images is set as υ=1 and the large coefficient of balloon force for the strong-edge images is set as υ=1. 5. For the DRLSE method, two values are selected to make a comprehensive evaluation for the constant regional coefficient: one value is relatively small and the other is relatively large. Therefore, the relatively small and the relatively large constant regional coefficients for the weak-edge images are set as υ=0. 6 and υ=0. 8 respectively; the relatively small and the relatively large constant regional coefficients for the strong-edge images are set as υ=0. 8 and υ=1. 0 respectively. For our method, the linear coefficient α and the constant coefficient k of the variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x for the weak-edge images are set as α= = k 8, 0. 02; the linear coefficient α and the constant coefficient k of the variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x for the strong-edge images are set as α= = k 15, 0. 25. Since the large nonlinear coefficient β may lead υ ( )</p><p>x more sensitive to noises and object edges while the small nonlinear coefficient β may lead υ ( )</p><p>x more insensitive to noises and object edges, the nonlinear coefficient β of the variable regional coefficient υ ( )</p><p>x are set as empirical value β = 3 for both the weak-edge images and the strong-edge images.</p><p>The scale factor σ of the Gaussian kernel function controls the amount of the local regional information introduced to the local regional fitting means and variances. A large scale factor σ  introduces more local regional information to local regional fitting means and variances, so the contour curve can be insensitive to noises but may lose more details of object edges. A small scale factor σ introduces less local regional information to local regional fitting means and variances, so the contour curve can keep more details of object edges but may be sensitive to noises. So the scale factor σ of the Gaussian kernel function is set as 1.5 in this paper. Figs. 4 and 5 are the segmentation results for the weak-edge images and the strong-edge images respectively which are randomly added the salt and pepper noise. The experimental results in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref> show that our method obtains more accurate segmentation results than the GAC method and the DRLSE method when the two kinds of images are added the salt and pepper noise.</p><p>Since the relatively small linear coefficient α and constant coefficient k used for the weak-edge images in our method and because of the characteristics of the pepper and salt noise, the segmentation results of the weak-edge images are not as good as the segmentation results of the strong-edge images. However,  their segmentation results are still better than the segmentation results of the GAC method and the DRLSE method.</p><p>Figs. 6 and 7 are the segmentation results for the weak-edge images and the strong-edge images respectively which are randomly added the Gaussian noise. The experimental results in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref> show that our method obtains more accurate segmentation results than the GAC method and the DRLSE method when the two kinds of images are added the Gaussian noise.</p><p>The experimental results of the DRLSE method in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>show that the disadvantage of the constant regional coefficient is particularly serious for the images with Gaussian noise. The experimental results of our method in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>show that our method obtains more accurate segmentation results for the images with Gaussian noise than the images with pepper and salt noise.   Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">8</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9</ref> show that our method obtains more accurate segmentation results than the GAC method and the DRLSE method when the two kinds of images are added the speckle noise.</p><p>Since the characteristics of the speckle noise is similar to the characteristics of the Gaussian noise, the advantage of our method is also prominent for the images with speckle noise. The experimental results of our method in Figs. 4, 5, 8 and 9 prove this conclusion.</p><p>In all experiments of noisy images, our method obtains more accurate segmentation results with insensitive to noises and without missing object edges while the segmentation results of both the GAC method and the DRLSE method have fallen into local minima or missed object edges, which proves the robustness and the effectiveness of our method. In all experiments of our method, the segmentation results of the strong-edge images are better than the segmentation results of the weak-edge images which prove that our method is more effective to the strong-edge images in noisy image segmentation; the segmentation results of both the  images with Gaussian noise and the images with speckle noise are better than the segmentation results of the image with pepper and salt noise which prove that our method is more robust to the Gaussian noise and the speckle noise.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>In this paper, we analyze the properties of noise points and object edge points, and propose a variable regional coefficient and an improved edge stop function based on the different local regional properties of them. By applying the variable regional coefficient and the improved edge stop function to the energy function of level set function, an improved edge-based level set method combining local regional fitting information is proposed for noisy images. Due to the variable regional coefficient and the improved edge stop function overcoming the shortcomings of constant regional coefficient and traditional edge stop functions, the improved edge-based level set method obtains accurate segmentation results with insensitive to noises and without missing object edges for the noisy images which are added three sorts of noises (Gaussian noise, salt and pepper noise and speckle noise) respectively. Therefore, the improved edge-based level set method combining local regional fitting information is robust to noises and is efficient.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Noise points in synthetic image.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,319.24,58.62,216.00,216.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Segmentation results of our method for the synthetic image. From left to right are the results with noise density 0.01, 0.02, 0.03, 0.04 respectively. From top to bottom are the results with three sorts of noises (salt and pepper noise, Gaussian noise and speckle noise) respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,86.51,58.62,432.00,324.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Compared segmentation results of the strong-edge images which are randomly added the salt and pepper noise. (a) noisy images with the initialization curve; (b) the GAC method; (c) and (d) are the DRLSE method with small and large constant regional coefficient respectively; (e) our method. From top to bottom are the results with noise density 0.01, 0.02, 0.03, 0.04 respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,61.74,58.62,461.98,214.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Compared segmentation results of the weak-edge images which are randomly added the salt and pepper noise. (a) noisy images with the initialization curve; (b) the GAC method; (c) and (d) are the DRLSE method with small and large constant regional coefficient respectively; (e) our method. From top to bottom are the results with noise density 0.01, 0.02, 0.03, 0.04 respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,61.74,428.94,461.98,286.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figs. 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>and 9 are the segmentation results for the weak-edge images and the strong-edge images respectively which are randomly added the speckle noise. The experimental results in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Compared segmentation results of the strong-edge images which are randomly added the Gaussian noise. (a) noisy images with the initialization curve; (b) the GAC method; (c) and (d) are the DRLSE method with small and large constant regional coefficient respectively; (e) our method. From top to bottom are the results with noise density 0.01, 0.02, 0.03, 0.04 respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,71.55,58.62,461.98,214.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Compared segmentation results of the weak-edge images which are randomly added the Gaussian noise. (a) noisy images with the initialization curve; (b) the GAC method; (c) and (d) are the DRLSE method with small and large constant regional coefficient respectively; (e) our method. From top to bottom are the results with noise density 0.01, 0.02, 0.03, 0.04 respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,71.55,430.13,461.98,285.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Compared segmentation results of the strong-edge images which are randomly added the speckle noise. (a) noisy images with the initialization curve; (b) the GAC method; (c) and (d) are the DRLSE method with small and large constant regional coefficient respectively; (e) our method. From top to bottom are the results with noise density 0.01, 0.02, 0.03, 0.04 respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,61.74,58.62,461.98,214.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Compared segmentation results of the weak-edge images which are randomly added the speckle noise. (a) noisy images with the initialization curve; (b) the GAC method; (c) and (d) are the DRLSE method with small and large constant regional coefficient respectively; (e) our method. From top to bottom are the results with noise density 0.01, 0.02, 0.03, 0.04 respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,61.74,321.34,461.98,285.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="4,86.51,58.62,432.00,258.63" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>JS, DSC, RSE values for the segmentation results in Fig.3.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Noise density 0.01</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>0.04</cell></row><row><cell>Salt and</cell><cell>0.9961/</cell><cell>0.9924/</cell><cell>0.9906/</cell><cell>0.9855/</cell></row><row><cell>pepper</cell><cell>0.9981/</cell><cell>0.9962/</cell><cell>0.9953/</cell><cell>0.9927/0.0038</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.0010</cell><cell>0.0020</cell><cell>0.0024</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gaussian</cell><cell>0.9882/</cell><cell>0.9842/</cell><cell>0.9814/</cell><cell>0.9701/</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.9941/</cell><cell>0.9920/</cell><cell>0.9906/</cell><cell>0.9848/0.0079</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.0031</cell><cell>0.0041</cell><cell>0.0049</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Speckle</cell><cell>0.9953/</cell><cell>0.9923/</cell><cell>0.9915/</cell><cell>0.9876/</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.9976/</cell><cell>0.9961/</cell><cell>0.9957/</cell><cell>0.9938/0.0032</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.0012</cell><cell>0.0020</cell><cell>0.0022</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>C. Liu et al. / Signal Processing 130 (2017) 12-21</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>This research is partially supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (Nos. 61370127, 61473031, and 61472030), Program for New Century Excellent Talents in University (NCET-13-0659), Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (2014JBZ004), Beijing Higher Education Young Elite Teacher Project (YETP0583). The opinions expressed are solely those of the authors and not the sponsors.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Segmentation of 3D images using the random walking technique on a randomly created image adjacency graph</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fabijanska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Goclawski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="524" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MILCut: a sweeping line multiple instance learning paradigm for interactive image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="263" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient algorithm for level set method preserving distance function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Estellers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zosso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thiran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bresson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4722" to="4734" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Level set image segmentation with Bayesian analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurocomputing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994">2008. 1994-2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">active contour model driven by fractional order fitting energy, Signal Process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="150" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced distance regularization for re-initialization free level set evolution with application to image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Niu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurocomputing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Snakes: active contour models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Witkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Terzopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Vis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fronts propagating with curvature-dependent speed: algorithms based on Hamilton-Jacobi formulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sethian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A geometric model for active contours</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Caselles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kimmel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Vis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Level set evolution without re-initialization: a new variational formulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="430" to="436" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distance regularized level set evolution and its application to image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3243" to="3254" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving level set method for fast auroral oval segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2854" to="2965" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal approximations by piecewise smooth functions and associated variational problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mumford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. Pure Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="577" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Active contours without edges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vese</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Curve evolution implementation of the Mumford-Shah functional for image segmentation, denosing, interpolation, and magnification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yezzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Willsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1169" to="1186" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the statistical interpretation of the piecewise smooth Mumford-Shah functional</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cremers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SSVM</title>
		<meeting>SSVM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="213" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implicit active contours driven by local binary fitting energy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Active contour model driven by local histogram fitting energy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="655" to="662" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shapes, shocks, and deformations I: The components of two-dimensional shape and the reaction-diffusion space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kimia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tannenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Vis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A PDE-based fast local level set method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Merriman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="410" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sethian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Level Set Methods and Fast Marching Methods</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reinitialization-free level set evolution via reaction diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="271" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kornprobst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Mathematical Problems in Image Processing: Partial Differential Equations and the Calculus of Variations</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A convex variational level set model for image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast distance preserving level set evolution for medical image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Konwar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ICARCV</title>
		<meeting>ICARCV</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Active contours driven by localizing region and edge-based intensity fitting energy with application to segmentation of the left ventricle in cardiac CT images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurocomputing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A level set method based on the Bayesian risk for medical image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3699" to="3711" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Level set method for image segmentation in the presence of intensity inhomogeneities with application to MRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gatenby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Metaxas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2007" to="2016" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Edge location to subpixel values in digital imagery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tabatabai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="524" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RAGS: region-aided geometric snake</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mirmehdi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="640" to="652" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Region-based strategies for active contour models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ronfard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Vis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimization of region-scalable fitting energy for image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1940" to="1949" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scale-space and edge deletion using anisotropic diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Perona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="629" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Locally monotonic diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1379" to="1389" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A robust medical image segmentation method using KL distance and local neighborhood information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Biol. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magnetic resonance image tissue classification using a partial volume model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Shattuck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Sandor-Leahy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schaper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rottenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leahy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="856" to="876" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probability density difference-based active contour for ultrasound image segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2028" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
