<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A partial Hadamard transform approach to the design of cancelable fingerprint templates containing binary biometric representations</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-08-20">20 August 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Song</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<email>song.wang@latrobe.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Engineering and Mathematical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">La Trobe University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>VIC 3086</addrLine>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Guang</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
							<email>d.deng@latrobe.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Engineering and Mathematical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">La Trobe University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>VIC 3086</addrLine>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jiankun</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
							<email>j.hu@adfa.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Engineering and Information Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of New South Wales at the Australian Defence Force Academy (UNSW@ADFA)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2600</postCode>
									<settlement>Canberra</settlement>
									<region>ACT</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A partial Hadamard transform approach to the design of cancelable fingerprint templates containing binary biometric representations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-08-20">20 August 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F447D2763444CEFEE14D14FCEC972CB7</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.patcog.2016.08.017</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 28 February 2016 Received in revised form 11 August 2016 Accepted 18 August 2016</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T14:58+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Cancelable biometrics Binary biometric representation Stochastic distance Partial Hadamard transform Biometric template protection</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>As an important biometric template protection technique, cancelable biometrics provides enhanced security for biometric-based authentication. Representing biometric information in binary form is useful in biometric template protection because it offers simplicity in feature representation and provides benefits in matching and storage. Therefore, it is no surprise that cancelable biometrics often exploits binary biometric representations as resultant templates. However, very often such binary biometric representations contained in cancelable biometrics have security shortfalls, because once they are compromised, the biometric features that they represent are likely to be retrieved. In this paper we propose an efficient non-invertible transformationthe partial Hadamard transform to securely protect binary biometric representations in the design of cancelable biometrics. When this non-invertible transform is applied to the DFT of the binary biometric representations, the resultant templates are complex vectors, from which the original binary vectors cannot be restored. A prominent feature of the proposed approach is that it preserves the stochastic distance between binary vectors after the transformation. This stochastic distance preserving property is theoretically proved and further demonstrated and verified by experiments. The cancelable fingerprint templates designed by the proposed partial Hadamard transform meet the requirements of revocability, diversity, non-invertibility and performance. Matching performance of the designed cancelable templates compares favorably with state-of-the-art methods that also involve binary biometric representations; for example, the Equal Error Rate of the proposed method in the lost-token scenario is 1% for FVC2002 DB1, 2% for FVC2002 DB2 and 5.2% for FVC2002 DB3.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The strengths and advantages of utilizing biometrics in access control and identity authentication are witnessing a widespread deployment of biometric systems. However, privacy and security concerns over fraudulent use of biometric data <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> make biometric template protection all the more important. Research into biometric template protection spans a wide spectrum of biometrics from fingerprint <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, face <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, finger-vein <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, palmprint <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> to multimodal biometrics <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>Biometric template protection can be broadly classified into two categories: cancelable biometrics and bio-cryptosystems <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Biohashing <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref> is one of the early techniques for cancelable biometrics. In recent years, cancelable fingerprint templates have received much research interest; see e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. In the design of cancelable fingerprint templates, some researchers focused more on exploiting local minutia structures to extract invariant features <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, while some researchers spent more effort on the design of non-invertible transformations <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref>. Protected biometric templates in cancelable biometrics often end up in binary form, because binary biometric representations offer simplicity in feature representation and provide benefits in matching and storage <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. For example, binary biometric representations take the form of identically, independently distributed binary strings in Biohashing <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> and non-uniformly, sparsely distributed binary strings in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</p><p>However, very often binary biometric representations contained in cancelable biometrics have security shortfalls, because once they are compromised, the biometric features that they represent can be retrieved. Security concerns over the Biohashing scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> were analyzed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28]</ref>. Cheung et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, Kong <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> and Lee et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> investigated Biohashing's invertibility issue, showing that the non-invertible transformation in Biohashing may become invertible. The permutation process is another security loophole that exists in some recently developed cancelable Contents lists available at ScienceDirect journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/pr biometrics, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>. In these methods, the resultant binary bit strings were permuted through a user-specific token to generate the final binary templates. Since permutation is a reversible process, once the permutation key/matrix is compromised, an adversary is able to figure out the topology of feature vectors <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. This can further put raw biometric data at risk.</p><p>Protection of binary biometric representations has not yet been effectively addressed in the design of cancelable biometrics. In this paper we propose an efficient non-invertible transformationthe partial Hadamard transform to protect binary biometric re- presentations. The proposed transformation builds upon the Hadamard transform <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> but employs a partial Hadamard matrix so as to realize non-invertibility. It is well known that the Hadamard transform appeals to fast implementation since it only involves additions and subtractions. We did some early work on applying the Hadamard transform to cancelable template design <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, but it was preliminary and incomplete. The proposed approach in this paper is more comprehensive. In particular, we show a prominent feature of the proposed approach, that is, it preserves the stochastic distance between binary vectors after the transformation. This stochastic distance preserving property is theoretically proved and further demonstrated and verified by experiments.</p><p>In addition, some binary biometric representations are nonuniformly and sparsely distributed, which imposes an undesirable restriction on the search space. To resolve this, we first take the discrete Fourier transform (DFT) on the binary strings and then the partial Hadamard transform. The proposed transformation can be used to secure any binary biometric representation in the design of cancelable biometrics. It turns out that the cancelable templates designed by using the partial Hadamard transform meet the re- quirements of revocability, diversity, non-invertibility and performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, evaluated over the public databases FVC2002 DB1-DB3 [35] and FVC2004 DB2 <ref type="bibr">[36]</ref>.</p><p>We summarize the contributions of the proposed approach as follows:</p><p>1. The proposed partial Hadamard transform is both effective and efficient in the design of cancelable templates containing binary biometric representations. It is effective because it renders strong protection of binary biometric representations, while preserving their stochastic distance after the transformation. It is efficient because it takes advantage of the implementational and computational efficiency of the Hadamard transform. 2. Recognition performance of the proposed approach compares favorably with the existing methods that also contain binary biometric representations; for example, the Equal Error Rate (EER) of the proposed method in the lost-token scenario is 1% for FVC2002 DB1, 2% for FVC2002 DB2 and 5.2% for FVC2002 DB3.</p><p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows. Section 2 introduces some preliminaries on the Hadamard transform. Section 3 describes the proposed approach, which includes the DFT, the partial Hadamard transform and distance measures. A compre- hensive system analysis is given in Section 4, where the stochastic distance preserving property is theoretically proved. In Section 5, we evaluate the proposed approach through experiments, firstly verifying the property of stochastic distance preservation and then designing cancelable fingerprint templates using the proposed partial Hadamard transform. The conclusion and future work is given in Section 6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Preliminaries on the Hadamard transform</head><p>In this section, we present some preliminaries on the Hadamard transform, which lays the foundation of our new method for the design of cancelable biometrics containing binary biometric representations. The mathematical core of the Hadamard transform is the Sylvester-Hadamard matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, or Hadamard matrix for short, denoted as H n . The Hadamard matrix H n is of dimension × 2 2</p><p>n n and created in a recursive manner:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">= ⊗ - H H H n n 1 1</formula><p>where ⊗ is the Kronecker product, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">= - ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥ H 1 1 1 1 1</formula><p>The Hadamard matrix H n has some special properties [32]:</p><p>1. All entries are 71. , where = M 2 n and I is an identity matrix of × M M, or equivalently,</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">= - H H n M n 1 1</formula><p>.</p><p>The Hadamard transform, y, of a × 2 1</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">n vector x is defined as = ( ) y H x 1 n</formula><p>Since all elements of H n are 7 1, the Hadamard transform in (1) involves only additions and subtractions but no multiplication. This feature brings about a significant computational advantage, making the Hadamard transform appealing to communications and signal or image processing related applications, for which sustained savings in computation are desired. Direct calculation of (1) would incur 2 2n operations. Taking advantage of the properties of the Hadamard matrix, there are fast methods for computing the Hadamard transform. One of them [32] is to decompose H n and express it as:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>= ( )</head><formula xml:id="formula_4">H A 2 n n</formula><p>where A is called fast Hadamard transform matrix, written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">= ⋯ ⋯ ⋮ ⋯ - ⋯ -⋯ ⋮ ⋯ - ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ A 1 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 1 1 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 1</formula><p>It follows from (2) that the Hadamard transform in (1) can be restructured into</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>= ( ( ⋯( ))) ( ) H x A A Ax 3 n</head><p>The Hadamard transform computed via (3) requires only ( • ) n 2 n additions.</p><p>If the observation vector y in (1) is known, it is obviously in- appropriate to apply the full-order Hadamard transform to securing the source vector x, because x can be easily retrieved through matrix inversion. In the next section we shall show how to protect a biometric source vector with binary values using the partial Hadamard transform.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">A partial Hadamard transform approach to cancelable fingerprint templates</head><p>A binary biometric representation in the data domain can be described by a binary-valued vector</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">= [ ( ) ( ) … ( -)] ( ) t d d d m 0 , 1 , ,<label>1 4 d T</label></formula><p>where ( ) ∈ { } d i 0, 1 . t d can be either a randomly generated vector with possibly a uniform distribution (as in the case of Biohashing <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>), or a sparsely, non-uniformly distributed binary vector with many more zeros than ones (as in the case of cancellable biometrics <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>). It is vital to safeguard t d because it contains essential biometric information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">The DFT of binary vectors</head><p>Since the entries of the binary vector t d are either 0 or 1, especially when elements of t d are sparsely distributed, operating directly on t d can potentially narrow down the search space when a reverse-engineering-oriented approach is applied. Motivated by the duality between time and frequency, just like the Dirac delta function in the time domain having a flat spectrum in the frequency domain, we resort to the Fourier transform to address the issue. The DFT of t d should render a dense data representation in the transformed domain. We now take the N-point DFT of t d , where ≥ N m and is a power of 2, i.e., = N 2 n , so that the DFT operation can be performed using the powerful FFT algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[37]</ref>.</p><p>The N-point DFT of t d is given by = ( ) t Ft 5</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">D d where = [ ( ) ( ) ⋯ ( -)] t D D D N 0 , 1 , , 1 D T</formula><p>, and the DFT matrix F is ex- pressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">= ⋯ ⋯ ⋯ ⋮ ⋮ ⋮ ⋯ ⋮ ⋯ - ( -) - ( -) ( -)( -) ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ F W W W W W W W W W 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 N N N N N N 2 1 2 4 2 1 1 2 1 1 1 with = π - W e j N</formula><p>2 / . Note that the DFT operation in ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) is invertible, since the DFT matrix F is unitary (and hence nonsingular). The purpose of taking the DFT is to spread out the spectrum of t d such that its frequency samples in t D are not sparsely distributed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">The partial Hadamard transform</head><p>In this section we develop a non-invertible transformation aimed to protect t D . With t D secure, the binary vector t d will also be safe. The proposed transformation builds upon the Hadamard transform , introduced in Section 2.</p><p>Let us define a row vector of length r, denoted by</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">= [ ⋯ ] ( ) K k k k , , ,<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">r 1 2</formula><p>where &lt; r N with = N 2 n (N is the length of the vector t D ), and all entries of K are strictly positive integers with ≠ k k i j for all ≠ i j. The vector K can be generated randomly and plays the role of a parameter key or token, which is of great importance in cancelable biometrics. We use K to construct a submatrix of H n , denoted by Hn , such that the ith row of Hn is the k i th row of H n , for ∈ [ … ] i r 1, , . Thus, the size of Hn is × r N. Once Hn is formed using the random vector K , we can perform the following partial Hadamard transform</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>= ¯( ) t H t 7</head><p>H nD to obtain a complex-valued vector t H of length r. According to the properties of the Hadamard matrix (see Section 2), the transformation in ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) is non-invertible in that Hn is a row-reduced sub- matrix of H n and is always column rank deficient. From a linear algebra point of view, for a system of linear equations, as represented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, there exist multiple solutions to such an underdetermined system. Therefore, t D to be protected is hidden among many solutions to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, making the search for the true t D a tremendously difficult task even if both the transformed template t H and the parameter key K are compromised (loss of the para- meter key K causes the revelation of the partial Hadamard matrix Hn ); see details of non-invertibility analysis in Section 4.3. Figs. 1-3 show the graphical illustration of fingerprint images with minutiae labeled and the corresponding transformed templates given by t H , drawn in the complex plane.</p><p>Although the transformation in ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) realizes many-to-one mapping, an idea explored in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, the proposed method is fundamentally different to <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> insomuch as the partial Hadamard matrix Hn is formed in a totally different manner to the random key in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, and what is more, it is the large size of the key matrix in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> that makes its storage space-consuming and the generation of cancelable templates computationally expensive. On the contrary, storing the key, namely the random vector K in (6), and performing the partial Hadamard transform manifest the strengths of the new method.</p><p>Despite the fact that both the proposed and Biohashing methods apply some sort of projection-based technique with a non-square projection matrix, it is worth remarking that the proposed method bears little resemblance to the Biohashing algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Firstly, the random vectors used to generate the Biocode in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> are disparate to the partial Hadamard matrix Hn . Sec- ondly, the Biohashing algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> suffers performance degradation in the lost-token scenario. By contrast, the proposed partial Hadamard transform in (7), when applied to cancelable fingerprint templates, is shown to have satisfactory performance in the lost-token case; see the experimental results in Section 5.2. Thirdly, Biohasing and the proposed method differ in feature extraction. The conditions that the feature extractors of the Biohashing algorithm must satisfy were shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> (see Eqs. ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">24</ref>) therein). However, feature extraction of the proposed method does not require to satisfy these conditions. This can be clearly seen from the binary vectors used in Section 5.2. Fourthly, the transformed templates of Biohashing and the proposed method are in different formats. The binary bit-string (Biocode) is the protected or transformed template in Biohashing, whereas the binary string in the proposed scheme is the untransformed feature vector which needs protection. The transformed, protected template in our method ends up being a complex vector [see <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>], which shares no common feature with the Biocode in Biohashing.</p><p>We now comment on the benefits of the parameter key K . Despite Hn being the transformation matrix, it does not need to be stored in the database, smartcard or mobile device, because we can readily use the parameter key K to construct Hn from a full- order Hadamard matrix. Since K is generated at random, changing K varies the partial Hadamard matrix Hn , thus achieving revoc- ability for cancelable biometrics. Apparently, storing K requires little memory space. Another benefit offered by the proposed approach is the implementational and computational efficiency. As the entries of Hn are either +1 or -1, the partial Hadamard transform in (7) involves no multiplication. There are numerous ways to implement <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> based on the known computational structures of the Hadamard transform [32].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">The distance measures</head><p>In this section we design the distance measures for the binary vectors in the binary space and the transformed vectors (after the DFT and partial Hadamard transform) in the transformed domain.</p><p>Suppose that there are two binary vectors t d and x d , both in the form of (4). For binary vectors, it is straightforward to measure their Hamming distance. So the normalized Hamming distance between t d and x d in the binary space (or data domain) is given by , and the superscript T denotes the transpose of a real vector/matrix, or the conjugate transpose of a complex vector/matrix, as the case may be.</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">( )= ( ) ( ) + ( ) ( )  t x t x t x w w , dist ,</formula><p>After taking the N-point DFT of t d and x d , we obtain t D and x D ; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>. We then randomly generate two parameter keys in the form of <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>, which can be used to construct two partial Hadamard matrices, one for transforming t D and the other for transforming x D . Applying the partial Hadamard transform in (7) to t D and x D yields t H and x H , respectively. We utilize the Euclidean metric to measure the distance between t H and x H in the transformed do- main:  <ref type="figure"> t</ref> x , H H range from 0 to 1, where 0 means closest and 1 means farthest. In the context of cancelable templates, at the verification stage we can readily use <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> to calculate the similarity scores between the enrolled and query biometrics; see the application of (10) to fingerprint matching in the design of cancelable fingerprint templates in Section 5.2.</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">( )= + ( )  t</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">System analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">The system model</head><p>The cancelable biometrics that involves binary biometric representations can be modelled as having two parts: data transformation and verification. It follows from the data transformation proposed in ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) and (7) that a binary vector t d in the data domain is converted to the transformed-domain vector t H by = ( ) t I PH Ft 11</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">H p n d = ( ) t I t Q 12 H p d = ( ) t I t 13 H p Q</formula><p>where t H is the ( × ) P is a permutation matrix depending on the randomly gener- ated parameter key K in (6), I p is a "partial" identity matrix of ( × ) r N whose the main di- agonal elements are 1 and all other elements are zero,</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">r 1 transformed vector,</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>=</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Q PH F</head><p>n is a unitary matrix, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">= t Qt Q d .</formula><p>To recapitulate in simple words, a unitary transformation is carried out on t d and the result is permuted. The top r elements are then taken out to form the vector t H .</p><p>In the verification process, a query binary vector x d is transformed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> into x H . The verification process involves evaluating the distance between t H and x H in the transformed domain, as expressed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>. A binary decision is made based on</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">( )  t x , H H : τ τ ( ) = ( )&lt; ( ) ⎧ ⎨ ⎩  t x v 1, , 0, otherwise<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">H H H H</formula><p>where τ H is the predefined threshold and "1" means that x H is verified to match t H . </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Stochastic distance preservation</head><p>A basic requirement for biometric template protection is that if a biometric feature vector is verified to match another feature vector in the non-transformed domain, then they should also be verified to match in the transformed domain. Analogous to <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>, let the matching rule in the data domain (i.e., non-transformed domain) be defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">τ (ϵ) = ( )&lt; ( ) ⎧ ⎨ ⎩  t x v 1, , 0, otherwise<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">d d d d</formula><p>To simplify discussion, without loss of generality, we assume that the length of x d is fixed and equal to N (this can be easily done through zero-padding before the DFT if the length of x d is less than N). Geometrically, the matching rule in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> defines an N-dimensional hyper-sphere centered at t d with a radius of</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">τ ( + ) t t x x d T d d T d d .</formula><p>Vectors inside the hyper-sphere are regarded the same as t d , while those outside the hyper-sphere are regarded not. Verification in the transformed domain has the same geometrical interpretation. Let  d and  H denote the set of vectors inside the hyper-sphere given by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">15</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_16">14</ref>), respectively. With these definitions, we can see that ideally the authentication system should establish a mapping:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">→   d H .</formula><p>However, because the actual mapping is highly nonlinear due to permutation and truncation, we seek another mathematically tractable way to perform analysis.</p><p>Referring to Eqs. ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">13</ref>), we define the corresponding vector x Q for the query binary vector x d . Since the orthogonal transfor- mation preserves the vector length, we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">( )= ( ) ( )= ∑ | ( ) -( )| ∑ | ( )| + ∑ | ( )| ( ) = = =    t x t x t x t x t x k k k k , , ,<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">d d Q Q d d k N Q Q k N Q k N Q 1 2 1 2 1 2</formula><p>On the other hand, we can rewrite (10) into N N matrix with the first r elements of the main diagonal equal to 1 and the rest elements equal to zero, Eq. ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">( )= ∑ | ( ) -( )| ∑ | ( )| + ∑ | ( )| ( ) = = =  t x t x t x k k k k ,<label>18</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">H H k r Q Q k r Q k r Q 1 2 1 2 1 2</formula><p>We further define the partial energy of a signal vector u as</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">∑ ( )= | ( ) | ( ) =  u u i j k ; ,<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">k i j 2</formula><p>where ≥ j i and it is assumed that ( )=  u i ; , 0 0. A special case is the energy of the signal vector ( )  u N ; 1, . With this definition, we can rewrite ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_22">16</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">18</ref>) as Since x d can be regarded as a random vector, the orthogonal transformation of it is also a random vector. In addition, we use a permutation matrix whose permutation order is made according to a uniform distribution, that is, in each row of the permutation matrix, the location of the non-zero element is a uniformly distributed random variable. Based on this formulation, we can write the following expectation values:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">( )= ( ) ( )+ ( ) ( )     t x e t x N N N , ;<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">( ) = ( ) ( ) ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥ ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥   e e E r r N E N ; 1, ; 1, 22 d d ( ) = ( ) ( ) ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥ ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥   t t E r r N E N ; 1, ; 1, 23 d d ( ) = ( ) ( ) ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥ ⎡ ⎣ ⎢ ⎤ ⎦ ⎥   x x E r r N E N ; 1, ; 1, 24 d d</formula><p>Using these results, we define the stochastic distance by replacing each term in ( <ref type="formula">20</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">21</ref>) with its corresponding expectation value, which yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">^( )= ( ) ( ) + ( ) ( ) ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦     t x e t x E N E N E N , ;<label>1,</label></formula><p>; 1, ; 1, 25</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">d d d d d ^( )= ( ) ( ) + ( ) ( ) ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦ ⎡ ⎣ ⎤ ⎦     t x e t x E r E r E r , ;<label>1, ; 1, ; 1, 26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_32">H H d d d</formula><p>It can be readily seen that</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">^( )= ^( ) ( )   t x t x , ,<label>27</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">H H d d</formula><p>This proves that in a stochastic sense, the distance between two binary vectors is preserved after the partial Hadamard transform. The above analysis provides a theoretical justification of the experimental results in Section 5.1.</p><p>Remark: It follows from the derivations leading to ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_33">27</ref>) that stochastic distance preservation is a statistical property, not a deterministic one. As such, for a specific instance, ( )= ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">  t x t x , , H H d d</formula><p>may not hold. Given an instance of ( )  t x , H H , its distance to the mean value is random and not necessarily close to the mean, just like a white noise process with zero mean, for which each instance position is unpredictable and might not be close to 0. Therefore, the property of 'stochastic distance preservation' should not be understood as a mere distance preservation property for every instance of ( ) <ref type="figure"> t</ref> x , </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Non-invertibility analysis</head><p>Non-invertibility is an essential requirement for biometric template protection. To meet this requirement, the transformed vector t H [see (11)] should not allow the binary vector t d to be reconstructed. Now we analyze the worst-case scenario where the stored template t H and the parameter key K in (6) are both compromised and the transformation method is known by the adversary. With the knowledge of the parameter key K , the ad- versary can retrieve the transformation matrix Hn in (7). However, the transformation in ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) constitutes an underdetermined system of linear equations, thus having many solutions to t D , all of which satisfy <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. The true solution is the DFT of the binary vector t d . It is well known that a key property of the Fourier transform is to decorrelate highly correlated signal samples, leading to a relatively flat spectrum. Hence, even though elements of the binary vector t d might be sparsely distributed, its frequency samples are evenly distributed. Since the true solution is hidden among many other solutions, it makes the search for the true t D practically infeasible.</p><p>One may argue that for an underdetermined system such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, it is easy to compute the pseudo-inverse of Hn , yielding the least squares (LS) solution. It is true that the LS solution is a solution to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, but it is only one of many possible solutions. Moreover, the LS solution has no correlation with the true t D . In fact, the LS solution and the true t D can be far apart in metric terms; see an illustrative example in our earlier work <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> and the details of the test result in Section 5.1, demonstrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>. When the true t D is pro- tected securely, the adversary is unable to retrieve the binary vector t d . Thus, the important information about raw biometric data is protected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Computational complexity analysis</head><p>The computational complexity of the proposed approach is low, which is manifested by the fast Fourier transform (FFT) and fast methods for calculating the Hadamard transform. Due to the fact that computational speed is largely affected by software development platforms and code optimization levels, (•)</p><p> is a just in- dication of an algorithm's the computational cost <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[38]</ref>. Hence, we use it to demonstrate the computational efficiency of our method.</p><p>The proposed algorithm mainly consists of the DFT and the partial Hadamard transform. The N-point DFT in ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) can be im- plemented via a Radix-2 FFT algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[37]</ref>, e.g., the N-point decimation-in-time FFT algorithm or the N-point decimation-infrequency FFT algorithm. The associated computational cost is</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">( )  N N log 2 .</formula><p>With the decomposition given in (3), the computational complexity of the partial Hadamard transform in ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) is ( )  Nn , where = N 2 n . Overall, the main computation of the proposed al- gorithm amounts to ( ( + ))  N n N log 2 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Experimental results and analysis</head><p>The proposed method is evaluated for two cases: Case 1evaluation over independently, randomly generated binary vectors; and Case 2design of cancelable fingerprint templates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Case 1evaluation over independently, randomly generated binary vectors</head><p>In this case, binary vectors of length ( = ) 4096 2 12 were in- dependently, randomly generated using a wide range of probabilities. The probability of element d(i), = … -i m 0, , 1, of t d taking the value of one is expressed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">( ( ) = ) = ( ) P d i p 1 28</formula><p>r where we set in the experiment = … p 5%, 10%, 15%, , 95%, re- spectively. The parameter key K in (6) was also randomly gener- ated, whose length r ¼2000. The binary vectors generated went through first the DFT in ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) and then the partial Hadamard transform in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> governed by K .</p><p>To assess the effectiveness of the proposed method, we used the distance measures in ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> to respectively measure the distance in the data domain and the distance after the partial Hadamard transform in the transformed domain. The plot showing the probability versus distance is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>. It can be seen in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> that the mean distance curves before and after transformation are almost overlapped, which indicates that the distance between binary vectors is well preserved after the partial Hadamard transform. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref> also shows that the mean dis- tance between binary vectors both before and after transformation decreases as the probability of one increases. This comes as no surprise; when binary one occurs more frequently, it is more likely for binary vectors to match each other. Some statistical tests were carried out on the absolute difference between distance measures before and after transformation by generating 200 independent binary vectors for each value of p in the range of [ ] 5%, 95% ; see (28). Hence, there were 100 distance comparisons before and after transformation, respectively, for each value of p. Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref> respectively show the mean and variance of the absolute difference between distance measures before and after transformation. Observations are that both the mean and the variance are close to 0, which demonstrates that the proposed approach preserves the stochastic distance between binary vectors after the transformation, as theoretically proven in Section 4.2.</p><p>To investigate whether the proposed method can withstand such an invertible attack as the one demonstrated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> (Section 5), we randomly generated binary vectors of length ( = ) 4096 2 12 . The percentage of one in these binary vectors varied from 1%, 2%, … to 15%, which fits in with the case where binary strings involved in cancelable templates usually have more 0s than 1s. Then we randomly generated the parameter key K of length r ¼1500 so as to perform the partial Hadamard transform. According to [27]  (Section 5), we calculated the LS (least squares) estimate based on the transformed template. The distance between the original binary vector and its LS estimate is plotted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>. Clearly, this distance is large enough to claim that the LS estimate is dissimilar to the original binary vector. Hence, the proposed method is robust against such an invertible attack.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Case 2design of cancelable fingerprint templates</head><p>In this section, the proposed method is applied to cancelable template design. Specifically, we built cancelable fingerprint templates using the proposed partial Hadamard transform based on the binary strings generated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. The algorithm used to generate the binary strings is shown as follows:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Input: The minutia set</head><p>Step 1: Form the pair-minutiae vectors according to Eq. ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</p><p>Step 2: Find the length n to quantize each pair-minutiae vector. n bits cover the dynamic range of [ -] 0, 2 1 n , or equivalently 2 n bins.</p><p>Step 3: Inspect each quantized pair-minutiae vector and index a bin by 1 if the value of the quantized pair-minutiae vector falls in it only once. All other bins are indexed by 0. Output: The binary string of length 2 n</p><p>We then tested our cancelable fingerprint template design over the public databases FVC2002 DB1-DB3 [35] and FVC2004 DB2 <ref type="bibr">[36]</ref>. Each database contains 800 fingerprint images with 8 impressions per finger. Quality of fingerprint images in these databases can be vastly different, varying from reasonably good quality to very low quality. Details of each database are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">1</ref>. To evaluate the proposed approach, we focus on the following three areas:</p><p>1. Performance in the lost-token scenario 2. Revocability and diversity</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Unlinkability</head><p>The binary vectors used in the tests were of length 2 15 according to the binary strings from <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. The randomly generated parameter key K was of length 15,000. We make use of the dis- tance measures ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> to determine similarity between binary vectors before and after transformation. That is, the similarity score of two binary vectors in the data domain is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">( )= -( )= - + ( )  t x t x e e t t x x S , 1 , 1<label>29</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">d d d d d T d d T d d T d</formula><p>and the similarity score of two binary vectors after the partial Hadamard transform is obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">( )= -( )= - + ( )  t x t x e e t t x x S , 1 , 1<label>30</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">H H H H H T H H T H H T H</formula><p>As for cancelable fingerprint templates, in order to protect original biometric information, fingerprint matching should take place in the transformed domain. Thus, we use <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref> to calculate similarity scores of the cancelable templates designed by the proposed method in the transformed domain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1.">Performance in the lost-token scenario</head><p>We conducted experiments to evaluate the recognition performance of the proposed method in the worst case, i.e., the losttoken scenario, where an imposter obtains a user's key and uses it to perform authentication. This was simulated by assigning the same K to all users in the dataset. The performance indices adopted in our experiments were the Equal Error Rate (EER), False Acceptance Rate (FAR) and False Rejection Rate (FRR), which is related to the Genuine Acceptance Rate (GAR) by + = GAR FRR 1. We conducted both genuine testing and imposter testing over the four databases, i.e., FVC2002 DB1-DB3 and FVC2004 DB2. The first and second sample images of each finger were used as the template and query, respectively, leading to 100 genuine scores and ( = ( × ) ) 4950 100 99 /2 imposter scores for each database. The Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) under the lost-token scenario for each dataset is plotted in Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>. For comparison purpose, the ROC of the binary strings without template protection (i.e. prior to transformation) is also shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>. It can be seen that recognition performance of the binary strings before and after transformation is very similar for FVC2002 DB1 and DB2, while the   pre-transformation performance is better than that of post-transformation for FVC2002 DB3 and FVC2004 DB2. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9</ref> illustrates the genuine and imposter distributions of the datasets for FVC2002 DB2 and DB3 with template protection in the lost-token scenario. The genuine and imposter distributions are plotted based on the genuine and imposter testing scores, respectively. Accordingly, the genuine and imposter distributions reflect the matching result distribution between same users and different users, respectively. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">2</ref> reports the lost-token EER comparison of the proposed method with the state-of-the-art methods that also use binary strings/codes. The EER of the proposed method in the lost-token scenario is 1% over FVC2002 DB1, 2% over FVC2002 DB2, 5.2% over FVC2002 DB3 and 13.3% over FVC2004 DB2. Compared to FVC2002 DB1 and DB2, the EER is higher for FVC2002 DB3 since fingerprint images in this database are of lower quality. The EER for FVC2004 DB2 is the highest among all the four databases, which is attributed to images in this database being poor quality, because during fingerprint acquisition, the individuals were requested to deliberately distort their fingerprints <ref type="bibr">[36]</ref>. For FVC2002 DB2, our method performs better than <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref> but marginally worse than <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. However, the method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> is implementationally more demanding than the proposed method, because the Graph-based Hamming Embedding algorithm has to extract a binary string from each of the minutia vicinities and fingerprint matching is also exhaustive with pairwise comparisons across all binary codes. For FVC2004 DB2, the EER of the proposed method is worse than that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>, which could be due to parameter setting and tuning in the phase of feature extraction and representation, as explained below.</p><p>It is worth noting that with binary strings being the input to the proposed algorithm, matching performance of the generated cancelable templates depends on how well the binary string represents biometric features of interest. Binary strings that accurately represent the invariant local minutia structures are bound to result in better performance. So how to come up with a good feature representation is always of importance in cancelable biometrics.</p><p>Theoretically speaking, there is a potential risk of the attack via record multiplicity (ARM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[39]</ref> for the proposed method. This is because when an adversary knows the transformation method and obtains a sufficient number of transformed templates plus the parameter keys, the ARM can nullify the rank deficient condition of (7) to retrieve t D (and further the binary vector t d ). To mitigate the risk of the ARM, we can cut down the length r of the parameter key K so that it significantly increases the difficulty for the ad- versary to accumulate such a large number of transformed templates and the associated parameter keys. For example, for the binary vector t d of length 2 15 , if the length r of K is reduced to 800, then the adversary must successfully attack more than 40 different applications, in which a user has enrolled his/her fingerprint, so as to acquire enough transformed templates and the corresponding parameter keys to launch the ARM. Obviously, this is practically difficult or even infeasible.</p><p>Although reducing the key length makes the ARM difficult, it can impact on matching performance, as shown by our experiment. We reduced the length r to 800 to evaluate the matching performance of the proposed method over FVC2002 DB2. For r ¼800, the EER dropped to 4.1%, compared to 2% when r¼ 15,000 (refer to Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">2</ref>). This test demonstrates that there is always a trade-off between matching accuracy and security. The ARM is an unsolved, challenging issue for cancelable templates. Although it is not the focus of the proposed method, our scheme provides a trade-off solution for the conflicting demands of security strength and matching performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2.">Revocability and diversity</head><p>Revocability and diversity are fundamental properties of cancelable biometrics. We carried out tests to investigate whether reissued templates that originate from the same fingerprint are correlated. We generated 100 transformed versions of the first impression of each finger in FVC2002 DB2. We then compared these pseudo-imposter templates with the original ones. To show clear comparison, the pseudo-imposter distribution is drawn in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10</ref>, together with the genuine and imposter distributions when each user in the database has a different key. It is clear from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10</ref> 8. ROC of each dataset without template protection (pre-transformation) and with template protection (post-transformation) in the lost-token scenario.  that the pseudo-imposter and imposter distributions overlap substantially, meaning that the transformed versions of the same finger are different and unrelated to one another. This is also supported by the mean and standard deviation values for both pseudo-imposter and imposter distributions. The mean and standard derivation of the pseudo-imposter distribution are 0.0409 and 0.0189, respectively, compared with 0.0356 (mean) and 0.0138 (standard derivation) of the imposter distribution. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11</ref> illustrates a specific example in which transformed templates obtained from the same fingerprint impression using two different parameter keys look disparate. To show the results clearly, we only plotted the first 50 elements of the transformed template t H in either graph in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3.">Unlinkability</head><p>The unlinkability tests measure if the transformed templates generated from the same fingerprint are different enough so that fingerprint templates of the same individual generated for different applications cannot be cross-matched. We based our tests on two indicators specified in <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[40]</ref>: the false cross-match rate (FCMR) and the false non-cross-match rate (FNCMR). FCMR is defined as the ratio of successful matching attempts between non-mated pairs to the total matching attempts of non-mated pairs, and FNCMR refers to the ratio of unsuccessful matching attempts between mated pairs to the total matching attempts of mated pairs.</p><p>The FNCMR was obtained by matching the transformed templates (using different keys) of the first and second impressions of each finger in FVC2002 DB2. The FCMR was acquired by matching the transformed template the first impression of each finger against the transformed template of the first impression of different fingers in FVC2002 DB2. The FNCMR versus FCMR curve is plotted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">12</ref>. It is shown that unlinkability of the cancelable templates designed by the proposed method exhibits the expected behavior of a cross-comparator <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[40]</ref>, i.e., + ≈ FCMR FNCMR 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion</head><p>We have proposed a partial Hadamard transform-based ap- proach to the design of cancelable fingerprint templates containing binary biometric representations. Due to the nature of the Hadamard transform, the new method is computationally effi- cient and thus suitable for resource-limited applications, e.g., smartcards and mobile phones. The proposed approach has a nice propertystochastic distance preservation, that is, the stochastic distance between binary vectors is preserved under the proposed transformation (the DFT and partial Hadamard transform). This   property is theoretically proved and verified by experiments. Using the proposed approach, the generated cancelable fingerprint templates satisfy all the design criteria for cancelable biometrics, namely revocability, diversity, non-invertibility and performance. Matching performance of the cancelable fingerprint templates designed by using the proposed partial Hadamard transform compares favorably with the state-of-the-art cancelable templates that also involve binary biometric representations.</p><p>As the performance of the proposed method is affected by the quality of binary biometric representations, we will investigate effective ways to capture discriminative biometric feature information while coping with biometric uncertainty, so that better binary biometric representations can be produced. Also, how to fuse different modalities <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[41]</ref> in the design of cancelable multimodal templates remains a future topic for us.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where 'dist' denotes the Hamming distance, and ( ) t w d and ( ) x w d are the Hamming weight of t d and x d , respectively. Equivalently, (8) can be expressed using the Euclidean distance:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Left: the image of impression 1, fingerprint no. 7 in FVC2002 DB2 with minutiae shown and labeled. Right: the transformed template given by the complex vector t H .</figDesc><graphic coords="4,75.98,58.61,180.91,375.43" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .Fig. 3 .</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Left: the image of impression 1, fingerprint no. 38 in FVC2002 DB1 with minutiae shown. Right: the transformed template given by the complex vector t H .</figDesc><graphic coords="5,85.76,58.61,191.98,282.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. The mean distance of binary vectors in the data domain and after the partial Hadamard transform (PHT) in the transformed domain.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. The mean of the absolute difference between distance measures before and after transformation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig.6. The variance of the absolute difference between distance measures before and after transformation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig.7. The distance between a randomly generated binary vector and its LS estimate.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig.9. Genuine and imposter distributions for FVC2002 DB2 and DB3 with template protection in the lost-token scenario.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Genuine, imposter and pseudo-imposter distributions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig.11. The first 50 elements of the transformed templates of impression 1, fingerprint no. 7 in FVC2002 DB2 using two different parameter keys.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. FCMR versus FNCMR evaluated over FVC2002 DB2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2. Any two distinct rows of H n are orthogonal.3. H n is symmetric and orthogonal. That is,</figDesc><table><row><cell>H H n n T</cell><cell>=</cell><cell>I M</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Information about the databases used in our experiments.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Database</cell><cell>FVC2002</cell><cell cols="2">FVC2002 FVC2002</cell><cell>FVC2004</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>DB1</cell><cell>DB2</cell><cell>DB3</cell><cell>DB2</cell></row><row><cell>No. of fingers</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell>No. of images per</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>finger</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Resolution</cell><cell>500 dpi</cell><cell>569 dpi</cell><cell>500 dpi</cell><cell>500 dpi</cell></row><row><cell>Sensor type</cell><cell>Optical</cell><cell>Optical</cell><cell>Capacitive</cell><cell>Optical</cell></row><row><cell>Image size</cell><cell>388 Â 374</cell><cell cols="2">296 Â 560 300 Â 300</cell><cell>328 Â 364</cell></row><row><cell>Image quality</cell><cell>Good-</cell><cell>Medium</cell><cell cols="2">Medium-Low Very low</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Medium</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Equal error rate (in percentage) comparison under the lost-token scenario.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Cancelable templates using binary</cell><cell cols="4">FVC2002 FVC2002 FVC2002 FVC2004</cell></row><row><cell>strings</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>DB1</cell><cell>DB2</cell><cell>DB3</cell><cell>DB2</cell></row><row><cell>Jin et al. [20]</cell><cell>1.19</cell><cell>6.94</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>8.66</cell></row><row><cell>Wang and Hu [21]</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>7.5</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Wong et al. [22]</cell><cell>1.97</cell><cell>2.54</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>9.2</cell></row><row><cell>Jin et al. [23]</cell><cell>4.36</cell><cell>1.77</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>21.82</cell></row><row><cell>Wang and Hu [24]</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2.3</cell><cell>6.12</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Wang and Hu [25]</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Proposed method</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5.2</cell><cell>13.3</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>d d d d d d</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>This work was supported in part by the ARC grants LP110100602, LP100200538, LP100100404 and LP120100595.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ratha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Biometrics perils and patches</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2727" to="2738" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Delaunay quadrangle-based fingerprint authentication system with template protection using topology code for local registration and security enhancement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inf. Forensics Secur</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1179" to="1192" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extraction and fusion of partial face features for cancelable identity verification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Toh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Teoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3288" to="3303" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A finger-vein based cancellable bio-cryptosystem, network and system security</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lect. Notes Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7873</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="784" to="790" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free row-co-occurrence cancelable palmprint fuzzy vault</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Leng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Teoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2290" to="2303" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multibiometric cryptosystems based on feature-level fusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nagar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nandakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inf. Forensics Secur</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biometric template security</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nandakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nagar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EURASIP J. Adv. Signal Process. Spec. Issue Adv. Signal Process. Pattern Recognit. Methods Biom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">579416</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biohashing: two factor authentication featuring fingerprint data and tokenised random number</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Teoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C L</forename><surname>Ngo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2245" to="2255" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Random multispace quantization as an analytic mechanism for biohashing of biometric and random identity inputs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Teoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C L</forename><surname>Ngo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1892" to="1901" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anonymous and revocable fingerprint recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Farooq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tsai-Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ratha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generating cancelable fingerprint templates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ratha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chikkerur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">String-based cancelable fingerprint templates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 6th IEEE Conference on Industrial Electronics and Applications (ICIEA)</title>
		<meeting>6th IEEE Conference on Industrial Electronics and Applications (ICIEA)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1028" to="1033" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free cancelable fingerprint templates based on local minutiae information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-Y</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Toh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst. Man Cybern. Part B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="980" to="992" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symmetric hash functions for secure fingerprint biometric systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tulyakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Farooq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mansukhani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Govindaraju</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2427" to="2436" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A revocable fingerprint template for security and privacy preserving</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Teoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">KSII Trans. Internet Inf. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1327" to="1341" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancelable fingerprint templates using minutiae-based bitstrings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Netw. Comput. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pair-polar coordinate-based cancelable fingerprint templates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10-11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2555" to="2564" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A robust alignment-free fingerprint hashing algorithm based on minimum distance graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Das</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Karthik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Garai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3373" to="3388" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancelable fingerprint templates with Delaunay triangle-based local structures, cyberspace safety and security</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lect. Notes Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fingerprint template protection with minutiae-based bit-string for security and privacy preserving</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Teoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Expert Syst. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6157" to="6167" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alignment-free cancelable fingerprint template design: a densely infinite-to-one mapping (DITOM) approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4129" to="4137" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced multi-line code for minutiae-based fingerprint template protection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Teoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L D</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1221" to="1229" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A non-invertible randomized graphbased Hamming embedding for generating cancelable fingerprint template</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Teoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Goi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design of alignment-free cancelable fingerprint templates via curtailed circular convolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1321" to="1329" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A blind system identification approach to cancelable fingerprint templates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An efficient dynamic reliability-dependent bit allocation for biometric discretization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B J</forename><surname>Teoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Toh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1960" to="1971" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biometric template transformation: a security analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nagar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nandakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SPIE 7541, Media Forensics and Security II</title>
		<meeting>SPIE 7541, Media Forensics and Security II</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">754100</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the security of biohashing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kalker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SPIE-IS&amp;T Electronic Imaging, Media Forensics and Security II</title>
		<meeting>SPIE-IS&amp;T Electronic Imaging, Media Forensics and Security II</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7541</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">75410</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>8 pages</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An analysis on invertibility of cancelable biometrics based on BioHashing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-H</forename><surname>Cheung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>You</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of International Conference on Imaging Science, Systems, and Technology</title>
		<meeting>International Conference on Imaging Science, Systems, and Technology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="45" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling IrisCode and its variants as convex polyhedral cones and its security implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1148" to="1160" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inverse operation and preimage attack on Bio-Hashing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Workshop on Computational Intelligence in Biometrics: Theory, Algorithms, and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hadamard Matrix Analysis and Synthesis With Applications to Communications and Signal/Image Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yarlagadda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hershey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht, the Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Hadamard transform-based method for the design of cancellable fingerprint templates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Congress on Image and Signal Processing</title>
		<meeting>the International Congress on Image and Signal Processing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1682" to="1687" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Maltoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Maio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Prabhakar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Fingerprint Recognition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Proakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Manolakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Digital Signal Processing: Principles, Algorithms, and Applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Upper Saddle River, New Jersey, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Golub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Van Loan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Matrix Computations</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attacks via record multiplicity on cancelable biometrics templates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Concurr. Comput.: Pract. Exp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1593" to="1605" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Criteria towards metrics for benchmarking template protection algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Simoens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Beato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Busch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Newton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preneel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE/IAPR International Conference on Biometrics</title>
		<meeting>IEEE/IAPR International Conference on Biometrics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="498" to="505" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutual dependency of features in multimodal biometric systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electron. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Australia. She obtained her Ph.D. degree from the Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, University of Melbourne, Australia. Her research areas are biometric security, blind system identification and wireless communications</title>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Electronic Engineering, La Trobe University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He has obtained his Ph.D. degree in image processing from La Trobe University. His main research interest is in the field of statistical signal processing, Generalized linear systems, data compression</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">He has published 9 papers as either sole author or first author in the prestigious IEEE Transactions Image Processing</title>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Guang Deng is an Associate Professor in the Department of Electronic Engineering, La Trobe University, Australia</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He has worked in Ruhr University Germany on the prestigious German Alexander von Humboldt Fellowship 1995-1996; research fellow in Delft University of the Netherlands 1997-1998, and research fellow in Melbourne University, Australia 1998-1999. Jiankun&apos;s main research interest is in the field of cyber security including Image Processing/Forensics and machine learning where he has published many papers in highquality conferences and journals including IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (PAMI)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ARC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983. 2000</date>
			<pubPlace>Canberra, Australia; China</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Jiankun Hu is full Professor and Research Director of Cyber Security Lab, School of Engineering and IT, University of New South Wales ; Ph.D. in Control Engineering from Harbin Institute of Technology, China in 1993 and Masters by Research in Computer Science and Software Engineering from Monash University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>He has served in the editorial board of up to 7 international journals and served as Security Symposium Chair of IEEE flagship. Australian Research Council) Grants and has served at the prestigious Panel of Mathematics, Information and Computing Sciences (MIC), ARC ERA (The Excellence in Research for Australia. Evaluation Committee</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
