<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Multiple-Input Multiple-Output OFDM with Index Modulation: Low-Complexity Detector Design</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Beixiong</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
							<email>zheng.bx@mail.scut.edu.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE, Ertugrul Basar, Senior Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Miaowen</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Fangjiong</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<email>eefjchen@scut.edu.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Miaowen</forename><forename type="middle">Wen</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electronic and Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South China University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510641</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electronic and Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South China University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510641</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Mobile Communications Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210096</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Istanbul Technical University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Multiple-Input Multiple-Output OFDM with Index Modulation: Low-Complexity Detector Design</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D9DCADD8B416159A843A8B98408DC61F</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803</idno>
					<note type="submission">This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T09:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>OFDM with index modulation (OFDM-IM)</term>
					<term>spatial modulation (SM)</term>
					<term>MIMO systems</term>
					<term>sequential Monte Carlo (SMC)</term>
					<term>maximum-likelihood (ML) detection</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Multiple-input multiple-output orthogonal frequency division multiplexing with index modulation (MIMO-OFDM-IM), which provides a flexible trade-off between spectral efficiency and error performance, is recently proposed as a promising transmission technique for energy-efficient 5G wireless communications systems. However, due to the dependence of subcarrier symbols within each subblock and the strong inter-channel interference, it is challenging to detect the transmitted data effectively while imposing low computational burden to the receiver. In this paper, we propose two types of low-complexity detectors based on the sequential Monte Carlo (SMC) theory for the detection of MIMO-OFDM-IM signals. The first detector draws samples independently at the subblock level while the second detector draws samples at the subcarrier level with further reduced complexity. To meet the constraint of the subcarrier combinations within each subblock, the second detector is further coupled with a carefully designed legality examination method. Attributed to the effectiveness of legality examination and deterministic SMC sampling, both proposed detectors achieve near-optimal error performance for the MIMO-OFDM-IM system.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>W ITH the increasing demand for higher spectral effi- ciency and reliability in the next generation wireless communications, multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems have been receiving great attention for their ability in improving the transmission rate and error performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Recently, a novel MIMO scheme called spatial modulation (SM) has emerged as an appealing candidate to fulfill the spectral and energy efficiency requirements of the next generation wireless communication systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. In SM, information bits are conveyed by not only the modulated symbol but also the index of the active transmit antenna. Compared with classical MIMO, SM has a number of advantages, including reduced interchannel interference, relaxed inter-antenna synchronization requirements, and reduced receiver complexity <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Owing to its various advantages, design and analysis of SM transmission in various scenarios, e.g., adaptive SM <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, generalized SM <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, and energy evaluation of SM <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, are extensively investigated. Specially, for practical multipath fading channels, single-carrier aided SM <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> is conceived as an appealing technique to eliminate inter-antenna interference and achieve high energy efficiency with only one active antenna at any time instant. Compared with single-carrier transmission, orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM) is usually more favored for multipath fading channels as it facilitates low-complexity receiver design by converting the multipath fading channel into several parallel flat fading channels in the expense of an increased peak-toaverage-power ratio (PAPR) at the transmitter.</p><p>By replacing the antenna indices in the MIMO system with the subcarrier indices of the OFDM signal, the concept of SM has been successfully transplanted to OFDM systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. As the representative frequency-domain extension of SM, OFDM with index modulation (OFDM-IM), which activates a subset of subcarriers to carry the modulated symbols simultaneously, is proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. In OFDM-IM, the information is embedded in both subcarrier indices and Mary constellation domains. Compared with classical OFDM, OFDM-IM provides a more flexible trade-off between the spectral efficiency and the error performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, and has the potential to achieve much better bit error rate (BER) performance for low-to-mid spectral efficiencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</p><p>Owing to its interesting properties and superior BER performance, OFDM-IM has attracted considerable research interest over the past few years <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. A subcarrier-level interleaving method is proposed for OFDM-IM to attain coding gains from uncorrelated subcarriers <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, OFDM-IM coupled with the coordinate interleaving principle is proposed to explore potential diversity gains of OFDM-IM. By extending the index modulation to include both the in-phase and quadrature dimensions, a generalization of OFDM-IM is proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, a low-complexity maximumlikelihood (ML) detector is developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. By introducing the index modulation in both space and frequency domains, a generalization of space-frequency index modulation is proposed to convey information via antenna index, subcarrier index, and M -ary modulation bits <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. To reduce the intercarrier interference caused by Doppler shift and/or transceiver imperfection, OFDM-IM merged with intercarrier interference self-cancellation is proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, a hybrid OFDM-IM technique is proposed to enhance the spectral efficiency and deal with the severe intercarrier interference problem encountered in underwater acoustic communications. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, the optimal number of active subcarriers selection problem is investigated. In recent times, the performance of OFDM-IM is analyzed in terms of ergodic achievable rate <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> and average mutual information <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>.</p><p>Due to the advantages of OFDM and MIMO transmission techniques, the combination of them has been regarded as a promising solution for enhancing the data rates of next generation wireless communications systems. More recently, by combining OFDM-IM with MIMO transmission techniques, a novel MIMO-OFDM with index modulation (MIMO-OFDM-IM) scheme is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, which exhibits the potential to surpass the classical MIMO-OFDM. Specifically, by deactivating a subset of subcarriers, MIMO-OFDM-IM has the potential to achieve much better BER performance than classical MIMO-OFDM, resulting in higher energy efficiency for practical systems. Then, the error performance of the MIMO-OFDM-IM scheme is investigated theoretically for different types of detectors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> and its adaptation to visible light communications systems is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. In this scheme, since each transmit antenna transmits an independent OFDM-IM block, its spectral efficiency can reach N t times that of OFDM-IM, where N t denotes the number of transmit antennas. Inheriting from OFDM-IM, MIMO-OFDM-IM is also able to provide an interesting trade-off between the spectral efficiency and the error performance by adjusting the number of active subcarriers in each OFDM-IM subblock. However, due to the dependence of the subcarrier symbols within each OFDM-IM subblock and the strong inter-channel interference (ICI) between the transmit antennas of the MIMO-OFDM-IM system, it becomes much more challenging to detect the active subcarrier indices and modulated symbols. Although the ML detector is able to achieve optimal performance, it necessitates an exhaustive search with prohibitive computational complexity, which makes itself impractical for MIMO-OFDM-IM. To reduce the detection complexity, several low complexity detectors, e.g., simple minimum mean square error (MMSE) detector, log-likelihood ratio (LLR) based MMSE detector, and ordered successive interference cancellation (OSIC) based MMSE detector are proposed for the detection of MIMO-OFDM-IM <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. However, those existing low complexity detectors suffer from a significant error performance loss compared to the ML detector. Therefore, the design of lowcomplexity detection algorithms for MIMO-OFDM-IM with near-optimal error performance remains an open as well as challenging research problem.</p><p>In this paper, in order to achieve near-optimal error performance while maintaining low computational complexity, two types of detection algorithms based on the sequential Monte Carlo (SMC) theory are proposed for MIMO-OFDM-IM. By regarding each OFDM-IM subblock as a super modulated symbol drawn from a large finite set, the first type of detector draws samples independently at the subblock level. Although it is capable of achieving near-optimal performance with substantially reduced complexity, its decoding complexity can be still unsatisfactory when the size of the OFDM-IM subblock grows much larger. To further reduce the complexity, the second type of detector is proposed to draw samples subcarrierwise from the modified constellation with a much smaller size.</p><p>To meet the constraint on the legal active subcarrier combinations within each OFDM-IM subblock, the second type of detector is coupled with a carefully designed examination method to avoid illegal samples. Thanks to the effectiveness of the deterministic SMC sampling and legality examination, it only suffers from a marginal error performance loss. Finally, computer simulation and numerical results in terms of BER and number of complex multiplications (NCM) corroborate the superiority of both proposed detection methods.</p><p>The rest of this paper is organized as follows. Section II introduces the system model of MIMO-OFDM-IM. Section III gives a brief introduction of deterministic SMC and a sequential structure of MIMO-OFDM-IM. The deterministic SMC aided detection methods are developed in Section IV. The computational complexity of different detection methods is analyzed and compared in Section V. Section VI provides the computer simulation and numerical results. Finally, conclusions are given in Section VII.</p><p>Notation: Upper and lower case boldface letters denote matrices and column vectors, respectively. (•)</p><p>T , (•) H , and (•) • p denotes the p -norm and ∅ represents the empty set. count(•) returns the number of non-zero elements in a set or a vector. N K denotes the binomial coefficient, which is defined to be zero if N &lt; K.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. OVERVIEW OF MIMO-OFDM-IM</head><p>In this paper, we consider a MIMO-OFDM-IM system equipped with N t transmit and N r receive antennas <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. The block diagram of the MIMO-OFDM-IM transmitter is depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. Each MIMO-OFDM-IM frame is comprised of a total number of mN t incoming data bits. These bits are divided into N t groups for N t transmit antennas, each of which contains m bits for the generation of an OFDM-IM block to be transmitted from a transmit antenna. These m bits are further divided into G subgroups, each of which consists of p bits, i.e., m = Gp. Assuming N F available subcarriers of each block, each subgroup is then used to generate an OFDM-IM subblock consisting of N = N F /G subcarriers.</p><p>Unlike classical OFDM, which maps all data bits to the constellation points for all subcarriers, OFDM-IM separates p bits of each subblock into two parts for different purposes: the first part with p 1 = log  subcarriers, while the remaining N -K subcarriers are set to be idle;<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> the second part with p 2 = K log 2 M bits is mapped into K modulated symbols for the K active subcarriers via M -ary modulation. The mapping between the p 1 bits and the subcarrier combination patterns can be implemented by using a look-up table or the combinatorial method <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. Consider the g-th (1 ≤ g ≤ G) OFDM-IM subblock at the t-th (1 ≤ t ≤ N t ) transmit antenna. Accordingly, the output of the first part should be the indices of K active subcarriers, which are given by the following set:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">J g t = {j g t (1), . . . , j g t (K)}<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where j g t (k) ∈ {1, . . . , N } for k = 1, . . . , K, and the elements of J g t are sorted in an ascending order, i.e., j g t (1) &lt; j g t (2) &lt; • • • &lt; j g t (K). The output of the second part should be K modulated symbols {s g t (n)} n∈J g t , where s g t (n) is drawn from a complex alphabet S with | S| = M and we assume that E |s g t (n)|<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> = 1 for the normalization of signal constellation. Therefore, the g-th OFDM-IM subblock element at the t-th transmit antenna can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">x g t = [x g t (1) x g t (2) • • • x g t (N )]</formula><p>T , where</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">x g t (n) = s g t (n), n ∈ J g t 0, otherwise .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>From above, it is clear that each subblock of the MIMO-OFDM-IM contains a fixed number of active subcarriers, whose positions carry information through the subcarrier indices.</p><p>After generating all OFDM-IM subblocks, each OFDM-IM block is created by concatenating G OFDM-IM subblocks in each branch of the transmitter, which is denoted by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">x t = x 1 t T x 2 t T • • • x G t T T [x t (1) x t (2) • • • x t (N F )] T ,</formula><p>where 1 ≤ t ≤ N t . To fully benefit from the frequencyselective fading, a G × N block interleaver (a.k.a. OFDM-IM with interleaved grouping in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>) is employed in each branch of the transmitter. Before transmission, each OFDM-IM block is first transformed into the time-domain signal block by employing an N F -point inverse discrete Fourier transform (IDFT), and then appended with a CP of length N cp , which is longer than the maximum delay spread of the channel. The spectral efficiency of MIMO-OFDM-IM, measured in terms of bit/s/Hz, is thus given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">η = mN t N F + N cp = N t log 2 N K N + N cp /G + N t K log 2 M N + N cp /G .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, after passing through the frequencyselective MIMO channel, the CP is removed and an N F -point discrete Fourier transform (DFT) followed by a G × N block deinterleaver is employed at each receive antenna to obtain the received block in the frequency domain. Specifically, for the r-th (1 ≤ r ≤ N r ) receive antenna, the g-th (1 ≤ g ≤ G) received subblock after block deinterleaving can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">y g r = ρ N t N K Nt t=1 diag h g r,t x g t + w g r (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">)</formula><p>where y g r [y g r (1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">y g r (2) • • • y g r (N )]</formula><p>T , ρ is signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) per receive antenna, h g r,t denotes the corresponding channel vector of dimensions N × 1 which contains the channel frequency responses (CFRs) for the g-th OFDM-IM subblock, and w g r is the N × 1 vector comprised of zeromean independent additive white Gaussian noise (AWGN) samples with unit variance. Here the factor N K is applied at the transmitter to balance the total transmit power, which is referred to as power reallocation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. Furthermore, for the n-th (1 ≤ n ≤ N ) subcarrier of the g-th (1 ≤ g ≤ G) OFDM-IM subblock, the signal vector observed at the receiver can be collected as where ȳg n is the received signal vector, Hg n is the corresponding channel matrix which contains the CFRs between the transmit and receive antennas at the n-th subcarrier, xg n is the data vector which contains the simultaneously transmitted symbols from all transmit antennas at the n-th subcarrier, and wg n is an N r × 1 AWGN vector whose elements have zero mean and unit variance. After applying the matched filter and noise whitening 2 to (5), the output can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">     y g 1 (n) y g 2 (n) . . . y g Nr (n)      ȳg n = ρ N t N K      h g 1,1 (n) h g 1,2 (n) . . . h g 1,Nt (n) h g 2,1 (n) h g 2,2 (n) . . . h g 2,Nt (n) . . . . . . . . . . . . h g Nr,1 (n) h g Nr,2 (n) . . . h g Nr,Nt (n)      Hg n ×      x g 1 (n) x g 2 (n) . . . x g Nt (n)      xg n +      w g 1 (n) w g 2 (n) . . . w g Nr (n)      wg n<label>(5</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">ỹg n (A g n ) -1/2 Hg n H ȳg n = ρ N t N K (A g n ) 1/2 xg n + wg n (<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">A g n = Hg n H Hg n , and wg n = (A g n ) -1/2</formula><p>Hg n H wg n is an N t × 1 AWGN vector whose elements have zero-mean and unit variance. Let us stack the received signal vectors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> for N consecutive subcarriers of the g-th (1 ≤ g ≤ G) OFDM-IM subblock, which can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">     ỹg 1 ỹg 2 . . . ỹg N      ỹg = ρ N t N K       (A g 1 ) 1/2 0 . . . 0 0 (A g 2 ) 1/2 . . . 0 . . . . . . . . . . . . 0 0 . . . (A g N ) 1/2       Ãg ×      xg 1 xg 2 . . . xg N      xg +      wg 1 wg 2 . . . wg N      wg n (<label>7</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">)</formula><p>where ỹg is the received signal vector after stacking, Ãg is a block diagonal channel matrix whose diagonal elements are (A g n ) 1/2 with n = 1, . . . , N and the off-diagonal elements are zero matrices 0 of size N t × N t , xg is the data vector after stacking all g-th OFDM-IM subblocks, and wg is a N t N × 1 AWGN vector whose elements have zero-mean and unit variance. By considering a joint detection for all g-th OFDM-IM subblocks from different transmit antennas, the ML detector based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> for MIMO-OFDM-IM is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">xg = arg min xg ỹg - ρ N t N K Ãg xg 2 . (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">)</formula><p>Although the ML detector can achieve optimal error performance, its computational complexity increases exponentially with the size of subblock and the number of transmit antennas. From (8), it can be observed that the search complexity per subblock is of order N C M K Nt for the ML detector, which is costly and even infeasible for the practical implementation of the receiver.</p><p>Considering the immense computational complexity required by the ML detector, the MMSE-LLR detector is developed later in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> to solve this drawback. In 2 The matched filter and noise whitening maximize the received SNR without changing the noise whitening characteristics. this detector, the MMSE filter is first employed to decouple the superimposed OFDM-IM subblocks at the receiver, and a sophisticated LLR calculator is then applied to determine the indices of the active subcarriers. Although this detector exhibits significantly reduced complexity due to the decoupling of the subblocks, its performance is far inferior to that of the ML detector. Therefore, it is very demanding to design a more effective detector for MIMO-OFDM-IM while maintaining low detection complexity at the receiver. To this end, we propose two novel detectors based on the SMC theory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. INTRODUCTION TO DETERMINISTIC SMC AND SEQUENTIAL STRUCTURE FOR MIMO-OFDM-IM</head><p>The SMC method, also referred to as particle filter, is a class of the sampling based sequential Bayesian inference methodologies for general dynamic systems, which has been widely applied in wireless communications <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>. In the following, we will first briefly introduce the concept of the deterministic SMC and then construct the sequential structure for MIMO-OFDM-IM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Basic Concept of Deterministic SMC</head><p>In most applications of digital communications, the transmitted signals take values from a finite set and the received signals are the superimposition of transmitted signals corrupted by Gaussian noise. The a posteriori distribution can be thus computed by performing an exhaustive search over all possible realizations of the transmitted signal block, whose computational complexity grows exponentially with the size of the transmitted signal block. Instead of the exhaustive search and computation, the objective of the deterministic SMC method is to numerically approximate the a posteriori distributions of the states of some Markov processes, given some noisy and partial observations. At each sampling interval, we draw symbol samples from the given finite set to construct new sequential particles, and then update their corresponding importance weights, where an illustrative example is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>. Specifically, after calculating the importance weights for all hypotheses generated by the previous particles</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">(X t-1 ) (b) β b=1</formula><p>, we only retain β most promising hypotheses associated with the highest importance weights as the new particles</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">(X t ) (b) β b=1</formula><p>while discarding other hypotheses immediately at each sampling interval. More detailed descriptions of the deterministic SMC concept will be given in Section IV with the proposed algorithms.</p><p>It has been shown that the deterministic SMC-based detectors can achieve near-ML performance with much lower computational cost to the receiver for various communications systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>. Moreover, attributed to its nature of being soft-input and soft-output, SMC based detection can also be efficiently employed in coded communication systems. However, to apply the deterministic SMC theory in a specific system, it is essential to construct the sequential structure based on the observed signals for the sampling procedure, which varies for different communication scenarios.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Sequential Structure for MIMO-OFDM-IM</head><p>To apply the SMC theory to the detection of MIMO-OFDM-IM, we construct the sequential structure based on the observed signals in the sequel. Inspired by the successive interference cancellation (SIC) method for the MIMO detection <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>, we apply the QL decomposition <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">3</ref> to the matrix (A g n )</p><p>1/2 in (6) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">(A g n ) 1/2 = Q g n L g n , n = 1, . . . , N, g = 1, . . . , G<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where Q g n is a unitary matrix, and L g n is a lower triangular matrix. The lower triangular operation is carried out by the left multiplication of the vector ỹg n in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">6</ref>) by</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">(Q g n ) H to obtain zg n = (Q g n ) H ỹg n , which can be further written as      z g 1 (n) z g 2 (n) . . . z g Nt (n)      zg n = ρ N t N K      l g 1,1 (n) l g 2,1 (n) l g 2,2 (n) . . . . . . . . . l g Nt,1 (n) l g Nt,2 (n) . . . l g Nt,Nt (n)      L g n ×      x g 1 (n) x g 2 (n) . . . x g Nt (n)      xg n +      v g 1 (n) v g 2 (n) . . . v g Nt (n)      vg n (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">vg n = (Q g n ) H</formula><p>wg n is still an N t × 1 zero-mean AWGN vector with unit variance elements as the matrix Q g n is unitary. Based on the structure in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, the SIC may be applied to detect the data vector xg n in a sequential manner, i.e., the interference due to the previously decoded symbols is subtracted from the observed sample before decoding the next symbol. However, one should keep in mind that unlike the classical MIMO-OFDM in which the symbols carried on the different subcarriers are independently generated, the symbols carried on different subcarriers within each OFDM-IM subblock are binded together in the MIMO-OFDM-IM due to the index modulation. Therefore, to be suited to MIMO-OFDM-IM, the SIC method for MIMO-OFDM-IM has to be performed in a subblock-by-subblock manner, resulting in a search complexity as high as of order N t N C M K . Moreover, the SIC method may suffer from the problem of error propagation, which also limits its error performance. In this paper, we will not employ the SIC method but instead exploit the aforementioned sequential structure for the low-complexity detector design of MIMO-OFDM-IM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. LOW-COMPLEXITY DETECTORS FOR MIMO-OFDM-IM</head><p>In this section, we will develop two types of SMC-based detectors by using the structure of (10) as the kernel for MIMO-OFDM-IM. As will be shown by computer simulations, the new algorithms can avoid error propagation successfully and provide near-optimal error performance for MIMO-OFDM-IM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Deterministic SMC Aided Subblock-wise Detection</head><p>After the lower triangular operation, the sequential structure in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> can be exploited by applying the SMC method to draw samples starting from the first transmit antenna and ending to the last one. Indeed, if we simply regard each OFDM-IM subblock x g t as a super modulated symbol drawn from a large finite set, we have the a posteriori distribution of {x g t }</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nt t=1</head><p>conditioned on {z g t } Nt t=1 as</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">P {x g t } Nt t=1 {z g t } Nt t=1 ∝ Nt t=1 p z g t X g t P (x g t )<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where , which can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">z g t [z g t (1) z g t (2) • • • z g t (N )] T denotes the observed subblock in the t-th (1 ≤ t ≤ N t )</formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">P X g t Z g t ∝ t t =1 p z g t X g t P (x g t ) , t = 1, . . . , N t (12)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">Z g t {z g t } t t =1</formula><p>. From the perspective of the probability theory, our aim is to estimate the a posteriori probability of each OFDM-IM subblock </p><formula xml:id="formula_26">P x g t = Φ i {z g t } Nt t=1 , Φ i ∈ Φ, t = 1, . . . , N t<label>(13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">{Φ i } N C M K i=1</formula><p>with | Φ| = N C M K denotes the set including all possible realizations of the OFDM-IM subblock. Instead of the direct computation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>, which is too computationally expensive, we seek to numerically approximate (13) by using the deterministic SMC theory to substantially reduce the complexity at the receiver.</p><p>Let (X g t ) (b) with b = 1, . . . , β be the particles drawn by the SMC method at the t-th sampling interval on the basis of subblock, where β denotes the total number of particles. To implement the SMC method, we first generate a set of incomplete particles for the OFDM-IM subblocks, and then update the corresponding importance weights for those particles with respect to the distribution of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> until the subblock at the last antenna is reached. Moreover, to update the importance weights, it is crucial to design the trial distribution which minimizes the variance of the importance weights conditioned upon the previous particles and the observed signals <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>.</p><p>Under the criterion of minimum conditional variance of the importance weights, we simply choose the trial distribution as</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">ψ x g t Z g t , X g t-1 (b) ∝ P x g t Z g t , X g t-1 (b)<label>(14)</label></formula><p>for t = 1, . . . , N t . Proposition 1: With the trial distribution given in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_28">14</ref>), the importance weight for the SMC can be updated according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">( g t ) (b) ∝ g t-1 (b) • p z g t X g t-1 (b)<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where p z g t</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">X g t-1<label>(b)</label></formula><p>can be regarded as the prediction distribution of the current observed subblock z g t under the condition of the previous particle X g t-1 (b) .</p><p>Proof: See Appendix A. In the MIMO-OFDM-IM system, each OFDM-IM subblock has a finite number of realizations, i.e., N C M K . For this reason, the deterministic SMC sampling can be applied by first enumerating all possible subblock realizations at each sampling interval and then calculating their associated prediction distributions exactly based on the previous particles paired with the specific subblock sample. In other words, with the given particle X g t-1</p><p>(b) , we calculate each prediction distribution</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">(γ g t ) (b) [i] p z g t x g t = Φ i , X g t-1 (b)<label>(16)</label></formula><p>for Φ i ∈ Φ to get a more precise result. If the specific subblock sample x g t = Φ i is assumed in the prediction distribution, the update for the importance weight in (15) can be revised as</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">( g t ) (b) [i] ∝ g t-1 (b) • (γ g t ) (b) [i] • P (x g t = Φ i )<label>(17)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">∝ g t-1 (b) • (γ g t ) (b) [i]<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where i = 1, . . . , N C M K , and (18) holds due to the equal probability assumption for all subblock realizations. Since the noise vector <ref type="formula" target="#formula_19">10</ref>) is white Gaussian, the prediction distribution (γ g t )</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">vg n = (Q g n ) H wg n in (</formula><p>[i] can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">(γ g t ) (b) [i] = 1 π N exp -z g t -(u g t ) (b) [i] 2<label>(19)</label></formula><p>Algorithm 1 Deterministic SMC aided subblock-wise detection 1: Perform the lower triangular operation to obtain (10); 2: Enumerate all possible realizations of X g Γ with their a posteriori probabilities given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>, and retain the β initial particles (X g Γ )</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">(b) β b=1</formula><p>with the highest a posteriori probabilities as the initial importance weights</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">( g Γ ) (b) β b=1 ; 3: for t = Γ + 1 to N t do 4:</formula><p>Update the importance weights according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>, b = 1, . . . , β;</p><p>5:</p><p>Pick up and retain β particles with the highest importance weights among the β| Φ| hypotheses with weights set</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">( g t )<label>(b)</label></formula><p>[i] , b = 1, . . . , β, i = 1, . . . , N C M K ; 6: end for 7: Compute the a posteriori probability for each subblock via <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>, and the estimate of each subblock is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">x g t = arg max Φi∈ Φ P x g t = Φ i {z g t } Nt t=1 , t = 1, . . . , N t .</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">(u g t ) (b) [i] (u g t (1)) (b) [i] (u g t (2)) (b) [i] • • • (u g t (N )) (b) [i]</formula><p>T denotes the mean vector of z g t , whose n-th (1 ≤ n ≤ N ) element is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">(u g t (n)) (b) [i] = ρ N t N K t-1 t =1 l g t,t (n) (x g t (n)) (b) + ρ N t N K l g t,t (n)Φ i (n)<label>(20)</label></formula><p>with Φ i (n) being the n-th element of the sample vector Φ i . 1) Initialization and Summary of Subblock-Wise Algorithm: By assuming the SMC process starts at the Γ-th transmit antenna, we compute the a posteriori distributions P X g Γ Z g Γ exactly by enumerating all possible realizations of X g Γ , where the total number of possible realizations is | Φ| Γ and Γ &lt; N t . 4  According to the deterministic SMC and (10), the a posteriori probabilities P (X g Γ )</p><p>Z g Γ can be expressed as , where β ≤ B Γ . After the initialization, the importance weights are updated according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. At each sampling interval on the basis of subblock, current β particles with the highest importance weights are selected as the survivors over β| Φ| possible hypotheses departed from the previous particles. When the recursion reaches the last sampling interval, i.e., t = N t , β</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">P (X g Γ ) (b) Z g Γ ∝ Γ t=1 (γ g t ) (b) [i] .<label>(21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_45">4 If Γ ≥ Nt, we can compute P X g N t Z g N t</formula><p>exactly based on the deterministic SMC; however, it is too computationally expensive.</p><p>particles and the corresponding importance weights are then used to estimate the a posteriori probability for each subblock in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>, given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">P x g t = Φ i {z g t } Nt t=1 ∼ = 1 g Nt β b=1 I (x g t ) (b) ; Φ i g Nt (b)<label>(22)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">Φ i ∈ Φ, g Nt = β b=1</formula><p>g Nt (b) , and I (; ) denotes the indicator function <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>. Notably, the importance weights obtained at the last sampling interval is applied to compute the a posteriori subblock probabilities, for those weights provide better estimations <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref> and we detect the corresponding subblocks at the last step. Moreover, the a posteriori probability estimated in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_46">22</ref>) can be readily applied to the detection with soft output, which is compatible with the coded system. Finally, we summarize the deterministic SMC aided subblock-wise detection in Algorithm 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Deterministic SMC Aided Subcarrier-wise Detection</head><p>Although the detector proposed in Section IV-A achieves considerable reduction in computational complexity with respect to the ML detector, its complexity still grows exponentially with the size of subblock. To circumvent this problem, we propose another novel detection algorithm based on the deterministic SMC in this subsection, which draws samples at the subcarrier level. To prevent from outputting illegal subblock realization, the subcarrier-wise detector takes into account the constraint of the active subcarrier combinations within each subblock when drawing samples. By exploiting the sequential structure in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, the subcarrier-wise SMC method detects the information starting from the first transmit antenna and ending to the last transmit antenna and draws samples subcarrier-wise from the first subcarrier to the last subcarrier within the g-th subblock at each transmit antenna.</p><p>Considering the dependence of the subcarrier symbols within each subblock, the distribution of (11) can be rewritten at the subcarrier level as</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">P {x g t } Nt t=1 {z g t } Nt t=1 ∝ Nt t=1 N n=1 p z g t (n) X g t,n P x g t (n) x g t,n-1<label>(23)</label></formula><p>where X g t,n</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">X g t-1 , x g t,n , x g t,n {x g t (n )} n n =1</formula><p>, and X g 0 =</p><p>x g t,0 = ∅ is defined. Similarly, based on (23), the sequential distributions can be constructed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">P X g t,n Z g t,n ∝ t t =1 n n =1 p z g t (n ) X g t ,n P x g t (n ) x g t ,n -1<label>(24)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_51">∝ P X g t-1 Z g t-1 n n =1 p z g t (n ) X g t,n P x g t (n ) x g t,n -1<label>(25)</label></formula><p>where t = 1, . . . , N t , n = 1, . . . , N , Z g t,n</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">Z g t-1 , z g t,n , z g t,n {z g t (n )} n n =1 , Z g 0 = z g t,0 = ∅ is defined, and<label>(25)</label></formula><p>is obtained due to the independence among the subblocks generated from different transmit antennas. Unlike the detector proposed in Section IV-A that estimates the information subblock-wise, the aim of the subcarrier-wise detection is to estimate the a posteriori probability at the subcarrier level, which is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">P x g t (n) = X i {z g t } Nt t=1 , X i ∈ X<label>(26)</label></formula><p>where t = 1, . . . , N t , n = 1, . . . , N , i = 1, . . . , M + 1, and X {0, S} with | X | = M + 1 denotes the modified constellation. However, due to the dependence of subcarrier symbols within each subblock, it is infeasible to compute <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> directly. Therefore, we resort to the SMC theory by carefully considering this dependent relationship.</p><p>Suppose that X g t,n (b) with b = 1, . . . , β are the particles drawn by the SMC method at each sampling interval on the basis of subcarrier. Similarly, we can choose the trial distribution as</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">ψ x g t (n) Z g t,n , X g t,n-1 (b) ∝P x g t (n) Z g t,n , X g t,n-1 (b)<label>(27)</label></formula><p>for t = 1, . . . , N t , n = 1, . . . , N . Proposition 2: With the trial distribution given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>, the importance weight for the SMC can be updated according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">g t,n (b) ∝ g t,n-1 (b) • p z g t (n) X g t,n-1 (b)<label>(28)</label></formula><p>where p z g t (n) X g t,n-1</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">(b)</formula><p>denotes the prediction distribution of the currently observed signal z g t (n) under the condition of the previous particle X g t,n-1</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(b)</head><p>. Proof: See Appendix B. In MIMO-OFDM-IM, the symbol x g t (n) carried on each subcarrier takes values from the modified constellation X with | X | = M + 1. However, those subcarrier symbols within each subblock are not drawn independently from the finite set X as they must meet the constraint of the K active subcarrier combinations, which makes the calculation of the exact prediction distribution based on the deterministic SMC method a challenging problem. With a given hypothesis</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">X g t,n-1 (b)</formula><p>, X i , we update the importance weight by revising (28) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">g t,n (b) [i] ∝ g t,n-1 (b) γg t,n (b) [i] P x g t (n) = X i x g t,n-1 (b)<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">P x g t (n) = X i x g t,n-1 (b)</formula><p>indicates the nonindependent relationship of subcarrier symbols within each subblock and</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">γg t,n (b) [i] p z g t (n) x g t (n) = X i , X g t,n-1 (b)<label>(30)</label></formula><p>denotes the exact prediction distribution. Since the noise vector </p><formula xml:id="formula_61">vg n = (Q g n ) H wg n in (</formula><p>[i] in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_58">29</ref>) can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">γg t,n<label>(b)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_64">[i] = 1 π exp -z g t (n) -(ũ g t (n)) (b) [i] 2<label>(31)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">(ũ g t (n))<label>(b)</label></formula><p>[i] denotes the mean of z g t (n), which is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">(ũ g t (n)) (b) [i] = ρ N t N K t-1 t =1 l g t,t (n) (x g t (n)) (b) + ρ N t N K l g t,t (n)X i . (<label>32</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_67">)</formula><p>For the update of the importance weight in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>, it is essential to determine the conditional probability P x g t (n) = X i x g t,n-1 (b) , as it justifies the dependent relationship of subcarrier symbols within each subblock. In the following, we will give two schemes to calculate the conditional probability P x g t (n) = X i x g t,n-1</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">(b) .</formula><p>1) Exhaustive Searching Scheme: According to the Bayes theorem, we can obtain the conditional probability exactly as <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> where</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">P x g t (n) = X i x g t,n-1 (b) = P x g t (n) = X i , x g t,n-1 (b) P x g t,n-1 (b) = Φi∈ Φ P {Φ i (n )} n n =1 = x g t,n-1 (b) , X i Φi∈ Φ P {Φ i (n )} n-1 n =1 = x g t,n-1 (b)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_70">Φ i = [Φ i (1) Φ i (2) • • • Φ i (N )]</formula><p>T . According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>, if the hypothesis</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">x g t,n-1 (b)</formula><p>, X i is illegal, we will have</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">P x g t (n) = X i x g t,n-1 (b)</formula><p>= 0, such that, the illegal hypotheses can be avoided. However, it is costly to calculate the conditional probability exactly based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> as it invokes an exhaustive search over all possible realizations of the OFDM-IM subblock at every sampling interval on the basis of subcarrier.</p><p>2) Natural Numbers Mapping Scheme: To strike a tradeoff between the complexity cost and the estimation accuracy, we hereafter develop a more efficient method to estimate the conditional probability in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> and to avoid the propagation of illegal particles. Let us denote the number of non-zero elements in x g t,n-1 as δ (b) . Assuming that subcarriers within a subblock are uniformly activated and the modulated symbols are uniformly drawn from an M -ary constellation, we can estimate the conditional probability as</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">(b) n-1 = count x g t,n-1</formula><formula xml:id="formula_74">P x g t (n) = X i x g t,n-1 (b) ∼ =          1 M • K -δ (b) n-1 N -n + 1 , X i ∈ S N -K + δ (b) n-1 -n + 1 N -n + 1 , X i = 0 (<label>34</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_75">)</formula><p>where t = 1, . . . , N t , n = 1, . . . , N , and i = 1, . . . , M + 1.</p><p>Based on (34), x g t,N</p><p>(b)</p><p>with t = 1, . . . , N t after the SMC sampling procedure are forced to meet the fixed number constraint of active subcarriers within each subblock, i.e., δ (b) N = K for b = 1, . . . , β. It is worth pointing out that the calculation of (34) does not involve any specific mapping rule for the subcarrier combination, which is more general and practical. However, when N C = N K , the calculation of (34) will encounter the infiltration of some illegal realizations, i.e., the conditional probabilities of some illegal realizations are not zero. To detect those illegal realizations without using a look-up table, we resort to the combinatorial method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> to examine the legality of the realization. The combinatorial method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> provides a one-to-one mapping between natural numbers and the combination patterns of K active subcarriers, which is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">ζ = j(K) -1 K + • • • + j(2) -1 2 + j(1) -1 1 (<label>35</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_77">)</formula><p>where t and g are omitted as <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> is general for all subblocks, and 0 ≤ ζ ≤ N K -1. Based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>, we can easily examine the legality of the realizations by simply regarding those realizations with ζ ≥ N C as illegal.</p><p>Example 1: Suppose BPSK modulation, N = 4 and K = 2 and the combinatorial method is applied to determine the indices of the two active subcarriers out of four available subcarriers, as shown in the table in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. The graphical tree is also illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref>. As can be seen, based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>, we can easily exclude those illegal realizations with ζ ≥ 4.</p><p>For the calculation based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref>, it can be readily verified that the ratio of the number of the illegal realizations to that of legal ones is N K -N C /N C , which is typically small. For this reason, we only examine the legality of the particles when they reach the last subcarrier within each subblock, i.e., n = N .</p><p>Remark: As illustrated above, the method based on (34) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> does not require any look-up table and is general for different N and K values, which is more efficient and practical than the calculation based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>. Owing to its simplicity and generality, the calculation based on ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_74">34</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> will be adopted to estimate the conditional probability <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref> for our computer simulations in Section VI.</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">P x g t (n) = X i x g t,n-1 (b) in</formula><p>3) Initialization and Summary of Subcarrier-Wise Algorithm: We assume that the SMC process starts on the Λ-th subcarrier of the subblock at the Γ-th transmit antenna and enumerate all legal realizations of X g Γ,Λ , where Γ ≤ N t , Λ ≤ N , and the total number of legal realizations is 5 According to the deterministic SMC and (10), we can enumerate all legal realizations of X g Γ,Λ and compute their a posteriori probabilities exactly as</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">B Γ,Λ ≤ | Φ| Γ-1 | X | Λ .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_80">P X g Γ,Λ (b) Z g Γ,Λ ∝ Γ-1 t=1 (γ g t ) (b) [i ] Λ n=1 γg Γ,n<label>(b)</label></formula><p>[i] [i ] and γg</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">P x g Γ (n) = X i x g Γ,n-1 (b)<label>(36</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_82">Γ,n (b) [i]</formula><p>are given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref>, respectively. Then we retain the β particles</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">X g Γ,Λ (b) β b=1</formula><p>with the highest a posteriori probabilities as 5 If Γ ≥ Nt and Λ ≥ N , we can compute P X g N t ,N Z g N t ,N exactly based on the deterministic SMC; however, it is too computationally expensive.</p><p>Algorithm 2 Deterministic SMC aided subcarrier-wise detection 1: Perform the lower triangular operation to obtain (10); 2: Enumerate all legal realizations of X g Γ,Λ with their a posteriori probabilities given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref>, and retain the</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">β initial particles X g Γ,Λ (b) β b=1</formula><p>with the highest a posteriori probabilities as the initial importance weights Update and examine the particles associated with the importance weights according to ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_58">29</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_76">35</ref>), b = 1, . . . , β; 5: end for 6: for t = Γ + 1 to N t do 7:</p><p>for n = 1 to N do Pick up and retain β particles with the highest importance weights among the β| X | = β (M + 1) hypotheses with the set of weights end for 14: end for 15: Compute the a posteriori probability for each subblock via <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref>, and the estimate of each subblock is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">x g t = arg max Φi∈ Φ P x g t = Φ i {z g t } Nt t=1 , t = 1, . . . , N t .</formula><p>the initial importance weights</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">g Γ,Λ<label>(b) β b=1</label></formula><p>, where β ≤ B Γ,Λ .</p><p>After the initialization, we update the importance weight according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>. At each sampling interval on the basis of subcarrier, current β particles with the highest importance weights are selected as the survivors over β| X | = β (M + 1) possible hypotheses departed from the previous particles. Specially, when the recursion reaches the last subcarrier of each subblock, i.e., n = N , the legality of the possible samples will be first examined according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> and legal particles with the highest importance weights are selected as the survivors over those legal hypotheses. When the recursion reaches the bottom, i.e., t = N t and n = N , the particles associated with the importance weights are then used to compute the a posteriori probability for each subcarrier symbol in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>, given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">P x g t (n) = X i {z g t } Nt t=1 ∼ = 1 g Nt,N β b=1 I (x g t (n)) (b) ; X i g Nt,N<label>(b) (37)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">X i ∈ X and g Nt,N = β b=1 g Nt,N<label>(b)</label></formula><p>. However, as emphasized above, due to the dependence of subcarriers within each subblock, we cannot estimate each symbol independently based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref> as the demapping of OFDM-IM subblock may fail. Simply, by considering the joint estimation for active subcarriers and modulated symbols within each subblock, we can estimate the a posteriori probability for each subblock similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> to solve this problem as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">P x g t = Φ i {z g t } Nt t=1 ∼ = 1 g Nt,N β b=1 I x g t,N<label>(b)</label></formula><p>;</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">Φ i g Nt,N<label>(b)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">x g t,N<label>(b)</label></formula><p>with t = 1, . . . , N t are extracted from</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">X g Nt,N<label>(b)</label></formula><p>Φ i ∈ Finally, we summarize the deterministic SMC aided subcarrier-wise detection in Algorithm 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. COMPLEXITY ANALYSIS AND COMPARISON</head><p>In this section, the computational complexity of the proposed SMC-based detectors is compared with the detectors developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, where the detection complexity is measured by average NCM performed per subcarrier. To facilitate comparison, the number of receive antennas is assumed to be equal to the number of transmit antennas, i.e., N r = N t .</p><p>A. Complexity of Detectors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> Explicitly, the complexity of the ML detector in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_14">8</ref>) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">C ML = N t (N t + 1) N C M K Nt .<label>(39)</label></formula><p>After employing the MMSE filtering to eliminate the interference between the subblocks of different transmit antennas, the simple MMSE detector developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> decodes the MIMO-OFDM-IM signal in a subblock-wise manner, whose complexity is</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">C simple MMSE = 7N 3 t + N 2 t + N C M K . (<label>40</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_96">)</formula><p>For the MMSE-LLR detection, the complexity is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_97">C MMSE-LLR = 7N 3 t + N t (N t + M + 1)<label>(41)</label></formula><p>where a decomposition detection based on LLR calculation for each subcarrier is achieved after the MMSE filtering. Moreover, a novel OSIC based sequential MMSE-LLR detector, which referred to as MMSE-LLR-OSIC, is also proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> to further improve the error performance, whose complexity can be approximated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">C MMSE-LLR-OSIC ∼ = 3N 4 t + 7N 3 t + N t (6N t + M + 1) .<label>(42)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Complexity of Proposed Detectors</head><p>As shown in Algorithms 1 and 2, the complexity of the proposed SMC-based detectors mainly consists of three parts:</p><p>-the lower triangular operation to construct the sequential structure for MIMO-OFDM-IM; -the initialization of the importance weights; -the update of the importance weights. By using Householder transformations <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref> to the QL decomposition, the complexity to construct the sequential structure of (10) for per subblock is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">C QR ≈ 2N N 3 t /3 + 2N N 2 t .<label>(43)</label></formula><p>1) Proposed subblock-wise detection: For per subblock, the complexity of the initialization for the importance weights based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> is</p><formula xml:id="formula_100">C ini1 = βN • Γ (Γ + 5) /2 + βΓ<label>(44)</label></formula><p>and the complexity of the update for the importance weights based on ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_33">18</ref>) from (Γ + 1)-th subblock to the last one is</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">C udp1 = βN • N C M K • (N t + Γ + 7) (N t -Γ) /2. (<label>45</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_102">)</formula><p>After neglecting some lower order terms, the complexity in terms of average NCM performed per subcarrier for the proposed subblock-wise detection is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">C pro1 = (C QR + C ini1 + C upd1 ) /N ≈ 2N 3 t /3 + 2N 2 t + N 2 t -Γ 2 βN C M K /2.<label>(46)</label></formula><p>2) Proposed subcarrier-wise detection: For per subblock, the complexity of the initialization for the importance weights in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref> is</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">C ini2 =βN • (Γ -1) (Γ + 4) /2 + βΛ • (Γ + 2) + β (Γ -1 + 2Λ)<label>(47)</label></formula><p>and the complexity of the update for the importance weights based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref> to the rest of the subcarriers is</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">C udp2 =βN • (M + 1) • (N t + Γ + 9) (N t -Γ) /2 + β (N -Λ) • (M + 1) (N t + 4) .<label>(48)</label></formula><p>Therefore, the complexity in terms of average NCM performed per subcarrier for the proposed subcarrier-wise detection is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">C pro2 = (C QR + C ini2 + C upd2 ) /N ≈ 2N 3 t /3 + 2N 2 t + N 2 t -Γ 2 β(M + 1)/2<label>(49)</label></formula><p>where the lower order terms have been neglected in <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(49)</ref>. However, to be more accurate, exact NCM without neglecting any terms will be compared for different types of detectors in the numerical results of Section VI.</p><p>In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">I</ref>, a brief summary of the computational complexity measured by the average NCM for different detectors of MIMO-OFDM-IM is provided. As seen from Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">I</ref>, the brute-force ML detection leads to prohibitive computational complexity and the highest order of detection complexity with respect to the constellation size M . The proposed subblockwise detection requires much lower computational complexity than the brute-force ML detection while the proposed subcarrier-wise detection shows the same level of computational complexity as the MMSE-LLR method. </p><formula xml:id="formula_107">N C M K N t O M KN t Simple MMSE 7N 3 t + N 2 t + N C M K O M K MMSE-LLR 7N 3 t + Nt (Nt + M + 1) O (M ) MMSE-LLR-OSIC ∼ = 3N 4 t + 7N 3 t + Nt (6Nt + M + 1) O (M ) Proposed subblock-wise detection 2N 3 t /3 + 2N 2 t + N 2 t -Γ 2 βN C M K /2 O M K Proposed subcarrier-wise detection 2N 3 t /3 + 2N 2 t + N 2 t -Γ 2 β(M + 1)/2 O (M )</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. SIMULATION AND NUMERICAL RESULTS</head><p>In this section, we verify the effectiveness of the detection algorithms for MIMO-OFDM-IM via computer simulation and numerical results. In the computer simulations, a MIMO channel with frequency-selective Rayleigh fading is considered, where the maximum delay spread of the channel is equal to 10×T s , where T s denotes the sampling period of the digital system. Each OFDM-IM block consists of N F = 512 subcarriers and is appended by a CP of length N cp = 16. It is assumed that channel state information is unknown to the transmitter but perfectly known to the receiver. For ease of comparison, the number of receive antennas is set to be equal to the number of transmit antennas, i.e., N r = N t . To initialize the SMC process, we set Γ = 1 for Algorithm 1, and Γ = 1 and Λ = N for Algorithm 2. Moreover, for fair comparison, we adopt the same number of particles β for both deterministic SMC aided detection methods in the following simulations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Error Performance Comparison</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> shows the BER comparison results of different detection algorithms for the MIMO-OFDM-IM system with N t = 4, K = 1, and QPSK modulation. As seen from Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>, the proposed subblock-wise detector achieves nearoptimal BER performance for the MIMO-OFDM-IM system with reduced complexity for both N = 2 and N = 4 cases. Although the proposed subcarrier-wise detector is slightly inferior to the subblock-wise detector, it is favorable for its lower computational complexity than that of the subblockwise one, which will be shown in the next subsection. Both our detectors show considerably better performance than those of MMSE based detectors. Specially, the simple MMSE and MMSE-LLR detectors suffer from a significant performance loss and their diversity order is always equal to one. On the other hand, both proposed detectors show to attain the same diversity order as the ML detection.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">6</ref> shows the BER comparison results of different detection algorithms for the MIMO-OFDM-IM system with N t = 4, N = 4, and BPSK modulation. It can be observed that similarly the proposed subblock-wise detector achieves near-optimal performance while the proposed subcarrier-wise detector only suffers from a marginal performance loss compared to the ML detection. Although the MMSE-LLR-OSIC detector outperforms the other two MMSE based detectors at the cost of a higher complexity, its performance is still far from optimal (ML detection). By comparing the two scenarios with different number of active subcarriers (K = 1 and K = 2), we  observe that the BER performance of all detectors degrades as the number of active subcarriers increases. This can be understood as each active subcarrier will be allocated less power when more subcarriers are activated simultaneously for transmission. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7</ref>, the BER performance of different detection algorithms is compared for the MIMO-OFDM-IM system with N = 4, K = 2, and QPSK modulation. As the ML detection requires an immense amount of computation, its BER curve is not shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7</ref>. It can be seen that the proposed detectors   outperform the MMSE based detectors significantly. Moreover, we observe that unlike the simple MMSE and MMSE-LLR detectors, the BER performance of both proposed detectors is improved as the number of receive antennas (N r = N t ) increases. This can be understood since the diversity order of the simple MMSE and MMSE-LLR detectors is equal to one regardless of the number of receive antennas while a diversity order of N r is obtained by both proposed detectors. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref>, the BER performance of different detection algorithms is compared for the MIMO-OFDM-IM system with N = 4, K = 4, and BPSK modulation. From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">8</ref>, we observe that the subcarrier-wise detector also has the potential to achieve almost the same performance as the subblockwise one for this configuration. This can be understood since both proposed detectors can approach the optimal performance when the number of particles is large enough (e.g., β = 32). Therefore, the deterministic SMC aided detectors are able to provide a flexible trade-off between the computational complexity and the error performance by adjusting the number of particles.  Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">9</ref> shows the BER comparison results of different detection algorithms for the MIMO-OFDM-IM system with N t = 4, N = 4, and K = 3. It still can be observed that when the number of particles is large enough, the subcarrierwise detector achieves almost the same performance as the subblock-wise one for different modulation orders. Moreover, the performance of all detectors degrades with the increase of the modulation orders. Specially, the performance gain of the MMSE-LLR-OSIC detector over the MMSE-LLR one is smaller with higher modulation orders.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Complexity Comparison</head><p>In Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">10</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">11</ref>, the computational complexity for different types of detectors is compared in terms of exact NCM performed per subcarrier. As expected, the computational complexity of the ML detection is prohibitive and increases exponentially with the number of transmit antennas. However, our proposed detectors achieve rather low computational complexity, which is comparable to that of MMSE based detectors. Interestingly, the computational complexity of the MMSE-LLR-OSIC detector seems to be more susceptible to the number of transmit antennas and the subcarrier-wise detector has the potential to achieve a lower complexity than the MMSE-LLR detector when the number of transmit antennas increases. On the other hand, the computational complexity of the subblock-wise detector is sensitive to the size of subblock and is always higher than that of the subcarrier-wise one.</p><p>In summary, the proposed detection algorithms are able to provide an effective trade-off between BER performance and computational complexity. Moreover, the proposed detection algorithms achieve near-optimal performance while maintaining considerably lower complexity that is comparable to that of the simple MMSE and MMSE-LLR detectors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we have proposed two low-complexity detectors derived from the SMC theory for the MIMO-OFDM-IM system. The first proposed subblock-wise detector draws samples at the subblock level, exhibiting near-optimal performance for the MIMO-OFDM-IM system. The second proposed subcarrier-wise detector draws samples at the subcarrier level, exhibiting substantially reduced complexity with a marginal performance loss. An effective legality examination method has been also developed to couple with the subcarrierwise detector. Computer simulation and numerical results have validated the outstanding performance and the low complexity of both proposed detectors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A PROOF OF PROPOSITION 1</head><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, the importance weight is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_108">( g t ) (b) = P (X g t ) (b) Z g t ψ (X g t ) (b) Z g t .<label>(50)</label></formula><p>Although <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(50)</ref> is not sequential, we can come up with a sequential version by exploiting the property of the trial distribution. In order to work in a sequential manner, the trial distribution is supposed to satisfy</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">ψ X g t Z g t = ψ X g 1 Z g 1 t t =2 ψ x g t X g t -1 , Z g t .<label>(51)</label></formula><p>Furthermore, (51) can be rewritten in a recursive form as ψ X g t Z g t = ψ X g t-1 Z g t-1 ψ x g t X g t-1 , Z g t .</p><p>Based on ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_108">50</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_110">52</ref>), the update recursions for the importance weights are then given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_111">( g t ) (b) = g t-1 (b) × P (X g t ) (b) Z g t ψ X g t-1 (b) Z g t-1 ψ (x g t ) (b) X g t-1 (b) , Z g t (<label>53</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_112">)</formula><p>where b = 1, . . . , β. With the trial distribution of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_28">14</ref>) satisfying ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_110">52</ref>), (53) can be further written as (55)</p><formula xml:id="formula_113">( g t ) (b) ∝ g t-1<label>(b)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_114">∝ g t-1 (b) • p z g t Z g t-1 , X g t-1<label>(b)</label></formula><p>(56)</p><formula xml:id="formula_115">= g t-1 (b) • p z g t X g t-1 (b)<label>(57)</label></formula><p>where (55) holds due to the independence of the previous particle X g t-1</p><p>(b) and the current subblock x g t , (56) is obtained by neglecting the constant term p Z g t-1 /p (Z g t ), and (57) holds due to the independence of the noise samples, completing the proof.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX B PROOF OF PROPOSITION 2</head><p>Similar to the proof of Proposition 1, the update recursions for importance weights are given by (60)</p><formula xml:id="formula_116">= g t,n-1 (b) • p z g t (n) X g t,n-1 (b)<label>(61)</label></formula><p>where ( <ref type="formula">60</ref>) is obtained by neglecting the constant term p Z g t,n-1 /p Z g t,n , and (61) holds due to the independence of the noise samples, completing the proof.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>- 1 stand</head><label>1</label><figDesc>for transpose, Hermitian transpose, and matrix inversion operations, respectively. (•) (b) denotes the b-th particle drawn by the SMC sampling, its associated importance weight, or its prediction distribution. (•) [i] denotes the hypothesis drawn with the sample being the i-th element of a finite set, its associated importance weight, or its prediction distribution. {x n } N n=1 denotes a N -size set, whose elements are x 1 , . . . , x N . diag{x} returns a diagonal matrix whose diagonal elements are included in x. | • | denotes the absolute value if applied to a complex number or the cardinality if applied to a set. The probability density function (PDF) and the probability mass function (PMF) are denoted by p (•) and P (•), respectively. ψ (•) represents the trial distribution chosen for the SMC sampling. E{•} stands for expectation and • denotes the floor function. The order of detection complexity with respect to the constellation size is denoted by O (•).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Block diagram of MIMO-OFDM-IM transmitter.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Illustration of the deterministic SMC.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,316.40,282.46,245.14,65.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>) where b = 1 ,</head><label>1</label><figDesc>. . . , B Γ , B Γ = | Φ| Γ , and (X g Γ ) of X g Γ .Then we retain the β particles (X g Γ )</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>) where b = 1 ,</head><label>1</label><figDesc>. . . , B Γ,Λ , realizations of X g Γ,Λ , and (γ g t )</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>; 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>for n = Λ + 1 to N do 4:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Update the importance weights according to<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>, b = 1, . . . , β; 9: if n = N then Compute ζ mapping for K active subcarrier indices extracted from each hypothesis x g t,N -1 (b) , X i according to (35), and set the importance weights for those illegal hypotheses (ζ ≥ N C ) to zero, b = 1, . . . , β, i = 1, . . . , M + 1;</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, b = 1, . . . , β, i = 1, . . . , M + 1; 13:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>= 4 ,Fig. 5 .</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. BER performance comparison of different detection algorithms for MIMO-OFDM-IM with Nt = 4, K = 1, and QPSK modulation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. BER performance comparison of different detection algorithms for MIMO-OFDM-IM with Nt = 4, N = 4, and BPSK modulation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. BER performance comparison of different detection algorithms for MIMO-OFDM-IM with N = 4, K = 2, and QPSK modulation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. BER performance comparison of different detection algorithms for MIMO-OFDM-IM with N = 4, K = 3, and BPSK modulation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. BER performance comparison of different detection algorithms for MIMO-OFDM-IM with Nt = 4, N = 4, and K = 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Complexity comparison of different detection algorithms for MIMO-OFDM-IM with K = 1, and QPSK modulation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Complexity comparison of different detection algorithms for MIMO-OFDM-IM with N = 4, and BPSK modulation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(c) 2016 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing where b = 1, . . . , β. With the trial distribution of (27), (58) can be further written as</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing</figDesc><table><row><cell>IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON SIGNAL PROCESSING, VOL. XX, NO. XX, XXX 2017</cell><cell>3</cell></row></table><note><p><p>2</p>N K bits is used to select K active 1053-587X (c) 2016 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing</figDesc><table /><note><p><p>) 1053-587X (c) 2016 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p>IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON SIGNAL PROCESSING, VOL. XX, NO. XX, XXX 2017 4</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing</figDesc><table><row><cell>IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON SIGNAL PROCESSING, VOL. XX, NO. XX, XXX 2017</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>based on the observed subblocks {z g t } Nt t=1 , where Φ</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><p>)</p>1053-587X (c) 2016 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing</figDesc><table><row><cell>IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON SIGNAL PROCESSING, VOL. XX, NO. XX, XXX 2017</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>C C</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C C</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C C</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C C</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C C</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C C</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Fig. 4. Illustration of the counter based scheme.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>distribution γg t,n</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>10) is white Gaussian, prediction 1053-587X (c) 2016 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>TABLE I DECODING</head><label>I</label><figDesc>COMPLEXITY COMPARISONS IN TERMS OF AVERAGE NCM PERFORMED PER SUBCARRIER</figDesc><table><row><cell>Detector</cell><cell>Computational complexity</cell><cell>Order of complexity</cell></row><row><cell>Brute-Force ML</cell><cell>Nt (Nt + 1)</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1053-587X (c) 2016 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON SIGNAL PROCESSING, VOL. XX, NO. XX, XXX 2017 12</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Note that to modulate an integer number of bits, only N C =</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>p 1 subcarrier combination patterns are permitted and the remaining N K -N C patterns are considered to be illegal.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>The QL decomposition can be obtained in analogy with the QR decomposition, which can be derived by using the Gram-Schmidt process starting from the last column of the designated matrix.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_3"><p>IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON SIGNAL PROCESSING, VOL. XX, NO. XX, XXX 2017</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>1053-587X (c) 2016 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON SIGNAL PROCESSING, VOL. XX, NO. XX, XXX 2017 1053-587X (c) 2016 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TSP.2017.2673803, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON SIGNAL PROCESSING, VOL. XX, NO. XX, XXX 2017</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 61431005, 61501190, 61671211), by the Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province (No. 2016A030311024), by the open research fund of National Mobile Communications Research Laboratory, Southeast University (No. 2017D08), and by the China Scholarship Council.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Massive MIMO for next generation wireless systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Larsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Edfors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tufvesson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Marzetta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-02">Feb. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MIMO for millimeter-wave wireless communications: Beamforming, spatial multiplexing, or both?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Heath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nix</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rangan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Viswanath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fundamentals of Wireless Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Mesleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sinanovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2228" to="2241" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-07">Jul. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial modulation for multiple-antenna wireless systems: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Renzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-12">Dec. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial modulation for generalized MIMO: Challenges, opportunities, and implementation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Renzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ghrayeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sugiura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hanzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-01">Jan. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design guidelines for spatial modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Renzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hanzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Surveys Tuts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>First quarter</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Index modulation techniques for 5G wireless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Basar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-07">Jul. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power allocation-aided spatial modulation for limited-feedback MIMO systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>El-Hajjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hanzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2198" to="2204" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-05">May 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transmit precoded spatial modulation: Maximizing the minimum euclidean distance versus minimizing the bit error ratio</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Renzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hanzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2054" to="2068" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-03">Mar. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Link adaptation for spatial modulation with limited feedback</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3808" to="3813" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-10">Oct. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive spatial modulation for wireless MIMO transmission systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="602" to="604" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-06">Jun. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simplified adaptive spatial modulation for limited-feedback MIMO systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2656" to="2666" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-07">Jul. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lowcomplexity signal detection for generalized spatial modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-03">Mar. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient compressed sensing detectors for generalized spatial modulation systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Renzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>to be published</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved soft-input soft-output detector for generalized spatial modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Process. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-01">Jan. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy evaluation of spatial modulation at a multi-antenna base station</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stavridis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sinanovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Renzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Veh. Technol. Conf. (VTC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Veh. Technol. Conf. (VTC)<address><addrLine>Las Vegas, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-09">Sept. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An energy saving base station employing spatial modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stavridis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sinanovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Renzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Computer Aided Modeling and Design of Communication Links and Networks (CAMAD)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Computer Aided Modeling and Design of Communication Links and Networks (CAMAD)<address><addrLine>Barcelona, Spain</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-09">Sept. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="235" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A power saving dual-hop architecture based on hybrid spatial modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stavridis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sinanovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Renzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems and Computers (ASILOMAR)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems and Computers (ASILOMAR)<address><addrLine>Pacific Grove, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-11">Nov. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1366" to="1370" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spectral efficiency and energy efficiency optimization via mode selection for spatial modulation in MIMO systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>to be published</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single-carrier SM-MIMO: A promising design for broadband large-scale antenna systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V S</forename><surname>Hari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chockalingam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sugiura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Renzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Masouros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hanzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Surveys Tuts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1687" to="1716" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A lowcomplexity detection scheme for generalized spatial modulation aided single carrier systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Communications Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1072" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-06">June 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low-complexity tree search-based detection algorithms for generalized spatial modulation aided single carrier systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)<address><addrLine>Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May 2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subcarrier-index modulation OFDM</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Abu-Alhiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Symp. Personal, Indoor, Mobile Radio Commun. (PIMRC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Symp. Personal, Indoor, Mobile Radio Commun. (PIMRC)<address><addrLine>Tokyo, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-09">Sep. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="181" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced subcarrier index modulation (SIM) OFDM</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tsonev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sinanovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Global Commun. Conf. (GLOBECOM)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Global Commun. Conf. (GLOBECOM)<address><addrLine>Houston, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-12">Dec. 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="728" to="732" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Orthogonal frequency division multiplexing with index modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Basar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Aygolu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Panayirci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Poor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5536" to="5549" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-11">Nov. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Index Modulation for 5G Wireless Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lowcomplexity ML detector and performance analysis for OFDM with in-phase/quadrature index modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1893" to="1896" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-11">Nov. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OFDM with interleaved subcarrier-index modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1447" to="1450" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-08">Aug. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Index modulated OFDM with interleaved grouping for V2X communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Intell. Transport. Syst. (ITSC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Intell. Transport. Syst. (ITSC)<address><addrLine>Qingdao, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-10">Oct. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1097" to="1104" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OFDM with index modulation using coordinate interleaving</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Basar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Wireless Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="384" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-08">Aug. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalization of orthogonal frequency division multiplexing with index modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5350" to="5359" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-10">Oct. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized spaceand-frequency index modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Datta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Eshwaraiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chockalingam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4911" to="4924" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-07">Jul. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Index modulated OFDM with intercarrier interference cancellation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)<address><addrLine>Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May 2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Index modulated OFDM for underwater acoustic communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimizing the energy efficiency of OFDM with index modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. Syst. (ICCS)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. Syst. (ICCS)<address><addrLine>Macau, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-11">Nov. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="35" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized selecting sub-carrier modulation scheme in OFDM system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC) Workshop</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC) Workshop<address><addrLine>Sydney, Australia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-06">Jun. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="907" to="911" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the achievable rate of OFDM with index modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Poor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1919" to="1932" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-04">Apr. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subcarrier-index modulation aided OFDM -will it work</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ishikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sugiura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hanzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Access</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2580" to="2593" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-06">Jun. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple-input multiple-output OFDM with index modulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Basar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Process. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2259" to="2263" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">Dec. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On multiple-input multiple-output OFDM with index modulation for next generation wireless networks</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3868" to="3878" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-08">Aug. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized LED index modulation optical OFDM for MIMO visible light communications systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Basar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Panayirci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Uysal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)<address><addrLine>Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May 2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new class of soft MIMO demodulation algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Doucet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2752" to="2763" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-11">Nov. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequential Bayesian algorithms for identification and blind equalization of unit-norm channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bordin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G S</forename><surname>Bruno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Process. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2157" to="2161" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-11">Nov. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An enhanced deterministic sequential Monte Carlo method for near-optimal MIMO demodulation with QAM constellations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Aggarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Prasad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2395" to="2406" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-06">Jun. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multilevel sequential Monte Carlo algorithms for MIMO demodulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Aggarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="750" to="758" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-02">Feb. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Bayesian approach for nonlinear equalization and signal detection in millimeter-wave communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nallanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3794" to="3809" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-07">Jul. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bit-level deterministic sequential Monte Carlo method for MIMO wireless systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)<address><addrLine>Beijing, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-05">May 2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3622" to="3626" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Equal-diagonal QR decomposition and its application to precoder design for successive-cancellation detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-K</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kavcic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-01">Jan. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On sequential Monte Carlo sampling methods for Bayesian filtering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Doucet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Godsill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Andrieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics and computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive joint detection and decoding in flat-fading channels via mixture Kalman filtering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2079" to="2094" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-09">Sep. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accuracy and Stability of Numerical Algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Higham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">He is currently working toward the Ph.D. degree with South China University of Technology</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Siam; Guangzhou, China; Guangzhou</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Beixiong Zheng received the B.S. degree from South China University of Technology</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
