<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Event-Based Consensus for Linear Multiagent Systems Without Continuous Communication</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lantao</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Cyber-Systems and Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with the State Key Laboratory of Industrial Control Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Zhejiang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>310027</postCode>
									<settlement>Hangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Changyun</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
							<email>ecywen@ntu.edu.sg</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Cyber-Systems and Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with the State Key Laboratory of Industrial Control Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Zhejiang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>310027</postCode>
									<settlement>Hangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fanghong</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Cyber-Systems and Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with the State Key Laboratory of Industrial Control Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Zhejiang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>310027</postCode>
									<settlement>Hangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zhitao</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Cyber-Systems and Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with the State Key Laboratory of Industrial Control Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Zhejiang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>310027</postCode>
									<settlement>Hangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical and Electronic Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanyang Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hongye</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Cyber-Systems and Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with the State Key Laboratory of Industrial Control Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Zhejiang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>310027</postCode>
									<settlement>Hangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical and Electronic Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanyang Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical and Electronic Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanyang Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Su</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Electrical and Electronic Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanyang Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Event-Based Consensus for Linear Multiagent Systems Without Continuous Communication</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BFBE487BF8C6569AEA8971C965B15E3C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TCYB.2016.2610419</idno>
					<note type="submission">received May 19, 2016; revised August 1, 2016; accepted September 12, 2016.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T09:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Event-based consensus</term>
					<term>leader-follower consensus</term>
					<term>multiagent systems</term>
					<term>nonleader consensus</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this paper, we propose a new distributed event-trigger consensus protocol for linear multiagent systems with external disturbances. Two consensus problems are considered: one is a leader-follower case and the other is a nonleader case. Different from the existing results, our proposed scheme enables each agent to decide when to transmit its state signals to its neighbors such that continuous communication between neighboring agents is avoided. Clearly, this can largely decrease the communication burden of the whole communication network. Besides, since the control signal for each agent is discontinuous because of the event-triggering mechanism, the existence of a solution for the closed-loop system in the classical sense may not be guaranteed. To solve this problem, we employ a nonsmooth analysis technique including differential inclusion and Filippov solution. Through nonsmooth Lyapunov analysis, it is shown that uniformly bounded consensus results are derived and the bound of the consensus error is adjustable by choosing suitable design parameters.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>I N RECENT years, distributed control has received a great deal of attention due to its potential applications in various areas, such as surveillance systems, satellite formation flying, electric power systems, intelligent transportation systems, etc. In the area of cooperative control, consensus is an important and fundamental research topic which aims to make a group of agents reach the same agreement by exchanging information only with their neighbors. Various consensus results can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and references therein.</p><p>On the other hand, network control has also been actively researched as it has the advantages in improving control efficiency and reducing the maintenance cost. One key problem brought about by network control is how to address the communication constraints as a network only has limited resources. Compared with the traditional time-scheduled control approach, event-trigger control is an effective tool which aims to reduce the communication burden while ensuring satisfactory system performance. Actually, through careful research and comparisons, it is found that some ideas and approaches in event triggered systems are quite close to those employed in switched/impulsive systems a decade ago. For example, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the system model and controller switching rule are very similar to the event triggering mechanism studied recently. Thus, it is also possible to employ the techniques used in switched/impulsive systems to address issues related to the event triggered systems. More details about event triggered systems and switched/impulsive systems can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, etc.</p><p>Nowadays, since each agent, such as a robot, is tending to be equipped with a microprocessor which has only limited resources, event-based consensus has become a hot research topic <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, the problem of quantized iterative learning consensus tracking for digital networks with time-varying topologies is considered, while <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> investigates the iterative learning problem for multiple system nodes with event-triggered scheme and quantization. However, these two references only consider discrete-time linear systems. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, an event-trigger control strategy is proposed for a group of first-order agents. However, the proposed approach requires continuous communication between neighbors. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, an event-trigger control approach for both singleintegrator and double-integrator agents is proposed. Though continuous communication between neighbors is avoided, the communication graph is required to be undirected and the results cannot be extended to high-order systems. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, both the event-triggered and self-triggered consensus problems are studied for linear multiagent systems, but continuous communication is required in the event-triggered case and the communication graph is also undirected. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, two conditions with or without continuous communication between neighboring agents for linear multiagent systems are presented. However, the triggering event for each agent involves not only its own state signals, but also its neighbors' states as well as control signals. This makes the triggering mechanism complicated. Besides, possible external disturbance to each agent is not considered. More results about event triggered consensus can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> and references therein.</p><p>2168-2267 c 2016 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission.</p><p>See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p><p>In this paper, we propose a new event-trigger consensus protocol for general linear multiagent systems. In contrast to the existing results, our proposed protocol has the following major advantages or novelties: first, each agent itself decides when to transmit its state signals to its neighbors such that continuous communication between neighboring agents is avoided. Moreover, each state of one agent can be transmitted to its neighbors asynchronously. This will largely decrease the communication burden. Additionally, since the closedloop system is discontinuous because of the event-triggering mechanism, the existence of a classical solution may not be guaranteed. So unlike the existing approaches which simply assume the existence of the classical solution, we adopt nonsmooth analysis techniques, including Filippov solution and differential inclusion, to analyze the closed-loop systems. Utilizing our proposed control protocol, two consensus problems for linear systems, namely, the leader-follower case and the nonleader case, are considered with external disturbances taking into consideration, and a high gain approach is proposed to compensate for the effects of the external disturbances on the final consensus error. Through Lyapunov analyses, it is shown that our proposed event-based protocol achieves uniformly bounded consensus, and the size of the consensus error bound is adjustable by choosing suitable design parameters.</p><p>The remaining part of this paper is organized as follows. Section II describes some mathematical preliminaries including graph theory and some background of nonsmooth analysis. Section III gives the system model, event triggering mechanism and control objective. Sections IV and V present the design and analysis of control protocols for the leader-follower case and nonleader case, respectively. Two simulation examples are presented in Section V to verify the established theoretical results. Finally, Section VI concludes this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. MATHEMATICAL PRELIMINARIES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Notations</head><p>In this paper, we use the following notations: R n×m denotes n × m real matrix and I N denotes identity matrix of dimension N. 1 denotes a column vector of appropriate dimension with all its entries equal to one. A ⊗ B denotes the Kronecker product of matrices A and B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Graph Theory</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">A communication graph G = (V, E, A) contains a node set V = {1, . . . , N}, an edge set E ⊆ V × V and an adjacency matrix A = [a ij ] ∈ R N×N such that a ij &gt; 0 if (j, i) ∈ E, and a ij = 0 if (j, i) / ∈ E.</formula><p>For an edge (i, j), i is called the parent node while j is called the child node, and i is a neighbor of j. We assume no self-loop exist in this graph. The graph is called directed if an edge is an ordered pair of different vertices. Otherwise, it is called undirected. A directed path from vertices j to i is a list of ordered edges with j being the starting node and i is the ending node. A directed graph contains a spanning tree if there is a root vertex, which has no parent node, such that directed paths from this vertex to all the other vertex exist in the graph. The graph G is said to be strongly connected if for any i, j ∈ V there is an ordered path from i to j in G. A directed graph has a spanning tree if it is strongly connected, but not vice versa. L is called the Laplacian matrix of graph G satisfying L ii = i =j a ij and L ij = -a ij , i = j.</p><p>Lemma 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>: Zero is an eigenvalue of L with 1 as a right eigenvector and all the nonzero eigenvalues have positive real parts. Zero is a simple eigenvalue of L if and only if G contains a directed spanning tree.</p><p>Lemma 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>: Suppose that G is strongly connected. Let r = [r 1 , . . . , r N ] be the positive left eigenvector of L associated with the zero eigenvalue and R = diag(r 1 , . . . , r n ). Then, L RL + L T R is the symmetric Laplacian matrix associated with an undirected connected graph. Let ξ be any vector with positive entries. Then, min ξ T x=0,x =0 (x T Lx/x T x) &gt; (λ 2 ( L)/N), where λ 2 ( L) denotes the smallest nonzero eigenvalue of L.</p><p>Lemma 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>: For a nonsingular M-matrix M, there exists a positive diagonal matrix G such that GM + M T G &gt; 0. Moreover, G can be given by diag(g 1 , . . . , g N ), where g = [g 1 , . . . , g N ] T = (M T ) -1 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Nonsmooth Analysis</head><p>For a differential equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ẋ(t) = X(x(t))<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where X : R d → R d is measurable but discontinuous, the existence of a continuously differentiable solution is not guaranteed. In this paper, we consider the Filippov solution <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Definition 1: Let B(R d ) denote the collection of all subsets of R d . The Filippov set-valued map F[X] : R d → B(R d ) is defined by F[X](x) ∩ ς&gt;0 ∩ μ(ς)=0 co X B R d , ς \o , x ∈ R d (2)</formula><p>where o is the set of x at which X(x) is discontinuous.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">B(R d , ς)</formula><p>is the open ball of radius ς centered at x, co denotes the convex closure, and ∩ μ(ς)=0 denotes the intersection over all sets o of Lebesgue measure zero.</p><p>Definition 2: Filippov solutions are defined to be those absolutely continuous curves satisfying the differential inclusion of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">ẋ(t) ∈ F[X](x).</formula><p>The existence of the Filippov solution is ensured by the following lemma.</p><p>Lemma 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>: Assume X : R d → R d is measurable and locally essentially bounded, i.e., bounded in any bounded neighborhood of every point of definition excluding the sets of measure zero. Then for all x 0 ∈ R d , there exists a Filippov solution to (1) with the initial condition x(0) = x 0 .</p><p>For the Lyapunov analysis of the nonsmooth differentiable equations, we need the following lemma.</p><p>Lemma 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>: Let x(•) be a Filippov solution to ẋ(t) = X(x(t)) on an interval containing t, and V : R d → R be a Lipschitz and regular function. Then V(x(t)) is absolutely continuous and (d/dt)V(x(t)) exists almost everywhere</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">d dt V(x(t)) ∈ V(x), for a.e. t ≥ 0 ( 3 ) where V(x) = ∩ ν∈∂V(x(t)) ν T F[X](x). (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. PROBLEM FORMULATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. System Model</head><p>In this paper, we consider a set of N identical agents with general linear dynamics. The dynamics of these agents are described as below, similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">ẋi = Ax i + B[u i + ω i ] (<label>5</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">)</formula><p>in which x i ∈ R n is the state vector, u i ∈ R p is the control input vector, A and B are known constant matrices with compatible dimensions, and ω i ∈ R p denotes external disturbances. For system (5), the following two assumptions are made. Assumption 1: For system ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">5</ref>), all the eigenvalues of A are nonzero and have nonpositive real parts. The pair (A, B) is controllable.</p><p>Assumption 2: There exists positive constants υ i such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">||ω i || ≤ υ i , i = 1, . . . , N.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Triggering Event Design</head><p>In the conventional control protocol, each agent needs to transmit its state signals to its neighbors continuously, which requires a relatively high bandwidth of the communication channel. This is not desirable especially when the network resources are limited. Inspired by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, we will design an event triggering mechanism for each agent to decide when to transmit its state signals to its neighbors. In this way, continuous communication between different agents is no longer needed, which can largely decrease the consumption of network resources.</p><p>To better describe the nature of our proposed event-trigger mechanism, we introduce the state measurement error e i for agent i's state</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">x i = [x i1 , x i2 , . . . , x in ] as e i (t) = ⎛ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎝ e i1 (t) e i2 (t) . . . e in (t) ⎞ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ ⎠ = ⎛ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎝ x i1 (t) -x i1 (t i1k ) x i2 (t) -x i2 (t i2k ) . . . x in (t) -x in (t ink ) ⎞ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ ⎠ , i = 1, . . . , N<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where {t imk }, imk ∈ z + , m = 1, . . . , n, are the time instants at which the signal transmitting event for agent i's mth state is triggered. Let x im,s denote agent i's mth piecewise constant sampled signal, then the triggering event for agent i's mth state is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">x im,s (t) = x im (t imk ), t ∈ t imk , t imk+1 ), i = 1, . . . , N<label>(7)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">t imk+1 = inf{t ∈ R| |e im (t)| ≥ d im }, m = 1, . . . , n, t im1 = 0 (8)</formula><p>where d im is a positive constant denoting the threshold of the triggering event. This triggering event mechanism means that whenever (8) is triggered, the time will be marked as t imk+1 for agent i's mth state and the sampled value x im (t imk+1 ) will be transmitted to its neighbors. During the time t ∈ [t imk , t imk+1 ), the sampled value of x im (t) holds as a constant x im,s (t), i.e., x im,s (t) only needs to be transmitted to its neighbors once in this time interval. Therefore, each agent's state information is broadcast to its neighbors intermittently.</p><p>As seen from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, each local controller has the following three functions: 1) receives and stores the transmitted signals from its neighbors and itself; 2) computes and updates the control input u i ; and 3) monitors agent i's current state signals x i (t) obtained by the sensors constantly, and then decides whether to transmit them to its neighbors or not. Therefore, similar to the existing results using state-feedback, sensors are used to obtain its state signals for each agent. Then with the state signals obtained, the event-triggering rules ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">6</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">8</ref>), which are implemented by software program, can be evaluated in the local controller. In summary, the implementation and evaluation of our proposed event-triggering rules ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">6</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">8</ref>) in the local controller need no extra hardwares.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Control Objective</head><p>In this paper, we aim to design a control law to make the N agents modeled by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> achieve consensus under the event triggering mechanism <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>. We will consider two different consensus protocols: one is a leader-follower case in which the graph contains a directed spanning tree with the leader being the root node and the other one is a nonleader case with the communication graph strongly connected. In the following, we will address these two cases separately.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. DISTRIBUTED HIGH-GAIN PROTOCOL FOR LEADER-FOLLOWER GRAPHS</head><p>In this section, we study the leader-follower case. For simplicity, we assume that the agent indexed by 1 is the leader, while the remaining N -1 agents are the followers. Thus, the objective of this section is to propose a distributed consensus protocol under which ||x i (t)x 1 (t)|| (i = 2, . . . , N) is bounded. For the leader, we assume u 1 = 0 and the graph G among the N agents satisfies the following assumption.</p><p>Assumption 3: The graph G contains a directed spanning tree with the leader as the root node.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Distributed High Gain Consensus Protocol</head><p>Different from the existing results addressing this problem, we assume that each agent's states are transmitted to its neighbors only when the prefixed events are triggered. The proposed consensus protocol is given as</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">u i = α i Kζ i (i = 2, . . . , N) (9)</formula><p>where α i is a positive design constant denoting the controller gain,</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">ζ i = N j=1 a ij (x i,s (t) -x j,s (t)) = N j=1 a ij ⎛ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎝ x i1,s (t) -x j1,s (t) x i2,s (t) -x j2,s (t) . . . x in,s (t) -x jn,s (t) ⎞ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ ⎠ , K = -B T Q with Q &gt; 0</formula><p>satisfying the following algebraic Riccati equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">QA + A T Q -QBB T Q + κI = 0 (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_16">)</formula><p>in which I is a unit matrix, κ and are positive constants specified by the designer. Since the vertex indexed by 1 is the leader and it has no neighbors, the Laplacian matrix L associated with graph G can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">L = 0 0 1×(N-1) L 2 L 1 . Let ξ = [ξ T 2 , . . . , ξ T N ] T , where ξ i = N j=1 a ij (x i -x j ).</formula><p>Then, it follows that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">ξ = (L 1 ⊗ I n ) ⎡ ⎢ ⎣ x 2 -x 1 . . . x N -x 1 ⎤ ⎥ ⎦.<label>(11)</label></formula><p>From ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">5</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, and (11), we can get</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">ξ = (I N-1 ⊗ A)ξ + L 1 α ⊗ BK ζ + (L 1 ⊗ B) ω<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">ζ = [ζ T 2 , . . . , ζ T N ] T , α = diag(α 2 , . . . , α N ), and ω = [ω T 2 -ω T 1 , . . . , ω T N -ω T 1 ] T . With Definitions 1 and 2, we have ξ ∈ (I N-1 ⊗ A)ξ + L 1 α ⊗ BK F(ζ ) + (L 1 ⊗ B) ω<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">F(ζ ) = [F(ζ 2 ), . . . , F(ζ N )]. Now we need to analyze F(ζ i ) = N j=1 a ij (F(x i,s (t) -F(x j,s (t)), i = 2, . . . , N.</formula><p>As can be seen, it is enough to study one entry of F(x i,s (t)) since F(x j,s (t)) has the same properties. Without loss of generality, we consider F(x im,s (t)), m = 1, . . . , n. Note that it is also sufficient to analyze the condition that x im,s (t) &gt; 0, as the same analysis can be repeated for the case that x im,s (t) ≤ 0.</p><p>From (8) we know</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">x im -d im ≤ x im,s ≤ x im + d im . (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">)</formula><p>Then for all υ im ∈ F[x im,s (t)], we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">x im -d im ≤ υ im ≤ x im + d im (<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">)</formula><p>which gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">υ im = x im + μ im d im (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">)</formula><p>where μ im can be any number in the set [-1, 1]. Then we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">F[ζ i ] = N j=1 a ij F x i,s -F x j,s = N j=1 a ij x i + D i -x j -D j = ξ i + χ i (<label>17</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">D i = [u i1 d i1 , . . . , u in d in ] T , with u ip ∈ [-1, 1], p = 1, . . . , n, χ i = N j=1 a ij (D i -D j ). Let χ = [χ T 2 , . . . , χ T N ] T , we have F[ζ ] = ξ + χ. (<label>18</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_31">)</formula><p>Substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_30">18</ref>) into <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">ξ ∈ (I N-1 ⊗ A)ξ + L 1 α ⊗ BK (ξ + χ ) + (L 1 ⊗ B) ω. (19)</formula><p>Now, we give the following theorem showing the main result of this section.</p><p>Theorem 1: Consider system (5) satisfying Assumptions 1-3, and the event-trigger-based control protocol ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">7</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) in which α i &gt; g i , [g 2 , . . . , g N ] T = (L T 1 ) -1 1, G = diag(g 2 , . . . , g N ) and K = -B T Q, Q &gt; 0 is the solution of (10) with 0 &lt; &lt; λ 0 where λ 0 is the smallest eigenvalue of GL 1 + L T 1 G. Then all the followers can track the leader with the tracking error uniformly bounded, and the size of the bound is adjustable by choosing suitable design parameters. Besides, the Zeno behavior is excluded.</p><p>Proof: We choose the Lyapunov function as</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">V = N i=2 g i 2 α i ξ T i Qξ i . (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">)</formula><p>By Lemma 4 we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">V = N i=2 g i α i ξ T i Q ξi = ξ T αG ⊗ Q (I N-1 ⊗ A)ξ + L 1 α ⊗ BK (ξ + χ ) + ξ T αG ⊗ Q (L 1 ⊗ B) ω = 1 2 ξ T αG ⊗ QA + A T Q + α GL 1 + L T 1 G α ⊗ QBK ξ + ξ T αGL 1 ⊗ QB ω -ξ T αGL 1 α ⊗ QBB T Q χ ≤ 1 2 ξ T αG ⊗ QA + A T Q -λ 0 α2 ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + ξ T αGL 1 ⊗ QB ω -ξ T αGL 1 α ⊗ QBB T Q χ. (<label>21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">)</formula><p>Note that</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">ξ T αGL 1 ⊗ QB ω = ξ T σ1 2 α ⊗ QB 2 σ1 GL 1 ⊗ I ω ≤ σ 1 2 ξ T α2 ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + 2 σ 1 (GL 1 ⊗ I) ω 2 ≤ σ 1 2 ξ T α2 ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + 2 σ 1 σ max (GL 1 ) N i=2 (υ i + υ 1 ) 2<label>(22)</label></formula><p>where σ 1 is a positive constant. Also</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">-ξ T αGL 1 α ⊗ QBB T Q χ = -ξ T σ 2 2 α ⊗ QB 2 σ 2 GL 1 α ⊗ B T Q χ ≤ σ 2 2 ξ T α 2 ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + 2 σ 2 GL 1 α ⊗ B T Q χ 2 (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">)</formula><p>where σ 2 is a positive constant.</p><p>Choosing 0 &lt; &lt; λ 0 -σ 1 -σ 2 and α i &gt; g i , then substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_37">22</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_38">23</ref>) into <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">V ≤ 1 2 ξ T αG ⊗ QA + A T Q -α2 ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + 2 σ 1 σ max (GL 1 ) i=N i=2 (υ i + υ 1 ) 2 + 2 σ 2 GL 1 α ⊗ B T Q χ 2 ≤ 1 2 ξ T αG ⊗ QA + A T Q -αG ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + 2 σ 1 σ max (GL 1 ) N i=2 (υ i + υ 1 ) 2 + 2 σ 2 GL 1 α ⊗ B T Q χ 2 ≤ - κ 2 λ min αG ξ 2 + (<label>24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">)</formula><p>where 2 and λ min ( αG) is the smallest eigenvalue of αG. By Lemma 4, we know V ≤ -(1/2)κλ min ( αG)||ξ || 2 + . Since χ and υ i , i = 1, . . . , N, are bounded, must be bounded. So we get that the consensus errors ξ are uniformly bounded and the bound is given as</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">= (2/σ 1 )σ max (GL 1 ) N i=2 (υ i + υ 1 ) 2 + (2/σ 2 )||GL 1 α ⊗ B T Q)χ ||</formula><formula xml:id="formula_43">ξ 2 ≤ 4σ max (GL 1 ) σ 1 N i=2 (υ i + υ 1 ) 2 + 4 σ 2 GL 1 α ⊗ B T Q χ 2 κλ min αG . (<label>25</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">)</formula><p>From ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_43">25</ref>), we can get that by increasing α i at the expense of increasing the control energy, the size of the first part of the numerator in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>, i.e., the effect of the external disturbance, can be reduced. The size of the second part of the numerator can be decreased by decreasing the event triggering threshold d i , at the expense of more triggering events. Besides, it is known that (10) has a unique positive definite symmetric solution Q if (A,B) is controllable <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. Moreover, Q depends continuously on κ and lim κ↓0 Q = 0, thus the effect of the second part of the numerator in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_43">25</ref>) is adjustable by adjusting κ. Therefore, the size of the final consensus error bound is adjustable by choosing suitable design parameters. Now, we need to show how the Zeno behavior, i.e., the phenomenon that the event is triggered infinitely times in a finite time interval, can be avoided. This can be done by showing that for each x im (t imk ), i = 1, . . . , N, m = 1, . . . , n, it will take t * im &gt; 0 time units to change from x im (t imk ) to x im (t imk+1 ). To this end, by recalling that e im (t</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">) = x im (t) -x im (t imk ), ∀t ∈ [t imk , t imk+1 ) we have d dt |e im | = d dt (e im * e im ) 1 2 = sign(e im )ė im ≤ |ẋ im |. (<label>26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_46">)</formula><p>By Assumption 1, we know x i is globally bounded. Since ẋim (t) is continuous function of the system states x i , then there must exist a constant τ im &gt; 0 such that |ẋ im | ≤ τ im . By noting that e im (t imk ) = 0 and lim t→t imk+1 e i (t) = d im , we obtain that the lower bound of interexecution times t * im must satisfy t * im ≥ (d im /τ im ). This completes the proof.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. DISTRIBUTED HIGH-GAIN PROTOCOLS FOR STRONG CONNECTED GRAPHS WITH EXTERNAL DISTURBANCES</head><p>In this section, we extend the above results to strongly connected communication graphs where there is no leader. The dynamics of the N agents are the same as <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>. In this case, we assume the communication graph satisfies the following assumption.</p><p>Assumption 4: The communication graph is strongly connected.</p><p>We give the distributed control law as</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">u i = α i Kζ i , i = 1, . . . , N<label>(27)</label></formula><p>where α i , ζ i (i = 1, . . . , N), and K are defined in the same way as the leader-follower case. Let ξ = [ξ T 1 , . . . , ξ T N ] T , where</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">ξ i = N j=1 a ij (x i -x j ), we have ξ = (L ⊗ I n )x. Then, it can be obtained that ξ ∈ (I N ⊗ A)ξ + L α ⊗ BK F(ζ ) + (L ⊗ B)ω (<label>28</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">ζ = [ζ T 1 , . . . , ζ T N ] T , α = diag(α 1 , . . . , α N ) and ω = [ω T 1 , . . . , ω T N ] T .</formula><p>Then, by the same analysis in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_22">14</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_30">18</ref>) we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">ξ ∈ (I N ⊗ A)ξ + L α ⊗ BK (ξ + χ ) + (L ⊗ B)ω. (<label>29</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">)</formula><p>Let r = [r 1 , . . . , r N ] T be the positive left eigenvector of L associated with the zero eigenvalue. Define R diag(r 1 , . . . , r N ) &gt; 0 and suppose λ 1 ( L) is the smallest nonzero eigenvalue of L = RL + L T R. Based on (29), we give the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 2: Choose the design parameters as α i &gt; r i and 0 &lt; &lt; (λ 1 ( L)/N) for the distributed controllers <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>. Then, under Assumptions 1, 2, and 4, the event-trigger-based control protocol ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">7</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> ensures that the tracking errors are uniformly bounded with their bounds adjustable by choosing suitable design parameters and the Zeno behavior is excluded.</p><p>Proof: Choose the Lyapunov function as</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">V = N i=1 r i 2 α i ξ T i Qξ i . (<label>30</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">)</formula><p>Then, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">V = N i=1 r i α i ξ T i Q ξi = ξ T αR ⊗ Q (I N ⊗ A)ξ + L α ⊗ BK (ξ + χ ) + ξ T αR ⊗ Q (L ⊗ B)ω = 1 2 ξ T αR ⊗ QA + A T Q -α L α ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + ξ T αRL ⊗ QB ω -ξ T αRL α ⊗ QBB T Q χ. (<label>31</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_56">) Let ξ = ( α ⊗ I n )ξ , then ξ T α-1 r ⊗ I n = ξ T α ⊗ I n α-1 r ⊗ I n = x T L T ⊗ I n (r ⊗ I n ) = x T L T r ⊗ I n = 0 (<label>32</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_57">)</formula><p>where we used the fact that r T L = 0. Because α-1 r ⊗ I n is positive, using Lemma 2, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">ξ T L ⊗ I n ξ T &gt; λ 1 L N ξ T ξ = λ 1 L N ξ T α2 ⊗ I n ξ. (<label>33</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">)</formula><p>Substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_58">33</ref>) into <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref> gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">V ≤ 1 2 ξ T ⎡ ⎣ αR ⊗ QA + A T Q - λ 1 L N α2 ⊗ QBB T Q ⎤ ⎦ ξ + ξ T αRL ⊗ QB ω -ξ T αRL α ⊗ QBB T Q χ. (<label>34</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_61">)</formula><p>Similar to ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_37">22</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_38">23</ref>), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">ξ T αRL ⊗ QB ω = ξ T σ 1 2 α ⊗ QB 2 σ 1 RL ⊗ I ω ≤ σ 1 2 ξ T α2 ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + 2 σ 1 (RL ⊗ I)ω 2 ≤ σ 1 2 ξ T α2 ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + 2 σ 1 σ max (RL) N i=1 υ 2 i (<label>35</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_63">)</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">-ξ T αRL α ⊗ QBB T Q χ = -ξ T σ 2 2 α ⊗ QB 2 σ 2 RL α ⊗ B T Q χ ≤ σ 2 2 ξ T α2 ⊗ QBB T Q ξ + 2 σ 2 R L α ⊗ B T Q χ 2<label>(36)</label></formula><p>where σ 1 and σ 2 are positive constants. Then substituting <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_64">36</ref>) into <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">V ≤ 1 2 ξ T ⎡ ⎣ αR ⊗ ⎛ ⎝ QA + A T Q - ⎛ ⎝ λ 1 L N -σ 1 -σ 2 ⎞ ⎠ QBB T Q ⎤ ⎦ ξ + 2 σ 1 σ max (RL) N i=1 (υ i ) 2 + 2 σ 2 R L α ⊗ B T Q χ 2 ≤ 1 2 ξ T αR ⊗ QA + A T Q -QBB T Q ξ + 2 σ 1 σ max (RL) N i=1 υ 2 i + 2 σ 2 RL α ⊗ B T Q χ 2 ≤ - 1 2 κλ min αR ξ 2 +<label>(37)</label></formula><p>where 2 and λ min ( αR) is the smallest eigenvalue of αR. From (37), the consensus error vector ξ is uniformly bounded and the bound is given as</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">= (2/σ 1 )σ max (RL) N i=1 υ 2 i + (2/σ 2 )||RL α ⊗ B T Q)χ ||</formula><formula xml:id="formula_67">ξ 2 ≤ 4 σ 1 σ max (RL) N i=1 υ 2 i + 4 σ 2 RL α ⊗ B T Q χ 2 κλ min αR . (<label>38</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_68">)</formula><p>Similar to the analysis in the proof of Theorem 1, the size of the consensus error bound can be reduced by suitably choosing the design parameter α i and κ. Since the eigenvalues of matrix A are nonzero and have no positive real parts, all the states of the N agents are bounded. Thus, by the same analysis in the proof of Theorem 1, the Zeno behavior can be excluded. This complete the proof. Remark 1: Note that <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> proposes an event-based consensus protocol for linear multiagent systems without continuous communication between neighboring agents. However, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> the triggering event for each agent depends not only on its own sampled states, but also its neighbors' sampled states as well as the latest control signals. This makes the event triggering mechanism extremely complicated. Besides, whenever the designed event for one agent is triggered, all the states of this agent need to be broadcast to its neighbors. While in this paper, it is seen from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">7</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>) that each state of an individual agent has one triggering event which only depends on its own signal changing rate, and the agent can transmit its multiple state signals to its neighbors asynchronously. Therefore, our proposed event-based protocols are simpler and more resources-saving in real implementation.</p><p>Remark 2: Note that in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, the final consensus error bound is determined by the threshold of the triggering event. The size of the bound can be only decreased by reducing the threshold, which is at the expense of increasing the number of triggering events (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr">Remark 3]</ref>). In this paper, besides reducing the event threshold, the size of the final consensus error can also be adjusted by suitably choosing the parameters of Riccati equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>. This will also be illustrated in the simulation example below.</p><p>Remark 3: When A has zero or positive eigenvalues, uniformly bounded consensus can still be achieved by following the same procedures of proofs in Theorems 1 and 2. The reason we need Assumption 1 is to exclude the Zeno behavior. Since without this assumption, the consensus trajectory of all the agents may go to infinity which will make the time interval between two triggering events not lower bounded. How to relax Assumption 1 is a challenging topic still under investigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. SIMULATION EXAMPLES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Example 1: The Leader-Follower Case</head><p>In this section, we provide a simulation example to illustrate the effectiveness of our proposed control protocol in the leader-follower case by considering the following linear system:</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">ẋi1 ẋi2 = 0 1 -1 0 x i1 x i2 + 0 1 (u i + ω i ). (<label>39</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_70">)</formula><p>The communication graph is given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, where the vertex indexed by 1 is the leader which is only accessible  by agent 2. Clearly, this communication graph satisfies Assumption 3, and we can get [g 1 , g 2 , g 3 ] = <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. The leader's initial states are set as <ref type="bibr">[4 5</ref>], and the remaining three followers' initial values are all set to be [-5 -6], [- <ref type="bibr">10 15]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr">[15 -10]</ref>, respectively. The disturbances associated with the agents are assumed to be ω 1 = 0, ω 2 = 0.5 * sin(t), ω 3 = 0.8 * sin(t), and ω 4 = 0.4 * cos(2t). To show the size of the tracking error is adjustable by tuning the parameters of the Riccati equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> when the event thresholds are fixed, as discussed in Remark 2, we set all the event triggering thresholds as d im = 1, i = 1, 2, 3, 4, m = 1, 2, and the controller gains as α 1 = 4, α 2 = 5, and α 3 = 6. Then we consider the following two pairs of parameters.  2) = 1 and κ = 1. Accordingly, we can get  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> show the trajectories of these four agents, while Figs. 5 and 6 illustrate the actual state signals of agent 1 and the corresponding sampled values transmitted to its followers. Since the remaining three agents broadcast their state information to their neighbors in a similar pattern, they are omitted here. The control signal for the three followers are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9</ref>. From the simulation results, it is observed that uniformly bounded consensus is obtained with our proposed control scheme. Also, the bound of the consensus error is adjustable by choosing suitable design parameters. Note that our proposed event-trigger mechanism only requires each agent to broadcast its information to its neighbors intermittently as shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">5</ref> and<ref type="figure">6</ref>. This can largely reduce the  communication burden. Clearly, the simulation results verify our theoretical analysis and illustrate the effectiveness of our proposed event-trigger control scheme.</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">Q = 1.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Example 2: The Nonleader Case</head><p>Now, we consider the nonleader case with its application to a class of robots described <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> J qi + Dq i + MgL sin(q i ) = u i + ω i , i = 1, 2, 3, 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref> where q i , qi , u i , and ω i are the angle, angular velocity of the rigid link, the control signal and the external disturbances, respectively. J denotes the rotation inertia of the servo motor, D is the damping coefficient, L is the length from the axis of joint to the mass center, M is the mass of the link, and g is the gravitational acceleration. The parameters of system <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref> are MgL = 5 and D = 0.002. By neglecting the damping effects  and linearizing system <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(40)</ref> around zero, we have where x i1 = q i and x i2 = qi , i = 1, 2, 3, 4. The communication graph of these four robots are given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">10</ref>. Clearly, for system (41), Assumptions 1 and 3 are satisfied. For simulation, the initial conditions for these four agents are set as [1 1], [0 0], [-1 1], and [1 -1], respectively. The external disturbances are assumed to be ω 1 = 0.02 sin(0.5t), ω 2 = 0.05 * sin(t), ω 3 = 0.08 * sin(t), and ω 4 = 0.04 * cos(2t). Then, to design the controller, we set all the event triggering thresholds as Note that, in this simulation example, we apply the control signal obtained from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_47">27</ref>) to the practical system (40) directly to verify the effectiveness of our proposed control protocol. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">11</ref> shows the state trajectories of these four agents. Note that the actual state signals and their corresponding transmitted values of agent 1 are illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">12</ref>, while the results of agents 2-4 are omitted due to their similarity to those of agent 1. The control signals for these four agents are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">13</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">14</ref>. Again, the simulation results are consistent with the theoretical analyses which verifies the effectiveness of our proposed control protocol.</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">ẋi1 ẋi2 = 0 1 -5 0 x i1 x i2 + 0 1 (u i + ω i )<label>(41)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_73">d im = 0.1, i = 1, 2, 3, 4, m = 1, 2, r = [1 1 1 1] T , α 1 = α 2 = α 3 = α 4 = 1.5, = 0.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we consider the event-based consensus problem for general linear multiagent systems with external disturbances. Two consensus protocols, i.e., the leader-follower case and the nonleader case, are studied separately. An event triggering mechanism for each agent to transmit its state signals to its neighbors is designed, by which continuous communication between the neighboring agents is avoided. To study the discontinuous closed-loop system caused by the event triggering mechanism, nonsmooth analysis techniques including the Filippov solution and differential inclusion are adopted. It is shown that our proposed event-based scheme achieves uniformly bounded consensus. As a future work, it is worthy to explore the tools employed in switched/impulsive systems, such as those in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, to consider problems involving event triggered systems, due to their similarities. From 1989 to 1991, he was a Research Associate and then a Post-Doctoral Fellow with the University of Adelaide, Adelaide, SA, Australia. Since 1991, he has been with the School of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, Nanyang Technological University, Singapore, where he is currently a Full Professor. His current research interests include control systems and applications, intelligent power management system, smart grids, cyber-physical systems, complex systems and networks, model-based online learning and system identification, and signal and image processing. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Functions of ith local controller.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,358.51,53.20,157.92,87.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Communication graph of Example 1.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,365.50,52.88,144.00,115.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Trajectory of x i1 , i = 1, 2, 3, 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Trajectory of x i2 , i = 1, 2, 3, 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>= 1 and κ = 0.1. Then, we obtain Q = 0.4662 0.0488 0.0488 0.4445 such that K = [-0.0488, -0.4445].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. x 11 and x 11,s .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Control signal for agent 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Control signal for agent 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Control signal for agent 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 10 .Fig. 11 .</head><label>1011</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Communication graph of Example 2.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,365.00,298.70,144.72,115.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 12 .Fig. 13 .</head><label>1213</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. x 1 and x 1,s .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14. Control signal for agents 3 and 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Lantao</head><label></label><figDesc>Xing received the bachelor's degree in automation engineering from the China University of Petroleum, Beijing, China, in 2009. He is currently pursing the Ph.D. degree in control science and engineering with Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China. His current research interests include nonlinear systems, multiagent systems, and quantized and adaptive control. Changyun Wen (F'10) received the B.Eng. degree from Xi'an Jiaotong University, Xi'an, China, in 1983 and the Ph.D. degree from the University of Newcastle, Callaghan, NSW, Australia, in 1990.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Dr. Wen is an Associate Editor of a number of journals including Automatica, the IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON INDUSTRIAL ELECTRONICS, and the IEEE Control Systems Magazine. He is an Executive Editor-in-Chief for the Journal of Control and Decision. From 2000 to 2002, He served as an Associate Editor of the IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON AUTOMATIC CONTROL. He has been actively involved in organizing international conferences playing the roles of the General Chair, the General Co-Chair, the Technical Program Committee Chair, the Program Committee Member, the General Advisor, and the Publicity Chair. He was a recipient of the Institution of Engineers, Singapore Prestigious Engineering Achievement Award 2005. He is a member of the IEEE Fellow Committee from 2011 to 2013 and a Distinguished Lecturer of the IEEE Control Systems Society from 2010 to 2013.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the China Scholarship Council, in part by the 111 Project under Grant B07031, in part by the National Nature Science of China under Grant 61134007, Grant 61223004, and Grant 61433013, in part by the Public Projects of Zhejiang Province under Grant 2015C31124. This paper was recommended by Associate Editor G.-P. Liu.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus problems in networks of agents with switching topology and time-delays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Olfati-Saber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1520" to="1533" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-09">Sep. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reaching a consensus in a dynamically changing environment: A graphical approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D O</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Control Optim</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="575" to="600" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An overview of recent progress in the study of distributed multi-agent coordination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Informat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="427" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-02">Feb. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus seeking in multiagent systems under dynamically changing interaction topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="655" to="661" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-05">May 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cooperative Control of Distributed Multi-Agent Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shamma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Hoboken, NJ, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synchronization of multi-agent systems with delayed control input information from neighbors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2152" to="2164" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coordination of groups of mobile autonomous agents using nearest neighbor rules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jadbabaie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="988" to="1001" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-06">Jun. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus of multiagent systems subject to partially accessible and overlapping Markovian network topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q.-L</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TCYB.2016.2570860</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern., to be published</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leader-following consensus of nonlinear multiagent systems with stochastic sampling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TCYB.2015.2514119</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern., to be published</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust stability of a multi-agent system under arbitrary and time-varying communication topologies and communication delays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Popov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Werner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2343" to="2347" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-09">Sep. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed consensus of linear multiagent systems with adaptive dynamic protocols</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1986" to="1995" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust output synchronization of a network of heterogeneous nonlinear agents via nonlinear regulation theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Isidori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Marconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Casadei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2680" to="2691" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-10">Oct. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed containment control of multi-agent systems with general linear dynamics in the presence of multiple leaders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robust Nonlin. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="534" to="547" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Input-to-state stabilization of switched nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1111" to="1116" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-07">Jul. 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-triggered real-time scheduling of stabilizing control tasks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tabuada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1680" to="1685" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-09">Sep. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An introduction to event-triggered and self-triggered control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P M H</forename><surname>Heemels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tabuada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE 51st Annu. Conf. Decis. Control (CDC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE 51st Annu. Conf. Decis. Control (CDC)<address><addrLine>Maui, HI, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3270" to="3285" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Soh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Switched and Impulsive Systems: Analysis, Design and Applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">313</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-triggering in distributed networked control systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lemmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="586" to="601" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-03">Mar. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An ISS self-triggered implementation of linear controllers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mazo</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Anta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tabuada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1310" to="1314" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed networked control systems: A brief overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q.-L</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ins.2015.07.047</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-08">Aug. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantized iterative learning consensus tracking of digital networks with limited information communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TNNLS.2016.2532351</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Neural Netw. Learn. Syst., to be published</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iterative learning control for discrete-time systems with event-triggered transmission strategy and quantization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.automatica.2016.05.031</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-10">Oct. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed event-triggered control for multi-agent systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Dimarogonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Frazzoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1291" to="1297" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-05">May 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-triggered cooperative control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Dimarogonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Eur. Control Conf. (ECC)</title>
		<meeting>Eur. Control Conf. (ECC)<address><addrLine>Budapest, Hungary</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3015" to="3020" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-based broadcasting for multi-agent average consensus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Seyboth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Dimarogonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="252" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-01">Jan. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus of linear multi-agent systems by distributed event-triggered strategy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="148" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-01">Jan. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-based consensus of multi-agent systems with general linear models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-P</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="552" to="558" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed event-based control for interconnected linear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Guinaldo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Dimarogonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lehmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Asynchronous Control for Networked Systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cham, Switzerland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="179" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-based leader-following consensus of multi-agent systems with input time delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-P</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1362" to="1367" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-05">May 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A distributed event-triggered transmission strategy for sampled-data consensus of multi-agent systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q.-L</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1489" to="1496" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observer-based output feedback event-triggered control for consensus of multi-agent systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4885" to="4894" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-09">Sep. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sampled-data consensus in multi-agent systems with asynchronous hybrid event-time driven interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-03">Mar. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event based agreement protocols for multi-agent networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2125" to="2132" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus of second-order heterogeneous multi-agent systems under a directed graph</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Amer. Control Conf. (ACC)</title>
		<meeting>Amer. Control Conf. (ACC)<address><addrLine>Portland, OR, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="802" to="807" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing fully distributed consensus protocols for linear multi-agent systems with directed graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1152" to="1157" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-04">Apr. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discontinuous dynamical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cortes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Control Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-06">Jun. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Optimization and Nonsmooth Analysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Philadelphia, PA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>SIAM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed adaptive consensus protocols for linear multi-agent systems with directed graphs in the presence of external disturbances</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE 33rd Chin. Control Conf. (CCC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE 33rd Chin. Control Conf. (CCC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1632" to="1637" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Least squares stationary optimal control and the algebraic Riccati equation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Willems</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="634" />
			<date type="published" when="1971-12">Dec. 1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive fuzzy tracking control of nonlinear time-delay systems with dead-zone output mechanism based on a novel smooth model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L P</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1998" to="2011" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">Dec. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
