<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Challenges and Best Practices in Industry-Academia Collaborations in Software Engineering: A Systematic Literature Review</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-07-29">July 29, 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Vahid</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
							<email>vahid.garousi@hacettepe.edu.tr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Software Engineering Research Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hacettepe University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ankara</settlement>
									<country key="TR">Turkey</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kai</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
							<email>kai.petersen@bth.se</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Software Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Blekinge Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Baris</forename><surname>Ozkan</surname></persName>
							<email>baris.ozkan@atilim.edu.tr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Information Systems Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Atilim University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ankara</settlement>
									<country key="TR">Turkey</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Information and Software Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Maral Software Engineering Consulting Corporation</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Calgary</settlement>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Challenges and Best Practices in Industry-Academia Collaborations in Software Engineering: A Systematic Literature Review</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-07-29">July 29, 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A651A7871C883D2065C0D6DCAFF8B7AC</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.infsof.2016.07.006</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received date: 31 December 2015 Revised date: 5 May 2016 Accepted date: 23 July 2016 Preprint submitted to Journal of Information and Software Tech.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T17:15+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Software engineering</term>
					<term>industry-academia collaborations</term>
					<term>industry</term>
					<term>universities</term>
					<term>challenges</term>
					<term>success patterns</term>
					<term>best practices</term>
					<term>systematic literature review</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Context:</head><p>The global software industry and the software engineering (SE) academia are two large communities. However, unfortunately, the level of joint industry-academia collaborations in SE is still relatively very low, compared to the amount of activity in each of the two communities. It seems that the two 'camps' show only limited interest/motivation to collaborate with one other. Many researchers and practitioners have written about the challenges, success patterns (what to do, i.e., how to collaborate) and antipatterns (what not do do) for industry-academia collaborations.</p><p>Objective: To identify (a) the challenges to avoid risks to the collaboration by being aware of the challenges, (b) the best practices to provide an inventory of practices (patterns) allowing for an informed choice of practices to use when planning and conducting collaborative projects.</p><p>Method: A systematic review has been conducted. Synthesis has been done using grounded-theory based coding procedures.</p><p>Results: Through thematic analysis we identified 10 challenge themes and 17 best practice themes. A key outcome was the inventory of best practices, the most common ones recommended in different contexts were</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Industry-Academia Collaboration (IAC) in Software Engineering (SE) has been an important topic since the early years of SE <ref type="bibr">(around 1969)</ref>. In an applied field such as SE, industrial impact of research is of utmost importance. For example, there are projects such as the ACM SIGSOFT Impact project (www.sigsoft.org/impact) which have measured and analyzed the impact of software engineering research on practice. To highlight the importance of IACs in SE, and to discuss success stories and how to bridge the gap between industry and academia, various workshops and panels are regularly organized at international research conferences, such as a panel called "What Industry wants from research" at the ICSE 2011 conference in which ideas from companies such as Toshiba, Google and IBM were presented. More recently an international workshop on the topic of long-term industrial collaborations on software engineering (called WISE) was organized in September 2014 in Sweden which hosted several talks on the subject.</p><p>In his classic book "Software Creativity 2.0" <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, Glass and DeMarco dedicated two chapters to "theory versus practice" and "industry versus academe" and have presented several examples (which they believe are ''disturbing") on the mismatch of theory and practice.</p><p>In a keynote talk entitled "Useful software engineering research: leading a double-agent life" in the IEEE International Conference on Software Maintenance (ICSM) in 2011, Lionel Briand mentioned that: "Though in essence an engineering discipline, software engineering research has always</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T been struggling to demonstrate impact. This is reflected in part by the funding challenges that the discipline faces in many countries, the difficulties we have to attract industrial participants to our conferences, and the scarcity of papers reporting industrial case studies".</p><p>To bridge the gap between industry and academia and to foster IAC, a number of researchers from academia and also practitioners from industry have systematically studied and reported challenges, best practices (patterns for successful collaborations) and anti-patterns. As the SE field matures, to ensure the relevance and impact of academic research activities, there is a major need for further IACs in this area. As the number of studies focusing on the IAC in SE has increased, it is important to systematically synthesize the state-of-the-art in this area <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>. Such a synthesis would provide many benefits to the broader community of researchers and practitioners, to be better aware of the challenges in collaborations and what (not) to do to ensure success. In other words, researchers and practitioners may use the results presented in this work to identify the potential risks by being aware of potential challenges, make informed decisions about what practices to utilize to ensure successful IACs.</p><p>In this work, we utilize a Systematic Literature Review (SLR) and systematic mapping (SM) process <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> to select the relevant studies, extract data and then synthesize the above aspects in IAC in SE.</p><p>After a careful and systematic paper selection process, our study pool included a set of 33 studies (from the set of 49 identified candidate studies) published in the area of between 1995 and 2014. The full version of our systematic mapping data is available through a publicly-accessible online repository <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. We utilized grounded-theory-based qualitative synthesis to derive the list of challenges and best practices (success patterns) in IACs.</p><p>The remainder of the article is organized as follows. Section 2 discusses related work. Section 3 describes our research goal and research method. Sections 4 presents the results of the study. Section 5 discusses the results, and presents implications of the SLR results for researchers and practitioners, and presents the potential threats to validity of our study. Finally, Section 6 concludes this study and states the future work directions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Context and Related Work</head><p>The context of our study is in the scope of experiences and lessons learnt about IACs as reported by SE practitioners and researchers. Since our goal</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>is not to review nor synthesize the technical aspects of IACs reported in the literature, but instead to review and synthesize the challenges, best practices and anti-patterns of IACs, we have thus narrowed our focus to only "experience" papers reported by SE practitioners and researchers, and not the regular technical papers which have reported (empirical) applications of theoretical approaches in industrial contexts. We, as the SE community, are observing more and more papers on industrial case studies as the result IACs in recent years. There are even specific venues for such papers, e.g., the Software Engineering in Practice (SEIP) track of the ICSE (International Conference on Software Engineering), the industry track of the ICST (IEEE International Conference on Software Testing, Verification and Validation), and several recent special issues of the international SE journals on IACs.</p><p>Getting the exact statistics of technical papers in the scope of IACs in not straightforward since different keywords are used by authors in paper titles and abstracts, e.g., "industrial" case studies, "commerical". However, based on our recent experience in conducting a few bibliometric studies in SE, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>, we used a heuristic-based keyword to search for and get coarse statistics on the number of technical papers in the scope of IACs from the Scopus database, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. As discussed above, we acknowledge that this simplistic heuristic-based approach is not the best way to precisely count the annual rate of papers on industrial case studies and IAC in SE, but it is a quick and rough approach to get some coarse statistics. Based on experience in our recent bibliometric studies in SE, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>, we searched for the word "software" in "source titles" (venues) and the phrase "industrial case" in title, abstract and keywords of papers. Given the above search query, the Scopus database returned 1577 records, which after we randomly analyzed, were a rough acceptable set of industrial case studies and IAC in SE. Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows the the annual number of these papers and, as we can see, there has been an increase in the number of technical IAC papers in recent years.</p><p>As discussed above, since our goal in this work is to review and synthesize the challenges, best practices and anti-patterns of IACs, our focus in this work will be only on "experience" papers reported by SE practitioners and researchers, which we searched for and populated as the pool of primary studies (more details in Section 3. <ref type="bibr">3.3)</ref>.</p><p>Since this work is a secondary study about IAC in SE, as to the related work, we searched for secondary studies about IAC in SE, but we did not find any. A remotely-related work is <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> which is a SLR of experimental</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T studies conducted in software industry. However, it covers no aspect of IAC.</p><p>We found only two secondary studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref> about IAC in all broad areas of science. The study reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> is a review of the literature on university-industry relations with respect to academic engagement and commercialization, which has been authored by a team of 13 researchers from across Europe. The study presents a SLR of research on academic scientists involvement in collaborative research, contract research, consulting and informal relationships for university-industry knowledge transfer, which the authors refer to as "academic engagement". The study reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> is another more recent (published in 2015) SLR on collaborations between universities and industry. The review resulted in identifying the following five key aspects, which underpin the theory of IAC: necessity, reciprocity, efficiency, stability and legitimacy. The authors then integrated these key aspects into an overarching process framework shown in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> which we partially utilize in the current work when we want to classify challenges and patterns over the phases of the collaboration life-cycle (from project inception to conclusion).</p><p>Overall, the related work shows that there are only limited synthesized experiences of IACs in general, and we did not identify any in the area of software engineering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Method</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Overview of the research method used</head><p>Our literature review was carried out in two phases. In the first phase, a systematic mapping study was performed following the guidelines by Petersen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. The systematic mapping aimed at giving an overview of which SE topics (sub-areas) and other aspects (e.g. use of research methods) have been covered in this area. Thereafter, we conducted on the systematic review based on the guidelines by Kitchenham and Charters <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> focusing on research synthesis of the findings of individual studies to derive the challenges and patterns.</p><p>After identifying the need for the review, we specified the research questions (RQs), which are explained in Section 3.2. The process (review protocol) that we developed in the planning phase and then used to conduct this SLR study is outlined in Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>. The process starts with paper identification and selection (discussed in detail in Section 3.3). Then, we characterized the demographics of the included primary studies using the systematic mapping approach (detailed to be discussed in Section 3.4.1). Afterwards, we conducted the qualitative synthesis (details to be discussed in Section 3.4.2).</p><p>To further put this study in context, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref> positions this study with respect to the literature and IAC in which practitioners and researchers have been involved and reported their experiences from.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Goals and Research Questions</head><p>The goal of this study is to systematically review the state-of-the-art and practice in the area of IAC. The following research questions (RQs) are raised.</p><p>• RQ1 -Collaboration models: What type of IAC models have been proposed?</p><p>• RQ2 -Challenges/ impediments: Which challenges or impediments for IACs have been raised by the papers?</p><p>• RQ3 -Patterns (best practices): What patterns have been proposed for IACs?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Study Identification</head><p>Let us recall from our SLR process (Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>) that the first phase of our study is article selection. For this phase, we followed the following steps in order: Based on the SM and SLR guidelines <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>, to find relevant studies, we searched the following three major online search academic article search engines: (1) IEEE Xplore, (2) ACM Digital Library, and (3) Google Scholar. In addition to the formal published literature, the authors actually wanted to include the grey literature too, and to conduct a multi-vocal literature review (MLR), e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. But they were not able to find a minimum number of reasonable blog entries, or other grey sources on this subject. It seems that practitioners have not written much (or anything) on this topic.</p><p>In order to ensure that we included as many relevant studies as possible in the pool of selected studies, we identified potential search keywords regarding</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>the focus of each of our RQs. Using an iterative improvement process, we extracted four lists of search keywords as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>The first and second groups were about industry and academia. The third group is synonym terms conveying the concept of "collaboration". The last term is about the "software engineering" domain. The Cartesian product of the four sets resulted in 3 * 2 * 3 * 3 = 54 combinations which we searched for. In terms of the search time-window, the searches were conducted in January-February 2015 and thus only studies available in the above search engines by that time were included in our pool.</p><p>To decrease the risk of missing relevant studies, similar to previous SM and SLR studies, our search strategy also included forward and backward snowballing using the guidelines from <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>. For snowballing, we randomly picked five of the articles already in the pool and we randomly searched the articles citing them (forward snowballing) and cited from them (backward snowballing) to ensure that the relevant ones were also in our pool.</p><p>With the above search strings and search in specific venues, we found 49 studies which we considered as our initial pool of potentially-relevant primary studies (also depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>). At this stage, studies in the initial pool were ready for application of inclusion/exclusion criteria described next.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.2.">Inclusion and exclusion</head><p>In our study, the following inclusion criterion was considered: Does a given study present findings relevant for IAC in SE? The response to be picked by each of the three authors could be: 0='exclude', 1='uncertain', and 2='include'. Only studies written in English language and only the ones which were electronically available were included. If a conference study had a more recent journal version, only the latter was included. If multiple studies with the same title by the same author(s) were found, the most recent one was included and the rest were excluded.</p><p>To apply the inclusion/exclusion criteria to the initial pool, all three authors inspected the studies in the initial pool and assigned a vote based on the above scale to each study. We decided to use a threshold of four marks </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>for the decision on study exclusion, i.e., studies with cumulative votes of less than four marks were excluded. To vote on each study, we reviewed its title, abstract and keywords. If not enough information could be found in those sources, a more in-depth evaluation inside the paper text was conducted.</p><p>Based on the results of the joint voting, the size of the pool of selected studies decreased from 49 to 33. We discuss a few examples of the excluded papers.</p><p>The study <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> was in our initial paper but was excluded since its focus was not on industry-academia "collaborations", but rather on evaluating rigor and industrial relevance of industrial evaluations of SE techniques and approaches. Although the study reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> had a related title "Industry academia collaboration model: The design challenges", after reading and voting, it was excluded since ts focus was not on "research collaborations" but rather on "employability" of graduates, as the study was motived by the following need: "a need for industry-academia partnership has been strongly felt to enhance the employability of engineering graduate workforce and make them industry ready." Finally, as the third example, the study <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> was excluded since it provides messages and recommendations to Researchers active in the Requirements engineering community to connect to industry and it is not on industry-academia "collaborations" per se.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.3.">Final pool of primary studies and online repository</head><p>After the initial search and the follow-up analysis for exclusion of unrelated and inclusion of additional studies, the pool of selected studies was finalized with 33 studies. The final pool of selected studies has also been published in an online repository using the Google Docs system, and is publicly accessible online (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>). The classifications of each selected publication according to the classification scheme described in Section 3.4.1 are also available in the online repository.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Extraction and Analysis 3.4.1. Systematic Mapping</head><p>To develop our systematic map, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>, we analyzed the studies in the pool and identified the initial list of attributes. We then used attribute generalization and iterative refinement to derive the final map.</p><p>As studies were identified as relevant to our research project, we recorded them in a shared spreadsheet (hosted in the online Google Docs spreadsheet <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>) to facilitate further analysis. The following information was recorded for With the relevant studies identified and recorded, our next goal was to categorize the studies in order to begin building a complete picture of the subject area. Although we did not a-priori develop a categorization scheme for this project, we wanted to answer each of the study's RQs using the data to be stored in the systematic map.</p><p>We refined these broad interests into a systematic map using an iterative approach. The authors conducted an initial pass over the data, and based on (at least) the title, abstract and introduction of the studies, created a set of initial categories and assigned studies to those categories. When the assignment of studies to categories could not be clearly determined just based on the title, abstract and introduction, more of the study was considered. In this process, both the categories and the assignment of studies to categories were further refined.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> shows the final data extraction form (classification scheme) that we developed after applying the process described above. In the table, column 1 specifies whether the information to be extracted is for the purpose of characterizing the demographics of the included primary studies using the systematic mapping (SM) approach or to answer the study RQs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3)</ref>. Column 2 is the corresponding attribute/aspect. Column 3 is the set of all possible values for the attribute. Finally, column 4 indicates for an attribute whether multiple selections can be applied. For example, for the first row (Contribution type), the corresponding value in the last column is "M" (Multiple). It indicates that one study can contribute more than one type of options (e.g., method, tool, etc.). In contrast, for the row corresponding to research type, the corresponding value in the last column is "S" (Single), denoting that each primary study could only be mapped under one of the given types.</p><p>We utilized the following techniques to derive the list of categories for each attribute: attribute generalization, clustering and aggregation. If there were several items under the "Other" category which were the same and more than five instances, we grouped them to create new categories. We believe all of the categories in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> are self-explanatory and thus we do not discuss them one by one in the text.</p><p>To extract data, the studies in our pool were reviewed with the focus of each RQ and the required information was extracted. The data extraction phase was conducted collaboratively among the authors and data were recorded in the online spreadsheet <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. The data extracted by one author was peer reviewed by at least one other.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>To justify why a given mapping was done for a given primary study, we incorporated as much explicit "traceability" links between our mapping and the primary studies as possible, by explicit color-coding inside the paper PDF file, and also by placing comments inside the cells of the online repository <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows the screen-shot of color-coding according to our RQs inside the PDF file of one of the primary studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Such a color-coding scheme especially helped us in the peer review process by ensuring easy locating of the phrases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.2.">Synthesis and Coding (SLR)</head><p>For the RQs regarding collaboration challenges, and best practices (success patterns), our data extraction process yielded a large set of qualitative data for each of the above aspects. For example, for the "challenges" RQ, we extracted 209 single phrases (challenges) from the primary studies, e.g., "A common problem is that research solutions don't fit with present business and development methods" from the primary study <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. On the other hand, for best practices, our data pool included 430 single phrases, e.g., "Doing your homework [targeting researchers] and learning the domain establishes a com-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>: Color-coding of the phrases in the primary studies according to our RQs to ensure explicit traceability. The example screen-shot is from the primary study <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, Pink = challenges, Green = success criteria/best practices, Strike-through = anti-patterns, Yellow = SE topic areas and projects observed mon understanding and vocabulary" from the primary study <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. We had to choose suitable qualitative synthesis methods to synthesize such aspects, worded differently but meaning the same concept semantically, to ensure that our study would provide digestible and aggregated findings for the readers. For example, in our data collection for "challenges", our pool included the following two phrases: "there is a lack of well-trained requirements engineers" from the primary study <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and "Lack of RE (requirements engineering) Education" from <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>.</p><p>By reviewing the qualitative data analysis literature, the best methods we chose for this context was "coding" (from grounded theory) of the aspects in two abstraction levels, i.e., open codes and axial codes <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. We decided to not conduct 'selective' coding since it was at a high level of abstraction in our case, i.e., for "challenges", if we had to do selective coding, the code would be "challenges" itself (refer to a well-documented example by a social scientist in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>).</p><p>Coding is a widely-used approach in qualitative data analysis in social sciences and related disciplines. Glaser <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> described substantive (open) Lack of SE education coding as a way to "generate an emergent set of categories and their properties which fit, work and are relevant for integrating into a theory". Strauss and Corbin <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> defined open coding as "the process of breaking down, examining, comparing, conceptualizing, and categorizing data". Focusing in the qualitative SE literature, we reviewed several highly-cited papers and also a good guideline <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30]</ref>. Our synthesis method of choice related to coding was "thematic analysis" which we utilized in our extraction and synthesis process.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>Note that synthesis using the above approach was conducted to derive the aggregated sets of challenges and best practices (success patterns). We discuss next more details and a few examples of how we conducted the synthesis. Let us take the "challenges" as the example again. As discussed in the data extraction phase (the previous sub-section), there were many phrases in the primary studies which were worded differently but meant the same concept semantically. When we did the data extraction, we did one level of coding by applying the open coding. All authors independently conducted the open coding on two included papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31]</ref> and thereafter compared and discussed the coding results to align their understanding of the coding process. The remaining papers were coded independently by the authors.</p><p>Once we had all the open codes, each author conducted axial coding independently. We wanted to see how our team of three SE researchers would perform freely when asked to do axial coding independent from the other two researchers. In particular, the identification of higher level concepts from the open codes depend on the experience and interpretation of the researcher. Thus, conducting the coding independently and thereafter comparing and discussing the results leads to more reliable results, as suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Once the independent axial coding was finished, we then put our extracted codes (cluster) together and cross reviewed them. To our surprise, we noticed quite</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>different levels of abstractions on how each of the researchers had conducted axial coding, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>. Note that, intentionally and knowingly, in the first iteration, the researchers did not want to set (settle on) a uniform abstraction level for codes clustering. The rationale was to observe, in an explanatory fashion, what kind of results such an independent axial coding approach would yield.</p><p>As we can see in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>, without setting a uniform abstraction level for codes clustering, the three researchers conducted the clustering quite differently in terms of abstraction levels, i.e., while the researcher #1 (labeled anonymously) created 37 clusters for the "challenges" aspect and distributed the papers under those clusters, researcher #2 and #3 developed 24 and 10 clusters, respectively. With no predefined granularity, we made no prior decision regarding the level of detail worth coding. As a result, we produced codes on different levels of detail (e.g., coarse ones such as "communicationrelated issues" and finer ones such as "Gathering developer opinions"), which were difficult to delineate against one another subsequently. The exact same challenge has been reported in grounded theory in general (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>), and in a SE-related qualitative study of pair programming <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, in which the authors used coding and grounded theory for qualitative analysis of pair programming and faced certain challenges when researchers had no predefined granularity for coding.</p><p>On the other hand, similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, the other challenge that we also experienced was regarding having no predefined level of acceptable subjectivity. As defined in the grounded theory procedures (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>), the nature of the chosen codes can be anywhere on the spectrum, ranging from codes that reflect observations that any observer could agree with to codes that interpret the observation to a degree that could be called 'wishful thinking'. Grounded theory as such does not provide a criterion for deciding where "grounded in data" ends and wishful thinking begins. As a consequence, in our first iteration, we noticed that the three researchers mixed objective-descriptive and subjective-evaluative attitudes for selecting codes. This led to codes of different nature (e.g., descriptive ones such as "Stability of the organization" and assumption-bearing ones such as "Resistance to change") existing side-byside, which made it harder to decide which code to use in a particular case. As a result, after the first round of axial coding, to minimize subjectivity, we decided to set the level of acceptable subjectivity, to be followed by all three researchers, to "objective-descriptive".</p><p>In summary, by utilizing the foundations of the grounded theory (e.g., [26, </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T 27]</formula><p>) and useful heuristics and the coding-scheme development methodology from the SE-related qualitative study of pair programming <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, we developed our qualitative synthesis and coding approach as reported above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results</head><p>We first present the study demographics. Thereafter, the identified collaboration models are presented (RQ1). The results of RQ2 and RQ3 (challenges and best practices, respectively) are presented thereafter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Study demographics (Systematic mapping)</head><p>Author affiliation: Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref> shows the ratio of authors from academia (employment with a university or research institute), industry (employment with a company), and joint authorships (authors from both industry and academia authoring a paper together). Around half of the papers were written by academia authors only (17 papers). It is positive to see that the other half (15 papers) was written collaboratively with industry practitioners, thus incorporating both perspectives. Only a single study has been reported by authors from industry.</p><p>Knowledge areas researched in the collaborations: In order to answer which SE areas have been discussed the most in the papers, we used the 15 knowledge areas (KAs) proposed in the Software Engineering Body of Knowledge (SWEBOK) version 3.0 <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> as a reference. Topics of the collaboration projects in the papers were identified and classified by one author to the KAs and was peer reviewed by another author. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8</ref> depicts the SWEBOK KAs covered by the papers and the number of the papers that discuss projects from each KA. Papers discussing collaborative projects related to software testing (7 papers), requirements (6 papers) and models and methods (6 papers) are the majority. The least frequently KAs addressed by the project topics were SE economics (one paper) and maintenance (one paper). There were 13 papers that were generic and did not discuss projects in the context of any of the KAs.</p><p>Types of contributions: The frequencies of the number of studies by different contribution facets are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9</ref>. As the frequencies data of Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9</ref> depict, all of the 33 papers reported guidelines (also referred to as recommendations, patterns, and success factors, in this study).</p><p>Seven papers contributed collaboration models, to be reviewed in Section 4.3. We defined "collaboration model as a (semi-) formal specification of   <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36]</ref> is an example of such a model.</p><p>Two papers discussed methods (techniques). To bridge the gap among academics and practitioners in non-functional requirements, the authors of <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> recommended using "situational method engineering" <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> to provide customizable solutions and techniques. Kaindl et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> suggested using an approach called "problem frames" <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>, which they believe is promising to classifying, analyzing and structuring software development challenges of the industry partners.</p><p>Two papers contributed processes. The technology transfer model proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> was accompanied by a process-driven approach. Kaindl et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> described a process, which evolves research results from "less applied" to "more applied" to "ready for prime time".</p><p>Four papers contributed empirical studies in this context. Petersen and Engström <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> used an interview-based study to develop a taxonomy to be used for finding relevant research solutions for practical problems. Rombach et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> follows a systematic case-study approach. Martínez-Fernández and Marques <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> used the "focus group" approach, which is considered a suitable technique to obtain the perception of a group of selected people on a defined area of interest. The authors of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> reflected on their experiences based on the success factors for IAC in the context of several empirical studies that they had conducted as part of a collaboration with industrial partners in the area of software product lines.</p><p>Five other papers made "other" contribution. Connor et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> presented design and delivery of a Masters course in software Requirements Engineering (RE) that was designed to overcome some of the issues that have caused the research-practice gap. Ostweil et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> determined the impact of software engineering research on practice. Wohlin <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> specifically presented the Top 10 challenges of Empirical software engineering research with industry. Petersen and Engström <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> presented a taxonomy and how to use it to bridge the communication gap between industry and academia. Morris et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> presented a dependency chain of research results.</p><p>Research types: In a different classification, we mapped studies by their research facet (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). The results are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">10</ref>. As can see in the frequencies data, a majority 72% (24 of 33) of the studies are experience reports, i.e., a team of authors being involved in IAC have presented their experience. Apart from the 24 experience reports, in terms</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>of maturity (level) of research approaches, we classified the remaining papers as follows: six papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref> under empirical studies, three opinion papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49]</ref>, and no philosophical papers.</p><p>Here are some examples of how the above classifications were done. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> was classified under opinion papers since "The paper summarizes, clarifies and extends the results of two panel discussions, one at the Twelfth Conference on Advanced information Systems Engineering (CAiSE00) and the other at the Fourth IEEE Conference on Requirements Engineering (ICRE00)". Only a small ratio (5 out of 33) are rigorous empirical studies on IACs, i.e., <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41]</ref>. For example, Ostweil et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> conducted a narrative (informal) meta-analysis of several studies in SE sub-areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Scale of empirical evidence/experience</head><p>With regard to scale/experience of evidence, we captured the number of research projects reported, the number of industry partners involved, and the time duration of the reported experience/results in years. For all three variables, only a subset of papers provided the information.</p><p>With regard to the number of research projects (see Figure <ref type="figure">11</ref>), it is evident that the majority of papers only reported on a small number of research projects in the range between one and five projects, with the clear majority reporting experiences from only one project (7 of 17 papers providing information about the number of projects).</p><p>Only 13 papers reported the number of industry partners involved (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">12</ref>), the figure reports the number of partners at least involved in the research collaboration between industry and academia. For example, in one   study <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref> the authors mention that 12 large companies and many small have been involved. In most cases only a few industry partners were involved. One case <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> stands out with an involvement of 30 industry partners. Out of 33 papers, 12 papers reported the length of the collaborations (Figure <ref type="figure">13</ref>). It is interesting to observe that several longitudinal experiences have been reported. Seven papers reported experiences from joint research work with industry of at least 10 years.</p><p>Thus, in summary, we highlight once again that the primary studies in our pool are mostly experience reports (24 out of 33) and opinion papers (4 out of 33). Only a small ratio (5 out of 33) are rigorous empirical studies on IACs. Thus, the primary studies have a different strength of evidence associated with them than more traditional academic papers. Hence, it is fair to say that most of the primary studies do not always reflect ground truth that can be validated by rigorous evidence. As a result, their statements need to be taken and synthesized with caution. Thus, in the rest of this SLR, when we extract and synthesize the challenges and best practices, as a critical reflection and assumption, we do not differentiate the level of reported evidence in different studies. Based on the scale of empirical evidence/experience in each paper, as quantified by research facet types, number of research projects, number of industrial partners, and time duration of the reported experience, and as extracted by our SLR, one can assess how strongly the statements in each of the primary studies are supported by evidence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">RQ1 -Collaboration models</head><p>As discussed in Section 4.1 (systematic mapping of studies), five papers contributed collaboration models, which we briefly review next. Gorschek et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> presented a technology transfer model, comprising on the following seven steps:</p><p>• Identify potential improvement areas based on industry needs, through process assessment and observation activities.</p><p>• Formulate a research agenda using several assessments to find research topics, and formulate problem statements while studying the field and the domain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>• Formulate a candidate solution in cooperation with industry.</p><p>• Conduct lab validation (for example, through lab experiments).</p><p>• Perform static validation (for example, interviews and seminars).</p><p>• Perform dynamic validation (for example, pilot projects and controlled small tests).</p><p>• Release the solution step by step, while remaining open to smaller changes and additions.</p><p>The work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref> presented a collaboration model for industry-academia collaborative practice research which includes 10 factors for ensuring success and 10 action principles for collaboration management.</p><p>The work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> adopted the idea of "Reflective Systems Development (RSD)" <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref> from the information systems (IS) community to IAC. The authors mentioned that the sharing of world-views required to ensure that such collaboration is successful is dependent on effective communication and the development of a shared world view, which is realized by using RSD.</p><p>The work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> discussed a spiral model for innovation-based industrial development developed in and used by the Fraunhofer Institute for Experimental Software Engineering (IESE) in Germany.</p><p>Last but not the least, Runeson and Minör <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref> presented an "architectural" model for IACs, inspired by Kruchten's software architecture model. The model has four views: time, space, activity and domain, which correspond to the four questions/aspects of IAC: when, where, how and what.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">RQs 2 and 3: Challenges and best practices</head><p>We present and organize the challenges and best practices of IACs along the lifecycle of IAC. Furthermore, since challenges and best practices are related, i.e., a best practice is utilized to address a given challenge, we present them together and answer both RQs 2 and 3 jointly. The life-cycle has been inspired by the work of Ankrah and Omar <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> (see the conceptual process framework for IAC in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>). The life-cycle perspective determines where in the collaboration process a given challenge or pattern will have the main impact. This indicates where corrective actions have to be taken. Challenges should be addressed as early as possible. The mapping to the life-cycle is done for each challenge, and pattern. The lifecycle phases are defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>• Problem formulation (F): During the formulation stage, the problem has to be properly discussed and understood by both sides, and a topic should be selected to collaborate on (interesting to both sides), and contracting (agreement of collaboration)-related activities should be conducted.</p><p>• Planning (P) The planning activity comprises of defining specific research objectives, and time planning.</p><p>• Operationalization (O): The operationalization comprises of activities where the actual work on the research takes place (conducting case studies, training, etc.).</p><p>• Transfer and Dissemination (T): In the transfer and dissemination phase, the results developed during and obtained by the research are applied in the organization and paper publications take place. In writing papers, special attention should be made regarding IP protection and confidentiality of industry partners business and technical data.</p><p>The complete overview of challenges and best practices identified are provided in Tables A. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> and B.7. The synthesis resulted in 10 categories/themes of challenges identified through synthesis using open and axial coding. Below each axial code (e.g. mismatch between industry and academia) the list of detailed open codes related to each theme is presented. The number of studies and the related references for each open code are also stated. Which lifecycle phase each open code belongs to is specified (F, P, O, and T). In a few cases more than one phase is concerned. Tables A. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> and B.7 also show that a variety of codes were related to the end-to-end process, denoting that they are not specific to a particular phase.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.1.">Problem Formulation</head><p>Challenges: With regard to the problem formulation, 12 challenges have been reported (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">A</ref>.6): C02, C05, C18, C20, C22, C23, C25, C34, C53, C53, C61 and C63. The challenge of not understanding the industry problems (C02) becomes a hinder for starting the collaboration. As pointed out by Runeson <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref>, it is not possible to push the solution to the industry as often the solutions do not fit into the industry context <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, or are not scalable <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, the differences in objectives <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51]</ref> (C22), reward systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref> (C25), and what is perceived as useful (C23) hinder to</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T establish collaborations. For example, Glass and Hunt <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref> point out that only few researchers would be interested in doing the development ("D") of R&amp;D. With regard to rewards, it was pointed out that academia does not value industry impact and that there is no academic reward for industry collaborations and success <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45]</ref>. The perception of what is useful becomes apparent in different ways, for example giving low priority to postgraduate studies from the industry perspective <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref> and the lack of consideration of human factors in academic research <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref> (e.g., neglecting the fact that software development is conducted by humans). As a consequence, the initiation of IAC projects is usually challenging.</p><p>After having decided to collaborate, it is difficult to manage intellectual property rights early on (C60 and C61). Runeson <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref> points out that legal departments are not experienced in contracting for research. The consideration of what-if scenarios in contracts also takes a considerable effort <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref>.</p><p>Best practices: During the formulation of the research collaboration, buy-in and support from industry collaborators need to be encouraged and obtained <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref> (BP20). Different stakeholders need to commit, in particular company management is of importance <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>. An important means to gain commitment is the ability to communicate well in early meetings (BP18), the most frequently mentioned best practice.</p><p>Further suggestions have been made to get commitment. 'Proper' topic selection (BP19) is of importance early in the process <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref> and topics need to be prioritized <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. To choose a topic of interest, the problems of the companies have to be well understood. Kaindl et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> suggests to use a systematic method for this purpose, call the problem frame approach (BP30).</p><p>Glass and Hunt <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref> suggests to find out why theories succeed or fail in industry projects. Deep investigations of the problem area should be undertaken <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref> to understand potential reasons for companies to participate <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>.</p><p>Additionally, it helps to be able to refer to prior experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref> (BP9) and present replicated results that were successful across projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref> as well as success stories <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>.</p><p>After having been successful to obtain commitment and deciding to collaborate, contractual concerns are apparent, namely intellectual property rights, project management <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53]</ref> and the status/role of the researcher. With regard to property rights, it is recommended to be flexible and have simple management <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(BP86). It was recommended in multiple sources to</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>employ the researcher (e.g. full employment <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, internships <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55]</ref>, or at least part-time <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref>) (BP87).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key findings (most frequently given suggestions):</head><p>i) The most common challenges during problem formulation are the differences between industry and academia in terms of time horizons, objectives, reward systems and perceptions of what is useful.</p><p>ii) The frequently-mentioned suggestions for addressing the mismatch and to get commitment are proper presentation and communication, and topic selection.</p><p>iii) Invest in order to understand the problems of industry to gain their commitment using systematic research approaches (should be done by both sides).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.2.">Planning</head><p>Challenges: During the planning phase, several challenges have been reported (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">A</ref>.6). We discuss the major ones (discussed in more than one papers) below.</p><p>With regard to the research method, it is challenging to incorporate change (C07) into and running flexible research projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>.</p><p>The differences in time horizons (C21) make planning and agreeing on a schedule for the research project challenging. Long-term goals of research (solving a challenging research problem) often do not align well with shortterm goals of the companies <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">66,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">64]</ref>, i.e. industry and academia have different time horizons. Long time investments into research also make the research project a risky endeavor <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>. The overall long time required to transfer may lead to a failure of the research project <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref>. With regard to planning, it was observed that, in practice, industry deadlines override academic interest <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>.</p><p>Besides the planning of the time-line, projects in general require clear goals. Setting goals for research projects with academia and industry was reported as challenging (C48), industry-academia research projects lack clear directions <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref> (C26). In research, there is no guarantee for success of improvements <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>, while success is a requirement for companies to collaborate</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53]</ref>. That is, there is a conflict in the goal definition between the two sides.</p><p>Best practices: With regard to planning, general recommendations are to plan ahead of time (BP102), and to assure careful planning and nurturing of the research project <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60]</ref>. A conscious choice for an effective model for research collaboration should be made <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref> (see Section 4.3 for the different models proposed).</p><p>The goal should be to make long-term commitments (BP17) and funding <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">63,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref> while applying short-term goals mixed with long-term goals <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. Long-term commitments imply that a high degree of commitment from the partners are needed <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref>.</p><p>The commitments made shall be based on common objectives between industry and academia <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42]</ref> (BP45) and an early agreement on mutual goals and roles in the project shall be achieved <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>. Besides agreeing on common objectives, also the right time for starting the collaboration has to be considered <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref> (BP52), in particular both parties have to be aware of their time horizons when agreeing on the planning <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>.</p><p>When deciding who to involve in the project, the industry partners should be actively <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> involved and provide relevant and best-in-class employees (e.g., best testers) to give input to research <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref> (BP54). With regard to the involvement of researchers, it was emphasized that researchers should be involved beyond research activities <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref>, for example they should be encouraged to also participate in development <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(BP53).</head><p>A part of planning is also to choose the principle research methodology to use (BP66-BP73). The most frequently recommended research method was case study research <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key findings (most frequently given suggestions):</head><p>i) The difference in time horizon is the most generic challenge observed (more than one quarter of all included studies refer to the challenge)</p><p>ii) Other common challenges are limitations in planning to achieve high validity of the results and the challenge to achieve clear and realistic ambitions and goals in projects.</p><p>iii) To address i) and ii) common objectives and a common understanding have to be achieved, e.g. related to an awareness of different</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T time horizons.</formula><p>iv) The most common research method suggested to consider in planning was case study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.3.">Operationalization</head><p>Challenges: Multiple challenges arise with regard to the research method during the conduct of the research (C06, ..., C10). The challenges reported were context dependence and lack of generalizability <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> (also internally in the company when using pilot studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>), lack of control in the industrial environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">66]</ref>, lack of the ability to create repeatable results <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> and bias and subjectivity of the researcher <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. The technology transfer process itself has been highlighted as a validity threat <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref>. This may be explained by the fact that the quality of evidence is not as important to practitioners <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, hence affecting the research and quality of data available to the researcher.</p><p>As the goal of research is to lead to practical improvements, practitioners require certain set of skills to work with research solutions (C11, ..., C15). However, this is a hinder as it is difficult and costly to train practitioners <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> (C43). Overall, lack of willingness to high investment in time and effort (C49), and the lack of resources available (C56, ..., C59) have been highlighted, both for operationalization <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">66,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42]</ref> and transfer <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57]</ref>. Companies also have to fight for resources internally <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref> hampering the ability to collect data <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. The shortage of time is not one-sided, also there is a lack of resources on the academic side <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref>.</p><p>Confidentiality and privacy are also hinders in publishing due to restrictions in disclosure <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref> and were highlighted as too stringent <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>. The access to data is another concern <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref> (C60).</p><p>Confidentiality and privacy are also hinders in publishing due to restrictions in disclosure <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref> and were highlighted as too stringent <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>. The access to data is another concern <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(C60).</head><p>Best practices: There is a general need to conduct more empirical studies in industry <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> and place more emphasis on evaluating solutions in realistic contexts <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref>. In the literature, we identified various practices which were suggested to realize industry-based studies.</p><p>An important basis for designing a useful solution for industry practice is to understand industry problems and to have the willingness to base the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>research on these problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">64,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">63,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56]</ref> (BP29). Industry needs and problems have to be actively elicited <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51]</ref> by being in close contact with the industry and to monitor needs <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45]</ref>. As part of the active elicitation is to have practitioners explain their projects and challenges <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. From a research perspective it is of importance that the problems are non-trivial <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>.</p><p>When collaborating with industry benefits for the organization have to become visible during the research (operationalization) and the solution transfer to practice <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">65,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50]</ref>. Stakeholders, such as the developers, have to be satisfied <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref>. As pointed out by Raschke et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> early success needs to be delivered for a continued collaboration. When no solution is transferred attractive and interesting knowledge for the practitioners should be produced that is valuable for both parties <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">66]</ref>.</p><p>More concretely, the following criteria important for a solution transferred to industry should be demonstrated:</p><p>• Sustainability: Solution is valid over a prolonged period of time <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>.</p><p>• Adaptability/customizability/evolvability: Solution can be tailored and is easy to evolve depending on the contexts <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">65,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57]</ref>.</p><p>• Scalability: Solution scales to the complexity of problems observed in industry <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref>.</p><p>• Portability: Design alternative scenarios of how to use the solution <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>.</p><p>• Simplicity: Provide a simple and elegant solution <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>.</p><p>• Usability: The solution should be simple to use <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>.</p><p>• Credibility: The solution should be mature and have credibility with regard to its usefulness <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51]</ref> After having defined the problem, a solution has to be developed. With regard to the solution design, multiple studies suggest to evaluate the solution in the laboratory before taking them to industry practice <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42]</ref> (BP118). Thereafter, they should be evaluated in the industry environment (also referred to as dynamic validation) in a controlled setting <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>, for example, in pilot projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> (BP119). For solutions to become useful in industry, tool support (at least prototypes) is often needed <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67]</ref> (BP121). During the solution design, the importance of the user interface design was</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>highlighted <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67]</ref>. User interfaces should have a familiar look to practitioners, resembling the look and feel of the interfaces they are used to in their practical work <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref>. Such expectations seems to indicate that, in some cases, once an IAC project is finished, industry wants to see an industry-strength product out of the project instead of a research prototype. While such an expectation may not be very realistic given the constraints of the university research teams, we have seen in our own IAC projects that such tools can be developed jointly by both sides <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[68]</ref>.</p><p>During the design and evaluation of the solution, it is also important that researchers and practitioners work as a team <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31]</ref> (BP51) with the mindset of collaborating to improve a situation rather than transferring a research solution <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref>. Thereby, multiple stakeholders from industry across department boundaries should be involved <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>. During the collaboration, the roles should change (BP53), while in the beginning the researcher drives the application of the solution, the practitioners need to take more active roles over time <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>.</p><p>Working as a team requires the researchers' on-site presence in the company <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60</ref>] (BP61). The visibility of the researcher is important <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60]</ref>. Martínez-Fernández and Marques <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> suggests regular presence with one day per week, while Runeson <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref> considers this too infrequent, suggesting several days per week. On-site, the practitioners should provide access to employees and managers <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> and assure an easy access to the researcher <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> (BP62). Also, access to real-world data (e.g. defect databases, depending on the research question) needs to be given <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. The researcher, on the other hand, should actively participate beyond the research projects and discussion <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57]</ref>, e.g., social events in the company (BP63).</p><p>From the perspective of research method, it is recommended to utilize established data collection methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> (e.g. to conduct semi-structured interviews <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>) and to follow scientific guidelines <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> (such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[69]</ref> for case studies and <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref> for experiments) (BP66-BP73). Data should be collected face-to-face whenever possible <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref> (e.g. using interviews rather than paper version questionnaires <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>). Different types of data need to be collected (quantitative as well as qualitative, data triangulation) <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref>.</p><p>During the interpretation of the research results, it is important to be aware of the influence of context as a confounding factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60]</ref>. Thus, it is important to make conscious decisions to tailor research results to the context <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref> and to be aware of constraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref>. To</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>increase the validity and awareness for context influence, it is suggested to switch contexts <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> by leveraging on internal and external units for analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref> and to investigate multiple cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key findings (most frequently given suggestions):</head><p>i) The most frequently mentioned challenge is the lack of resources available from industry and academia side (25% of all included studies).</p><p>ii) Validity concerns need to be addressed when industry is involved.</p><p>iii) Four recommendations for the operational phase stand out. Approximately 50% of all studies recommend to base solutions based on real-world problems observed in industry. The key benefits need to be shown and demonstrated to the industry partner. The researcher should also be co-located at the company and have regular presence.</p><p>iv) Also, specific quality attributes of a solution have been identified that should be fulfilled, most commonly customizability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.4.">Transfer and dissemination</head><p>Challenges: We can notice a lot of challenges categorized under the 'T' phase in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">A</ref>.6 almost under all the challenge categorizes. For example, the difficulty to work with the research solution will remain a challenge during the transfer and dissemination of findings to the industry partner (C10). Sometimes, results produced by research are not exploitable, since they are too abstract for example (C03). Research (e.g., in pilots) is often limited to scale (C29), and in many cases, 'toy' examples are utilized initially <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. Also, the complexity of industrial systems and technologies can be quite substantial, which also is a challenge for the transfer <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref>. There are of loss of champions in projects, e.g,. due to staff turnover, or that champions may simply leave the company and thus, dissemination will be hard without the initial dedicated champion (C54). Furthermore, to conduct transfer and dissemination, time and effort investments are needed <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(C56).</head><p>Best practices: The transfer can only be successful if benefits are</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>achieved with regard to the measures discussed for the operationalization earlier (see BP40 and BP41 in Table <ref type="table">B</ref>.7). To determine the overall success of the transfer, a measurement program should be defined <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref> (BP112) to be able to objectively measure and compare 'before' and 'after' cases. As an overall measurement, return on investment (ROI) should be captured <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41]</ref> (BP112).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key findings (most frequently given suggestions):</head><p>i) The main hindrances in transfer are when research results are not demonstrated on an industrial scale, and there is a lack of availability of time to conduct the transfer.</p><p>ii) Practices important during operationalization are also important for technology transfer, in particular the ability to demonstrate benefits and achieving the important quality attributes mentioned earlier.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.5.">Complete life-cycle</head><p>Challenges: The end-to-end category contains the largest number of challenges (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">A</ref> <ref type="bibr">.6)</ref>. The challenges under category will affect all phase (activities) in the IAC life-cycle (Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>). For example, if research results are not relevant for practice (C01), the companies may reject them early on, or realize at a later stage that a transfer is not possible. On the other hand, if the objectives of academia and industry are different (C22), this will be a major obstacle during the inception of a IAC project.</p><p>Furthermore, specific skills and experiences are relevant and a challenge for collaboration <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37]</ref> (C12 and C15). If the researchers have deficiencies in practical software engineering education <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> (C11), it will hamper them to have informed communication with practitioners <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Also, if the researcher has deficiencies of the company context <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> (C14), it may be challenging to communicate the relevant information to initiate a project, and to find a research solution fitting the context, and hence benefiting the company.</p><p>The differences between industry and academia also become an end-toend challenge. Communication gaps between industry and academia are a common challenge <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>, while communication has to take place endto-end and continuously. The difference in terminology (C24) is a reason for <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref>. The lack of a common vocabulary makes a the learning of the context challenging. A root-cause for for terminology problems are the lack of standard terminologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> and the lack of consensus on terminologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref>. Besides using different terminologies practitioners and researchers also use different communication channels <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> (e.g., industry conferences versus academic conferences and proceedings, as well as journals). Different cultures have been highlighted as another difference <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref>. A concrete example is the unwillingness to disclose weaknesses and improvements in industry, while this willingness exists, to some extent, in academia <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>, for example in the form of discussing validity threats to research. Research and academia value empirical evidence differently <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55]</ref> (C28). In academia, the strength of evidence is valued highly, while industry values local opinions (what works in the company) more than empirical evidence <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref>. Consequently, it is challenging to find an acceptable level of rigor in industrial studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>. This will manifest itself in the problem formulation and planning (negotiation of commitments from industry to provide access to data to achieve rigor), as well as the operationalization (the actual access and quality of data provided).</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T communication gaps</formula><p>The drop of interest in early and late phases of the life-cycle hampers the collaboration (C16, ..., C20). Multiple causes for the drop of interest have been reported, strongly related to human and organizational factors, namely the company 'inertia' preventing the use and acceptance of new methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67]</ref> (C19), the unwillingness to admit the need for external collaboration to address a challenge <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>, and the "Not invented here" syndrome <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>. From an organizational perspective, an inflexible organizational structure hampers to utilize and develop innovative solutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>.</p><p>Whenever collaborating, trust and respect are challenging and take time to establish <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61]</ref> (C62) and once there are issues, they are hard to fix (undo). These have an effect on how to define contractual and privacy concerns regarding access to data.</p><p>Best practices: During the whole process of collaboration, it is important for researchers and practitioners to share knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref> (BP6). Various ways of achieving this have been proposed. Overall, it is important to inform companies what is happening in research <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53]</ref>. On an institutional level, authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">66]</ref> suggest to companies to make better use of the competencies of university researchers. Ties between industry and academia can be built by enrolling people from industry in academia, involving industrial lectures, and formulating thesis topics together with industry <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref>. With re-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>gard to research collaboration, regular meetings and workshops (BP1) aid in knowledge exchange. Different ways of organizing those have been proposed, such as regular meetings and discussions <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54]</ref>, workshops and seminars <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">63]</ref>, communication networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>, and public presentations as well as posters <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. Further ways of dissemination are blogs <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, reports and publications, training through tutorials and demo applications, and industry-tailored reports <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, and tool-based collaboration platforms <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>.</p><p>From a content perspective, researcher should ensure to share research results frequently during the IAC (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56]</ref>) and also the state of the art (existing techniques and findings) <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. Petersen and Engström <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> suggest to describe context, objective, desired effect, and scope of challenges and solutions to enable communication and knowledge sharing.</p><p>Overall, since communication in IAC is challenging due to a different use of terminologies in industry versus academia (C24), it is important to build a common vocabulary <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">64,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref> (BP5), e.g. in the form of taxonomies <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref> and through standards <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. Another means for improving communication is the use of examples <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref> (BP7) for both challenges and solutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>. Knowledge sharing is further facilitated by a good communication ability <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. The need for communication and social skills (BP4) has been highlighted by various studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55]</ref>. To assure effective communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref>, it has been suggested to improve the communication between technical and business people <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>.</p><p>Knowledge transfer should be complemented by training of researchers and practitioners <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51</ref>] (BP2). A prerequisite for successful collaboration are well-trained software engineers <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>. Furthermore, expertise in relation to project and people management is also essential <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>. Here, prior experience of IAC helps to ease the collaboration <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref>.</p><p>Collaboration requires commitment across the project life-cycle. Management commitment needs to be ensured <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>, in particular top management needs to be on board <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42]</ref>. To achieve management buy-in, convincing success stories are needed <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>. Solutions need to be presented in a way suited for upper management <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>. Also, the developers who should be part of studies need to be committed <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref>.</p><p>To get access, contacts and commitment, a champion is needed (BP16). The importance of an insider committed to the project has been frequently highlighted (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42]</ref>). A good champion is charismatic <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, has a network within the company <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref>, and must have a sincere</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>interest in the project and collaboration <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>, and discusses the project benefits with project managers in the company <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>. Companies should help in finding a good champion <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50]</ref>.</p><p>The researcher should take the responsibility for the research life-cycle <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref> (BP21) and commit resources to manage the relationship to the company <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>.</p><p>Researchers and practitioners should have mutual respect and appreciation for each other <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref> (BP46) and understand as well as resolve differences in perspectives <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45]</ref>. It is important to interact in a friendly manner <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> appreciating each others' strengths <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref> and competencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> (BP47 and BP48).</p><p>The research project should be managed in an Agile fashion <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">65]</ref>. This comprises of multiple ways enabling agility in research projects with industry (sorted by frequency of mention).</p><p>• Iterative research process <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref> • Incremental and graduate delivery of results instead of big-bang <ref type="bibr">[62, 50,</ref> </p><p>• Flexibility with regard to the solution <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> (modification based on industry need)</p><p>• Flexibility with regard to the researchers' interest <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref> • Define short-term objectives <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref> • Organizational structure in the organization should support agility <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref> • Run smaller projects <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref> • Flexibility for coordination <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> • Flexibility in research proposals <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> From a managerial point of view, risks have to be managed (BP56-BP60). The organizational structure should enable flexibility as mentioned above <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>, though one should be aware of the risk of a lack of organizational stability <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref> (e.g. leading to loss of champions). The lack of resources should be factored in as a risk for achieving rigorous research <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref>. Furthermore, management overhead should be avoided by decreasing overhead in administrative activities <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>, also referred to as "Lean research" <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>. To support management, it is recommended to establish a measurement program <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> and to formulate concise and measurable objectives <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>Key findings (most frequently given suggestions):</p><p>i) The main challenge from the overall lifecycle perspective is the lack of relevance of research for practice.</p><p>ii) The most frequently mentioned practices (at least 25% of all included studies) to be successful in the overall end to end process were to run regular workshops and seminars, ensure management engagement, the need for champions, and to conduct the IAC in an agile way.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.6.">Mapping of best practices to challenges</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">5</ref> shows the mapping of the challenges to the practices illustrating which practice is useful in addressing a challenge. Only in a few instances, the literature made an explicit link stating that a particular challenge leads to a specific benefit of addressing a challenge. If an explicit link was made in the literature, this is indicated by the reference to the study making the link in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">5</ref>. Results produced through research are not relevant for practice BP17: Make long-term commitments <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>; BP62: Provide easy and frequent access for the researchers (makes solutions pragmatic and realistic <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>); BP51: Work in (as) a team (collaboration leads to dissemination and transfer <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>); BP66: Use case study method (leads to useful generally applicable results <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>); BP119: Pilot the solution with industry practitioners <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C02</head><p>Researchers do not understand the relevant problems from an industry point of view BP7: Run workshops and seminars (gives access to industry relevant problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref>);</p><p>Category: Lack of training, experience, and skills C11 Deficiencies in software engineering education BP17: Make long-term commitments (industry becomes willing to get involved in education <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref>; BP51: Work in (as) a team (collaborative approach transfers knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref>); BP66: Use case study method (case studies are useful for spreading knowledge and experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>); Continued on the next page... </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T Missing trust and respect BP5: Establish common and simple terminology (vocabulary) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>; BP40: Show benefits of the research solution for the industrial partner (valuable solutions make the industry open up <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[67]</ref>); BP51: Work in (as) a team [when done long enough builds relations and trusts <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>; BP77: Personally interact with the practitioners during data collection <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Discussion</head><p>We discuss next a summary of the systematic mapping and review results, the implications of those results, and the limitations and potential threats to the validity of the study.</p><p>Looking at the demographics of the studies included, multiple research gaps could be identified providing pointers for further work.</p><p>Software testing (discussed in 7 papers) and software requirements (in 6 papers) were the most popular, while SE economics (one paper) and maintenance (one paper) were the least mentioned. We suggest the community to initiate and report more IAC projects in the latter topics. There is a need for more processes and techniques to facilitate IAC in SE. While there are a handful number of empirical studies in IAC, there is a need for more work in this area, as the majority of papers were experience reports. The scale of empirical evidence/experience seems reasonable at the current state. However, we encourage further and larger scale IAC's. Given that in many cases individual projects and companies were part of the IAC, retrospective synthesis proved useful given that the findings would otherwise only be considered for a specific context. Five papers contributed collaboration models:</p><p>• A 7-step technology transfer model <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> • An Agile research collaboration model <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref> • Adaptation of the "Reflective Systems Development (RSD)" model from the information systems (IS) community in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> • A spiral model for innovation-based industrial development <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> • An "architectural" model for IAC <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>, inspired by a software architecture model</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>The empirical basis of all the above five models were based on experience papers. It would be interesting to empirically utilize the above models in IAC projects and report evidence, success and challenges in using those models.</p><p>It was also noteworthy that, from a reporting perspective, only a subset of studies explicitly reported the number of projects, the duration of the collaboration, and the number of industry partners. However, this is of importance to be reported in experience reports so that it can be later used to assess and compare the collaboration approaches.</p><p>We synthesized the findings of the literature with regard to challenges and best practices.</p><p>Practitioners and researchers can go into the phases of IAC and determine which challenges they are likely to face (risk management) and may utilize the inventory of best practices for the planning of their collaboration. However, the linkage to the success is not yet explicit. That is, we do not know, based on empirical evidence, which best practices contribute strongly to the success of IAC.</p><p>Technical research papers, as results of IAC, generally do not describe the context of the research project or the history of IAC when reporting the technical results. As an example case of a very small ratio of papers which do describe the context of the research project and IAC, is <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">73]</ref> which was a successful empirical IAC research project that provided details on IAC context in their studies. <ref type="bibr">Damm [73]</ref> worked in collaboration with industry and succeeded in transferring an outcome of the research (fault-slip through <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72]</ref>) to industry. In fact, the outcome became an industry-wide standard for Ericsson, which is a Fortune-500 company. This was achieved in the time frame of early 2003 to late 2006. All the mapped best practices were frequently mentioned, which is an early indicator for the importance of these factors for a successful IAC. Though, further research and data points are needed. Thus, future efforts need to be placed on studying the practices utilized in past collaborations, and relating them to success.</p><p>With regard to the relationships between challenges and best practices, we found that the link between specific challenges and best practices was not made explicit in many cases. In Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">5</ref> we mapped the challenges to practices only when the link was grounded in the data. Though, one could argue that many more links exist. For example, one may argue that the deficiencies in skills of practitioners to work with research solutions may be addressed by providing examples of challenges and solutions, highlighting the need for continuous learning on both sides, effective communication, creating</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T user documentation, etc. Though, to what degree the issue is addressed is not explicit. Thus, explicitly linking and investigating which challenges can be best addressed by specific practices should be investigated. Given that we do not have sufficient data, many combinations of practice-challenges mappings are possible. The combinations that seem reasonable could be formulated as a research hypotheses to be tested. For example, to address deficiencies in skills of practitioners, examples are more cost-efficient and useful than user documentation, etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Limitations and threats to validity</head><p>Potential threats to the validity of our study and the steps that we have taken to minimize or mitigate them are discussed in this section. The potential threats are discussed in the context of the four types of threats to validity based on a standard checklist for validity threats presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref>: internal validity, construct validity, conclusion validity and external validity. In dealing and minimizing the potential threats to validity, we have also benefited from our experience in our recent SM and SLR studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">75,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">76,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b76">77]</ref>.</p><p>Internal validity: Internal validity is a property of scientific studies which reflects the extent to which a causal conclusion based on a study and the extracted data is warranted. The systematic approach that has been utilized for article selection is described in Section 3.3. In order to make sure that this review is repeatable, search engines, search terms and inclusion/exclusion criteria were carefully defined and reported. Potential problematic issues in selection process could be limitation of search terms and search engines, and bias in applying exclusion/inclusion criteria.</p><p>As discussed in Section 5, technical research papers, as results of IAC, generally do not describe the context of the research project or the history of IAC when reporting the technical results. A very small ratio of papers describe those aspects. Our search strings targeted all the candidate papers by searching in "full-text" mode, however no such paper came to our candidate pool. We believe that such a small ratio of papers will not impact our results, i.e., the set of challenges, patterns and anti patterns, since the example technical study that we found <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">[72,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">73]</ref> discussed the aspects already in our synthesized sets.</p><p>Limitation of search terms and search engines could lead to incomplete set of primary sources. Different terms were used by the three authors to point to a similar concept. In order to mitigate risk of finding all relevant A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T studies, formal searching using defined keywords was done followed by manual search in references of initial pool (i.e., snowballing) and in web pages of active researchers in our field of study. For controlling threats due to search engines, not only we included comprehensive academic databases such as Google Scholar, but also we have searched special active venues related to the topic, e.g., the international workshop on long-term industrial collaboration on software engineering. Therefore, we believe that adequate and inclusive basis has been collected for this study and if there is any missing publication, the rate should not be high. Applying inclusion/exclusion criteria can suffer from researchers judgment and experience. Personal bias could be introduced during this process. To minimize this type of bias, joint voting was applied in article selection and only articles passing the threshold score were selected for this study.</p><p>Construct validity: Construct validities are concerned with whether the objects of study truly represents the theory behind the study. Threats related to this type of validity in this study were suitability of RQs and categorization scheme used for the data extraction.</p><p>To limit construct threats in this study, we preserved the tractability between research goal and questions. Research questions were designed to cover our goal and different aspects of the topic. Questions are answered according to a categorization scheme. For designing a good categorization scheme, we adapted a baseline classification from our recent SM and SLR studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">[74,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">75,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">76,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b76">77]</ref>, improved it with the goals of this SLR, and finalized the schema through an iterative improvement process.</p><p>Conclusion validity: Conclusion validity of a SLR study is provided when correct conclusions are reached through rigorous and repeatable treatment. In order to ensure reliability of our treatments, acceptable size of primary sources are selected and terminology in defined schema is reviewed by authors to avoid any ambiguity. All primary sources were reviewed by at least two authors to mitigate bias in data extraction. Each disagreement between authors was resolved by consensus among researchers.</p><p>Following the systematic approach and described procedure ensured replicability of this study and assured that results of similar study will not have major deviations from our classification decisions.</p><p>External validity External validity is concerned with to what extent the results of our SLR study can be generalized. As described in Section 3.3, defined search terms in the article selection approach resulted in having primary sources all written in English language; studies written in other A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T languages were excluded. The issue lies in whether our selected works can represent all types of literature in the area. For these issues, we argue that relevant literature we selected in our pool contained sufficient information to represent the knowledge reported by previous researchers or professionals.</p><p>Also, note that our findings in this study are mainly within the field of IAC in SE. Beyond this field, we had no intention to generalize our results. Therefore, few problems with external validity are worthy of substantial attention.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion and future work</head><p>By following a systematic literature review (SLR) process, this paper selected a pool of 33 sources (papers and books) in the area of IAC in SE and then classified and synthesized the challenges, success patterns and antipatterns of IAC in SE. The results presented a snapshot on the above issues with the hope of encouraging researchers and practitioners to be more aware of the challenges and anti-patterns and also apply success patterns to ensure successful IACs. For the SE research community to have a meaningful future, there is a critical need to both industry and academia to collaborate with one another. We believe that our results are an enabler in that direction. This can be achieved in different ways. Challenges may be utilized to assess risks in IAC. This allows to take proactive actions, which can be obtained from the list of best practices. What is particularly important to avoid has been reported through anti-patterns. Based on a case we found early indications that the frequently mentioned patterns may play an important role in successful IAC, though further data is needed given the limited availability of evidence.</p><p>Among our future work directions are the followings: (1) to practically apply the success patterns in our current/upcoming projects and evaluate their effectiveness, (2) to quantitatively and qualitatively measure the observed levels and impacts of challenges, success patterns and anti-patterns in our current and upcoming projects, and correlate them with project success measures, and (3) we had also extracted the set of anti-patterns in IACs, but due to space constraints, we could not present them. We plan to publish them in other upcoming papers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A. Complete list of challenges</head><p>The complete list of challenges is shown in Table A.6.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :Figure 2 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 1: A heuristic-based search approach to get coarse statistics on the number of "technical" industrial case study (IAC) papers from the Scopus database</figDesc><graphic coords="6,95.73,340.03,386.02,158.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :Figure 4 :</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Figure 3: A conceptual process framework for IAC (adopted from [13])</figDesc><graphic coords="7,167.51,524.31,234.06,131.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Position of this study with respect to the literature and IAC in which practitioners and researchers have been involved and reported their experiences from</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>S C R I P T each study: (1) study title, (2) year of publication, (3) affiliation countries, and (4) types of the authors affiliations (academic or industry).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Author affiliations (industry or academia)</figDesc><graphic coords="18,167.51,564.05,233.82,91.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: SE topic areas of the projects studied in the primary studies</figDesc><graphic coords="19,167.51,312.58,233.93,171.37" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Frequencies of the number of studies by different contribution facets</figDesc><graphic coords="19,167.51,518.93,234.01,137.43" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Type of Paper -Contribution Facet Type of Paper -Research Facet [1]SE area of the project(s) -SWEBOK 12 KAs</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10: Frequencies of the number of studies by different research facets</figDesc><graphic coords="21,165.94,493.56,281.18,173.86" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>FrequencyFigure 11 :Figure 12 :FrequencyFigure 13 :</head><label>111213</label><figDesc>Figure 11: Number of research projects studied in the primary studies</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>List of Search keywords</figDesc><table><row><cell>Listing 1</cell><cell cols="2">Listing 2 LIsting 3</cell><cell>Listing 4</cell></row><row><cell>Industry</cell><cell cols="3">Academia Collaboration Software engineering</cell></row><row><cell>Practice</cell><cell>Theory</cell><cell cols="2">Relationship Software</cell></row><row><cell>University</cell><cell></cell><cell>Relation</cell><cell>IT</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Data Extraction Form</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">SM/RQ Attribute</cell><cell>Categories</cell><cell>Multiple/Single</cell></row><row><cell>SM</cell><cell>SE topic areas</cell><cell>Knowledge areas (KAs) proposed in the Soft-</cell><cell>M</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ware Engineering Body of Knowledge (SWE-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BOK) version 3.0 [49]: Generic (not men-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>tioned), Requirements, Design, Construc-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>tion, Testing, Maintenance, Configuration,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(Project) Management, Process, Models and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>methods, Quality, Professional practice, SE</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>economics, Other</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SM</cell><cell>Contribution type</cell><cell>Guidelines / recommendations / patterns</cell><cell>M</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>/ success factors, Collaboration model,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Method / technique, Process, Empirical</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(Case) study only, Other</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SM</cell><cell>Research type</cell><cell>Solution proposal (example), Empirical</cell><cell>S</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>study, Experience paper, Opinion paper,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Philosophical paper, Other</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SM</cell><cell>Scale of evidence/ experience</cell><cell>No. of example project(s), No. of industry</cell><cell>M</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>partners, time duration (in years)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>RQ1</cell><cell>Collaboration models</cell><cell>Names of the collaboration models</cell><cell>M</cell></row><row><cell>RQ2</cell><cell>Challenges / impediments</cell><cell>Qualitative phrases from the paper</cell><cell>M</cell></row><row><cell>RQ3</cell><cell cols="2">Best practices (success patterns) Qualitative phrases from the paper</cell><cell>M</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>An example coding process for the "'challenges" aspect</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Example of phrase in pri-</cell><cell>Open codes</cell><cell>Axial codes</cell></row><row><cell>mary studies</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">"there is a lack of well-</cell><cell>Lack of well-trained soft-</cell><cell>Lack of SE training and</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">trained requirements engi-</cell><cell>ware engineers</cell><cell>technical skills</cell></row><row><cell>neers" [5]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">"Lack of RE (requirements</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>engineering)</cell><cell>education"</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>from [22]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Snapshot of the axial codes (clusters) by the three researchers after the independent axial coding was conducted. Different levels of abstractions followed by each researcher are noticeable</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reviewer 1 (37 themes)</cell><cell cols="2">Reviewer 2 (24 themes)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Reviewer 3 (10 themes)</cell></row><row><cell>Lack of research relevance (13)</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of research relevance (12)</cell><cell>Lack of research relevance/ re-</cell></row><row><cell>Lack of SE training (4)</cell><cell cols="2">Lack of SE knowledge (8)</cell><cell></cell><cell>search result not useful (11)</cell></row><row><cell>Differences in perspectives (2)</cell><cell cols="3">Limited usefulness of pilot evalu-</cell><cell>Research method and research</cell></row><row><cell>Reluctance to share (4)</cell><cell>ations (1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>data related (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Terminology mismatch (4)</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of responsiveness and access</cell><cell>Lack of SE training and technical</cell></row><row><cell>Scalability (1)</cell><cell>to resources (3)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>skills (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Effective communication (3)</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of research skills/awareness</cell><cell>Lack or drop of interest</cell></row><row><cell>Lack of collaboration methods for</cell><cell cols="3">of research from practitioners (4)</cell><cell>level/commitment (3)</cell></row><row><cell>current challenges (3)</cell><cell cols="2">Too high expectations (14)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Mismatch of industry/academia</cell></row><row><cell>Long term goals (7)</cell><cell cols="2">Different time horizons (17)</cell><cell></cell><cell>objectives, methodologies, goals,</cell></row><row><cell>Researcher bias (1)</cell><cell cols="3">Challenges in research validity</cell><cell>terminology (14)</cell></row><row><cell>Subjectivity (1)</cell><cell>(11)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Communication related issues (4)</cell></row><row><cell>Context dependence (3)</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of usefulness of traditional</cell><cell>Human and organizational fac-</cell></row><row><cell>Intellectual property rights issues</cell><cell cols="2">collaboration methods (8)</cell><cell></cell><cell>tors (other than communication)</cell></row><row><cell>(2)</cell><cell cols="3">Different objectives and priorities</cell><cell>(4)</cell></row><row><cell>Lack of research interest (2)</cell><cell>(15)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Management related issues (6)</cell></row><row><cell>Pilot limitations (1)</cell><cell cols="3">Arranging effective meetings (8)</cell><cell>Resource related issues (4)</cell></row><row><cell>High expectations from re-</cell><cell>Establishing</cell><cell>a</cell><cell>clear</cell><cell>Contractual, confidential, and</cell></row><row><cell>searchers (1)</cell><cell>goal/direction (7)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>privacy issues (5)</cell></row><row><cell>Research settings (1)</cell><cell cols="3">Difficult to transfer research solu-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Limited research skills (2)</cell><cell cols="2">tion to industry (7)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Project management (4)</cell><cell cols="3">Achieving effective communica-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Difficulty in transferring knowl-</cell><cell>tion (7)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>edge to industry (1)</cell><cell cols="2">No agreed terminology (6)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Requirements engineering (1)</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of tool support for research</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Industry constraints (6)</cell><cell>(3)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Academy constraints (1)</cell><cell cols="3">Hard to find and sustain cham-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Recognition of SE (1)</cell><cell>pion (4)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Champions (2)</cell><cell cols="3">Challenges to choose the right</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Expertise in the domain (1)</cell><cell>context (3)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lack of rewarding mechanisms</cell><cell cols="3">Contractual and privacy con-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(1)</cell><cell>straints (4)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Validity threats (2)</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of funding opportunities (4)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Balancing the research rigor (1)</cell><cell cols="2">Human/social factors (3)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Difficulties in adopting new tech-</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of academic rewards for IAC</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>nologies (1)</cell><cell>(2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Different interests within an orga-</cell><cell cols="2">Resistance to change (2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>nization (1)</cell><cell cols="2">Instable organization (1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Previous success as a success fac-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>tor (1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gathering developer opinions (1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Resistance to change (1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Identification of success factors</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SE solution awareness (1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Managing change (1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Mapping of Challenges to Practices</figDesc><table><row><cell>Challenge ID Challenge description</cell><cell>Best practices addressing the challenge</cell></row><row><cell>Category: Lack of research</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>relevance</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C01</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">-continued from the previous page</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Challenge ID Challenge description</cell><cell>Best practices addressing the challenge</cell></row><row><cell>C14</cell><cell cols="3">Deficiencies of knowledge by</cell><cell>BP61: Researcher should be co-located and be</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">the researcher of the company</cell><cell>present on the industry site [21];</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">context and technologies used</cell><cell>BP75: Use established guidelines and data collection</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>in practice</cell><cell></cell><cell>methods (here: interviews [37]);</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP87: Employ the researcher (gains useful industrial</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>experience [59]);</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Category: Lack or drop of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">interest/commitment</cell></row><row><cell>C16</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of commitment to provide</cell><cell>BP16: Need for champions and their attitudes [43];</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">access and time</cell><cell>BP17: Make long-term commitments [45];</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP18: Proper presentation and communication by</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>researchers in early meetings [46];</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP19: Proper topic selection [56];</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP40: Show benefits of the research solution for the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>industrial partner (gives support by top management</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>[65]);</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP46: Friendliness and reciprocal respect [21];</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP61: Researchers should be co-located and be</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>present on industry side (opens doors at the company</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>[43]);</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP64: Have frequent interaction through meetings</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(gives network access [55]);</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP86: Manage intellectual property rights [71];</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP119: Pilot the solution with industry practitioners</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(time and with that cost savings [53]);</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Category:</cell><cell cols="2">Mismatch</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>between</cell><cell>industry</cell><cell>and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>academia</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C24</cell><cell cols="3">Different terminology and ways</cell><cell>BP22: Prior positive experience (facilitates commu-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">of communicating</cell><cell>nication [43]);</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>BP77: Personally interact with the practitioners dur-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ing data collection [54]</cell></row><row><cell>C26</cell><cell cols="3">Different communication chan-</cell><cell>BP7: Run workshops and seminars (increases visibil-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">nels and directions of informa-</cell><cell>ity across organizations [63], allows to show relevance,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>tion flow</cell><cell></cell><cell>strength and ability [63]) ;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Category: Human and or-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">ganizational factors</cell></row><row><cell>C41</cell><cell cols="3">Resistance to change and in-</cell><cell>BP66: Use the case study method (only exploratory</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>flexibility</cell><cell></cell><cell>[62]);</cell></row><row><cell>C42</cell><cell cols="3">Lack of organizational stability</cell><cell>BP15: Ensure management engagement in the indus-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">and continuity</cell><cell>try side (reduces impact of organizational change [55]);</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Category:</cell><cell cols="2">Management-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">related issues</cell></row><row><cell>C48</cell><cell cols="3">Difficulty to achieve clear and</cell><cell>BP18: Proper presentation and communication by</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">realistic ambitions and goals in</cell><cell>researchers in early meetings [51];</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>projects</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C49</cell><cell cols="3">Willingness to put high invest-</cell><cell>BP40: Show benefits of the research solution for the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">ment in time/effort</cell><cell>industrial partner (valuable solutions save time [67]);</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Category:</cell><cell cols="2">Contractual,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">and privacy concerns</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Continued on the next page...</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">-continued from the previous page</cell></row><row><cell>Challenge ID Challenge description</cell><cell>Best practices addressing the challenge</cell></row><row><cell>C62</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table A .</head><label>A</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">6: Complete list of best practices Table A.6 -continued from the previous page Table B.7 -continued from the previous page</cell></row><row><cell>ID ID</cell><cell>Description Description</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3"># References # References</cell><cell>Phase Phase</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">ID C21 Different time horizons between industry and Description BP99 Be aware of and identify context factors that</cell><cell cols="3"># References 9 [64, 45, 62, 50, 23, 57, 55, 54, 66] 9 [31, 37, 58, 58, 45, 62, 55, 42, 54, 60] O Phase P</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Category: Lack of research relevance academia influence and constrain the research results</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">C01 Results produced through research are not rel-C22 Different interests and objectives BP100 Gain an inside view of the practices used at</cell><cell>8 6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>[21, 31, 51, 37, 63, 49, 22, 46] [51, 45, 57, 60, 56, 55] [22]</cell><cell>E2E F O</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">evant for practice C23 Different perception of what solutions and out-the company</cell><cell>6</cell><cell></cell><cell>[47, 58, 23, 59, 43, 56]</cell><cell>F</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">C02 Researchers do not understand the relevant problems from an industry point of view C03 Results produced by research are not measur-able and exploitable (mechanisms for exploit-ing them are missing) C04 University education not focused on industrial relevance C05 Research topic selection not driven by rele-vance Category: Research Method Related C06 Not properly addressing the validity of the re-search when industry is involved: Generaliz-ability, control and confounding factors, bi-ases, subjectivity, sample size, and repeatabil-ity C07 Running a flexible research project/method is challenging C08 Research in its nature is risky C09 Difficult to evaluate whether research ad-dresses future needs in practice making it chal-lenging to decide on solutions C10 Integrating new and improved solutions in the already existing context Category: Lack of training, experience, and skills C11 Deficiencies in software engineering education C12 Lack of training, experience, and skills (gen-M A N U S C R I P T 4 [22, 58, 48, 66] F 1 [46] O/T 1 [59] E2E 1 [56] F 6 [31, 67, 40, 42, 64, 66] P/O 1 [65] P/O 1 [46] E2E 1 [46] O/T 1 [46] O/T 4 [66, 22, 46, 23] E2E 2 [67, 71] E2E comes are useful C24 Different terminology (vocabulary) and ways of communicating 5 [37, 64, 40, 42, 23] E2E C25 Different reward systems 3 [58, 45, 66] F C26 Different communication channels and direc-tions of information flow 3 [51, 37, 57] E2E C27 Different cultures 3 [46, 23, 48] E2E C28 Different expectations on quality of evidence in research 3 [55, 64, 55] E2E C29 Different focus on scale of solutions 2 [23, 66] O/T C30 Different types of knowledge available (indus-try vs. academia) 2 [67, 37] E2E C31 Willingness for technology transfer from academia larger than acceptance of transfer from industry 1 [23] E2E C32 Different contexts 1 [53] E2E C33 Different business models 1 [55] E2E C34 Different perception of challenges 1 [47] F/P C35 Different requirements on novelty 1 [23] E2E Category: Communication related C36 Communication gaps between researchers and practitioners 3 [40, 56, 22] E2E C37 Difficulty of managing multiple research part-ners 1 [71] P/O C38 Difficulty to elicit information from developers 1 [62] O C39 Fulfilling the need of communicating on time-frames, topics, and responsibilities 1 [54] P BP101 Learn the domain and vocabulary 1 [21] F/O Category: Efficient research project management BP102 Plan the research project (time planning, esti-mation, collaboration, alignment with project goals) 4 [51, 62, 60, 66] P BP103 Decrease overhead and waste in research project administration 2 [51, 64] E2E BP104 Assure consistent reporting across documen-tation produced in research (reports, posters, etc.) 1 [51] O BP105 Assure the availability of time for adequate roles represented by practitioners to partici-pate in research activities 1 [42] O BP106 Design effective reward structures for good practice 1 [23] P BP107 Ensure that end research results hit the right trade-offs (e.g., quality and cost) 1 [58] O/T BP108 Integrate research into daily work 1 [61] O/T BP109 Save time of practitioners participating in re-search (e.g. in experiments) 1 [64] O BP110 Utilize Ph.D. students as resources in projects 1 [55] O A N U S C R I P T Category: Conduct measure-ment/assessment BP111 Establish a measurement program and define measurable objectives 2 [21, 65] E2E M BP112 Measure Return of Investment (ROI) 2 [62, 41] O</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">eral) C13 Deficiencies in skills of practitioners to work with the research solution C14 Deficiencies of knowledge by the researcher of the company context and technologies used in practice C15 Deficiencies in research skills from practition-ers Category: Lack or drop of inter-est/commitment C16 Lack of commitment to provide access and time C17 Lack of commitment to assess research results and forums (such as conferences) C18 Lack of commitment to invest money C19 Lack of commitment due to human factors (in-ertia, admit the need for external collabora-tion, 'not invented here' syndrome) C20 Lack of commitment due to competitive busi-ness Category: Mismatch between industry A C C E P T E D C40 Lack of prior relationships between a company and academia Category: Human and organizational factors C41 Resistance to change and inflexibility C42 Lack of organizational stability and continuity 2 2 2 1 2 1 1 4 1 1 3 C43 Difficulties in training practitioners due to high training cost and lack availability of time due to market pressure 1 C44 Intangible human factors with organization-wide impact 1 C45 Competition between industrial and external researchers 1 C46 Hard to find champions 1 C47 Solution incompatible with organizational cul-ture 1 Category: Management-related issues C48 Difficulty to achieve clear and realistic ambi-tions and goals in projects 4 C49 Lack of willingness to put high investment in time/effort 1 BP113 Combine quantitative and qualitative informa-tion to evaluate projects BP114 Develop a set of guidelines to evaluate bodies of evidence BP115 Evaluation criteria should support the R&amp;D project BP116 Measure innovativeness (innovation bench-marking) BP117 Measure solution stability as an indicator for applicability Category: Test/pilot solutions before using them in industry BP118 Test the solution in the lab/academic environ-ment first BP119 Pilot the solution with industry practitioners BP120 Test the solution through a proof of concept BP121 Build tool support (research prototypes) BP122 Have a separate academic solution branch from an industrial solution branch to further evolve the solution A C C E P T E D Category: Provide tool support for so-</cell><cell>1 1 1 1 1 3 2 1 1 1</cell><cell>[67, 41] [42, 55] [64] [64, 50] [58] [58] [67, 23, 53, 57] [23] [56] [67, 46, 53] [42, 53] [46] [56] [66] [55] [46] [51, 45, 46, 53] [46] [61] [49] [46] [53] [31] [21, 41, 42] [42, 46] [67] [53] [67]</cell><cell>O/T E2E E2E O E2E F/P E2E F/P E2E E2E E2E O/T E2E I/O P/O O/T P O/T O O/T O/T O/T O/T O O O O O</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">and academia C50 Difficult to find the right project infrastructure lutions</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>[64]</cell><cell>O/T</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">Continued on the next page... (management, collaboration environments) BP123 Provide technical support and documentation 3 [21, 37, 67]</cell><cell>O</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>for academic tools</cell><cell cols="4">Continued on the next page...</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Continued on the next page...</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Glass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Demarco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Software Creativity 2.0, developer.* Books</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Guidelines for performing systematic literature reviews in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Keele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
	<note>Ver. 2.3 EBSE Technical Report. EBSE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic literature reviews in software engineering -A systematic literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kitchenham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Brereton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Budgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Linkman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Software Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic mapping studies in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Feldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mujtaba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mattsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">12th International Conference on Evaluation and Assessment in Software Engineering, EASE 2008, University of</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bari, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-06">June 2008. 2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="27" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidelines for conducting systematic mapping studies in software engineering: An update</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vakkalanka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kuzniarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Software Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Online slr repository for industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Özkan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://goo.gl/gWrGrg" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Varma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A bibliometric assessment of canadian software engineering scholars and institutions</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996-2006. 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="29" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ruhe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A bibliometric/geographic assessment of 40 years of software engineering research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969-2009. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13431366</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Mntyl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Citations, research topics and active countries in software engineering: A bibliometrics study</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="77" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A bibliometric analysis of the turkish software engineering research community</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Springer Journal on Scientometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Software industry experiments: a systematic literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Dieste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Juzgado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry, CESI 2013</title>
		<meeting>the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry, CESI 2013<address><addrLine>San Francisco, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-05-20">May 20, 2013. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="8" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Academic engagement and commercialisation: A review of the literature on university-industry relations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Perkmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tartari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mckelvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Autio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Broström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Deste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Geuna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Grimaldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Research Policy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Universities-industry collaboration: A systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ankrah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-T</forename><surname>Omar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scandinavian Journal of Management</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">When and what to automate in software testing: A multi-vocal literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Mntyl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Press, Information and Software Technology</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The need for multivocal literature reviews in software engineering: complementing systematic literature reviews with grey literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V M</forename><surname>Vahid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Felderer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Press, 20th International Conference on Evaluation and Assessment in Software Engineering (EASE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidelines for snowballing in systematic literature studies and a replication in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">18th International Conference on Evaluation and Assessment in Software Engineering, EASE &apos;14</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London, England, United Kingdom</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">May 13-14, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identifying relevant studies in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Babar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Software Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="625" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method for evaluating rigor and industrial relevance of technology evaluations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ivarsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gorschek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Empirical Software Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Industry academia collaboration model: The design challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Manisha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Manuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">24th IEEE-CS Conference on Software Engineering Education and Training</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Waikiki, Honolulu, HI, USA, Proceedings</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-05-22">2011. May 22-24, 2011. 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="120" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">viewpoints: Requirements researchers: Do we practice what we preach?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hickey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Requir. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model for technology transfer in practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gorschek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Garre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Larsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bridging the research-practice gap in requirements engineering through effective teaching and peer learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Connor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Buchan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Petrova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sixth International Conference on Information Technology: New Generations, ITNG 2009</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Las Vegas, Nevada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-04-29">27-29 April 2009. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="678" to="683" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kaindl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brinkkemper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A B</forename><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Farbey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Greenspan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Heitmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C S</forename><surname>Do Prado Leite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mylopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I A</forename><surname>Siddiqi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Requirements engineering and technology transfer: Obstacles, incentives and improvement agenda</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="123" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Osborne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Best practices in quantitative methods</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Sage</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An example of how to perform open coding, axial coding and selective coding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gallicano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theoretical sensitivity: Advances in the methodology of grounded theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Glaser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sociology Pr</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Corbin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Basics of qualitative research: Grounded theory procedures and techniques, Basics of qualitative research: Grounded Theory procedures and techniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthesizing evidence in software engineering research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cruzes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dybå</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement</title>
		<meeting>the International Symposium on Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement<address><addrLine>Bolzano/Bozen, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-09">September 2010. 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2010</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research synthesis in software engineering: A tertiary study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cruzes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dybå</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Software Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recommended steps for thematic synthesis in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cruzes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dybå</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th International Symposium on Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement</title>
		<meeting>the 5th International Symposium on Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement<address><addrLine>Banff, AB, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-09-22">2011. September 22-23, 2011, 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="284" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Action research as a model for industry-academia collaboration in the software engineering context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">¸</forename><surname>Gencel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Asghari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Baca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Betz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering</title>
		<meeting>the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering<address><addrLine>Vasteras, Sweden</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-09-16">September 16, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="62" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Qualitative research: standards, challenges, and guidelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Malterud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">358</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="488" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A coding scheme development methodology using grounded theory for qualitative analysis of pair programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Salinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Plonka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Prechelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Guide to the Software Engineering Body of Knowledge (SWEBOK (R)): Version 3.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bourque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Garbajosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Keeni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Avison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Action research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Commun. ACM</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Action research use in software engineering: An initial survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S M</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Travassos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Third International Symposium on Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement</title>
		<meeting>the Third International Symposium on Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement<address><addrLine>Lake Buena Vista, Florida, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">October 15-16, 2009. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="414" to="417" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ESEM 2009</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cabot Sagrera, Bridging the gap among academics and practitioners in non-functional requirements management: some reflections and proposals for the future, Modelling and quality in requirements engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Franch Gutiérrez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ameller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ayala Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Verlagshaus Monsenstein und Vannerdat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Henderson-Sellers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ralyté</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ågerfalk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Situational Method Engineering</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Problem frames: analysing and structuring software development problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding relevant research solutions for practical problems: the serp taxonomy architecture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Engström</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering</title>
		<meeting>the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering<address><addrLine>Vasteras, Sweden</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-09-16">September 16, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of research on practice in the field of inspections, reviews and walkthroughs: learning from successful industrial uses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Rombach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ciolkowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jeffery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Laitenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mcgarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Shull</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM SIGSOFT Software Engineering Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Practical experiences in designing and conducting empirical studies in industry-academia collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Martínez-Fernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Marques</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2nd International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry</title>
		<meeting>the 2nd International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry<address><addrLine>CESI; Hyderabad, India</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-06-02">2014. June 2, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Success factors for empirical studies in industry-academia collaboration: a reflection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Grünbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rabiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry</title>
		<meeting>the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry<address><addrLine>CESI; San Francisco, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-05-20">2013. May 20, 2013. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="32" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determining the impact of software engineering research on practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Osterweil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ghezzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry, CESI 2013</title>
		<meeting>the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry, CESI 2013<address><addrLine>San Francisco, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-05-20">May 20, 2013. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Empirical software engineering research with industry: top 10 challenges</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Requirements engineering and industrial uptake</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Masera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wilikens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">3rd International Conference on Requirements Engineering (ICRE &apos;98)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Colorado Springs, CO, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">April 6-10, 1998. 1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="137" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Putting Requirements Engineering to Practice</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Embedding research in the industrial field: a case of a transition to a software product line</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Raschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zilli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Loinig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Steger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kreiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering</title>
		<meeting>the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering<address><addrLine>Vasteras, Sweden</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-09-16">September 16, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="8" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some researcher considerations when conducting empirical studies in industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Eldh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry, CESI 2013</title>
		<meeting>the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry, CESI 2013<address><addrLine>San Francisco, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-05-20">May 20, 2013. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="70" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding and improving technology transfer in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pfleeger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Systems and Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Get the cogs in synch: time horizon aspects of industry-academia collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Runeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Minör</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Svenér</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering</title>
		<meeting>the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering<address><addrLine>Vasteras, Sweden</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-09-16">September 16, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="28" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Agile collaborative research: Action principles for industry-academia collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sandberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pareto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Arts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The reflective practitioner: How professionals think in action</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schön</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<publisher>Basic books</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5126</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research collaborations between academia and industry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Rombach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Achatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Conference on Software Engineering, ISCE 2007, Workshop on the Future of Software Engineering, FOSE 2007</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Minneapolis, MN, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">May 23-25, 2007. 2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="36" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The 4+1 view model of industry-academia collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Runeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Minör</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering</title>
		<meeting>the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering<address><addrLine>Vasteras, Sweden</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-09-16">September 16, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="24" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">It takes two to tango -an experience report on industry -academia collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Runeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ICST 2012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fifth IEEE International Conference on Software Testing, Verification and Validation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Montreal, QC, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">April 17-21, 2012, 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="872" to="877" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topic selection in industry experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Misirli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Erdogmus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Juzgado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Dieste</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2nd International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry</title>
		<meeting>the 2nd International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry<address><addrLine>CESI; Hyderabad, India</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-06-02">2014. June 2, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Software Conflict 2.0: The art and science of software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Glass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>developer.* Books</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Embracing the engineering side of software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Briand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">96</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategies for industrial relevance in software engineering education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Regnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Systems and Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The success factors powering industry-academia collaboration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aurum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Angelis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dittrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gorschek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Grahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Henningsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kågström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rovegard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tomaszewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Toorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Winter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Software engineering research under the lamppost, in: IC-SOFT 2013 -Proceedings of the 8th International Joint Conference on Software Technologies</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Reykjavík, Iceland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-07">July, 2013, 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empirical studies for innovation dissemination: ten years of experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Baldassarre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Caivano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Visaggio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">17th International Conference on Evaluation and Assessment in Software Engineering, EASE &apos;13</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Porto de Galinhas, Brazil</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">April 14-16, 2013. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="144" to="152" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Industry academia collaboration: An experience report at a small university</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Krishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A P</forename><surname>Salas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings 22nd Conference on Software Engineering Education and Training</title>
		<meeting>22nd Conference on Software Engineering Education and Training<address><addrLine>Hyderabad, India</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-02">2009. 17-20 Feb. 2009, 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="121" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conducting empirical studies in industry: balancing rigor and relevance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Babar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry, CESI 2013</title>
		<meeting>the 1st International Workshop on Conducting Empirical Studies in Industry, CESI 2013<address><addrLine>San Francisco, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-05-20">May 20, 2013. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="14" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Foundations for long-term collaborative research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kanso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Monette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Longterm Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering, Vasteras, Sweden</title>
		<meeting>the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Longterm Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering, Vasteras, Sweden</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-09-16">September 16, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="48" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Useful software engineering research -leading a doubleagent life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Briand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE 27th International Conference on Software Maintenance, ICSM 2011</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Williamsburg, VA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">September 25-30, 2011, 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enablers and impediments for collaborative research in software testing: an empirical exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Enoiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Causevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering</title>
		<meeting>the 2014 ACM International Workshop on Long-term Industrial Collaboration on Software Engineering<address><addrLine>Vasteras, Sweden</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-09-16">September 16, 2014, 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="54" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An opensource tool for automated generation of black-box xunit test code and its industrial evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wiederseiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jolly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eskandar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Conference on Testing: Academic and Industrial Conference -Practice and Research Techniques (TAIC PART)</title>
		<meeting>the International Conference on Testing: Academic and Industrial Conference -Practice and Research Techniques (TAIC PART)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="128" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidelines for conducting and reporting case study research in software engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Runeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Höst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Empirical Software Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="164" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Runeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Höst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ohlsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Regnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Experimentation in Software Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lamprecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G.-J</forename><surname>Van Rooyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Models for technology research collaboration between industry and academia in south africa, in: Software Engineering Colloquium (SE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012 4th, IEEE, 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="17" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Faults-slip-through -a concept for measuring the efficiency of the test process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Damm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lundberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Software Process: Improvement and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Early and cost-effective software fault detection: Measurement and implementation in an industrial setting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L.-O</forename><surname>Damm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<pubPlace>Karlskrona</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>School of Engineering, Blekinge Institute of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ph.D. thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic mapping study of web application testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mesbah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Betin-Can</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mirshokraie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Software Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1374" to="1396" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Memon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Graphical user interface (GUI) testing: Systematic mapping and repository</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1679" to="1694" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cost, benefits and quality of software development documentation: A systematic mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi-Yusifoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Garousi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shahnewaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ruhe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Systems and Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Software test-code engineering: A systematic mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Garousi-Yusifoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Amannejad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Can</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information &amp; Software Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
