<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">RAWGraphs: A Visualisation Platform to Create Open Outputs</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michele</forename><forename type="middle">Mauri</forename><surname>Dipartimento</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Design</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Politecnico</forename><surname>Di</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Milano</forename><surname>Milano</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Italy</forename><surname>Tommaso</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elli</forename><surname>Dipartimento</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Design</forename><surname>Politecnico</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Milano</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Milano</forename><surname>Italy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giorgio</forename><surname>Caviglia</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giorgio</forename><surname>Uboldi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Milano, Italy</roleName><forename type="first">Calibro</forename><surname>Srls</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matteo</forename><surname>Azzi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michele</forename><surname>Mauri</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tommaso</forename><surname>Elli</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">RAWGraphs: A Visualisation Platform to Create Open Outputs</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E674616723880404E2B1011BFBC6A3DD</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1145/3125571.3125585</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T13:05+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Visualization tools</term>
					<term>data visualization</term>
					<term>visual interface</term>
					<term>open output</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>RAWGraphs is an open source web application for the creation of static data visualisations that are designed to be further modified. Originally conceived for graphic designers to provide a series of tasks not available with other tools, it evolved into a platform that provides simple ways to map data dimensions onto visual variables. It presents a chart-based approach to data visualisation: each visual model is an independent module exposing different visual variables that can be used to map data dimensions. Consequently, users can create complex data visualisations. Finally, the tool is meant to produce outputs that are open, that is, not subjected to proprietary solutions, which can be further edited.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CCS Concepts</head><p>• Human-centered computing~Visualization systems and tools • Human-centered computing~Information visualization • Human-centered computing~Graphical user interfaces • Information systems~Open source software</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>The use of data visualisation is common in many fields, and while many visual models have been identified in the past several years <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, their production is still difficult for non-technical users. While the recent development of visualisation libraries has enabled the creation of complex and highly customised solutions, consistent coding knowledge and a significant amount of time is required to master those tools. The idea behind RAWGraphs is to provide an infrastructure to encapsulate charts so that people without coding skills can reuse them with their own data. Starting from the experience gathered in DensityDesign lab, in particular working with newspapers <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, we realised that the creation visualisation process is not linear. Thus, it cannot be solved using a single tool. Rather, when designing visualisations, it is common to move from tool to tool depending on the function and approach one needs for a particular task.</p><p>Therefore, we created a platform to achieve the most difficult task without using code: the encoding of data dimensions on uncommon visual models. The outputs of this platform can be defined as being open; this means that they are specifically designed to be further modified and improved using other software, such as vector graphics editors (e.g. Adobe Illustrator, Inkscape, vectr.com).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PREVIOUS WORK</head><p>RAWGraphs builds upon previous work on visualisation tools, visualisation libraries and online platforms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visualisation toolkits</head><p>RAWGraphs was inspired by several tools that were previously created. Its drag-and-drop interface for mapping visual dimensions is similar to other tools, such as Tableau <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, Lyra <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and Polestar 1 . However, the cited tools use visual grammars that encode data directly to the visual properties of single graphical elements <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. RAWGraphs is based on reusable visual models, which makes it more similar to charting tools such as ManyEyes <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>Another feature is the possibility to create open outputs that can be further modified. Gephi <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, a visualisation tool for the creation of network graphs, is a good example; it provides an environment for visual customisation and the results can be exported in reusable vector formats, such a scalable vector graphics (SVG) and portable document format (PDF).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visualisation libraries</head><p>The availability of libraries that are focused on the creation of data visualisations enables the creation of complex, ad-hoc models. Many of these libraries are meant to provide visualisation grammar, binding data variables to visual elements. Vega <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and D3.js <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> are notable examples of this approach in which information encoding is related to low level items, enabling a high degree of customisation. However, building a visual interface that can expose all the mapping functions is highly problematic, and there is a risk that using visual mapping would be more complex than writing code. Inspired by the reusable charts proposed by Michael Bostock <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, in RAWGraphs we opted to create blocks of code (defined as charts) that contain all the functions needed to generate a specific visual model. For each chart, 1 https://github.com/vega/polestar we then exposed specific variables that can be bound to custom data sources and visual options related to the chart (e.g. height, width, padding between elements, etc.).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Online platforms</head><p>The evolution of web technologies and browsers has made the creation and maintenance of online tools simpler than offline applications. Furthermore, online tools do not require any kind of installation on local machines, making it possible to immediately use them in many environments. Analysing the current state of the art, tools such as Carto<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> and Datawrapper<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">3</ref> enable users to register and create a session. From the experience gathered from the creation of other tools, in particular Fineo <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">4</ref> , we realised that users might be concerned about sending their data to third-party servers.</p><p>Thus, we opted for a front-end-only solution without performing any server-side operation or providing any storage. This means that while the application is provided remotely, all the operations on the data are executed locally on the user's machine.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RAWGraphs platform</head><p>RAWGraphs is an open source web application mainly based on two libraries: AngularJS for the visual interface and D3.js for the creation of data visualisations.</p><p>It consists of three main parts: a JavaScript core, which provides all the functions needed to abstract reusable charts and bind the data source to visual variables, an angular application, which provides the visual interface, and single charts that work as plug-ins.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chart modules</head><p>RAWGraphs is meant to be an environment that is easily extendible. Thus, it takes advantage of the concept of reusable charts, defining a set of instructions for the creation of a specific chart and giving the user the ability to change the underlying data and customise the graphical variables.</p><p>The Chart module contains three main components:</p><p>The data model;</p><p>The visual options;</p><p>The rendering. Since most D3.js layouts operate on specific data structures (e.g. hierarchies for Bubble Charts or nodeslinks for Force-directed Graphs), provides a logical and graphical interface to let users transforming the data into the appropriate structure required by the chart. It also defines which visual variables are exposed in the interface. RAWGraphs will create the necessary graphical user interface (GUI) elements to enable users to choose which data dimensions to map to the visual properties.</p><p>Currently, four models are built into the RAWGraphs platform, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>: points (used for Cartesian distributions, e.g. scatter plots), trees (used to define hierarchies), graphs (node-links structures used, for example, in alluvial diagrams) and time series. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">5</ref> Each model can be used in different charts and extended based on the chart's needs.</p><p>In addition to the data model, each chart is also defined by general visual options independent from the data source. Examples are the width and height of the visualisation or the space between the graphical items. Visual options can even be associated with specific behaviours of the chart's visual elements: for example, letting the user choose which algorithm to apply to interpolate curves or enabling a user to normalise the data.</p><p>The rendering part is exclusive for each chart. The transformed data and the visual options are available and ready to use without any additional operations. By keeping the rendering part logically separated, a user can easily readapt other D3.js code blocks to RAWGraphs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>User Interface</head><p>The user interface used to create data visualisation is divided in five sections. As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>, the sections are: (1) load your data, (2) choose a chart, (3) map your dimensions, (4) customise your visualisation and (5) download.</p><p>In the first section, "load your data", users have three ways to inject custom data into the application: copying and pasting it from any spreadsheet or text editor, uploading a file containing tabular data (CSV, TSV, XLSX, JSON) or inserting an Application Programming Interface (API) endpoint URL. It is also possible to load a sample dataset meant to demonstrate the supported features of the application.</p><p>In the second section, "choose a chart", all the available charts are listed in a grid, showing the visual preview, the name of the visual model and the category to which it belongs. Once a chart is selected, a brief description is provided on the left side of the screen.</p><p>In the third section, "map your dimensions", users can map the data dimensions to the chart. The dataset dimensions are identified by the column headers; they are listed on the left side of the screen and the available chart dimensions are listed on the right. Two icons specify whether the dimension is mandatory and if more than a singular value can be inserted. For each dimension, the accepted data type is specified, consisting of numbers, strings and dates. The user can drag and drop data dimensions onto the chart dimensions. After all the mandatory dimensions are mapped, a preview of the chart is displayed, providing immediate visual feedback.</p><p>In the fourth section, "customise your visualisation", users can perform a general tuning of the chart adjusting the visual options listed on the left side of the screen and previewing the chart in real time.</p><p>Finally, in the last section, "download", users can export the result and use it, as it is, or with other tools. Four export formats are provided. Scalable vector graphics (SVG) is one type of export format; it provides a geometric description of the elements in the visualisation, which can be further modified using any type of vector editing software (e.g. Adobe Illustrator, Inkscape, vectr.com). Another type of export, portable network graphics (PNG), is a raster image that can be easily embedded into presentations and/or shared online. The third type is the data in the JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) format. While this is not a graphical format, it could be useful for dynamically recreating the visualisation. Finally, it is possible to embed the SVG code into any HTML document.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OPEN OUTPUTS</head><p>The ability to further modify the output is both technical and conceptual <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Technically, an output, such as SVG, allows for the free transformation of all the graphic elements of the chart. However, the output would not be as useful if the order of the elements, their naming and the way in which they are grouped are not designed to make the structure easily understandable and reworkable by the user; that is, clustering the visual elements based on their function (for example axis, marks, labels).</p><p>The ability to export SVG-embedded code and the JSON data model is compatible with this open-end approach. Because it is not possible to predict all the processes that users could follow while using the application, all the possible hooks to additional steps or actions have been left open and exposed. Thus, users are encouraged to explore new uses for these outputs, facilitating the emergence of new methodologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>COMMUNITY BUILDING</head><p>An early alpha version of the tool was originally published in 2013, and new versions were published in 2014 and 2017. The project is provided as a web application, and the full source code is hosted on a public repository.</p><p>In order to engage with users, we used three main channels: a Google Group, an issues page on GitHub and a gallery featuring the most interesting works created by users. The Google Group is a forum meant to be a place where users can ask general usage questions and receive a reply from a team member or experienced users. The issues page acts primarily as a place to report software bugs where users can address concerns related to technical problems or ask the team to fix bugs. Finally, in order to understand how the tool is used and repurposed in different professional environments, we asked the users to share their results by submitting them to our gallery.</p><p>After the launch of the 1.2.0 version, we released a series of tutorials. They were published in the learning section of the project's website. They aim to provide stepby-step information about the basic way to use the tool. The tutorials guide users through the production of each type of chart and provide them with some useful tips and tricks, such as shifting from "narrow" to "wide" data or understanding the correct data structure they have to feed into the application.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EVALUATION &amp; EARLY USAGE</head><p>Currently, we have a stable base of more than 9,000 users each month. Moreover, 110 issues were opened in the GitHub forum after the first release, and more than 250 users engaged in discussions in the Google Group. The gallery of works, launched with the 1.2.0 version of the software, helped us to understand how the tool is mainly used, and in which professional environments. Thirty-two works were submitted in six months, and 22 of them were featured on the project's website. Alluvial diagrams and bump charts are the types of charts that are most often used in all the submissions. The users have noted that this is mainly due to the fact that there is no simple way to produce these types of charts with the current tools. In half of the submitted works, the charts are heavily reworked using RAWGraphs as a first, generative tool. Then, other tools are used to create a unique visual style or rearrange the visual items to create novel visual models. This use of RAWGraphs highlights its ability to create open outputs. However, through the online group we created to foster the user community, it has become clear that less-technical users require a more polished result; they are asking for better disposition of labels, the ability to export legends and more clear axes for the visualisation. One feature that is often requested is the ability to export the result not just as a static image, but as an HTML bundle. This would allow users to reuse it on their own websites.</p><p>The learning section of the website counts 5,400 monthly page views. The five most read tutorials are, in order: alluvial diagrams, bar charts, treemaps, pie charts and bump charts.</p><p>Since the project is open source, it was possible to follow the public's response to the project and see which kinds of improvements were made. In most cases, new charts were added, mainly simple (such as circular dendrograms or paired bar charts). Other charts that were added were related to geography, such as Choropleth maps or Dorling maps. The modified code was re-shared with us only in few cases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>In this paper, we presented RAWGraphs, a web application for the quick creation of visualisations from a dataset. The application is open source and is meant to be expandable, even if coding skills are required. The outputs of the application are open, meaning they are intended to be reworked and finalised with other software tools. The application is now widely used, and we collected feedback with the understanding that the tool is used in academic and journalistic environments.</p><p>Although the users' reactions were mostly positive, from the feedback and comments we identified three directions for future work. First, in the current version, the legends (e.g. colour mapping) are visible only in the editing environment; they are lost once the chart is exported. Moreover, labels are visual items that are difficult to manage, and new functions should be provided to facilitate handling, filtering and sizing. To date, many contributors have created their own custom version of the application and they have added new visual models; however, it is still difficult for non-technical users to reuse these pieces of code. The creation of a visualisation marketplace, where users can share new charts and use them in their private sessions, would be a helpful improvement. Finally, the most engaging challenge will be to extend the current approach so users can create interactive visualisations, not just static ones. This requires adding the ability to export a bundle containing all the files (HTML and JavaScript) with the selected mapping. Moreover, this would allow users to map dimensions not only on visual features but also on interactions (such as tooltips or behaviours on selection). Of course, knowledge regarding web programming languages is needed, but it would be scalable depending on the number of details users want to modify. Logics aligned to the ones already applied in the current stage of the work would be investigated with the aim of opening new methodologies for a more computational way of creating a design, especially in the field data visualisation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. ♪ e interface of RAWGraphs highlighting the  ve sections. ♪ e interface is a single-page website, sections are added while the user is interacting with it.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,332.38,81.11,219.45,565.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="2,54.08,81.96,503.92,179.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://github.com/CartoDB/cartodb</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_1"><p>https://github.com/datawrapper/datawrapper</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_2"><p>http://www.densitydesign.org/research/fineo/Figure 1: Charts provided by RAWGraphs, grouped by data model</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Available models are fully described on the project's Wiki page, available at: https://github.com/densitydesign/raw/wiki/Models</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>We thank Professor Paolo Ciuccarelli and the entire DensityDesign Lab group for their feedback, suggestions and support. This work was supported by Contactlab.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AVAILABILITY</head><p>RAWGraphs is available at rawgraphs.io.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Design for information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Isabel</forename><surname>Meirelles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">9781592538065</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Rockport Publishers, Beverly, MA. ISBN</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Le mappe del sapere. Visual data di arti, nuovi linguaggi, diritti. Rizzoli</title>
		<editor>Gianluigi Colin and Antonio Troiano</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">ISBN</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9788817078078</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Milano, Italy</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polaris: A system for query, analysis, and visualization of multidimensional relational databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Stolte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Diane</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pat</forename><surname>Hanrahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/2945.981851</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. Comput. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lyra: An interactive visualization design environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arvind</forename><surname>Satyanarayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><surname>Heer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/cgf.12391</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vega-Lite: A grammar of interactive graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Arvind</forename><surname>Satyanarayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dominik</forename><surname>Moritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kanit</forename><surname>Wongsuphasawat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><surname>Heer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2016.2599030</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. Comput. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Many Eyes: A site for visualization at internet scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fernanda</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Viegas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Wattenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Van Ham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jesse</forename><surname>Kriss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matt</forename><surname>Mckeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2007.70577</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. Comput. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1121" to="1128" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gephi: An open source software for exploring and manipulating networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sebastien</forename><surname>Mathieu Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mathieu</forename><surname>Heymann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jacomy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/qshc.2004.010033</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Third International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="362" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data-driven documents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Bostock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vadim</forename><surname>Ogievetsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><surname>Heer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2011.185</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2301" to="2309" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Bostock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://bost.ocks.org/mike/chart/" />
		<title level="m">Towards Reusable Charts</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-07-24">2012. July 24. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing diagrams for social issues</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michele</forename><surname>Mauri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paolo</forename><surname>Ciuccarelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of DRS 2016, Design Research Society 50th Anniversary Conference</title>
		<meeting>DRS 2016, Design Research Society 50th Anniversary Conference<address><addrLine>Brighton, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
