<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Millimeter-Wave Channel Estimation Based on Two-Dimensional Beamspace MUSIC Method</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ziyu</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
							<email>zguo@seu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Electrical Engineering Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10027</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Xiaodong</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<email>wangx@ee.columbia.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Electrical Engineering Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10027</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Electrical Engineering Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10027</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Heng</surname></persName>
							<email>wheng@seu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Electrical Engineering Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10027</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Millimeter-Wave Channel Estimation Based on Two-Dimensional Beamspace MUSIC Method</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7A43067F3C495618BBC9439CCE1EDA9A</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TWC.2017.2710049</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T14:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Millimeter wave communications</term>
					<term>channel estimation</term>
					<term>two-dimensional MUSIC</term>
					<term>hybrid beamforming</term>
					<term>DFT beamformers</term>
					<term>beamspace processing</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Due to the spatial sparsity caused by the severe propagation loss, the millimeter-wave (mm-wave) channel estimation can be performed by estimating the directions and gains of the paths that have significant power. In this paper, we apply the beamspace two-dimensional multiple signal classification (MUSIC) method to estimate the path directions (the angles of departure and arrival) and use the least-squares method to estimate the path gains. Different from its element-space counterpart, the beamspace MUSIC method may exhibit spectrum ambiguity caused by the beamformers. In this paper, we therefore analyze the sufficient conditions on the beamformers under which the MUSIC spectrum has no ambiguity which also leads to the maximum number of resolvable path directions. Moreover, based on the uniform linear array with half-wavelength spacing, we show that the discrete Fourier transform (DFT) beamformers, which are naturally analog and often employed in the mmwave communication systems with hybrid precoding structure, can avoid the spectrum ambiguity and maximize the number of resolvable path directions. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC mm-wave channel estimator significantly outperforms existing estimators that are based on beam training and sparse recovery; and in the meantime, it requires much less training slots than these existing methods.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Millimeter wave (mm-wave) communication is a potential candidate technology for next-generation wireless communication systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. One key characteristic of the mm-wave systems is the severer propagation loss compared with the micro wave systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. For example, the propagation characteristics of the E-band signals are summarized in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Thus the traditional multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) channel models based on rich scattering fail to characterize the spatial sparsity of the mm-wave channel, whose impulse response is dominated by only a small number of scattering paths. Instead the mm-wave channel can be modeled in the parametric form, in terms of the path angles of departure/arrival (AoD/AoA) and the corresponding path gains. As a result, the mmwave channel estimation problem becomes estimating the path directions (angle pairs) and gains rather than estimating the MIMO channel matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p>The mm-wave channel estimation is often combined with beamforming, which is used to combat the severe path loss. Since the mm-wave signals are highly directional and consist of a few significant components, a straightforward and lowcomplexity mm-wave channel estimation method is to search in the angular space by adjusting the steering directions of the beamformer <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. However, the exhaustive search may be hampered by the high training overhead in practice. Efficient beam training strategies based on compressed sensing (CS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> are developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> where the estimation procedures are divided into multiple stages. At the initial stage, the angular space is coarsely searched with wide beams. In the subsequent stages, the searching beams become narrower and narrower. Finally, the estimated AoDs/AoAs achieve the desired resolution at the last stage.</p><p>Different from beam training methods, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> utilized the orthogonal matching pursuit algorithm to solve the mm-wave channel estimation problem and also gave some insight into the hybrid digital/analog precoding structure that has been widely adopted in the mm-wave communications systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Moreover, the massive MIMO channel estimation problem is also treated using the CS-based methods in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>. These CS-based methods regard the sparse multipath channel estimation as a sparse recovery problem. The virtual angular representation <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref> or angle grids <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> are used to describe the path directions. For each angle grid that represents a pair of TX/RX directions, there is a gain coefficient. Because of the spatial sparsity of the mm-wave channel, most of the gain coefficients should be zero, which means there is no path coming from/to those directions. The sparse recovery method aims to recover the nonzero gain coefficients, which naturally provides the estimates of the path directions, and at the same time reduces the training overhead as much as possible.</p><p>The channel estimation schemes mentioned above can be used to estimate the full channel state information (CSI). In <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, the Arnoldi iteration technique is applied to estimate the partial CSI of the mm-wave channel, i.e., the right and the left singular vectors are estimated at the transmitter and the receiver respectively. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> also develop iterative approaches to estimate the partial CSI of the mm-wave channel. In particular, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> aims to find the steering vector corresponding to the strongest path. The method developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, which exploits the knowledge of the channel covariance matrix, can be used to solve the mm-wave channel estimation Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">1:</ref> A mm-wave communication system employing hybrid analog/digital beamforming. problem too.</p><p>Different from the prior works mentioned above, we solve the mm-wave channel estimation problem based on the spatial spectrum estimation (SSE) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. Particularly, we use the two-dimensional beamspace multiple signal classification (MUSIC) approach and the least-squares method to estimate the path directions and path gains respectively. MUSIC is a classic method for estimating the angle-of-arrivals (AoAs) and has been employed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> for mm-wave communication systems. It can be easily extended to estimate the AoDs and AoAs jointly <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28]</ref>. In particular, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> considers the fast implementation of the two-dimensional MUSIC. However, the one-and two-dimensional MUSIC algorithms in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> are all performed in the element-space, which are impractical to be implemented with a small number of RF chains. For mm-wave communications employing hybrid beamforming, the receiving signals are first mixed by the beamformer and then sent to the RF chains. Thus for the channel estimation problem, it is the beamspace MUSIC that really works. The main contributions of this paper are summarized as follows:</p><p>1) We propose a new mm-wave channel training scheme inspired by the measurement results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, which show that at mm-wave band the clusters' central angles belong to large-scale fading while the path gains belong to small-scale fading. It means that we should be able to observe the path directions in a time span during which the path gains may have fluctuated significantly. This fluctuation mitigates the deep fading effect and thus helps to increase the estimation accuracy of the path directions.</p><p>Besides the beamspace MUSIC, the proposed mm-wave channel estimation framework also accommodates other SSE methods like the beamspace ESPRIT <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> and the maximum likelihood approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. 2) For the mm-wave channel estimator based on the twodimensional beamspace MUSIC, the spectrum ambiguity exists and the identifiability is theoretically solved. For the one-dimensional beamspace MUSIC, the spectrum ambiguity caused by inappropriate beamformers has been analyzed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. To avoid the ambiguity in the twodimensional beamspace MUSIC spectrum, in this paper we provide the sufficient conditions on the beamformers, which also maximize the number of resolvable path directions. Moreover, based on the uniform linear array with half-wavelength spacing, we show that the discrete Fourier transform (DFT) beamformers, which are often used in the hybrid beamforming structure of mm-wave communication systems, satisfy those conditions and thus can be utilized in the proposed channel estimator. The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. Section II presents the system model and introduces some existing mm-wave channel estimation schemes. In Section III, we introduce the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method and give sufficient conditions on the beamformers under which there is no ambiguity in estimating the path angles. Simulation results are presented in Section IV. Section V concludes the paper.</p><p>Notations: A, a, and a denote the matrix, vector, and scalar, respectively. A , A * , A H , and A -1 are matrix transpose, conjugate, conjugate transpose, and inverse, respectively. A [:,i] is the i th column of A, and diag{a} is a diagonal matrix with the elements of a on the diagonal. A ⊗ B and A B are the Kronecker product and the Khatri-Rao product of A and B respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. SYSTEM DESCRIPTIONS A. System and Channel Model</head><p>Consider a mm-wave communication system shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The transmitter and receiver are equipped with N t and N r antennas respectively. The hybrid analog/digital beamforming is adopted, which is a promising scheme that has been widely used to reduce the hardware cost in mm-wave communication systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. Within the hybrid structure, the antenna array at the transmitter is connected to the analog beamformer F ∈ C Nt×Mt implemented by phase shifters, and the analog beamformer is connected to M t (≤ N t ) RF chains. The same hybrid structure is used at the receiver, where the analog beamformer W ∈ C Nr×Mr is equipped with M r (≤ N r ) RF chains. The digital processors perform channel estimation and digital precoding. In this paper, we focus only on the mm-wave channel estimation problem.</p><p>Because of the sparse scattering, the ray-tracing representation is often used to model the mm-wave channel <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. Assuming that there are K clusters and each one contributes to a resolvable path, the channel model can be written as <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">H(q) = K k=1 α k (q)a r (θ k )a t (φ k ) ∈ C Nr×Nt ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where a t (•) and a r (•) are the antenna array response at the transmitter and receiver, respectively; α k (q)</p><p>i.i.d.</p><p>∼ CN (0, σ 2 k ) is the fading gain of the k th path; and q is used to index the time block within which the mm-wave channel is regarded as fixed. Assuming that the antenna arrays are installed in the horizontal direction, we denote φ k = sin( φk ) and θ k = sin( θk ) ∈ [-1, 1] as the departure and arrival directions of the k th path, where φk and θk are the physical azimuth angles of departure and arrival. In (1), we have assumed that the variation of the channel is only caused by the path gains {α k (q)} K k=1 , while the path angles remain unchanged. This time-varying assumption is based on the mm-wave channel measurements in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, which show that the clusters' central angles belong to large-scale fading while the path gains belong to small-scale fading. For notational convenience, (1) can be rewritten in a compact form as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">H(q) = A R Λ α (q)A T ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Λ α (q) = diag{α 1 (q), . . . , α K (q)} ∈ C K×K , A T = [a t (φ 1 ) . . . a t (φ K )] ∈ C Nt×K , and A R = [a r (θ 1 ) . . . a r (θ K )] ∈ C Nr×K .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Existing MM-Wave Channel Estimation Methods</head><p>Before we discuss our proposed mm-wave channel estimation scheme, we briefly summarize the methods developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>, which all exploit the angular-domain sparsity. To express such a sparsity, first the angular domain is divided into angle grids. Next we use { φi } Gt i=1 and { θi } Gr i=1 to denote the AoD and AoA grids respectively.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, the angle grids are uniformly separated with G t = N t and G r = N r in the so called virtual representation. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>, the size of the angle grids can be set according to the desired angular resolution. Based on these predefined angle grids, directions of all possible paths are approximated by {( φi , θj ), i = 1, . . . , G t , j = 1, . . . , G r }. Finally channel estimation is formulated as the problem to estimate the path gains associated with all those G t G r directions. Because of the spatial sparsity in the mm-wave channel, it is expected that the propagation paths are along a small number of directions, or in other words, most of the estimated path gains are zero. Following this manner, compressed-sensing-based algorithms have been developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> to reconstruct the path gains, while a multistage training strategy is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> to first locate path directions and then estimate path gains.</p><p>It should be noticed that the channel estimation schemes in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref> do not exploit the large-scale fading property of the path directions, which remain unchanged for the entire frame, and their estimation accuracies of the path directions are highly affected by the instantaneous path gains. Since the same algorithms are implemented repeatedly for each fading block, this may lead to heavy computational overhead, especially considering that the methods in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> are both iterative procedures. On the other hand, for the proposed channel estimation scheme, the main computation cost resides in the direction finding step, which is performed only once in each frame.</p><p>Moreover, the number of training time slots used in one block is different among the above mentioned channel esti-mators. Specifically, N tr training slots are used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, while N Beam t and N Beam r training beam patterns are used at the the transmitter and receiver respectively in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, corresponding to N Beam t N Beam r Mr training slots. For the estimator in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, the number of training slots is mainly determined by the desired grid resolution, i.e., it requires</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">k 0 K 2 k0K Mr log k0 G K training slots (G t = G r = G), where k 0 ≥ 2 is a predefined integer.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. BEAMSPACE MM-WAVE CHANNEL ESTIMATION</head><p>We apply the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC algorithm to estimate the path directions, and based on the estimated angles we then use the LS method to estimate the path gains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Channel Estimation Procedure</head><p>During one fading block, the pilot signal transmitted at the m th (m = 1, . . . , M t ) RF chain is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">p m (t) = E M t ϕ (t -(m -1)T ) ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where E is the transmit power allocated equally for each pilot signal, and ϕ(t) is the shaping pulse with duration T . As we can see from (3), the pilot signals transmitted by different RF chains are orthogonal to each other in the time domain, i.e., we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">MtT p i (t)p j (t)dt = E Mt , i = j, 0, i = j ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>assuming T ϕ 2 (t)dt = 1.</p><p>To perform channel estimation, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the same pilot signals are transmitted by the RF chains in each fading block. Denote the pilot signal sent by the m th RF chain in the q th block as p m (q, t) = p m (t -(q -1)T b ), for q = 1, . . . , N and m = 1, . . . , M t . Here T b denotes the block duration.</p><p>According to the discussion above, the output of the receiving beamformer can be represented as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">y(q, t) = W H H(q)F * p(q, t) + W H n(q, t) ∈ C Mr ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where p(q, t) = [p 1 (q, t), . . . , p Mt (q, t)] is the pilot signal vector and n(q, t) is the noise term, whose elements are assumed to be i.i.d. Gaussian.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>, the received signal expression, i.e., the input to the channel estimation algorithm, contains the analog beamformers W and F. Thus the beamforming matrices have direct impact on the channel estimation performance. In this paper, we only consider the paths whose directions are located in the beamforming sectors Ω φ and Ω θ (i.e., φ k ∈ Ω φ and θ k ∈ Ω θ , k = 1, . . . , K), and ignore the paths in the attenuated sectors.</p><p>As we can see from (1), the mm-wave channel can be parameterized by the large time-scale (path direction) and small time-scale (path gain) components. For the channel estimation algorithm developed in this paper, these components are estimated separately. In particular, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the path directions are assumed to be fixed during a frame, consisting of N fading blocks. The buffered N blocks of received signals are first utilized to estimate the path directions {(φ k , θ k )} K k=1 using the two-dimensional beamspace q q N N Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>: The frame structure for the proposed mm-wave channel estimator.</p><p>MUSIC algorithm. It should be noticed that the proposed two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC is not a simple extension of its element-space counterpart, which does not consider beamforming. As will be explained in the subsection III-D, inappropriate beamformers may induce spectrum ambiguity such that the path angles cannot be uniquely identified. The estimated path directions then form the basis of estimating path gains in each block. Specifically, using the estimate of path directions, we can estimate the path gains {α k (q)} K k=1 using the least-squares method and then get the estimate of the entire channel matrix H(q), q = 1, . . . , N . According to the discussion above, we need N blocks' pilots to estimate N channels , and we can see from (3) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>) that we need M t training slots in one block.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Forming Sample Covariance Matrix</head><p>Based on the orthogonality of the pilot waveforms, we apply matched-filtering to the received signal y(q, t) in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>) to obtain 1</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">y m (q) = MtT y(q, t)p m (q, t)dt, m = 1, . . . , M t = E M t W H H(q)F * [:,m] + n m (q) ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where we assume that the columns of W are orthogonal, based on which we have n m (q) = W H T n(q, t)p m (q, t)dt ∼ CN (0, σ 2 I Mr ). Substituting (1) into ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">6</ref>), we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">y m (q) = E M t W H K k=1 α k (q)a r (θ k )a t (φ k )F * [:,m] + n m (q) = E M t K k=1 F H [:,m] a t (φ k ) W H a r (θ k )α k (q) + n m (q) = E M t F H [:,m] a t (φ 1 ) W H a r (θ 1 ) • • • F H [:,m] a t (φ K ) W H a r (θ K ) α(q) + n m (q) = E M t F H [:,m] A T W H A R α(q) + n m (q) ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>1 Since we consider the narrow band channel model, the received pilot signals are still orthogonal to each other in the time domain.</p><p>where 2 α(q) = [α 1 (q) . . . α K (q)] . If we stack all the M t vectors in a column, we get the M t M r ×1 measurement vector</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">y(q) = [y 1 (q) . . . y Mt (q) ] = E M t      F H [:,1] A T . . . F H [:,Mt] A T      W H A R α(q) + n(q) = E M t F H A T W H A R B α(q) + n(q) ,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where n(q) = [n 1 (q) , . . . , n Mt (q) ] and B is the M t M r × K direction matrix. The k th column of B can be expressed as b(φ k , θ k ), where the function b(φ, θ) is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">b(φ, θ) = F H a t (φ) ⊗ W H a r (θ) .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, the measurement vectors from the N blocks are first collected for direction finding. Specifically, they are used to estimate the covariance matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">R y ∆ = E{y(q)y(q) H } R y ∆ = 1 N N q=1</formula><p>y(q)y(q) H , <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> which underlies the MUSIC approach shown next.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Two-Dimensional Beamspace MUSIC Method</head><p>Substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">8</ref>) into <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">R y = BE{α(q)α(q) H }B H + σ 2 I MtMr = BΛ α B H Rx +σ 2 I MtMr ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Λ α = E Mt 2 diag{σ 2 1 , . . . , σ 2 K }.</formula><p>To continue the MUSIC process, we assume that the direction matrix B has</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">2 Given A = [a 1 , . . . , a K ] ∈ C M ×K , Z = [z 1 , . . . , z K ] ∈ C N ×K , the Khatri-Rao product is defined as A Z = [a 1 ⊗ z 1 , . . . , a K ⊗ z K ] ∈ C M N ×K ,</formula><p>and ⊗ is the Kronecker product, which is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">A ⊗ X =    a 1,1 X • • • a 1,K X . . . . . . . . . a M,1 X • • • a M,K X    ∈ C M N ×KL where X ∈ C N ×L .</formula><p>full-column rank for now.</p><p>Taking the eigenvalue decomposition of the covariance matrix R x in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">R x = Udiag{η 1 , η 2 , . . . , η MtMr }U H (12)</formula><p>where {η i } MtMr i=1 are the eigenvalues of R x and sorted in descending order. Since the direction matrix B has full-column rank, i.e., rank(B) = K, we have rank(R x ) = K. Thus</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">η i &gt; 0, for i ≤ K , η i = 0, for i &gt; K . (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_18">)</formula><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, it is obvious that R y has eigenvalues</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">{η i = η i + σ 2 } MtMr i=1</formula><p>and the same eigenvectors as R x . So the eigenvalue decomposition of R y can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">R y = Udiag{η 1 , η 2 , . . . , η MtMr }U H ,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>where η i = σ 2 for i &gt; K because of <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. Then the matrix U can be partitioned as ) are the eigenvectors corresponding to the eigenvalue σ 2 and span the noise subspace. That is, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">U = [ U s | U n ]. The columns in U n ∈ C MtMr×(MtMr-K</formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">B H U n = 0. Hence b(φ k , θ k ) H U n = 0, k = 1, . . . , K.</formula><p>In other words, each path direction (φ k , θ k ) contributes a zero to the null spectrum</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">D(φ, θ) = b H (φ, θ)U n U H n b(φ, θ) .<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Thus the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method can estimate the K path directions by locating the K poles in the directional spectrum</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">P (φ, θ) = 1 b H (φ, θ)U n U H n b(φ, θ) ,<label>(16)</label></formula><p>where φ ∈ Ω φ and θ ∈ Ω θ . Note that U n in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">16</ref>) can be estimated by performing the eigenvalue decomposition on the sample covariance matrix R y defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>. Here the path number K is assumed to be known. In practice, we can estimate K by comparing the magnitudes of {η i } MtMr i=1 , i.e., there will be K eigenvalues whose magnitudes may be clearly distinguished from the ones corresponding to the noise subspace. Alternatively the AIC and the MDL methods developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> can be applied.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Analysis of the 2D Beamspace MUSIC Spectrum Ambiguity</head><p>As we can see from the discussion above, the true path directions {(φ k , θ k )} K k=1 contribute to K poles of P (φ, θ), i.e., b H (φ k , θ k )U n = 0 for k = 1, . . . , K. If in addition, it has another pseudo pole (φ K+1 , θ K+1 ) such that b H (φ K+1 , θ K+1 )U n = 0, then we say the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method exhibits ambiguity since the true path angles cannot be uniquely identified by searching the poles of P (φ, θ). Such a pseudo pole can only arise in the situation where b(φ K+1 , θ K+1 ) lies in the column space of B, i.e., the vectors {b(φ k , θ k )} K+1 k=1 are linearly dependent. Specific examples of beamforming matrices that cause such an ambiguity in one-dimensional beamspace MUSIC can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. In Section IV, an example is provided to show the spectrum ambiguity caused by the beamformers in the twodimensional case.</p><p>Based on the above discussions, we have the following proposition that gives the sufficient condition for avoiding the spectrum ambiguity in the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC.</p><p>Proposition 1. Assuming that {(φ k , θ k )} K k=1 are the true path directions, if the augmented direction matrix ) has full column rank for ∀(φ K+1 , θ K+1 ) ∈ (Ω φ , Ω θ ), then there will be only K poles indicating the true path directions in the spectrum defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">B a = [b(φ 1 , θ 1 ) . . . b(φ K , θ K ) b(φ K+1 , θ K+1 )] ∈ C (MtMr)×(K+1</formula><p>As we have seen, the rank of the augmented direction matrix B a affects the performance of the beamspace MUSIC method. By (9), the direction matrix is determined by the path directions and the beamformers F and W. Note that the path directions are random and unknown, and only the beamformers F and W can be designed. In what follows, we give a sufficient condition on F and W such that the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method will not have ambiguity.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, the maximum number of resolvable path directions K max ≤ M t M r -1, since otherwise U n does not exist. Proof: According to Proposition 1, it suffices to prove that</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">B = F H A T W H A R ∈ C MtMr×MtMr<label>(17)</label></formula><p>always has full rank, where</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">A T = [a t (φ 1 ) . . . a t (φ MtMr )] , A R = [a r (θ 1 ) . . . a r (θ MtMr )] ,<label>(18)</label></formula><p>for any</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">{φ i ∈ Ω φ } MtMr i=1</formula><p>and {θ i ∈ Ω θ } MtMr i=1 . To prove that B has full rank, we first derive an alternative representation of B.</p><p>According to condition 2), we can pick any</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">{υ i } Mt i=1 ∩ {φ i } MtMr i=1 = ∅ and {ω j } Mr j=1 such that F H [a t (υ 1 ) . . . a t (υ Mt )] and W H [a r (ω 1 ) . . . a r (ω Mr )] have full rank. Then { fi = F H a t (υ i ) ∈ C Mt } Mt</formula><p>i=1 forms a basis of the column space of F H A T ∈ C Mt×MtMr , and similarly { ŵj = W H a r (ω j ) ∈ C Mr } Mr j=1 forms a basis of the column space of W H A R ∈ C Mr×MtMr . Denoting the n th column of F H A T as f n , and the n th column of W H A R as w n , we can write</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">f n = Mt i=1 c i,n fi = Fc n , w n = Mr j=1 d j,n ŵj = Wd n , n = 1, . . . , M t M r ,<label>(19)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">F = f1 • • • fMt , W = [ ŵ1 • • • ŵMr ] , c n = [c 1,n • • • c Mt,n ] and d n = [d 1,n • • • d Mr,n ] .</formula><p>According to ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">17</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_30">19</ref>), the n th column in B can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">B [:,n] = f n ⊗ w n = Fc n ⊗ Wd n = F ⊗ W (c n ⊗ d n ) ,<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where we have used the property To continue, we will make use of the following lemma, and its proof is given in the appendix. Hence by Lemma 1 the matrix G defined in (21) has full rank. Using the property that rank(A 1 ⊗ A 2 ) =rank(A 1 )rank(A 2 ), we have that in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> the square matrix [ f1 , . . . , fMt ] ⊗ [ ŵ1 , . . . , ŵMr ] has full rank. Thus rank(B) =rank(G) = M t M r , which concludes the proof of Theorem 1.</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">(A 1 A 2 )⊗(A 3 A 4 ) = (A 1 ⊗ A 3 )(A 2 ⊗ A 4 )</formula><p>Remark: To avoid the MUSIC spectrum ambiguity, Theorem 1 provides us with a sufficient condition on the beamformers F and W in (5) so that the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method can uniquely identify the path angles. It can be seen as an extension of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, where the spectrum ambiguity of the one-dimensional MUSIC has been analyzed. The first condition guarantees no zero vector in the direction matrix, otherwise the full column rank condition in Proposition 1 will be violated. The second condition enables us to perform the rank analysis about F and W separately, rather than analyzing the direction matrix directly. This theorem also shows that to perform direction finding, the number of RF chains can be smaller than the number of paths, i.e., we can uniquely identify K path directions even with max{M t , M r } &lt; K. In particular, if we have M t = N t , M r = N r , and set F = I Nt , W = I Nr , then <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref> turns into the element-space MUSIC spectrum.</p><p>Corollary 1. The two-dimensional element-space MUSIC method can distinctly estimate N t N r -1 path directions.</p><p>Proof: It can be proved by checking conditions 1) and 2) with F = I Nt , W = I Nr . Obviously condition 1) is naturally satisfied. Condition 2) is also satisfied considering the fact that [a t (φ 1 ), . . . , a t (φ MtMr )] and [a r (θ 1 ), . . . , a r (θ MtMr )] are Vandermonde matrices.</p><p>As we have seen, the element-space MUSIC naturally avoids the spectrum ambiguity. However, its beamspace counterpart may be plagued by ambiguity under inappropriate beamformers. In the next subsection, we show that the DFT beamformers F D and W D given by ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_35">24</ref>) satisfy the two conditions in Theorem 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. DFT Beamformers</head><p>Assuming the uniform linear array spaced with halfwavelength is used at the transmitter, the antenna array response can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">a t (φ) = 1 √ N t 1, e jπφ , . . . , e j(Nt-1)πφ ∈ C Nt ,<label>(22)</label></formula><p>and the antenna array response at the receiver a r (θ) can be written in a similar way.</p><p>Based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>, the DFT beamformers at the transmitter and receiver are given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> F D = a t ( φ1 ) a t ( φ2 ) . . . a t ( φMt ) ∈ C Nt×Mt , W D = a r ( θ1 ) a r ( θ2 ) . . . a r ( θMr ) ∈ C Nr×Mr , <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> where</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">φi = φ1 + 2 N t (i -1), i = 1, . . . , M t , θj = θ1 + 2 N r (j -1), j = 1, . . . , M r .<label>(24)</label></formula><p>We can set φ1 and θ1 ∈ [-1, 1], then φMt and θMr may exceed 1 and the beams just wrap around. For example if φMt &gt; 1, we can let the M th t beam steer at φMt + 2k 0 , where k 0 is the integer that satisfies φMt + 2k 0 ∈ [-1, 1]. The beamforming sectors can be defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">Ω φ = [ φ1 , φMt ] and Ω θ = [ θ1 , θMr ] 4 .</formula><p>loss of generality, we assume that F D in ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>) corresponds to the first M t columns of the DFT matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">M F D = a t ( φ1 ) a t ( φ2 ) . . . a t ( φNt ) . (<label>25</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_38">)</formula><p>Similarly we assume that W D corresponds to the first M r columns of the DFT matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">M W D = a r ( θ1 ) a r ( θ2 ) . . . a r ( θNr ) . (<label>26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">)</formula><p>Here the DFT angles { φi } Nt i=1 and { θi } Nr i=1 are defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>.</p><p>Corollary 2. The two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method, whose null spectrum is defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>, can distinctly estimate M t M r -1 path directions using the DFT beamformers defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> for uniform linear array with half-wavelength spacing.</p><p>Proof: If suffices to show that conditions 1) and 2) in Theorem 1 hold with the DFT beamformers defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref>.</p><p>By the orthogonality of the DFT matrix, we have </p><formula xml:id="formula_41">F H D a( φi ) = 0 for i = M t +</formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">F H D i=1 a i a(φ i ) = 0 , a i = 0 ,<label>(27)</label></formula><p>which means that</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">Mt i=1 a i a(φ i ) is in the null space of F H D . Then we can write Mt i=1 a i a(φ i ) = Nt-Mt j=1 b j a( φj+Mt ) , a i = 0, b j = 0 . (28)</formula><p>However, the N t vectors in the above equation are linearly independent considering the fact that a(φ 1 ) . . . a(φ Mt ) a( φMt+1 ) . . . a( φNt ) is a Vandermonde matrix. So <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> can not hold. Similar argument applies to W D . Hence condition 2) is also verified.</p><p>Remark: According to the result in <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method can uniquely estimate at least M t +M r -2 path directions using the DFT beamformers. Our result indicates that the number of resolvable path directions is actually much larger.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. LS Estimation of Path Gains</head><p>Once the path angles are estimated by the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method, we can form the estimate B of the direction matrix in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>. Then we can use the least-squares method to estimate the path gains. Specifically, based on (8), the LS estimate of the path gains is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">α(q) = M t E B H B -1 B H y(q), q = 1, 2, . . . , N .<label>(29)</label></formula><p>The rank of the direction matrix has been analyzed in the proof of Theorem 1. Since the DFT beamformers satisfy conditions 1) and 2), as stated in Corollary 2, it is guaranteed that B has full column-rank using DFT beamformers. It should be noticed that the order of the elements in α(q) is determined by B. In other words, the k th element in α(q) is the gain of the path whose direction contributes to the k th column of B. Finally the procedure of proposed two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC (2-D BMUSIC) method for mm-wave channel estimation is summarized in Algorithm 1.</p><p>Algorithm 1 2-D BMUSIC mm-wave channel estimator.</p><p>1: Initialization: The noise covariance matrix σ 2 I MtMr . The number of paths K. R y = 0. Estimate the Path Directions 2: Form sample covariance and perform eigenvalue decomposition</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">R y = 1 N N q=1 y(q)y(q) H = [ U s | U n ]diag{λ 1 , λ 2 , . . . , λ MtMr }[ U s | U n ] H</formula><p>where U n consists of eigenvectors corresponding to the smallest M t M r -K eigenvalues. 3: Scan the 2-D BMUSIC directional spectrum defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> to find the K poles that provide the estimates of the path directions {φ k , θ k } K k=1 . There are G φ and G θ search grids within Ω φ and Ω θ respectively.</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">4: Compute A T = [a t (φ 1 ) . . . a t (φ K )], A R = [a r (θ 1 ) . . . a r (θ K )], and B [:,k] = b(φ k , θ k ), k = 1, . . . , K.</formula><p>Estimate the Block-Fading Channel 5: for q = 1 to N do 6:</p><p>Estimate the instantaneous path gains α(q) according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>. Then the block channel is estimated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">H(q) = A R diag( α(q)) A H T 7: end for Remark:</formula><p>The main computational complexity of the above channel estimation algorithm includes that for the eigenvalue decomposition on line 2, which is 3 t M 3 r ), and that for the grid search on line 3, which is</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">O(G φ G θ M 2 t M 2 r )</formula><p>. The LS estimator is used here because of its low computational complexity, which is O(K 2 M t M r +K 3 ) <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">5</ref> . In practice, we can replace the grid search step by the well known root-MUSIC technique to reduce the computational complexity. Denoting z t = e jπφ and z r = e jπθ , the root-MUSIC method estimates the path directions by calculating the roots of the null spectrum defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>, which can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">D(φ, θ) = (a t (z t ) ⊗ a r (z r )) H (F ⊗ W) U n U H n (F ⊗ W) H (a t (z t ) ⊗ a r (z r )) ,<label>(30)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">a t (z t ) = [1 z t . . . z Nt-1 t ] , a r (z r ) = [1 z r . . . z Nr-1 r</formula><p>] , and we have used the fact that b(φ, θ) = (F ⊗ W)</p><p>H (a t (z t ) ⊗ a r (z r )). The roots of (30) can be calculated according to the procedure shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, where the two-dimensional element-space root-MUSIC is considered. Since ambiguous poles in the MUSIC spectrum correspond to ambiguous roots in the root-MUSIC, the conditions presented in Theorem 1 also avoid ambiguous roots caused by beamformers in the two-dimensional beamspace root-MUSIC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. SIMULATION RESULTS</head><p>In this section, we present simulation results to illustrate the performance of the proposed channel estimator. The uniform linear arrays at the transmitter and receiver are equipped with N t = 32 and N r = 16 antenna elements respectively. There are M t = 8 RF chains at the transmitter and M r = 4 RF chains at the receiver. The DFT beamformers defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> are used in the simulations. For the mm-wave channel, we assume that in the considered beamforming sector Ω φ = [-0.2188, 0.2188] and Ω θ = [-0.1875, 0.1875], all K paths have equal power, i.e., σ 2 k = 1, k = 1, . . . , K <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. It should be noticed that the equal power assumption enables us to focus on investigating the spectrum ambiguity caused by the beamformers in the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method. At the band, the indoor measurements in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> and the outdoor measurements in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> show that the number of significant resolvable paths most likely ranges from 1 to 4, including the LoS path and the NLoS ones. The path directions {(φ k , θ k )} K are randomly generated with uniform distribution in [-1, 1]. The signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) is defined as E Ntσ 2 . For the channel estimation performance, we compare the proposed 2-D BMUSIC method with the beam training scheme in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, the Dantzig selector (DS) -based estimator in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>  6 , and the orthogonal matching pursuit (OMP) -based estimator in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. All results are averaged over 100 frames with N = 40, and in all channel realizations, the path directions {(φ k , θ k )} K k=1 are kept fixed so the variation is only caused by the path gains {α k (q)} K k=1 . In each block, the proposed 2-D BMUSIC method, the DS-based estimator, and the OMP-based estimator (N Beam t = 32, N Beam r = 16) use 8, 100, 128 training slots respectively. For the beam training scheme (k 0 = 2), the required number of training slots is 20 in the case K = 1 (G = 1024) and 288 in the case K = 3 (G = 768). Hence the training overhead of the proposed method is much smaller than that of the other methods to be compared. The grid resolution for AoD and AoA are denoted as ∆φ and ∆θ respectively.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref>, we show the channel estimation performance of different channel estimators with a single path. The normalized mean-squared error (NMSE) is defined as E{ H -H 2 F / H 2 F }, where H denotes the estimate of the channel. For the beam training scheme, ∆φ = ∆θ = 0.002. For the OMP-based estimator, ∆φ = 0.0055 and ∆θ = 0.0047. For the proposed 2-D BMUSIC channel estimator, ∆φ = 0.0055 and ∆θ = 0.0047.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref>(a), the channel estimator based on 2-D BMUSIC shows considerable performance gain. It is caused by the fact that the proposed channel estimator can benefit from the super-resolution MUSIC method, which significantly increases the estimation accuracy of the path directions. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref>(b), 6 The DS-based estimator presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> does not contain the beamformers, we thus use the fully digital outputs of the antenna array to implement the DS-based estimator.     (c) The two-dimensional beamspace directional spectrum with an ambiguous direction. SNR = 2dB.  we show the MSE of the estimated path angles, which is defined as E{(φ 1 -φ1 ) 2 + (θ 1 -θ1 ) 2 }. As we can see, the proposed channel estimator can find the path direction with very high accuracy. For the beam training scheme, we use dense grids which enables high angular resolution. However, as pointed out in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, the beam training scheme may possibly miss the path during the training stages. We thus show the detection probability of the path direction in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3(c)</ref>, where a successful detection means that the estimated AoD/AoD locates within half beamwidth from the real one <ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">7</ref> . As we have expected, the beam training scheme has relatively low detection probability.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">4</ref> </p><p>Nr respectively (i.e., φ2 = φ1 + 3 Nt and θ2 = θ1 + 5 Nr ). As a result, a spurious pole arises in the MUSIC spectrum, which causes spectrum ambiguity and disables the MUSIC method. The true path directions in the figure are 0.0685), (-0.0976, -0.1032), (0.0325, -0.0242), and the pseudo pole is in the direction (-0.1696, -0.0645). With these information, we can verify that the augmented direction matrix B a defined in Proposition 1 is approximately column rank deficient 8 . Not surprisingly, the scanning resolution has direct impact on the estimation accuracy of the path directions. We thus show the impact of the spectrum scanning resolution on the NMSE performance of the 2-D BMUSIC-based estimator in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">4(d)</ref>. Obviously the higher scanning resolution (i.e., larger G φ and G θ ) leads to the better estimation accuracy of the path directions, and thus the better NMSE performance. However, to increase the scanning resolution will inevitably increase the computational overhead. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have proposed a new high-resolution mm-wave channel estimation method by exploiting the fact that the path angles vary much more slowly than the path gains. A number of blocks of received signals are used to first estimate the path angles by searching the poles of the two-dimensional beamspace directional spectrum. We provide sufficient conditions based on which the beamformers can be designed to maximize the number of resolvable path directions. We further show that the popular DFT beamformers satisfy these conditions. Unlike the channel estimators based on the sparsity of angle grids, the proposed method benefits from the high-resolution of angle separation of the MUSIC method. Once the angles are estimated, the fading gains in each block within the frame can then be estimated using the least-squares method. Simulation results have demonstrated that with similar angle resolutions, the proposed two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC channel estimator achieves significantly higher estimation accuracy compared with existing methods, with much lower training slots. In this paper, we have focused on the 2-D channel models. For future work, we can extend the proposed method and the analysis to the 3-D case. Moreover, it would be interesting to extend the proposed scheme to MIMO-OFDM systems to solve the wideband mm-wave channel estimation problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head><p>To prove that the square matrix G has full rank, we show that if Gx = 0, then x = 0.</p><p>According to condition (b), we can arbitrarily pick M r columns from D to form a basis set. Without loss of generality, we select the first M r columns {d i } Mr i=1 as the basis, and the remaining column vectors can be represented as</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">d i = Mr j=1 β i j d j , i = M r + 1, . . . , M t M r .<label>(31)</label></formula><p>Then G can be explicitly written as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>. Notice that β i j = 0 according to condition (b).</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>, the first M r rows of Gx is a linear combination of the basis {d i } Mr i=1 . Thus we can write G [1:Mr,:] x = Mr i=1 λ 1 i d i . So if there exits x such that G [1:Mr,:] x = 0, then λ 1 = [λ 1 i . . . λ 1 Mr ] = 0 because {d i } Mr i=1 are linearly independent. The same argument applies to each of the remaining M t -1 row blocks, which leads to <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>.</p><p>Considering the matrix E ∈ C MtMr×MtMr in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>, it is obvious that any two rows with c i,j in different positions in the first M r columns cannot be linearly dependent since c i,j = 0 according to condition (a). We can permutate the rows of E into M r blocks E i , i = 1, . . . , M r , which is defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref>.</p><p>If we delete the zero columns in E i , we can write the new block matrix as So we get rank(E i ) = rank(E i ) = M t , i = 1, . . . , M r . Then rank(E) = M r × rank(E i ) = M t M r . Since the square matrix E in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref> has full rank, we can only have x = 0, which concludes the proof. </p><formula xml:id="formula_53">E i = [c i ,</formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Theorem 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>If the following two conditions are satisfied 1) for any (φ, θ)∈ (Ω φ , Ω θ ), we have F H a(φ) = 0 and W H a(θ) = 0, 2) for any {φ i |F H a(φ i ) = 0} MtMr i=1and {θ i |W H a(θ i ) = 0} MtMr i=1 , we have spark 3 F H [a t (φ 1 ) . . . a t (φ MtMr )]) = M t + 1 and spark W H [a r (θ 1 ) . . . a r (θ MtMr )] = M r + 1, then the two-dimensional beamspace MUSIC method can distinctly estimate K path directions without ambiguity for any K ≤ K max = M t M r -1 path directions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>in the last equation. Finally, we can rewrite B as B = F ⊗ W C D G (21) where C = [c 1 , . . . , c MtMr ] and D = [d 1 , . . . , d MtMr ].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Lemma 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>If the following conditions are satisfied (a) all elements of C are nonzero, (b) spark(C) = M t + 1 and spark(D) = M r + 1, then G defined in (21) has full rank. Next we verify that the matrix C defined in (21) satisfies condition (a). Otherwise suppose that c 1,1 = 0 without loss of generality. Then we get f 1 -Mt i=2 c i,1 fi = 0, which leads to rank([f 1 , f2 , . . . , fMt ]) &lt; M t and contradicts condition 2), since by assumption φ 1 ∈ {υ i } Mt i=1 . We next verify that matrices C and D satisfy condition (b). Note that C is the coordinate matrix of F H A T with respect to the basis set { fi } Mt i=1 , i.e., F H A T = [ f1 . . . fMt ]C, thus we have spark(C) = spark F H A T = M t + 1 by condition (2). Similarly spark(D) = M r + 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>estimator (a) The NMSE performance as a function of SNR.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>estimator (b) The NMSE of path angles as a function of SNR.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>estimator (c) Path detection probability as a function of SNR.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3: The channel estimation performance as a function of SNR. K = 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>∆θ) = (0.0089, 0.0077) (∆φ, ∆θ) = (0.0055, 0.0047) (∆φ, ∆θ) = (0.0044, 0.0038) (∆φ, ∆θ) = (0.0022, 0.0019) (d) The 2-D BMUSIC estimation performance with different scanning resolution.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4: The channel estimation performance with multiple paths K = 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a), we show the channel estimation performance of different channel estimators with K = 3 paths. For the beam training scheme, ∆φ = ∆θ = 0.0026. For the OMPbased estimator, ∆φ = 0.0022 and ∆θ = 0.0019. For the proposed 2-D BMUSIC channel estimator, ∆φ = 0.0022 and ∆θ = 0.0019 unless otherwise specified. The 2-D BMUSIC directional spectrum is shown in Fig. 4(b). As we can see, all the 3 path directions are clearly indicated by the spectrum poles and can be obtained by scanning the spectrum. In Fig. 4(c), however, the second beams in F D and W D shift 1 Nt and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>8</head><label></label><figDesc>Here B a = [b(-0.1850, 0.0685) b(-0.0976, -0.1032) b(0.0325, -0.0242) b(-0.1696, -0.0645)] ∈ C 32×4 . The singular values of B a are 0.81, 0.58, 0.48, and 0.09, based on which we can see that B a is approximately column rank deficient.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>c Mr+1 , . . . , c MtMr ]Γ i ∈ C Mt×(MtMr-Mr+1) ,<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> whereΓ i = diag{1, β Mr+1 i , . . . , β MtMr i }. According to condition (b) spark(C) = M t + 1, hence E i has full row rank.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>c 1 c0</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Mt,1 d 1 • • • c Mt,Mr d Mr c Mt,Mr+1 β Mr+1 Mr • • • c Mt,MtMr β MtMr Mr 1×(i-1) c 1,i 0 1×(Mr-i) . . . . . . . . . 0 1×(i-1) c Mt,i 0 1×(Mr-i) c 1,Mr+1 β Mr+1 i • • • c 1,MtMr β MtMr i . . . . . . . . . c Mt,Mr+1 β Mr+1 i • • • c Mt,MtMr β MtMr i    ∈ C Mt×MtMr(34)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1, . . . , N t . Note that {a( φi )} Nt i=Mt+1 spans the null space of F H D , and the DFT angles { φi } Nt i=Mt+1 are outside the beamforming sector. If there exits a φ ∈ Ω φ making F H D a(φ) = 0, then the null space of F H D would have a dimension larger than N t -M t since {a(φ), a( φMt+1 ), . . . , a( φNt )} are linearly independent. But this contradicts to the fact that rank(F H D ) = M t . The same argument applies to W D . Hence we have verified condition 1). If condition 2) does not hold, then we can find M t linearly dependent columns from the matrix F H D [a t (φ 1 ) . . . a t (φ MtMr )]. Without loss of generality, we assume that the first M t columns are linearly dependent. Then we can write</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_0"><p>spark(A) is the smallest number of linearly dependent columns in A.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_1"><p>If Mt = 1 or Mr = 1, the range of the corresponding beamforming sector can be set equal to the beamwidth. The range of Ω φ and Ω θ can be defined in other ways for different beamformers.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_2"><p>The columns in B can be calculated off-line.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_3"><p>The DS-and OMP-based estimators may produce multiple path directions, we thus regard the element with the highest power as the one indicating the path direction.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under grants 61471115 and 61329101, the 2016 Science and Technology joint research and innovation foundation of Jiangsu province under grant BY2016076-13, the Leading Talents Program of Guangdong Province under grant 00201510, and the Basic Research Program of Shenzhen under grant JCYJ20151117161854942. Ziyu Guo and Wei Heng are with the National Mobile Communications Research Lab., Southeast University, Nanjing 210096, China</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An introduction to millimeter-wave mobile broadband systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Pi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-06">Jun. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Millimeter-wave cellular wireless networks: Potentials and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rangan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Erkip</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-03">Mar. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="366" to="385" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coverage and capacity of millimeter-wave cellular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alkhateeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Heath</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-09">Sep. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Radio propagation path loss models for 5G cellular networks in the 28 GHz and 38 GHz millimeter-wave bands</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sulyman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Nassar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Samimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Maccartney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alsanie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-09">Sep. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-gigabit millimeter wave wireless communications for 5G: from fixed access to cellular networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Vucetic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-01">Jan. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Millimeter wave channel modeling and cellular capacity evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Akdeniz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Samimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rangan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Erkip</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1164" to="1179" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-06">Jun. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Channel estimation and hybrid precoding for millimeter wave cellular systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alkhateeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ayach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Leus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Heath</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Topics Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="831" to="846" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-10">Oct. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploiting spatial sparsity for estimating channels of hybrid MIMO systems in millimeter wave communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G.-T</forename><surname>Gil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Global Commun. Conf. (GLOBECOM)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Global Commun. Conf. (GLOBECOM)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3326" to="3331" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Channel estimation in millimeter wave MIMO systems with one-bit quantization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schniter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Prelcic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Heath</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Asilomar Conf. on Signals, Systems and Computers</title>
		<meeting>Asilomar Conf. on Signals, Systems and Computers</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coding the beams: Improving beamforming training in mmwave communication system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tsang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Poon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Addepalli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Global Telecommunications Conference (GLOBECOM)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Global Telecommunications Conference (GLOBECOM)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-12">Dec. 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beam codebook based beamforming protocol for multi-Gbps millimeter-wave WPAN systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pyo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Baykas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Funada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kojima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1390" to="1399" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-10">Oct. 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast channel estimation for millimeter wave wireless systems using overlapped beam patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kokshoorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Vucetic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Intern. Conf. Commun. (ICC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Intern. Conf. Commun. (ICC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-06">Jun. 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1304" to="1309" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Millimetre wave MIMO channel estimation using overlapped beam patterns and rate adaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kokshoorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Vucetic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1603.01926</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compressed sensing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Donoho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1289" to="1306" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-04">Apr. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatially sparse precoding in millimeter wave MIMO systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ayach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rajagopal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Abu-Surra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Pi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Heath</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1499" to="1513" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-03">Mar. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hybrid adaptive antenna array for long-range mm-wave communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Dyadyuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Antennas Propag. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-04">Apr. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase only RF precoding for massive MIMO systems with limited RF chains</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4505" to="4515" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-09">Sep. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compressed channel sensing: a new approach to estimating sparse multipath channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Bajwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haupt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sayeed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-06">Jun. 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1058" to="1076" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed compressive CSIT estimation and feedback for FDD multi-user massive MIMO systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3261" to="3271" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-06">Jun. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deconstructing multiantenna fading channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sayeed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2563" to="2579" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-10">Oct. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subspace estimation and decomposition for large millimeter-wave MIMO systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ghauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bengtsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Skoglund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Topics Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="528" to="542" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-04">Apr. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iterative joint beamforming training with constant-amplitude phased arrays in millimeter-wave communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="832" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-05">May 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-stage iterative antenna training for millimeter wave communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ngo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Global Telecommunications Conference (GLOBECOM)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-12">Dec. 2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hybrid analog-digital channel estimation and beamforming: training-throughput tradeoff</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bogale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Le</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5235" to="5249" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">Dec 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Moses</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Spectral Analysis of Signals</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Upper Saddle River, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pearson Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Heath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Daniels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Murdock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Millimeter Wave Wireless Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">249</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Joint transmission and reception diversity smoothing for direction finding of coherent targets in MIMO radar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Topics Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-02">Feb 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direction finding with automatic pairing for bistatic MIMO radar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-01">Jan. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ESPRIT-estimation of signal parameters via rotational invariance techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kailath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Acoust., Speech, Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="984" to="995" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-07">Jul. 1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MUSIC, maximum likelihood, and Cramer-Rao bound</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nehorai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Acoust., Speech, Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="720" to="741" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-05">May 1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Avoiding ambiguity in beamspace processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Amini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Georgiou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Process. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="372" to="375" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-05">May 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonparametric detection of signals by information theoretic criteria: performance analysis and an improved estimator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2746" to="2756" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-05">May 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L V</forename><surname>Trees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Optimum Array Processing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A CANDECOM-P/PARAFAC perspective on uniqueness of DOA estimation using a vector sensor array</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Miron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3475" to="2481" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-07">Jul. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polynomial root finding technique for joint DOA DOD estimation in bistatic MIMO radar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bencheikh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2723" to="2730" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-03">Mar. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">His research interests include statistical signal processing and its applications in wireless communications and cyber-physical systems. Xiaodong Wang (S&apos;98-M&apos;98-SM&apos;04-F&apos;08) received the Ph.D. degree in electrical engineering from Princeton University. He is a Professor of electrical engineering at Columbia University in New York. Dr. Wang&apos;s research interests fall in the general areas of computing, signal processing, and communications, and he has published extensively in these areas. Among his publications is a recent book entitled Wireless Communication Systems: Advanced Techniques for Signal Reception</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kukshya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rappaport</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Communications Society and Information Theory Society Joint Paper Award, and the 2011 IEEE Communication Society Award for Outstanding Paper on New Communication Topics. He has served as an Associate Editor for the IEEE Transactions on Communications, the IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, the IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing, and the IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<title level="s">IEEE J. Sel. Areas Commun.</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Shanghai, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">Apr. 2002. 2013. 2015. 2003. 2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="620" to="630" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ziyu Guo received the B.S. Degree in electrical engineering and the Ph.D. degree in communication and information systems both from Southeast University, China in 2011 and 2016 respectively</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Heng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">He received the B.S. degree in information engineering from Huazhong University of Science and Technologies in 1987, the M.S.degree in 1990 in signal and information processing and the Ph.D. degree in 1997 in communications and information system both from Southeast University. During 1997 to 2002 he was a research scholar in the Catholic University of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Mobile Communications Research Laboratory in Southeast University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>His research interests include mobile communications, signal processing</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
