<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">This article has been accepted for inclusion in a future issue of this journal. Content is final as presented, with the exception of pagination</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Azwirman</forename><surname>Gusrialdi</surname></persName>
							<email>azwirman.gusrialdi@ucf.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engi-neering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Central Florida</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>32816</postCode>
									<settlement>Orlando</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Zhihua</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
							<email>qu@ucf.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engi-neering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Central Florida</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>32816</postCode>
									<settlement>Orlando</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Life Fellow, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Marwan</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Simaan</surname></persName>
							<email>simaan@eecs.ucf.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engi-neering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Central Florida</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>32816</postCode>
									<settlement>Orlando</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">This article has been accepted for inclusion in a future issue of this journal. Content is final as presented, with the exception of pagination</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1B137276E0C4DB352F270539FC952CB6</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TITS.2017.2661958</idno>
					<note type="submission">received February 16, 2016; revised June 28, 2016, October 19, 2016, and January 19, 2017; accepted January 22, 2017.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T09:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Electric vehicles&apos; charging</term>
					<term>transportation networks</term>
					<term>distributed consensus algorithm</term>
					<term>cooperative control</term>
					<term>dynamical systems</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The increasing number of electric vehicles (EVs) on highways calls for the installment of adequate charging infrastructure. Since charging infrastructure has limited capacity, EVs need to wait at a charging station to get charged, and their waiting times may differ significantly from one location to another. This paper aims at developing a strategy to coordinate the queues among the charging stations, with only local information about traffic flows and the status of EV charging stations along a bidirectional highway, so that excessively long waiting times can be avoided. Specifically, a distributed algorithm is presented to schedule EV flows into neighboring charging stations, so that EVs are all appropriately served along the highway and that all the charging resources are uniformly utilized. In addition, a distributed decision making policy is developed to influence the aggregate number of EVs entering any given service station, so that each EV makes an appropriate decision (i.e., whether or not it should enter the next charging station) by contributing positively to meeting the desired queue length at service stations and by considering its own battery constraint. Performance improvement of the proposed strategy is illustrated via one of the highways in the United States, namely the Florida Turnpike.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>I T IS expected that by 2020 there will be not less than 3.1 million of electric vehicles (EVs) in use in the United States <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. The adoption of a large number of EVs can bring many advantages in comparison to internal combustion engine vehicles, including higher efficiency, lower carbon emission and less pollution <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. However, EVs have a more limited driving range (from 38 to 270 miles <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>) and, for long distance travels, they need to be charged periodically along the way. Therefore, the combination of the limited driving range, the long charging times (30 mins to 8 hours <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>), and the customer's satisfaction level when they wait for their EVs to get charged may have a direct impact on decisions by consumers to adopt the use of EVs in the future.</p><p>Numerous factors including installment of new charging infrastructure, advances in battery and charging technology, and development of smart (coordinated) charging strategy play an important role in addressing the above challenges. This paper focuses on the EVs' charging scheduling problem, a current topic of research, whose goal is to optimally utilize the existing charging network or infrastructure by taking advantage of information and communication technologies (ICT).</p><p>In particular, we study the scenario that along a bidirectional highway there are a number of service stations equipped with EV chargers. The chargers are located at service stations (typically close to a set of entrances and exits) where EV drivers would choose to charge their vehicles. It is obvious that, while battery charging time depends only upon the charger technology, waiting times of EVs at service stations are highly dependent upon traffic flows and may become unacceptably long with a local increase of EVs entering a given service station. Without appropriate scheduling and coordination, utilization of the charging stations on the highway may become very unbalanced since EV drivers do not have adequate information to decide where and when to charge their vehicles (e.g., each individual EV chooses randomly where to charge their batteries). This calls for both a scheduling algorithm of directing EV flows into service stations and a distributed decision model to facilitate individual EV drivers to make better charging decisions.</p><p>Literature review: Apart from studies on charging station infrastructure planning (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>), the EVs' charging scheduling problem has also received considerable attention in the literature, see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</p><p>Qin and Zhang <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> propose a (centralized) scheduling algorithm based on Dijkstras algorithm and by combining both the transport and power grid information to find optimal path for the EVs which improves the performance of the grid and transport systems, namely relieving traffic congestion, reducing power loss and optimizing load curve. Similarly, a hierarchical game approach is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> for navigation of EVs' charging by taking into account the impact from both the transportation and power systems and aimed at improving the economic benefits of the charging stations and the reliability of the power grid. Apart from the above results which consider both the transportation and power systems, much of the literature on EVs' charging scheduling has focussed solely on the transportation system for either urban or highway environments with the goal of balancing the demand across the charging network, reducing the queue length, or minimizing total travel time and waiting time at the charging stations. For example, the work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> proposes a dynamic charging assignment method for the EVs to optimize the charging station utilization and thus minimize the EVs' waiting time. The algorithm is computed via Simulated Annealing algorithm by a centralized control platform. Li et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> compare two charging station selection algorithms based on local information of an EV and global information obtained from a central server. It is shown that utilization of global information on the charging station workload helps improving the waiting time for the EVs. A routing problem is solved offline and in a centralized manner based on dynamic programming in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> for EVs on a network of charging nodes whose goal is to minimize the total traveling and charging time. Coninx et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> consider a scenario where EV drivers inquire the central controller for advice about specific charging station to choose and the relevant route to use. The drivers are to find the best tradeoff between the whole trip time, including waiting time at the charging station. The problem is solved in a centralized manner using the global information on the road traffic, location of charging stations and their occupancy. An algorithm of directing EV flows to charging stations is proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> to distribute the charging load and to minimize queuing time by having the EVs communicate with the transportation network.</p><p>Note that all the aforementioned results require global network information and centrally computing algorithms. Distributed EV charging and scheduling problem has recently been investigated to a limited extent, and a few results are now available. Bodet et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> propose a distributed strategy based on charging station reservation for scheduling the EV's charging so that the average waiting time is minimized. First, it is proven under certain assumptions (e.g. each station has equal charging capacity) that the waiting time is minimized if utilizations of all stations are equal. Based on this insight, the authors then propose a distributed method for locally balancing distribution of charging demands in order to approximate the system-wide distribution. A decentralized policy is designed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> to assign EVs to a network of charging stations with the goal of minimizing the queueing time. However, no precise analytic guarantees on load balancing is provided. Closer to our proposed method, Tan and Wang <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> propose a distributed scheduling approach based on A* algorithm and that makes use of charging station reservation system aimed at minimizing the total travel time for each EV.</p><p>It is worth noting that, in all the results of distributed scheduling, there is no rigorous analysis or proof, and validation is done by simulation alone. In addition, the dynamics/ changes in the transportation system such as time varying traffic flow are not explicitly considered in the design of the algorithms. Recent survey of algorithms for EV's charging can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statement of contributions:</head><p>We propose an analyticallyproven algorithm to distributively schedule EV's charging and optimize the utilization of charging resources along a highway.</p><p>Our first contribution is the development of dynamical model for average flow of EVs along the highway coupled with queues at the service stations. The dynamical model is used to design and investigate stability of the algorithm which adapts to the changes of communication network (in connectivity and delay) and transportation network (in flows and charging equipment availability). In contrast to the mathematical model of EV's charging demand based on fluid dynamic traffic model (represented by partial differential equation) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, our model is an aggregated average model in the discrete time domain and its simplicity/flexibility facilitates the analysis and design of the scheduling algorithm with performance guarantee.</p><p>The second contribution is the development of a distributed scheduling algorithm and a cooperative control algorithm for EVs' charging. In contrast to centralized algorithm where all data for the optimization or control is collected at a central aggregator which may require high-bandwidth communication and thus pose a potential bottleneck and delay, distributed algorithm is highly desirable due to its scalability (which reduces the computational and communication costs) with respect to the size of the EVs and charging network since it only requires local knowledge about the system. In a centralized system, the central aggregator is also vulnerable to a single point-of-failure which may yield the collapse of the whole system. Moreover, since for the case of centralized algorithm all data including the one containing the privacy of the EV drivers is collected at a central aggregator, the risk of exposing the data to cyber-attacks is also increased. On the other hand, distributed algorithm is robust to information intermittency in both communication networks and transportation network. For example, when a communication link between the service stations is broken, the information can still be transmitted using an alternative communication path which makes the entire system remain functional.</p><p>The distributed scheduling algorithm is inspired by the consensus algorithm and relies solely on information of local traffic flows at the neighboring service stations. Its objective is to schedule and direct the percentage of the EVs that enter each station. Note that recently the consensus algorithm has been applied to intelligent transportation systems such as for controlling vehicle platoons for highway safety <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> or for controlling traffic density in a highway network <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>.</p><p>Based on the optimized number of EVs that should enter each service station, a distributed algorithm of cooperative control is used as the decision making algorithm by taking advantage of local vehicle-to-infrastructure and vehicleto-vehicle communications. Specifically, this algorithm is designed for each EV to determine whether or not to pass a specific service station by taking into account its own battery charge constraints while meeting the desired flow level from the scheduling algorithm. The combination of the two algorithms ensures a uniform utilization of the available charging facility along the highway and in turn minimizes the aggregate waiting time of all the EVs that need to be charged as shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Note that our optimization objective is global in the sense that it involves (explicitly) all charging facilities on the highway, in contrast to the work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> which considers the (local) minimization of the performance of individual EV. Finally, in comparison to the preliminary version of our work on this problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, we propose in this paper a better distributed scheduling algorithm together with an improved decision making algorithm that preserves data privacy of each EV, and we also provide extensive simulations using the real traffic flow data from the Florida turnpike.</p><p>Organization: The rest of the paper is organized into 4 sections. In section II, discrete-time dynamic models are presented to describe the average flow of electric vehicles passing through the entrances/exits and entering the service stations, the proposed scheduling and control problem of electric vehicle charging is defined, and the objectives of the proposed algorithms are prescribed. In section III, the proposed consensus algorithm of distributed scheduling is presented for the transportation network, and its properties are rigorously analyzed. In section IV, the decision making algorithm based on cooperative control is proposed for individual drivers and studied. In section V, the Florida turnpike is used as the case study, and its traffic flow data are used to evaluate efficacy of the proposed algorithms. In section VI, conclusions are drawn.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. MODELING &amp; PROBLEM STATEMENT</head><p>Highways, such as the Florida Turnpike, consist of a fixed number of entrances/exits, service stations typically locate at or close to a subset of these entrances/exits, and these stations are upgraded to have EV chargers, which is illustrated by figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p><p>In what follows, we first model the average flow of EVs entering/passing through entrances/exits. Then, we choose to use the M/M/c queueing model to describe the number of EVs entering and waiting to be charged at service stations. These models contain the decision variables for which optimization and control problems can be formulated and solved. The scheduling problem aims at uniform utilization of the charging infrastructure within the transportation network, the problem of intelligent decision making by individual drivers calls for coordination with the network and among drivers, and both the problems need to be solved without requiring global information. For the sake of readability, the notations used in this paper are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. A Model for Average EV Flow</head><p>Consider an one-direction traffic flow along the highway segment, for example the northbound flow, and assume that there are N nodes (which include both extrances and exits) and they are numbered in an ascending order from south to north, as shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. Then, the following discrete-time model in figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> can be used to quantify the average traffic flow. That is, the average northbound vehicle flow α i (k) that approaches the i th node is defined as where k is the unit time increment, γ i is the net northbound flow increase (due to vehicles entering node i from local roadways through entrance/exit i ), y i-1 (kd i-1,i ) is the average EV flow coming from node (i -1) to node i , and d i-1,i denotes the travel time (of unit time increment) needed from one node to the next. At time k, the northbound continuing flow from the i th node can be calculated using</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">α i (k) = γ i (k), when i = 1 γ i (k) + y i-1 (k -d i-1,i ), if i = 1</formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">y i (k) = α i (k) + g i (k) -f i (k), (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">)</formula><p>where g i (k) is the northbound flow coming out from service station i , and f i (k) is the average flow entering the i th service station. Should node i have no service station, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">g i (k) = f i (k) = 0.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. A Queueing Model for Service Stations</head><p>Let the number of EVs at service station i at time k be denoted by x i (k) ≥ 0. The EV flow from the highway interacts with queue state x i (k) at the i th service station according to the following dynamics:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">x i (k + 1) = x i (k) + f i (k) -g i (k), f i (k) = p i (k)α i (k),<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where p i (k) ∈ [0, 1] is the percentage (portion) of EVs that approach the i th node and choose to enter its service station i . Let c i be the number of EV chargers at service station i which always serve from the front of its queue. As illustrated by figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>, an EV enters a service station by getting into the charging queue there until one of charging stations becomes open for it to use (i.e., first-come-first-served rule). Moreover, we assume that the capacity for the EVs to queue is sufficiently large. 1 We utilize the stochastic model to analyze the queue since the EVs arrival time and the service time at the station are not known, i.e., random in general. Specifically, we model the relationship between f i (k), μ i (k) and x i (k) as an M/M/c i queue, a standardized model for birth-death processes depicted in figure 4. To be more precise, the M/M/c i queue as a stochastic process has its states defined by the set ℵ = {0, 1, 2, 3, • • • }. In other words, the queue is the Markov process denoted by {x i (k) = l : l ∈ ℵ}. In this queue model, the mean arrival rate of the EVs at service station i , denoted by f i (k), is modeled as a Poisson process. The assumption on Poisson arrival process for the EVs is appropriate (and has been verified by experiments in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>) since in general the total number of vehicles on the highway is very large, 1 Otherwise, another model could be used and that model can include the impact on continuing traffic flow. a single EV uses a small percentage of highway and each EV makes independent decision to enter the highway/service station <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. Moreover, the charging times (i.e., service rate) is given by μ i and has an exponential distribution, which is confirmed for constant charging power by the commute distance distribution in <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. Note that the M/M/c i queue model has also been widely used in the EV's charging related literature for purpose of analysis, see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. The boundedness of the queue is guaranteed if the following condition is satisfied at the steady state:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">f i &lt; c i μ i (3)</formula><p>namely, the steady-flow number of EVs entering charging station i should be less than capacity of the station.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. A Simple Energy Model of EVs</head><p>In general, the energy consumption of EVs depend on many factors such as driving cycles <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. However, for the sake of simplicity in this paper we model the electricity consumption of the vth EV as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">e - v,i+1 = e + v,i -d i,i+1 r - v ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where e - v,i+1 is the state of charge of the vth vehicle as it approaches node (i + 1), e + v,i is the state of charge as it leaves node i , and r - v is the battery usage rate of the v-th vehicle. Let u v,i ∈ {0, 1} be the decision variable for individual EV and is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">u v,i = ⎧ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ 1 if vehicle v choose to charge at service station i 0 otherwise.<label>(5)</label></formula><p>When the vth EV departs service station i , its state of charge status becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">e + v,i = u v,i e v,max + (1 -u v,i )e - v,i ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where e v,max denotes the maximum capacity of its battery. Models ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">5</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">6</ref>) assume that an EV will leave with a full charge after entering a service station. Other models can be accommodated similarly so that partial charging or earlier departure can also be considered.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Distributed Scheduling and Cooperative Control</head><p>The objective of this paper is two-fold. The first goal is to design decision variables p i (k) in (2) for each service station so that the total charging demands are allocated equally across the network. In other words, we aim to optimize operation of highway network, namely all service stations on the highway are uniformly utilized. Let x i (k) c i μ i denote the utilization of service station i . The problem can be mathematically stated as to solve the following optimization problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">min p i (k) max i x i (k) c i μ i -min j x j (k) c j μ j =J<label>(7)</label></formula><p>distributively using only the (local) information of</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">y i-1 (k -d i-1,i ), x i-1 (k -1), γ i (k), x i (k -1)</formula><p>, and x i+1 (k -1) from the neighboring service stations.</p><p>The second goal is to design a cooperative decision making algorithm for individual EV, i.e., u v,i (k) in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">6</ref>), to choose a specific service station for charging by attempting to meet the optimally scheduled flow level in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> while taking into consideration its own state of charge, which is illustrated by figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>. In addition, the policy should also guarantee the EVs with low State-of-Charge (SoC) to receive first priority to be charged at the nearest service station. In order to formulate the problem, let N i (k) be the set of EVs approaching the i th service station and without loss of any generality, we assume the size of the set |N i (k)|=α i (k). Furthermore, let the solution to (7) be given by p * i (k). When approaching service station i , the EVs interact with neighboring EVs from the set N i and receive the information of p * i (k) from the service station by means of wireless communication as shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>. The EVs negotiate with the neighboring EVs based on its battery status to choose the best service station for it to get charged. The problem can then be mathematically stated as to solve the following optimization problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">min u v,i (k) p * i (k) -v u v,i (k) α i (k) 2 subject to e + v,i ≥ d i,i+1 r - v if i ∈ N i (k), u v,i (k) ∈ {0, 1}.<label>(8)</label></formula><p>The first constraint ensures that an EV will be charged at service station i whenever it does not have sufficient energy to reach the next service station.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. CONSENSUS-BASED DISTRIBUTED SCHEDULING ALGORITHM</head><p>In this section, we develop a scheduling algorithm to solve the distributed optimization problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. To this end, note that since x i (k) ≥ 0, we have J ≥ 0. The minimum of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">7</ref>) is then given by J min = min J = 0 obtained when</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">x 1 (k) c 1 μ 1 = • • • = x N (k) c N μ N .</formula><p>In other words, the cost function ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">7</ref>) is minimized when the utilization x i c i μ i reach a consensus for all service stations. In fact, the cost function J in (7) also serves as a Lyapunov function for the consensus protocol which will be presented in section III-C <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. Therefore, the optimization problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> can be reformulated as to find p * i (k) such that for all service stations i ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">p i (k) = p * i (k) ⇒ x i (k) c i μ i → η 0 (k). (<label>9</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">)</formula><p>In the remainder of this section, using the steady state solution of M/M/c i queue and for flow dynamics given in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">1</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">2</ref>), a consensus law is designed as the distributed solution to the scheduling problem that needs to be solved at the service stations. Moreover, we show convergence to a consensus followed by stability analysis of its value.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Approximation of EV Flow Out Using Steady State Solution of M/M/c i Queue</head><p>Before proceeding, we first need to derive the analytical expression of EV flow out at service station i as a function of the state x i . As described in section II-B, the charging service at service station i is modeled by the M/M/c i queue with mean arrival rate f i (k) and service rate μ i . It is known that the steady solution of x i (k) is equal to <ref type="bibr">[39, p. 214</ref>]</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">x i = ρ c i +1 i c i c i ! 1 (1 -ρ i /c i ) 2 ϕ i,0 + ρ i , ϕ i,0 = c i -1 n=0 ρ n i n! + ρ c i i c i !(1 -ρ i /c i ) -1 , (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_16">)</formula><p>where ρ i = f i /μ i denotes the utilization of the chargers at service station i . Next, at the steady state we have from (2) that the output flow from the service station is equal to g i = f i . Substituting this into <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, the input-output relationship between the dynamics (2) and the M/M/c i queue can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">x i = g c i +1 i μ c i +1 i c i c i ! 1 (1 -g i /μ i c i ) 2 ϕ i,0 + g i μ i , ϕ i,0 = c i -1 n=0 g n i μ n i n! + g c i i μ c i i c i ![1 -g i /(μ i c i )] -1</formula><p>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> Note that an identical result to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> is also obtained by applying the pointwise stationary approximation (PSA) method as presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>. Obtaining the analytical expression for g i (x i ) from ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>) is in general impossible. However, for the case of a single charger, i.e., c i = 1, the steady state solution simply reduces to</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">x i = g i μ i -g i ⇒ g i = μ i x i 1 + x i . (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_19">)</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>. Comparison between EV flow out function g i (x i ) in ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>) and its approximation ĝi (x i ) in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">13</ref>):</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">μ i = 2 and c i = 4.</formula><p>In order to derive the closed-form input-output solution of g i (x i ) (which is necessary to proceed with the design and analysis in the next subsection), in this paper we propose to decouple a single M/M/c i queue into c i M/M/1 queues. Using this idea and from <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>, the input-output solution g i (x i ) to equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> can then be approximated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">ĝi (x i ) = c i μ i x i 1 + x i . (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">)</formula><p>We compare the solution <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> with the numerical solution to equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> in order to evaluate whether the proposed approximation is suitable, and the comparison is shown in figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>. It is obvious from figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> that the approximation in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">13</ref>) is suitable for analytical design. Note that due to the over-approximation, as shown in figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>, it is possible that ĝi (x i ) &gt; x i when x i &lt; c i μ i which can be interpreted as all EVs are leaving the station since the queue length is less than the charging station's capacity. In the simulation, a constraint x i ≥ 0 is added as mentioned in Section II-B so that the queue length will not be negative for this particular case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Distributed Estimation Network of Total Charging Needs</head><p>Due to their constrained ranges, EVs need periodic charging during their long-haul travels. Let β i (k) denote the average number of charging required per vehicle for EVs passing through node i at time k. The value β i (k) is computed using the collected information at the i th node at time k including their battery status in (4) and their distances to destination. The total charging needs of the network is then given by N j =1 β j (k)γ j (k) . In the following we design an observer for each service station to estimate distributively the total charging needs of the network.</p><p>In order to gather locally information on charging needs, when an EV enters the highway at node i and at time t = kT , we assume that, with the help of vehicle-toinfrastructure (V2I) communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, it will register itself to be included in γ i (k), as depicted in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>. Each node then exchange information with their neighboring nodes by the means of infrastructure-to-infrastructure (I2I) communication and implement the following observer to distributively estimate the total charging need: for t ∈ [kT, (k + 1)T ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">η1 = ζ -η 1 + 2η 1 3 + η 2 3 ηi = ζ -η i + η i-1 3 + η i 3 + η i+1 3 , i = 2, • • • , (N -1) ηN = ζ -η N + 2η N-1 3 + η N 3 , (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">)</formula><p>where ζ is the controller gain and</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">η i (kT ) = N β i (k)γ i (k) .</formula><p>Observer ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">14</ref>) can be compactly written in the matrix form as</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">η = ζ(-I + P)η, (<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">)</formula><p>where η = [η 1 . . . η N ] T , I is the identity matrix and matrix P is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">P = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ 2 3 1 3 0 0 • • • 0 1 3 1 3 1 3 0 • • • 0 . . . . . . . . . 0 1 3 1 3 1 3 0 0 1 3 1 3 1 3 0 1 3 2 3 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ . (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">)</formula><p>Observe that matrix P is row stochastic, column stochastic and irreducible. The convergence of the proposed distributed observer ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">14</ref>) is shown in the following lemma. Lemma 1: By choosing the gain ζ ≥ 4 λ 2 δT where λ 2 is the second smallest eigenvalue of matrix (I -P) and 0 &lt; δ &lt; 1, the total charging needs of the network can be estimated by distributed observer <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>. Mathematically, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">η i (kT + δT ) → N j =1 β j (k)γ j (k) .</formula><p>Proof: It can be computed that the exponential convergence rate of observer ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">15</ref>) is given by ζ λ 2 and its settling time δT is equal to δT = 4(1/ζ λ 2 ). Since matrix P in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_28">16</ref>) is row-stochastic, column-stochastic and irreducible, we can guarantee, by choosing the gain ζ ≥ 4 λ 2 δT for a pre-defined 0 &lt; δ &lt; 1, that observer (15) converges asymptotically to a consensus, i.e., η(kT + δT ) → a o 1, where 1 ∈ n is the vector of 1s and a o = 1 T η(kT )/N <ref type="bibr">[38, ch. 5.2]</ref>. Therefore, for all i ∈ {1, • • • , N} the distributed observer converges to the total charging needs of the network.</p><p>Remark 1: The total charging needs can also be estimated using the existing freeway traffic estimation algorithms, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> which estimate traffic flow on the road segments along the highway.</p><p>Based on the estimated total charging needs and via I2I communication, the service station computes the consensus value of the normalized queue, i.e., the value η 0 (k) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Distributed Algorithm of Scheduling at Service Stations</head><p>In this subsection we describe the distributed scheduling algorithm executed by each service stations along the highway based on the idea of the consensus algorithm <ref type="bibr">[38, ch. 5.2.4</ref>]. Specifically, the goal is to design p i (k) in (2) for each service station so that 1) consensus is achieved as defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, 2) all the EVs on the highway are charged at least at one of the service stations. To this end, by the means of I2I communication (see figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>), the service stations adjust p i (k) using the information on the length of queue of their neighboring stations according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">p * 1 (k) = c 1 μ 1 α 1 (k) η 0 (k) 3 - 2x 1 (k) 3c 1 μ 1 + x 2 (k) 3c 2 μ 2 + g 1 (k) c 1 μ 1 p * i (k) = c i μ i α i (k) η 0 (k) 3 + x i-1 (k) 3c i-1 μ i-1 - x i (k) c i μ i + + x i+1 (k) 3c i+1 μ i+1 + g i (k) c i μ i , i = 2, • • • , (N -1) p * N (k) = c N μ N α N (k) η 0 (k) 3 - 2x N (k) 3c N μ N + x N-1 (k) 3c N-1 μ N-1 + g N (k) c N μ N (<label>17</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_32">)</formula><p>where α i (k) denotes the number of EVs approaching the i th service station and g i (k) is given by the approximation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. Furthermore, the value η 0 (k) ≥ 0 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> which serves as a leader can be computed from the following equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">N j =1 p * j (k)α j (k) = η i ((k -1)T + δT ) (<label>18</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">)</formula><p>which shows that the total number of EVs entering the service stations equals to the total charging needs.</p><p>The following theorem is the main result of the paper which shows that consensus (9) is guaranteed.</p><p>Theorem 1: Under queue dynamics (2) and the distributed scheduling algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>, all the charging stations are uniformly utilized and all EVs are charged at one of the service stations. Furthermore, the queues at all service stations are bounded if and only if the total charging needs is less than the total capacity of the service stations.</p><p>Proof: Let us define z i (k) = x i (k)/c i μ i . First we show that under <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, the consensus ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">9</ref>) is achieved. Substituting ĝi (x i ) in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">13</ref>) into (2) results in</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">z i (k + 1) = z i (k) + f i (k) c i μ i - c i μ i z i (k) 1 + c i μ i z i (k) . (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">)</formula><p>Furthermore, the following closed-loop dynamics is obtained by substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_31">17</ref>) into <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">z(k + 1) = Pz(k) + 1 3 [η 0 (k)1 -z(k)],<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where z = [z 1 . . . z N ] T . Since the matrix P in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_28">16</ref>) is primitive and row stochastic, it follows from <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> that system <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> asymptotically reaches a consensus given by z(k) → η 0 (k)1.</p><p>Next, we show further that by choosing η 0 (k) satisfying ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_33">18</ref>) then all EVs are charged at one of the service stations. When all EVs are charged, then the following constraint is satisfied</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">N-1 i=1 f i ⎛ ⎝ k - N-1 j =1 d j, j +1 ⎞ ⎠ + f N (k) = β N (k)γ N (k) + N-1 i=1 β i ⎛ ⎝ k - N-1 j =1 d j, j+1 ⎞ ⎠ γ i ⎛ ⎝ k - N-1 j =1 d j, j +1 ⎞ ⎠ . (21)</formula><p>Under update law <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> and assuming γ i (k) is constant, at the steady state the constraint (21) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">N i=1 f * i (k) = N i=1 β i (k)γ i (k)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">f * i (k) = p * i (k)α i (k)</formula><p>and which is equal to <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. Hence, all the EVs are charged at least once at the service stations.</p><p>Finally, we prove that z i (k) is bounded if and only if the total charging needs is less than the total capacity of the service stations, which can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">η i ((k -1)T + δT ) &lt; N j =1 c j μ j .</formula><p>For showing the necessity ( ⇒), first we observe that under update law <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, when the queues are bounded we have f * i (k) &lt; c i μ i for all stations i . Hence, we know that</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">N j =i f * j (k) &lt; N j =1 c j μ j .</formula><p>Combining the above inequality with (18) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">N j =i f * j (k) = η i ((k -1)T + δT ) &lt; N j =1 c j μ j .</formula><p>We show the sufficiency (⇐ ) by contradiction. Similar to the previous case, when the queues are not bounded, under the update law (17), we have f * i ≥ c i μ i for all service stations i . Hence, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">N j =i f * j (k) ≥ N j =1 c j μ j .</formula><p>Combining the above inequality with (18) results in</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">N j =i f * j (k) = η i ((k -1)T + δT ) ≥ N j =1</formula><p>c j μ j which completes the proof. Note that from (17) and since x i (k) c i μ i → η 0 (k), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">p * i → (c i μ i ) 2 η 0 (k) α i (k) [1 + c i μ i η 0 (k)] . (<label>22</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_47">)</formula><p>Furthermore, at the steady state the following equality holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">N j =1 (c j μ j ) 2 η 0 (k) 1 + c j μ j η 0 (k) = η i ((k -1)T + δT ) IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON INTELLIGENT TRANSPORTATION SYSTEMS</formula><p>which shows the relation between the number of queues at the steady state and the EV's total charging needs. In the following we provide some remarks regarding the proposed distributed scheduling algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. Remark 2: It is shown in the proof of the theorem that the constraint ( <ref type="formula">21</ref>) is satisfied at the steady state. The constraint (21) can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">f N (k) = β N (k)γ N (k) + N-1 i=1 ⎡ ⎣ β i ⎛ ⎝ k - N-1 j =1 d j, j +1 ⎞ ⎠ γ i ⎛ ⎝ k - N-1 j =1 d j, j +1 ⎞ ⎠ -f i ⎛ ⎝ k - N-1 j =1 d j, j +1 ⎞ ⎠ ⎤ ⎦ .</formula><p>The second term on the right hand side of the above equation represents the total number of EVs which are not charged at the previous (N -1)-service stations. Therefore, during the transient state, the last service station, i.e., station N projects its control input p * N (k) computed from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_31">17</ref>) into the above equality in order to guarantee that all the EVs get charged. Furthermore, in practice when β i (k) &gt; 1, the charging needs β i (k)γ i (k) are updated accordingly by considering number of EVs that have been charged at some of the stations.</p><p>Remark 3: The value of η 0 (k) can be computed from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_33">18</ref>) in a distributed fashion. First, we can write from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_31">17</ref>) that</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">f * i (k) = p * i (k)α i (k) = a i η 0 (k) + b i where b i is computed from the states x i (k)</formula><p>c i μ i of the corresponding station and its neighbors. The equality <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref> can then be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">⎛ ⎝ N j =1 a i ⎞ ⎠ η 0 (k) + N j =1 b i = η i ((k -1)T + δT ). (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">)</formula><p>Similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>, the service stations execute the following observer:</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">ȧ = ζ(-I + P)a, ḃ = -ζ(-I + P)b, where a = [a 1 , • • • , a N ] T (resp. b = [b 1 , • • • , b N ] T ) and initial conditions a i (0) = Na i (resp. b i (0) = Nb i ).</formula><p>As shown in lemma 1, for all service stations i the states will converge to a i → N j =1 a i and b i → N j =1 b i respectively. Hence, each service station can compute η 0 (k) from ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_51">23</ref>) independently.</p><p>Remark 4: It is worth to note that under the update law <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> the condition the total charging needs is less than the total capacity of the service stations is necessary and sufficient for the queues to be bounded. This is due to the nature of the consensus based update law <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> which forces the service stations to equally utilize their capacity and thus the chargers at each station can be used close to its limit capacity.</p><p>Remark 5: Consensus is also achieved under ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_31">17</ref>) for different queue model and its stability can be analyzed using the corresponding stability condition similar to (3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. COOPERATIVE CONTROL OF EVS' CHARGING</head><p>In this section, we design a cooperative control u v,i (k) in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">6</ref>) for each EV by solving distributively optimization problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>. In other words, the objective is to achieve the optimally scheduled percentage of EVs to be charged at every service station given by the aforementioned scheduling algorithm (i.e., the solution to optimization problem ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">7</ref>)) while meeting its own state-of-charge constraint, as depicted in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>.</p><p>The EVs, through their local computation, solve optimization (8) in a distributed manner by negotiating among themselves based on their state of charge and by using vehicleto-vehicle (V2V) communication. To this end, the communication network among the EVs moving toward the same service station needs to be connected (or facilitated by infrastructure via V2I and I2V communication). To be more precise, each EV is only required to exchange information locally with its surrounding EVs such that all EVs moving toward the same station are connected, i.e., the information from every EV can (indirectly) propagate to any other EVs. When approaching service station i , the EVs closest to the station will receive the information on p * i (k), d i,i+1 and α i (k) transmitted by the i th service station with the use of infrastructure-to-vehicle communication. Each EV belonging to the set N i (k) with |N i (k)| = α i (k) then utilize this information to compute independently the number of EVs entering service station i , i.e., u i total (k) which is the solution to the following optimization argmin</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">u i total (k) p * i - u i total (k) α i (k) 2 .</formula><p>Next, each EV check their residual battery level e - v,i and set</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">their control input u v,i (k) = 1 if e - v,i &lt; d i,i+1 r - v , i.e.</formula><p>, when they cannot reach service station (i +1) without getting charge at the i th station. Let s i denote the number of EVs that cannot reach the next station without getting charge at station i . Note that the value s i can be computed distributively via a consensus algorithm as described in the previous section. Without loss of generality, it is assumed that the drivers fully charge their batteries at the service station. The normalized required energy for the EVs until they are fully charged is then equal to</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">e r v,i = 1 - e - v,i</formula><p>e v,max .</p><p>The rest α i (k)s i EVs then exchange their e r v,i values with their neighbors and sort them in an ascending order distributively, for example using the method proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. As a final step, the EVs with</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">(u i total (k) -s i )th largest value of e r v,i set their input u v,i (k) = 1.</formula><p>The reason why the EVs do not exchange their current energy level e - v,i is because the information may reveal the charging habit of the owners. Moreover, in combination with the information on battery capacity, the average speed of the EVs on the highway and by assuming that the owners fully charged their batteries before departing to work, private information such as the residential location of the EV's owner may also be estimated and exposed. On the other hand, exchanging the values of the required energy e r v,i provides a better way to preserve or hide this private information since the drivers do not necessarily fully charge their batteries at the service station. The pseudo-code of the algorithm is given in algorithm 1. Note that the decision whether an EV should </p><formula xml:id="formula_58">for v = 1, . . . , α i (k) do 5: u i total (k) = argmin ( p * i - u i total (k) α i (k) ) 2 6:</formula><p>compute battery status e - v,i 7:</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">if e - v,i &lt; d i,i+1 r - v , i ∈ N i then 8: set u v,i (k) = 1 9: S i ← v 10:</formula><p>end if rank e r v,i distributively in an ascending order for v / ∈ S i using the method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> 15:</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">set u v,i (k) = 1 for (u i total (k) -s i )th largest e r v,i</formula><p>16: end for 17: end for be charged at a given service station can be implemented, e.g., as a recommendation to the driver, in existing in-car navigation technologies or as an app. in a smart phone. Remark 6: The number of EVs at the service station as a result of algorithm 1 may not always match the ones computed by distributed scheduling algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. This is either due to the uncertainty of the arrival/flow of EVs at the service station which influences the queue, or the first constraint in (8) captured by β i (k) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, or the stochastic nature of the driver's decision making. Such an uncertainty could be modeled as a (bounded) perturbation injected into dynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>. Note that since distributed scheduling algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> is performed in real time, the value η 0 (k) will be adjusted accordingly by taking into account the uncertainty of x i (k) at each station. If the total charging needs is less than the total charging capacity of the service stations and since the perturbation is bounded, the value η 0 (k) will remain bounded as shown in theorem 1. As a result, the states x i (k) c i μ i will attempt to track the value of η 0 (k), will reach consensus whenever η 0 (k) converges, and will stay bounded around η 0 (k) when η 0 (k) oscillates. Mathematically, the closed-loop dynamics (20) under bounded uncertainty w(k) ∈ R N with w(k) ∞ ≤ w can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">η 0 (k + 1) z(k + 1) = 1 0 1 3 1 P -1 3 I η 0 (k) z(k) + 0 w(k) . (<label>24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_62">)</formula><p>It is shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38,</ref><ref type="bibr">Lemma 5.31</ref>] that the states z(k) in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_61">24</ref>) remains bounded given that η 0 (k) is bounded.</p><p>V. SIMULATIONS In this section, we demonstrate and compare the performance of the proposed distributed scheduling using two Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. The map of entrances/exits and service stations on Florida Turnpike. The circles represent entrances/exits and the rectangles represent service stations. The numbers above the arrows represent the distance (in minutes increments) between two consecutive nodes and the numbers in the circles denote the label of the entrances/exits and service stations.</p><p>different simulation examples on the Florida Turnpike, which is one of the highways in the United States.</p><p>Consider a Florida Turnpike consisting of 69 entrances/exits, i.e., N = 69 including 8 service stations as depicted in figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>. The distances (in minutes increments) between the entrances/exits are summarized in figure <ref type="figure">7</ref> where it is assumed that the average velocity of the vehicles on the highway is equal to 60 miles/hour. For the sake of visualization and comparison, it is assumed that the EVs only need to be charged once along the highway, i.e., β i (k) = 1 for all i . This is a realistic assumption since it is reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> that EVs were charged 1.46 times per vehicle day driven on average. In addition, the simulation is performed for sampling time T equal to 20 minutes for both the (physical) transportation and communication networks. We also assume that at the beginning of the day there are no EVs queueing at the service stations, i.e., x i (0) = 0 for all i .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Algorithm Applied to Simulation Data</head><p>We first apply the proposed distributed algorithm to a constant traffic flow data where we set γ 14 (k) = 4, γ 36 (k) = 6, γ 54 (k) = 2 and γ i (k) = 0 for i = {14, 36, 54}. Furthermore, it is assumed that the six fast chargers are installed at each of the four service stations, namely c 29 = c 48 = c 50 = c 60 = 6 and μ 29 = μ 48 = μ 50 = μ 60 = 2 EVs/h. The simulation result is shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8a</ref>. As can be seen from the figure, all the four charging stations are uniformly utilized. Specifically, the consensus-based algorithm allocates equal number of EVs to each service station since all service stations have the same capacity as can be seen from figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8b</ref>.</p><p>Next, we compare the performance of the proposed distributed scheduling algorithm for two different communication structures as illustrated in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9</ref>. To this end, we consider the case of four charging stations as before and assume that γ 14 (k) = 12 and γ i (k) = 0 for i = 14. Distributed algorithm corresponding to communication structure shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9a</ref> is given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>. In addition, we modify <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> to incorporate the communication topology depicted in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9b</ref> where each charging station also receives information on the length of queues from the stations which are not its direct  neighbors. The results are shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">10</ref>. As can be observed from the figure, distributed algorithm based on both topologies result in the same utilization value at the steady state and the equal number of EVs are entering each service station. Furthermore, it can be seen that the topology given in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9b</ref> yields a better transient performance (i.e., the difference of utilization between the charging stations are smaller) in comparison to the communication topology in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9a</ref>. The result is intuitive since the charging stations in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9b</ref> receive more information than the ones in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9a</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Algorithm Applied to Real Florida Turnpike Data</head><p>Next, we utilize the real traffic data (per hour) obtained from Regional Integrated Transportation Information System (RITIS) database, namely the vehicles' net average flow at entrances/exits (nodes) 1 and 5 of the Florida turnpike, i.e., γ i (k) = 0 for all i = {1, 5} within 24 hours as depicted in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">11</ref>. As can be observed, the traffic flow between 8-9 AM and between 6-8 PM are relatively higher than the rest of the day since during this two time frame, people are going to their work and going back home respectively. In addition, it is assumed that the EVs penetration rate is equal to 2% of the total vehicles' net average flow.</p><p>Currently, there are in total 12 units Tesla superchargers with charging time approximately 30 minutes installed along the highway, specifically 6 units each at the Fort Drum Service Plaza (node 50) and Turkey Lake Service Plaza (node 60) respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>. Hence, we set c 50 , = c 60 = 6 and μ 50 = μ 60 = 2 Evs/h and c i = 0, μ i = 0 for i = {50, 60}. For this particular simulation, the proposed consensus-based distributed scheduling algorithm is compared with an alternative strategy without any coordination/cooperation between the service stations. We call this alternative strategy as Stateof-Charge (SoC)-based random strategy which employs the information on the battery's SoC of the EVs when approaching the service station. In this strategy, we first assigned a SoC threshold for charging given by S t . When an EV approaching the i -th service station, it will check whether its SoC is below the threshold S t . If its SoC is below S t , then the driver will recharge the battery at the i -th station, i.e., p i (k) = 1. Otherwise, the percentage p i (k) is given by a uniformly distributed random number, i.e., the EVs randomly decide whether to charge at station i . For the simulation, we set the SoC threshold S t equal to 30% of the maximum SoC. This strategy is consistent with the findings in <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> where it is reported that most drivers charge their EV's battery when it is nearly fully depleted. Hence, the SoC based random strategy can approximately model the charging behavior of the EV's driver in the absence of any coordination (thus it is decentralized in nature). Note that a strategy similar to SoC-based random strategy is also employed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> for evaluating their algorithm where it is assumed that the EV's driver will choose the closest station when the SoC is below 30%. The authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> also use a similar strategy, namely EVs will charge at the last station where they are able to reach, to compare and evaluate their charging algorithm. We perform monte carlo simulation (1000 trials with random initial SoC) for the SoC-based random strategy whose (average) result is shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">12a</ref>. As can be seen, there is a large difference of utilization between the two service stations since no information of the current queue length of the neighboring station is used for deciding whether to charge at a specific service station. Next, we apply the proposed consensus-based scheduling algorithm whose result is illustrated in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">12b</ref>. As can be observed, the consensus algorithm tries to allocate the EVs along the highway such that both service stations are uniformly utilized by using the information on the real time queue length at the neighboring stations. The number of EVs entering each service stations is illustrated in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">14b</ref>. It is interesting to note that similar results on uniform utilization of charging stations are  also observed via simulations in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> where the objective is to minimize the total travel time of individual EV and in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> where the authors aimed at reducing the road congestion.</p><p>Finally, we perform the simulation when both service stations have different number of charges available. Specifically, we set c 50 = 5 and c 60 = 7 (note that the total charging capacity in the network remains the same). The simulation results by applying the SoC-based random strategy is depicted in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">13a</ref>. The queues at both service stations vary significantly since most of the EVs decided to charge at the first station and no coordination is taken place. We improve the performance of the charging network by applying the consensusbased distributed scheduling algorithm whose result is shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">13b</ref>. It can be observed that the proposed algorithm results in a uniform utilization of the service stations in spite of the heterogeneity of their capacity. Specifically, based on the information of the neighboring service stations' queues, the EVs are allocated "proportional" to the capacity of each service station as can be seen from figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">14b</ref> where the service station with more capacity takes more EVs to be charged.  In order to further evaluate the performance improvement of the proposed strategy we also compute the root mean square of the difference between both service stations' utilization given by (setting</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">T f inal = 72) rms = 1 72 72 k=1 x 50 (k) c 50 μ 50 - x 60 (k) c 60 μ 60 2</formula><p>and the results are summarized in table II. As can be seen from the table, the proposed algorithm yields a lower value of root-mean-square compared to the SoC-based random strategy. Moreover, we also compare the total waiting time for the EVs at each station. From Little's law formula, the total waiting time at the i th station T i can be computed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">T i = T x i (k) f i (k) .</formula><p>Since additional time caused by the traffic congestion, i.e., driving time is assumed to be constant, the total waiting time is then equal to the increase of total travel time for the vehicles. It is interesting to note that, as discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, the uniform utilization of the service stations also results in the reduction of traffic congestions. The total waiting time for both the proposed strategy and SoC-based random strategy are summarized in table III. As can be seen from the table, the proposed strategy results in an (approximately) equal total waiting time for both service stations. Furthermore, the maximum total waiting time for the proposed strategy is lower than the random strategy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Evaluation of Proposed Algorithm for Different Parameters</head><p>In the following we evaluate the performance of the proposed algorithm for different parameters, namely different type of chargers and sampling time. First, we consider the case where both service stations are equipped with chargers whose charging time is equal to 1 hour per EV while the number of chargers at each station c 50 = c 60 = 6. As can be seen from figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">13b</ref>, even though the service stations are uniformly utilized, the queues increase over time and become unbounded. This is because the number of EVs entering each station is larger than the capacity of the service station at most of the time. Next, we increase the number of charger at each station to c 50 = c 60 = 10. As a result, the queues at each service stations remain bounded as can be observed from figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">15b</ref>. Hence, for charger with charging time equal to 1 hour per EV, we require more chargers compared to the fast charging case in order to keep the queues at each service station bounded.</p><p>Finally, in order to study the sensitivity of the proposed algorithm with respect to the time k (or sampling time T ) we simulate the proposed algorithm for different sampling time (updated time), namely T = 10 minutes and T = 5 minutes respectively. It can be observed from figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">16</ref> that the choice of T impacts the utilization value x i c i μ i of the service stations. However, as can also be observed from the figure, the average length of queues at the service stations, i.e., x i are about the same at a particular time of the day for different sampling time T . In practice, the size of T should be chosen depending on the traffic condition (e.g., volume of EVs on the highway). In addition, it is worth noting that in the paper we consider the worst case that communication is sampled at a slower rate (i.e., equal to the sampling rate of the transportation network). However, in practice the communication can be sampled at much faster rate depending on the traffic congestion or EVs speed, i.e., the consensus algorithm can be run asynchronously. This implies that the value η 0 (k) changes between the samples of the transportation/traffic model which makes the scheduling algorithm become more sensitive to the changes of traffic flow, i.e., the transient behavior.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we have developed a strategy consisting of a distributed scheduling algorithm and a cooperative control policy for individual EVs which optimize the operation of the overall charging network on a highway. First, a consensus-based distributed scheduling algorithm is presented which uses local information from the neighboring service stations and is designed so that all the charging stations are uniformly utilized. Next, we develop a negotiation strategy among the drivers by means of the V2V and V2I communications and based on their current battery level in order to meet the published scheduling level. It is confirmed from simulations that the proposed strategy improves the overall system performance compared to the SoC-based random strategy. It should be noted that by using graph theory (with nodes and edges represent entrances/exits/service stations and roads respectively), the highway transportation network studied in this paper can be extended to general road networks. Future research can be done to incorporate traffic congestions into the model, consideration of pricebased strategy (game-theoretic approach), installment of new charging infrastructure including additional batteries for replacement to further reduce the total waiting time, control of traffic congestions by the adjustment of the maximum speed limit for the EVs, and performance analysis of the proposed distributed strategy under communication failures or delays.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. A bidirectional highway segment with exit/entrance and service station.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,56.03,58.61,236.90,143.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. A queueing model for service station at node i.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Representation of a birth-death process for M/M/c i queue model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.Distributed scheduling and cooperative control of EVs using infrastructure-to-infrastructure (I2I), vehicle-to-vehicle (V2V), vehicle-toinfrastructure (V2I) and infrastructure-to-vehicle (I2V) communication.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Algorithm 1 1 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Distributed algorithm to solve optimization (8) Require: p * i , α i (k), d i,i+1 broadcasted by the service stations, a strongly connected communication topology between the EVs. for k = 1, 2, . . . , T f inal do 2: for i = 1, . . . , N do 3: set S i = {} 4:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Simulation results under the proposed consensus-based scheduling algorithm for constant traffic flow γ 14 (k) = 4, γ 36 (k) = 6, γ 54 (k) = 2 with c 29 = c 48 = c 50 = c 60 = 6 and μ 29 = μ 48 = μ 50 = μ 60 = 2 EVs/h. (a) Utilization of service stations. (b) Number of EVs entering service stations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Communication topologies of the service stations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Simulation results under the proposed consensus-based scheduling algorithm for different communication topologies and constant traffic flow γ 14 (k) = 12 with c 29 = c 48 = c 50 = c 60 = 6 and μ 29 = μ 48 = μ 50 = μ 60 = 2 EVs/h. (a) Consensus-based algorithm for topology in figure 9a. (b) Consensus-based algorithm for topology in figure 9b.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Vehicles' net average flow entering nodes 1 and 5 per hour for 24 hours based on RITIS database. (a) Consensus-based algorithm for topology in figure 9a. (b) Consensus-based algorithm for topology in figure 9b.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 12 .Fig. 13 .Fig. 14 .</head><label>121314</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Utilization of service stations for real Florida turnpike data with c 50 = c 60 = 6 and μ 50 = μ 60 = 2 EVs/h. (a) SoC-based random charging strategy. (b) Consensus-based algorithm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 15 .Fig. 16 .</head><label>1516</label><figDesc>Fig. 15. Utilization of service stations for real Florida turnpike data with μ 50 = μ 60 = 1 EV/h. (a) c 50 = c 60 = 6. (b)c 50 = c 60 = 10.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE I A</head><label>I</label><figDesc>LIST OF NOTATIONS Fig. 2. A model of average EV flow at the ith extrance/exit.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE III COMPARISON</head><label>III</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p>OF TOTAL WAITING TIME T i (IN MINUTES)</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the U.S. Department of Transportation under Award DTRT13GUTC51, in part by the U.S. National Science Foundation under Grant ECCS-1308928, in part by the U.S. Department of Energy under Award DEEE0006340 and Award DE-EE0007327, in part by the L-3 Communication Coleman Aerospace under Contract 11013I2034, in part by Texas Instruments' awards, and in part by Leidos under Contract P010161530. The Associate Editor for this paper was L. Vlacic.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scheduling and cooperative control of electric vehicles&apos; charging at highway service stations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gusrialdi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Simaan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE 53rd Annu. Conf. Decision Control (CDC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE 53rd Annu. Conf. Decision Control (CDC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6465" to="6471" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Transportation electrification: A technology overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Duvall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<pubPlace>Palo Alto, CA, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep. 1021334</note>
	<note>EPRI</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental impacts of hybrid and electric vehicles-A review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hawkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Strømman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Life Cycle Assessment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="997" to="1014" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-09">Sep. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sustainable options for electric vehicle technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Poullikkas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1277" to="1287" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-01">Jan. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance analysis of current BEVs based on a comprehensive review of specifications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Grunditz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Thiringer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Transport. Electrific</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-09">Sep. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An approach for the optimal planning of electric vehicle infrastructure for highway corridors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sathaye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transp. Res. E, Logistics Transp. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-11">Nov. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A corridor-centric approach to planning electric vehicle charging infrastructure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Nie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ghamami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transp. Res. B, Methodol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="172" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-11">Nov. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multi-period optimization model for the deployment of public electric vehicle charging stations on network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transp. Res. C, Emerg. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="128" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-04">Apr. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Charge scheduling of electric vehicles in highways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-N</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-S</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Hsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-H</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-B</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>nos. 11-12</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Comput. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2873" to="2882" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-06">Jun. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic park-and-charge balancing for fully electric and plug-in hybrid vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hausler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Crisostomi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schlote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Radusch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shorten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Intell. Transp. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="895" to="901" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-04">Apr. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PEV charging control for a parking lot based on queuing theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Midlam-Mohler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Serra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Marano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rizzoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Amer. Control Conf. (ACC)</title>
		<meeting>Amer. Control Conf. (ACC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-06">Jun. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1124" to="1129" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Queuing model for EVs charging at public supply stations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Said</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cherkaoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Khoukhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Wireless Commun. Mobile Comput. Conf. (IWCMC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-07">Jul. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="70" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proc. 9th Int</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal plug-in electric vehicle charging with schedule constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cortés</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 51st Annu. Allerton Conf</title>
		<meeting>51st Annu. Allerton Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-10">Oct. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="266" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal autonomous charging of electric vehicles with stochastic driver behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Donadee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ilic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Karabasoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Veh. Power Propuls. Conf. (VPPC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Veh. Power Propuls. Conf. (VPPC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-10">Oct. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric vehicles charging management in communication controlled fast charging stations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vardakas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE 19th Int. Workshop Comput. Aided Modeling Design Commun</title>
		<meeting>IEEE 19th Int. Workshop Comput. Aided Modeling Design Commun</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="119" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of a genetic algorithm based electric vehicle charging coordination on distribution networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-S</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Congr</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Congr</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-05">May 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="290" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The charging-scheduling problem for electric vehicle networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Wireless Commun. Netw. Conf. (WCNC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Wireless Commun. Netw. Conf. (WCNC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-04">Apr. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3178" to="3183" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anticipatory coordination of electric vehicle allocation to fast charging infrastructure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Coninx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Claes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vandael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Leemput</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Holvoet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Deconinck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Practical Applications of Heterogeneous Multi-Agent Systems. The PAAMS Collection</title>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Demazeau</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zambonelli</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Corchado</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bajo</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cham, Switzerland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8473</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="85" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A gametheory analysis of charging stations selection by EV drivers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Malandrino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Casetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-F</forename><surname>Chiasserini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reineri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perform. Eval</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-01">Jan. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimization of charging infrastructure usage under varying traffic and capacity conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bodet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schulke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Erickson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jablonowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE 3rd Int. Conf. Smart Grid Commun. (SmartGridComm)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE 3rd Int. Conf. Smart Grid Commun. (SmartGridComm)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-11">Nov. 2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="429" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Charging scheduling with minimal waiting in a network of electric vehicles and charging stations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 8th ACM Int. Workshop Veh. Inter-Netw</title>
		<meeting>8th ACM Int. Workshop Veh. Inter-Netw</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-09">Sep. 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal charging scheduling for large-scale EV (electric vehicle) deployment based on the interaction of the smart-grid and intelligent-transport systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="368" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-02">Feb. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Socially optimal charging strategies for electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Yudovina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Michailidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="837" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-03">Mar. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal routing of electric vehicles in networks with charging nodes: A dynamic programming approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pourazarm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cassandras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Malikopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Elect. Vehicle Conf. (IEVC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Elect. Vehicle Conf. (IEVC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time charging navigation of electric vehicles to fast charging stations: A hierarchical game approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7182331/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Smart Grid</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smart charging schedules for highway travel with electric vehicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Del Razo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-A</forename><surname>Jacobsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Transport. Electrific</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="160" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-06">Jun. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smart charging for electric vehicles: A survey from the algorithmic perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Surveys Tuts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1500" to="1517" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<pubPlace>2nd Quart</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Review of recent trends in optimization techniques for plug-in hybrid, and electric vehicle charging infrastructures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Rahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vasant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Abdullah-Al-Wadud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Adnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1039" to="1047" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial and temporal model of electric vehicle charging demand</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kwasinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Smart Grid</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-03">Mar. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control of vehicle platoons for highway safety and efficient utility: Consensus with communications and vehicle dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Syed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pandya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Syst. Sci. Complex</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="605" to="631" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed coordination and control for a freeway traffic network using consensus algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B.-Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-S</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Syst. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-03">Mar. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Routing in sparse vehicular ad hoc wireless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wisitpongphan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mudalige</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sadekar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Tonguz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1538" to="1556" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-10">Oct. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Vehicle Propulsion Systems: Introduction to Modeling and Optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Guzzella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sciarretta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin, Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic information management in smart grid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Tamang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Surveys Tuts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1746" to="1770" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd Quart.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Queueing network models for electric vehicle charging station with battery swapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H K</forename><surname>Tsang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Smart Grid Commun. (SmartGridComm)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Smart Grid Commun. (SmartGridComm)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-11">Nov. 2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-priority queuing for electric vehicles charging at public supply stations with price variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Said</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cherkaoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Khoukhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Wireless Commun. Mobile Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1049" to="1065" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-04">Apr. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electric vehicle charging facility as a smart energy microhub</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Alharbi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bhattacharya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Sustain. Energy</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>to be published</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cooperative Control of Dynamical Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London, U.K.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Valdez-Flores</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Applied Probability and Stochastic Process</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London, U.K.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple approximation for modeling nonstationary queues</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tipper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 15th Annu. Joint Conf</title>
		<meeting>15th Annu. Joint Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-03">Mar. 1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="262" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vehicular communication systems: Enabling technologies, applications, and future outlook on intelligent transportation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Papadimitratos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>De La Fortelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Evenssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brignolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cosenza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-11">Nov. 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Freeway traffic estimation within particle filtering framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mihaylova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Boel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hegyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-02">Feb. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time freeway traffic state estimation based on extended Kalman filter: A general approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Papageorgiou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transp. Res. B, Methodol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="167" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-02">Feb. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gossip algorithms for distributed ranking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chiuso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fagnani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schenato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zampieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Amer. Control Conf. (ACC)</title>
		<meeting>Amer. Control Conf. (ACC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-06">Jun. 2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5468" to="5473" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-stabilizing distributed sorting in tree networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Datta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tixeuil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Parallel Algorithms Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Extended range electric vehicle driving and charging behavior observed early in the EV project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Smart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Powell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>SAE Tech. Paper 2013-01-1441</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Supercharger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.teslamotors.com/supercharger" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-01-03">Jan. 3, 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Little&apos;s law</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D C</forename><surname>Little</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Graves</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Building Intuition (Insights From Basic Operations Management Models and Principles</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chhajed</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lowe</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="100" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
