<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Optimal Distributed Control for Secondary Frequency and Voltage Regulation in an Islanded Microgrid</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Yinliang</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fellow IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Hongbin</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Senior Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Yan</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Zhengshuo</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Optimal Distributed Control for Secondary Frequency and Voltage Regulation in an Islanded Microgrid</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7EAB406A6383729574AEDA40EB78B4B3</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TII.2018.2795584</idno>
					<note type="submission">This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TII.2018.2795584, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TII.2018.2795584, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T12:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>optimal distributed control</term>
					<term>finite-time convergence</term>
					<term>secondary control</term>
					<term>average voltage regulation</term>
					<term>islanded microgrid</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper proposes an optimal distributed control strategy for the coordination of multiple distributed generators in an islanded microgrid. A finite-time secondary frequency control approach is developed to eliminate the frequency deviation and maintain accurate active power sharing in a finite-time manner. It is demonstrated that the traditional distributed control approach with asymptotical convergence is just a special case of the proposed finite-time control strategy under the specific control parameter settings. Then, a secondary voltage control approach is presented to regulate the average voltage magnitude of all distributed generators to the desired value and achieve accurate reactive power sharing. The implementation of the proposed distributed control strategy only requires information exchange among neighboring local controllers through a sparse communication network. Simulations with an islanded microgrid testbed built in MATLAB/Simulink are conducted to validate the effectiveness of the proposed distributed control strategy.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NOMENCLATURE</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ni</head><p>The Line impedance between bus i and bus j</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. INTRODUCTION</head><p>ITH the gaining popularity in the utilization of distributed generation, especially renewable energy resources (RERs), the microgrid (MG) has emerged as a promising paradigm to accommodate the integration of intermittent components. High penetration and growing capacities of RERs poses many challenges to an islanded MG <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, such as power quality, frequency/voltage stability, supply reliability, etc.</p><p>Hierarchical control frameworks, which contain primary, secondary, and tertiary control levels, have been widely adopted for islanded MGs in recent literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. To dynamically maintain the supply-demand balance without any communication channel, the droop control approach, which emulates the behavior of a synchronous generator, attracts significant attentions <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. However, the traditional droop control based approaches suffer from several drawbacks. Voltage droop typically demonstrates a poor reactive power sharing performance due to the dependence on output line impedance <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The secondary control level eliminates the frequency and voltage deviations caused by the primary controller and the tertiary control level mainly considers economic dispatch and power flow optimization.</p><p>The focus of this paper is to develop a secondary control approach in an islanded MG. The objective is to restore the frequency/voltage to the desired value and maintain accurate active/reactive power sharing among all distributed generators (DGs). The existing secondary control strategies can be classified into three categories: centralized <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, decentralized <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, and distributed control <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. The traditional centralized strategy requires central communication and computation units to collect and process the massive information of all DGs. These requirements may degrade the overall system reliability and suffer from single point of failure problem. Decentralized control strategy may not be effective to coordinate all available resources within the MG in an optimal way due to lack of broader available algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, which enables all DGs to achieve a common goal through the peer-to-peer communication protocol. Due to the availability of renewable generators, MG's physical and communication topologies can be time-varying. To support plug-and-play functionality, the distributed control strategy provides a robust secondary control framework that works effectively in spite of time-varying communication networks. Moreover, distributed control strategies enable easier scalability, simpler communication network, and faster distributed data processing, which can facilitate highly efficient information sharing and decision making.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, a distributed cooperative secondary control of MG using feedback linearization was proposed. It is assumed that only leader DGs in the MG have direct access to the frequency/voltage reference values. Through distributed communication among neighboring controllers, the frequency and voltage of all DGs finally reach their desired values. A distributed averaging proportional integral (PI) controller was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> to eliminate the frequency deviations while ensuring accurate power sharing, but voltage restoration is not considered. A distributed-averaging-proportion-integral (DAPI) controller was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, which addressed the adjustable tradeoff between voltage restoration and accurate reactive power sharing. However, most existing literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> on distributed secondary control provide solutions for frequency/voltage restoration and active power sharing with asymptotical convergence speed. Since an islanded MG may suffer from the sudden and fast disturbances caused by the intermittency of RERs and load variations, fast response control algorithms, and even finite-time convergence are preferred, which can provide robust performance and stability, disturbance rejection features in addition to a finite settling time.</p><p>To expedite the convergence speed, a finite-time approximate consensus strategy was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, where the voltage control and reactive power sharing have not been investigated. A finite-time consensus-based voltage and frequency control was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, but voltage regulation is still model-dependent with some considerable oscillations in active power response when subjected to load variations. Following this research direction, a few finite-time voltage restoration strategies were proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, which designed the voltage controller independent from the frequency controller. However, the accurate reactive power sharing issue is not studied simultaneously.</p><p>To facilitate the decoupled design of secondary frequency and voltage controllers for an islanded MG, two control approaches with different convergence time are proposed. Firstly, a finite-time secondary frequency control approach is developed to eliminate the frequency deviation while maintaining the accurate active power sharing in a finite-time manner. Secondly, a secondary voltage control approach is presented to regulate the average voltage magnitude of all DGs to the desired value while guaranteeing accurate reactive power sharing. Only information exchange among neighboring local controllers through a sparse communication network is required for the realization of the proposed control strategy, thus it is adaptive, scalable, and enables efficient information sharing, fast decision making, and plug-and-play functionality. Finally, the effectiveness of the proposed control strategy is validated by the simulations with an islanded MG testbed built in MATLAB/Simulink under various operating conditions.</p><p>The main contributions of this paper are summarized as follows:</p><p>(1). An optimal distributed secondary control approach is proposed for frequency/active power and voltage/reactive power control in an islanded microgrid, which only requires information exchange among neighboring DGs through a sparse communication network;</p><p>(2). Finite-time convergence is achieved for frequency restoration and active power sharing, and it has been demonstrated that the traditional distributed control approach with asymptotical convergence is just a special case of the proposed optimal distributed control strategy under the specific control parameter settings;</p><p>(3). The scalability of the proposed distributed control strategy is investigated through a case study with the 42node distributed system. The rest of the paper is organized as follows. Section II introduces the preliminaries of graph theory and closed-loop optimal control algorithm. The distributed secondary controller for both frequency and voltage control is designed with stability guarantee in Section III. Section IV investigates the performance of the proposed strategy through multiple case studies and Section V concludes this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. PRELIMINARIES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Graph Theory</head><p>If there exists a transmission line ij connecting DG i and DG j, DG j is then considered to be in the neighborhood set of Ni, which denotes j∈Ni. DG i can receive information only from those in the neighborhood Ni with communication coefficient dij&gt;0, otherwise dij=0. If each DG unit is considered as a node, and the transmission lines are referred to edges, the topology of a MG can be considered as a graph. If dij=dji, the graph is undirected. If there exists a path which connects any two distinct units, the graph is considered to be connected. The diagonal term dii is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">, i ii ij j N d d j i      . (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">)</formula><p>The Laplacian matrix is defined as D= <ref type="bibr">[dij]</ref>. Assume the eigenvalues of the Laplacian matrix are arranged in an increasing sequence, the following relationship is valid <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">2 1 | | | | | |=0, 0, 1,..., . n i i n           </formula><p>(2) For an undirected graph, the following properties are valid <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">1 , 1 , 1 1 sign( ) 2 k k n n ij i j i j i ij j i i j i j d x x x x x d x x          (3) 2 , 1 1 ( ) 2 n T ij j i i j x Dx d x x     , 2 2 2 , 1 1 ( ) 2 n T ij j i i j x D x d x x     (4) 2 ( ) T T x Dx D x x   (5) 2 2 , 1 1 1 ( ) ( ) 2 n n T ij j i i i i j i x D C x d x x c x         (6) 1 ( ) ( ) T T x D C x D C x x    <label>(7)</label></formula><p>where x=(x1, …, xn) is the state variable needs to be exchanged among neighboring DG units, ci is the pinning gain, C=diag{c1,…,cn}, λ2 is the second smallest eigenvalue of D, which is also referred to algebraic connectivity of D, λ1 is the smallest eigenvalue of (D+C).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Closed-loop Optimal Control Algorithm</head><p>Consider the nonlinear dynamic system as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">0 ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ), (0) x t f x G x u t F x x x      . (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">)</formula><p>The performance index is expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">1 0 0 , , min ( , ) = min ( ) ( ) ( ) T x u x u J L x u dt L x u x Ru x dt       . (<label>9</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">)</formula><p>where L1 is the performance criterion for the state variable, R=diag{r1,…,rn} with ri as the control input weight. Define the Hamiltonian function <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> as: ( , ) ( , ) ( ) ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">H x u L x u S x F x   . (<label>10</label></formula><p>) where S(x) is the co-state variable set.</p><p>The optimal control is designed to minimize the Hamiltonian, which is given by  </p><p>, arg min ( , ) ( ) ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">x u u Lxu SxFx  <label>(11)</label></formula><p>The necessary condition for <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> to be valid is the first order derivate of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">10</ref>) with respect to (w.r.t.) u is zero:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">1 = ( ) ( )( ( ) ( ) ) 0 T H L x u Ru S x f x G x u u u            <label>(12)</label></formula><p>The optimal control law u can be derived from <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> as</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">  1 1 ( ) ( ) 2 T u R S xG x    . (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">)</formula><p>The steady-state, Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equation for the controlled nonlinear dynamic system ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">8</ref>) is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">  1 1 1 ( , ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) 4 [ ( ) ( )] 0. L x u S x F x L x S x f x S x G x R S x G x       <label>(14)</label></formula><p>Thus, the performance criterion is written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">  1 1 1 ( ) ( ) ( ) [ ( ) ( )] ( ) ( ) 4 L x S x G x R S x G x S x f x    <label>(15)</label></formula><p>Assume there exists a continuous differentiable function of Lyapunov candidate ( ) 0 V x  , which satisfying the following conditions:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">( ) ( ) ( ) ( ). dV x dV x dx S x F x dt dx dt   (16)   ( ) ( ) , &gt;0, 0&lt; &lt;1. dV x V x dt      <label>(17)</label></formula><p>Then, the system (8) is globally finite-time stable under the control law of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">13</ref>), which satisfies the following conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>: lim ( ( )) 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">( ( )) 0, t T V x t V x t t T         (<label>18</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">)</formula><p>with the finite settling time function given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">  1 0 1 ( ) . (1 ) T Vx      <label>(19)</label></formula><p>IV. PROPOSED DISTRIBUTED OPTIMAL CONTROL ALGORITHM Consider an islanded AC MG consisting of multiple inverter-based DGs. Each DG unit is composed of a DC voltage source, a voltage-source inverter (VSI), and an inductance-capacitance-inductance (LCL) filter, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">Qi Load i MG Power Calculation Current Controller Pi PWM Voltage Controller li i oi v fi C oi i Power Controller * li i * oi v ni  ni V bi v ci ci R jX  fi jX DC V Inverter Fig. 1.</formula><p>Block diagram of the primary droop control of a DG <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>.</p><p>The locally deployed LCL filter in each DG makes the output impedance inductive dominant <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, then the power sharing control laws that allow the active and reactive power to be shared based on DG units' rated capacities according to the droop settings, can be written as <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">ni i Pi i m P     (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">) ni oi Qi i V V m Q  <label>(21)</label></formula><p>where ωni and Vni are the nominal set points for frequency and voltage, ωi and Vni are the frequency and voltage of DG i, mPi and mQi are the frequency and voltage magnitude droop coefficients of DG i, respectively. The droop coefficient are generally set according to mPi=Δω/Pi,max and mQi=ΔV/Qi,max with the maximum acceptable frequency and voltage magnitude deviations Δω and ΔV.</p><p>The primary control cannot eliminate frequency and voltage deviations, which need to be compensated by employing the secondary control. According to the proposed distributed secondary control approach, only the local information and neighbors' information of DG i is required to update ωni and Vni in the primary control laws in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">20</ref>)&amp; <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>.</p><p>Differentiate ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">20</ref>) &amp; ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">21</ref>), choose the changing rate of frequency and active power output as the control variables, yield:</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">ni i Pi i i Pi m P u u           (22) = ni oi Qi i Vi Qi V V m Q u u      <label>(23)</label></formula><p>The nominal value of the frequency and voltage magnitude can be derived as: 0 ( ) ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">t P ni i i t u u d         (24) 0 ( ) ( ) t V Q ni i i t V u u d      <label>(25)</label></formula><p>The fundamental objectives of the proposed secondary control approach are to restore the DG's frequency and voltage magnitude to the desired values and achieve accurate active/reactive power sharing, which are summarized as follows:</p><p>(1). lim ( ) 0, ( ) , (3). Trade-off between lim ( ) 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">ref ref i i t T t t t T            ;<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">ref oi t V t V    and max max ( ) ( ) lim 0 ( ) ( ) j i t i j Q t Q t Q t Q t    .</formula><p>where </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Distributed Optimal Finite-time Secondary Frequency Control and Active Power Sharing</head><p>Consider an islanded MG with n DG units, the frequency and active power dynamic behavior after applying the control strategy in ( <ref type="formula">22</ref>) is described by the following state-space equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">P P x u x u           <label>(26)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">  1 = , , T n x     ,   1 1</formula><p>= , ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">T P P P n n x m P m P  , 1 =( , , ) n u u u     ,   1 = , , P P P n u u u  .</formula><p>Design the following two Lyapunov candidates as</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">2 2 2 2 4 2 = ( ) ( ) k k T r e f T r e f V x D x x x C x x k k             (<label>27</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">) 2 2 4 = k T P P P P V x D x k (<label>28</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_31">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">D ω =[d ωij ], C ω =diag{c ωi }, D P =[D Pij ], 1&lt;k&lt;2 is the fractional power constant.</formula><p>The partial derivatives of V ω and V P w.r.t x ω and x P , respectively, can be calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">1 1 = = 2[ ( ) sign( ) ( ) sign( ) ] i k k i i j j i j i j N i k k r e f r e f i i i V S d x c                          (29) 1 = 2 [ ( ) s i g n ( ) ] i k k P Pi Pij Pj j Pi i Pj j Pi i j N Pi V S d m P m P m P m P x          (30)</formula><p>The distributed optimal control law can be derived based on ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">13</ref>), ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>), ( <ref type="formula">30</ref>):</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">1 1 1 = [ ( ) sign( ) ( ) sign( ) ] i k k i i i j j i j i j N k k r e f r e f i i i u r d c                       (31) 1 1 = [ ( ) sign( )] i k k Pi Pi Pij Pj j Pi i Pj j Pi i j N u r d m P m P m P m P      <label>(32)</label></formula><p>Inspired by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, the finite-time convergence proof of the proposed optimal distributed control algorithm is presented as follows.</p><p>First, the global frequency and active power errors are defined as: <ref type="figure">,</ref><ref type="figure">,</ref><ref type="figure"></ref> ) </p><formula xml:id="formula_35">1 1 =( , )=( , , ) ref ref n n e e e            (33) 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 =( , )=(</formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">n</formula><formula xml:id="formula_37">       <label>(34)</label></formula><p>Choose the following Lyapunov candidate as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">    2 1 1 = = 0 2 2 T T e e P P P V V V e e e e      <label>(35)</label></formula><p>The first order derivative of (35) w.r.t. t is calculated as: </p><formula xml:id="formula_39">2 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 = = [ ( ) sign( ) ( ) sign( ) ] + ( ) sign( ) 1 ( ) ( ) 2 i n n i i P i P i i i n k k k k i i ij j i j i i i i i j N n k P k i Pi Pij Pj Pi Pj Pi i n k k k i i j j i i i i V e</formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">                                                 1 1 1 1 ( ) 2 n n k k k i P i P i j P j P i i i e r d e e        </formula><p>(36) According to the Cauchy inequality, the following relationship can be derived:</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">I II 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 1 1 2 2 2 2 1 1 [ ( ) ( ) 2 ( ) ( ) ] 2 1 [ ( ) ( ) ] 2 k n n k k i i j j i i i i i i k n k Pi Pij Pj Pi i V r d e e r c e r d e e                              . (<label>37</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">)</formula><p>According to the properties in ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) &amp; ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">7</ref>), the two terms on the right hand side of (37) can be rewritten as </p><formula xml:id="formula_43">2 2 2 I 2 2 2 2 2 2 1 1 =2 ( ) 2 ( ) =4 ( ) T k T k k e e R D C e D C R e e D C R V                        <label>(38)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">      <label>(39)</label></formula><p>Therefore,</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">        2 2 2 2 2 2 1 2 1 1 2 2 1 1 2 2 2 2 2 1 2 1 1 4 ( ) 4 ( ) 2 2 = 2 ( ) ( ) 2 ( ) ( ) . k k e Pe P k k k k k k e P P e P V D C V D V R D C V R D V                        (<label>40</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_46">)</formula><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>, the finite time stability of the frequency and active power control problem can be achieved within the settling time T=max {T ω , T P } as</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">      1 1 2 2 2 1 2 2 2 2 2 2 1 1 1 2 2 2 2 2 ( (0)) 2 ( (0)) = = 2 ( ) ( 1 ) (2 ) ( ) 2 2 ( ( 0 ) ) = (2 ) ( ) k k k e e k k k k k P eP P P k P R V e R V e T k D C k D C R V e T k D                                     (41)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Distributed Optimal Secondary Voltage Control and Reactive Power Sharing</head><p>Taking into account the power line impedance effect, the control objective of voltage restoration and accurate reactive power sharing cannot be achieved simultaneously, unless for a perfect symmetric configuration <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. To reach a compromise between accurate reactive power sharing and voltage regulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, a distributed optimal control strategy is designed to bring all DGs' voltages close to the desired value while ensure reactive power sharing accuracy.</p><p>The estimated average voltage (EAV) and reactive power dynamics after applying the control strategy is described by the following state-space equations:</p><p>1551-3203 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TII.2018.2795584, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">V V Q Q x u x u         <label>(42)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">  1 = , , T V o o n x V V </formula><p>, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">  1 1 = , , T Q Q Q n n x m Q m Q  .</formula><p>Design the following two Lyapunov candidates for EAV and reactive power sharing as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">  ref ref =2 [( ) ( )] T T V V V V V V V V V V x D x x x C x x    (43)   =2 T Q Q Q Q V x D x (44)</formula><p>The partial derivatives of ( <ref type="formula">43</ref>) and (44) w.r.t ˆând V Q x x , respectively, can be calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">= = 2 ( ) ( ) i ref V oj oi oi oi Vi Vij Vi j N oi V S d V V c V V V         (45) = 2 ( ) ˆi Q Pi Q i jQ j j Q i i j N Qi V S d mQ mQ x        (46)</formula><p>The distributed optimal control law for EAV and reactive power sharing can be derived based on ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">13</ref>), ( <ref type="formula">45</ref>), ( <ref type="formula">46</ref>):</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">1 = [ ( ) ( )] i ref Vi oi oj oi oi oi Vi Vij Vi j N u V r d V V c V V         (47) 1 = [ ( )] i Qi Qi i Qi Qij Qj j Qi i j N u m Q r d m Q m Q      <label>(48)</label></formula><p>Define the error terms for as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">1 1 1 1 1 1 1 =( , )=( , , ) n n Q Q Qn Q Qi i Qn n Qi i i i e e e m Q m Q m Q m Q n n        <label>(49) 1 =( , ,</label></formula><p>) <ref type="formula" target="#formula_48">42</ref>), ( <ref type="formula">47</ref>)&amp;(48), the dynamics of the error terms for EAV and reactive power sharing can be obtained as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">ref ref o o n V e V V V V    (50) From (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_56">Q Q Q Q e R D e   (51) ( ) V V V V V e R D C e   </formula><p>(52) Since all the eigenvalues of DQ are less than zero, the analytical solution to (51) can be obtained as follows: lim ( ) limexp( ) (0) (0) 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">T Q Q Q Q Q Q t t e t D t R e R e      11 . (<label>53</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_58">)</formula><p>where 1=(1,…,1) T . Thus, accurate reactive power sharing is achieved as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">1 1 1 1 ( )= = ( )= = ( )= ( ) n Q Qi i Qn n Qi i i m Q m Q m Q m Q n        <label>(54)</label></formula><p>The Laplace transformation of (52) can be represented by: ( ) (0)= ( ) ( ) <ref type="formula">55</ref>), the dynamic performance of the system in s domain can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">V V V V V V sE s e R D C E s   (55) From (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_61">1 ( )=[ ( )] (0) V V V V V E s sI R D C e    . (<label>56</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_62">)</formula><p>where I is the identity matrix.</p><p>Since ( ) 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">V V D C  </formula><p>, by using the final value theorem, it can be derived that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">  1 0 0 ( ) lim ( ) lim ( ) lim (0) 0 V V V V V V t s s sI R D C e t sE s s e          . (57) Therefore, 1 ( )= = ( ) = ( )= ref o o i o n V V V V       .</formula><p>(58) Next, the distributed updating law for the voltage magnitude is designed as =</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">V V V V V u x x D x    <label>(59)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">  1 = , , T V o o n x V V  with (0)= (0) V V x x . ( ) (0)= ( ) (0) ( ) V V V V V V sX s x sX s x D X s    .</formula><p>(60) Eqn. (60) can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">1 ( )= ( ) ( ) V V V X s s sI D X s   . (<label>61</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_68">)</formula><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, one can get that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">1 0 1 lim ( ) = T V s s sI D n    11 , thus, 2 1 0 0 1 0 0 lim ( )= lim ( )= lim ( ) ( ) = lim ( ) lim ( ) 1 = ( ) V V V V t s s V V s s T V x t sX s s sI D X s s sI D sX s x n           11 (62)</formula><p>It can be easily derived from (62) that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">1 1 1 ( )= = ( ) = ( ) ( ) n o o i o n o i i V V V V n          <label>(63)</label></formula><p>Combine ( <ref type="formula">58</ref>) with (63), yields,</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">1 1 ( ) n ref oi i V V n     . (<label>64</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_72">)</formula><p>Therefore, the average value of all bus voltage magnitudes will converge to the desired voltage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Communication delay analysis</head><p>Since a communication network is employed for the proposed distributed approach to transmit/receive neighboring information, communication delay is unavoidable. Therefore, the impact of communication delay should be analyzed.</p><p>According to (61), the proposed distributed voltage control algorithm with communication delay for a microgrid can be represented as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">( ) ( ) [ ( ( )) ( ( ))] oi oi oj j oi i Vij V t V t d V t t V t t           (<label>65</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_74">)</formula><p>where τi(t) is the time-varying delay which satisfies Eqn. (65) can be further rewritten in a matrix form as follows:</p><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ( )) o o o V V VV V t I D V t D C R V t t       </formula><p>. (66) According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, system represented in (66) is stable with a bounded communication delay. The maximum tolerable communication delay can be calculated using Ricatti equation based analysis as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, which is omitted for brevity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Algorithm implementation</head><p>The diagram of the proposed distributed control strategy is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The local secondary controller only requires reference values and information from neighboring controllers, using the peer-to-peer communication protocol. Next, the nominal values for each local DG, ωni and Vni, employed in the primary control stage, are updated by integrating the control input signals of uωi+uPi, and uVi+uQi, respectively. According to the proposed distributed control strategy, the frequency and voltage regulations can be implemented in different time scales. Thus, the design of active and reactive power controllers can be decoupled. </p><formula xml:id="formula_76">ref ref j j j o i jt i P Q V V j N    oi V Vi u Pi u i u  Qi u sin( ) oi i V t  ci ci R jX  bi v 2.</formula><p>A block diagram of the proposed optimal distributed control strategy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. SIMULATION STUDIES</head><p>In this section, the effectiveness of the proposed optimal distributed secondary control approach is demonstrated through several case studies. An islanded 5-bus MG (frequency 50 Hz, line-line AC voltage 380 V) as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>, which is built in the MATLAB/Simulink. The parameters of the DGs, transmission lines and loads are presented in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. General Performance Evaluation</head><p>Initially, the conventional droop control strategy is applied to the islanded MG, at t=1 s, the proposed control strategy is activated, at t=2 s, an additional load of 1.5 kW+0.9 kVAr is suddenly connected to the MG and then removed at t=3 s. Before implementing the proposed distributed secondary control, the frequency and voltage magnitude cannot reach the desired value under the primary droop control. The frequency profiles of all DGs are able to converge to the desired value within a finite-time of 0.4 s, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref> (a). The voltage magnitude of DGs are regulated to be close to 380 V (±1.5 V) within 0.6 s, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4 (b)</ref>. After applying the proposed secondary control algorithm, the active/reactive power can be shared close to the desired ratio in spite of load variations, as demonstrated in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4 (c)</ref>&amp;<ref type="figure">(d)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Convergence Speed Analysis</head><p>In this study case, the comparison of the proposed optimal distributed frequency controller (31)&amp;(32) with the one presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> is conducted for convergence speed analysis.</p><p>For simplicity, only the frequency response mean square error (MSE) of DG 1 is presented for comparison. The result of Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> verifies that the proposed distributed strategy can achieve faster convergence speed.  <ref type="figure">6</ref>, which indicates that convergence of the tracking error is faster if ki is closer to 1 while slower if ki is closer to 2. Notice that, when ki=2, the proposed control strategy actually becomes the traditional asymptotical convergence control algorithm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Impact of communication delay</head><p>Communication delay is unavoidable for distributed control algorithm which requires communications among neighboring DGs. Since communication delay may significantly affect the system's dynamic performance, the impact of communication delay on the proposed distributed method is investigated and compared with that of the traditional centralized method for two communication latency bounds of 200 ms and 500 ms, other conditions remain the same as those of Case A. The time delay is implemented by using a pure delay block e -τ(t)s in the simulation. However, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref> (a), the centralized approach fails to restore the frequency within 1 s before the occurrence of next event in the MG when the communication delay is increased to 500 ms. The proposed distributed approach still achieves acceptable performance with a communication delay of 500 ms as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">8 (b)</ref>, which shows its advantage over the centralized approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Robustness against parameter uncertainty</head><p>To investigate the robustness of the proposed control approach against parameter uncertainties, the line impedances are perturbed with a random range of 10%-30% with respect to the values in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>, other conditions remain the same as those of Case A. show that active and reactive power sharing can still be maintained with very small fluctuations. These behaviors are caused by the inaccurate estimated states due to the model uncertainties. However, the performances of active/reactive power sharing are still acceptable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Influence of bounded control input</head><p>Due to physical limitations, controller with bounded input should be considered for practical applications. The control parameter ri have a direct impact on the dynamic performance of the proposed distributed secondary control, which are investigated in this study case.  The value of ri balances between the convergence speed and the required control effort. Larger ri leads to slower convergence speed and smaller control effort. As shown in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">10 (a</ref>)&amp;(b), the frequency restoration time under the proposed distributed control approach with ri=1.5 is approximately 0.55 s, however, the control inputs exceed the boundary during the time period of 1 s-1.1 s. As shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">11 (a</ref>)&amp;(b), the frequency restoration process is completed with a longer time interval of 0.8 s when ri=3, but control inputs are maintained within the boundary and the ramping rate is also smaller than that of the case with ri=1.5. Notice that, the settling time provided in (41) is the upper bound of the convergence time, which is conservative, thus, the actual convergence time will not increase linearly with the value of ri.</p><p>From the above analysis, it can be concluded that one can easily adjust ri to handle the situation of bounded control input with ramping rate limit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. Plug and Play Capability</head><p>Plug and play is a technology allows new DGs to be added in and existing DGs to be removed out without any centralized supervision or redesigning the microgrid control system. It is desirable for MG to support plug-and-play functionality, due to the availability of renewable generators. The autonomous MG with five DGs and five loads is operating under the primary control at t=0 s, and the proposed distributed secondary control strategy is applied at t=1 s. An additional DG6 (power rating: 2.0 kW+1.0 kVAr, the corresponding line impedance Z16 is 0.08+j0.18 Ω) is suddenly connected at t=2 s, and then DG 3 is disconnected at t=3 s. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. Scalability Test</head><p>This study case investigates the scalability of the proposed distributed optimal control with the 42-node distribution system <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">13</ref>. By assuming the communication network to be the same as the power transmission line connections, the communication graph's algebraic connectivity is λ2=0.066.  It should be noted that, the maximum tolerable communication delay depends on the eigenvalues of the communication graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, which are determined by the number of devices (scalability), number of communication channels, connectivity (refer to the way the devices are connected). Large system may have a small maximum tolerable communication delay, which implies that the scalability of a distributed approach can be limited by the communication delay to some extent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSION</head><p>This paper proposes an optimal distributed control strategy for secondary frequency and voltage regulations in an islanded 1551-3203 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TII.2018.2795584, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics MG. The proposed control strategy is implemented using a neighbor-to-neighbor communication protocol, which enables efficient distributed data processing, supports plug-and-play functionality, and facilitates system scalable expansion. The proposed finite-time controller provides the frequency regulation and active power sharing be achieved within a finite time, which enables the decoupled design for voltage regulation and reactive power sharing at a different time scale. Simulation results demonstrate that the effectiveness of the proposed optimal distributed strategy in islanded MGs with unequal line impedances in spite of load variations and plugand-play operations. Future work will focus on the following four topics: 1) Investigation of priorities of DGs, since it might be more economical to control several important DGs in VSI mode, while controlling other less important DGs in current source mode.</p><p>2) Digital implementation of the proposed distributed control approach considering the communication package drops.</p><p>3) Rigorous analysis of maximum tolerable communication time delay for distributed finite-time control algorithm, especially for frequency control which is time critical.</p><p>4) Comprehensive study about the combination of communication delay and scalability, since the scalability of a distributed control depends on several factors, i.e., number of devices, communication topologies, communication delays, sampling rates. etc.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>being the tolerable communication delay upper bound.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1551-3203 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TII.2018.2795584, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>5 Fig. 3 . 5</head><label>535</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. A single-line diagram of the 5-bus MG TABLE I PARAMETERS FOR THE TESTED ISLANDED MG DG1&amp;DG2 3.0 kW+1.5 kVAr DG3~DG5 2.0 kW+1.0 kVAr DGs mP 5*10 -5 mP 6 . 5 * 1 0 -5 mQ 6*10 -4 mQ 8*10 -4 Z c 0.04+j0.25 Ω Zc 0.03+j0.15 Ω Lf 1.5 mH Lf 1.5 mH Cf 47 μF Cf 47μF Lines Z14 &amp;Z23 0.05+j0.15 Ω Z15&amp;Z25 0.04+j0.1 Ω Z 12 0.08+j0.2 Ω Z34 0.1+j0.25 Ω Loads L1 1.5 kW+1.5 kVAr L3 &amp;L4 2.0 kW+0.5 kVAr L2 2.5 kW+0.8 kVAr L5 1.0 kW+1.2 kVAr</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Performances of the proposed control approach under load variations</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Comparison between the traditional control method [17] and the proposed control strategy</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .Fig. 8 .</head><label>78</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Comparison of frequency dynamic responses with the communication delay bound of 200 ms</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. System performance under line parameters uncertainties Figs. 9 (a)&amp;(b) show that active and reactive power sharing can still be maintained with very small fluctuations. These behaviors are caused by the inaccurate estimated states due to the model uncertainties. However, the performances of active/reactive power sharing are still acceptable.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. System performance when ri=1.5</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. System dynamic performance under the plug-and-play operation As shown in Figs. 12 (a)&amp;(b), the frequency and voltage remain stable with only small transient variations in spite of DG's plug-and-play operations. As shown in Figs. 12 (c)&amp;(d), when DG5 is plugged in at t=2 s, the DGs in the islanded MG manage to share the loads under the desired ratios. It can be observed that the active and reactive power outputs of DG 3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 13 .Fig. 14 .</head><label>1314</label><figDesc>Fig. 13. Single-line diagram of the 42-node test systemBefore t=4 s, the 42-node test system is operating in the islanded mode with total loads of 180MW, 60MVAr, and DGs are controlled under the conventional droop control method. At t=4 s, the proposed distributed discrete algorithm is implemented, additional loads of 8.5 MW, 4.5 MVAr, are connected to the buses at t=12 s.The active/reactive power sharing performances of the test system are shown in Figs.14 (a)&amp;(b), respectively. The active and reactive power utilization ratio reach consensus within 5 s, which verifies the possible applications of the proposed distributed strategy to large systems.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>.</figDesc><table><row><cell>lim P t T </cell><cell>max ( ) ( ) i P t i P t P t max ( ) ( ) j j P t </cell><cell></cell><cell>0,</cell><cell>max ( ) ( ) i P t i P t</cell><cell></cell><cell>max ( ) ( ) j j P t P t</cell><cell>,</cell><cell>P t T  ;</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TII.2018.2795584, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics</figDesc><table><row><cell>max ( ) ( ) i P t i P t Q t max ( ) , ( ) i i Q t</cell><cell>are the active and reactive power</cell></row></table><note><p><p>utilization ratios of DG i, respectively.</p>1551-3203 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TII.2018.2795584, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics</figDesc><table /><note><p>1551-3203 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trends in microgrid control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Olivares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mehrizi-Sani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Etemadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Smart Grid</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1905" to="1919" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-07">Jul. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed subgradient-based coordination of multiple renewable generators in a microgrid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Power Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchical control of droop-controlled AC and DC microgrids -a general approach toward standardization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Vasquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Matas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vicuna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Castilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advanced control architectures for intelligent microgrids-Part I: Decentralized and hierarchical control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chandorkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Loh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1254" to="1262" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-04">Apr. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized cooperative control strategy of microsources for stabilizing autonomous VSC-based microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Divshali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alimardani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hosseinian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Abedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Power Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1949" to="1959" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-11">Nov. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust droop controller for accurate proportional load sharing among inverters operated in parallel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1281" to="1290" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-04">Apr. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multi-functional fully distributed control framework for AC microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Shafiee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Nasirian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Vasquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Davoudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Smart Grid</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to be published</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Potential-function based control of a microgrid in islanded and grid-connected models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mehrizi-Sani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Iravani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Power Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1883" to="1891" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-11">Nov. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Centralized control for parallel operation of distributed generation inverters in microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>So</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Smart Grid</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1977" to="1987" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-12">Dec. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A decentralized and cooperative architecture for optimal voltage regulation in smart grids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vaccaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Velotto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Zobaa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4593" to="4602" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-10">Oct. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Agent-based decentralized control method for islanded microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Smart Grid</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="649" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-03">Mar. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multi-objective distributed control framework for islanded AC microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bidram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Davoudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1785" to="1798" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-08">Aug. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed secondary control for islanded microgrids-A novel approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Shafiee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Juan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Power Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1018" to="1031" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-02">Feb. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smart coordination of energy storage units for voltage and loading management in distribution networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mokhtari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nourbakhsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Power Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4812" to="4820" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-11">Nov. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus-based secondary frequency and voltage droop control of virtual synchronous generators for isolated AC microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Emerg. Sel. Top. Circuits Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-09">Sept. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed adaptive virtual impedance control for accurate reactive power sharing based on consensus control in microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Smart Grid</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1749" to="1761" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed cooperative secondary control of microgrids using feedback linearization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bidram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Davoudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Power Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3462" to="3470" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-08">Aug. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synchronization and power sharing for droop-controlled inverters in islanded microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Simpson-Porco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Dorfler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bullo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2603" to="2611" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-09">Sep. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secondary frequency and voltage control of islanded microgrids via distributed averaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Simpson-Porco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Shafiee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Dorfler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Vasquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bullo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7025" to="7038" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-11">Nov. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-Ktime approximate consensus and its application to distributed frequency regulation in islanded AC microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Cady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dominguez-Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hadjicostis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 48th Hawaii Int. Conf. on Syst. Sci. (HICSS)</title>
		<meeting>48th Hawaii Int. Conf. on Syst. Sci. (HICSS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2664" to="2670" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed secondary voltage and frequency restoration control of droop-controlled inverter-based microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4355" to="4364" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed finite-time voltage and frequency restoration in islanded AC microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Davoudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5988" to="5997" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed robust finite-time secondary voltage and frequency control of islanded microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dehkordi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sadati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hamzeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Power Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3648" to="3659" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus problem in networks of agents with switching topology and time-delays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Olfati-Saber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murrary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1520" to="1533" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-09">Sep. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus problems for networks of dynamic agents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automa. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="950" to="955" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-04">Apr. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time stabilization and optimal feedback control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Haddad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>L'afflitto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Automa. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1074" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-04">April 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel distributed secondary coordination control approach for islanded microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Smart Grid</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to be published</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A distributed finite-time secondary average voltage regulation and current sharing controller for DC microgrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sahoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mishra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Smart Grid</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to be published</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining control strategies for microgrids islanded operation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A P</forename><surname>Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Moreira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Madureira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Power Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="916" to="924" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-05">May 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uniform marginal pricing for the remuneration of distribution networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jesus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yusta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Power Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1302" to="1310" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-08">Aug. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
