<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A meta-learning framework using representation learning to predict drug-drug interaction</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Deepika</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Geetha</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A meta-learning framework using representation learning to predict drug-drug interaction</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jbi.2018.06.015</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received Date: 14 January 2018 Revised Date: 22 June 2018 Accepted Date: 25 June 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-01-03T08:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Drug-drug interaction prediction</term>
					<term>Positive-Unlabeled learning</term>
					<term>Meta-learning</term>
					<term>Representation learning</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Motivation</head><p>Predicting Drug-Drug Interaction (DDI) has become a crucial step in the drug discovery and development process, owing to the rise in the number of drugs co-administered with other drugs.</p><p>Consequently, the usage of computational methods for DDI prediction can greatly help in reducing the costs of in vitro experiments done during the drug development process. With lots of emergent data sources that describe the properties and relationships between drugs and drug-related entities (gene, protein, disease, and side effects), an integrated approach that uses multiple data sources would be most effective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>We propose a semi-supervised learning framework which utilizes representation learning, positive-unlabeled (PU) learning and meta-learning efficiently to predict the drug interactions. Information from multiple data sources is used to create feature networks, which is used to learn the meta-knowledge about the DDIs. Given that DDIs have only positive labeled data, a PU learningbased classifier is used to generate meta-knowledge from feature networks. Finally, a metaclassifier that combines the predicted probability of interaction from the meta-knowledge learnt is designed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Node2vec, a network representation learning method and bagging SVM, a PU learning algorithm, are used in this work. Both representation learning and PU learning algorithms improve the performance of the system by 22% and 12.7% respectively. The meta-classifier performs better and predicts more reliable DDIs than the base classifiers.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Drug-drug interactions occur when two or more drugs are administered together, influencing each other's effects and altering the way they act in the human body. These interactions between drugs can cause unexpected side effects or can increase or decrease the therapeutic effect of a drug.</p><p>A typical example is when aspirin is taken along with blood-thinners like Warfarin (Coumadin), it can lead to excessive bleeding. In recent years, more drugs are being approved faster and the number of persons with multiple chronic conditions is continually increasing. Approximately 71% of the total health care spending in the United States is associated with care for Americans with more than one chronic condition <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>. Thus, the number of drugs administered with other drugs has increased and we have arrived at a situation where polypharmacy or the use of four or more medications by a patient, mostly common among adults aged over 65 years, is the new norm.</p><p>The results of a research study by Kashyap et al. <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref> on elderly Indian patients confirms the occurrence of severe drug interactions among them. In fact, 3 to 5% of all in-hospital medication errors are due to "preventable" drug-drug interactions (DDIs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. DDIs have caused the withdrawal of certain high-profile drugs from the market. Therefore, it is crucial to evaluate drugs for potential drug interactions.</p><p>Unfortunately, most DDIs are reported only after the patient has experienced them, when the drug has already hit the market. This greatly affects patients' health and raises big questions about drug safety. Though conventional methods like adverse drug event reports, clinical trials and preclinical toxicity studies report some DDIs, they are subject to long experimental duration and incur high cost due to large number of drug pairs that need to be tested. As a result, many researchers have focused on computational methods for predicting DDIs and, in turn, making the process easier.</p><p>Computational prediction methods for DDIs can be broadly categorized into knowledgebased, similarity-based and network-based inferences. Knowledge-based methods <ref type="bibr">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> utilize scientific literature documents (MEDLINE), Electronic Medical Records, clinical trials, and the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System (FAERS) to predict DDIs, which involve text mining and data mining techniques. Tari et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> proposed a novel approach using 'biological domain knowledge' to discover DDIs from MEDLINE abstracts. In this work, the text mining approach is integrated with automated reasoning to discover interactions that are not explicit in documents and not present in DrugBank. Duke et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> undertook a literature survey and analysis of Electronic Health Records and predicted the drug interactions present in those documents. Deep learning models like the Convolution Neural Network (CNN) and Recurrent Neural Network (RNN) are used to extract DDIs from scientific documents <ref type="bibr">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</p><p>The network-based inference method tries to infer indirect interactions between drugs using network inference algorithms from the biological network, involving various biomedical entities <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> constructed a drug interaction network using the clinical side-effect similarity measure. A label propagation algorithm was applied in this network to predict new interactions among drugs. Takarabe et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> designed a network-based analysis of drugs in the KEGG DRUG and JAPIC databases using Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) codes, drug targets, drug metabolizing enzymes and drug pathways. Based on the analysis, they developed a DDI retrieval system to search and predict interactions in the KEGG DRUG database. Cami et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> constructed a DDI network and used a multivariate model to predict drug interaction. New interactions were predicted using the network structure and properties of the drugs.</p><p>The similarity-based approach is built on the assumption that similar drugs interact with each other. A large number of similarity measures have been used to compute the similarities between the drugs pairs <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>. Vilar et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> analyzed the molecular structural similarity of different drugs in DrugBank to find DDIs. Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> computed the side-effect similarity among drug pairs and used it to predict drug interaction. Later, Vilar et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> modelled an interaction profile fingerprint as a similarity measure to identify drug-drug interactions. In this work, they observed an increase in the performance of the DDI prediction task after using heterogeneous features.</p><p>Recent studies have highlighted how important heterogeneous features are for DDI prediction task that use multiple data sources <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>. Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> proposed joint matrix factorization approach for drug repurposing by integrating multiple information sources. Fokoue et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> presented a framework using link prediction for the DDI task, considering 13 similarity measures for each drug pair. These similarity measures were used as features to create a logistic regression model to predict DDIs. Cheng and Zhao <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> calculated four types of similarities (genomic, phenotypic, therapeutic, and structural) as features of each drug pair. From these similarities, a heterogeneous network-assisted inference model using machine learning algorithms was built for the prediction task. Takeda et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> constructed interaction networks which incorporate pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic knowledge of the drug along with its structural similarities. Logistic regression was used to predict drug interaction, and the results indicate a large increase in predictive power when the similarity scores are integrated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PU Learning</head><p>Traditional binary classifiers in machine learning use positive and negative labels present in labeled data to classify unlabeled data. In scenarios where the labeled data for a particular task contains only positive labels, Positive-Unlabeled (PU) learning is a suitable option. In PU learning, we have two classes: the positive class, P (containing only positive examples), and the unlabeled class, U (containing positive and negative examples). The goal of PU learning is to identify appropriate positive examples from the unlabeled class <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>.</p><p>In the context of DDI prediction, we have a lot of data sources like DrugBank <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> and TWOSIDES <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, from which labeled data can be accessed. However, most of the available data sources provide information only about positive labels, i.e. two drugs that interact with each other.</p><p>Information about drug pairs that do not interact with each other [negative labels] is very less. Positive-Unlabeled learning addresses this issue by learning from the positive and the unlabeled data.</p><p>Hence, we propose a PU learning-based classifier to predict possible DDIs.</p><p>The two forms of PU learning, according to Mordelet and Vert <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, are transductive and inductive, and several authors have proposed different approaches to resolve PU learning problems.</p><p>Traditional binary classification algorithms cannot be used directly to solve PU learning problems as they require negative examples in the labeled data. Learning the classification algorithm only from positive labels, like a one-class SVM <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, results in poor performance, so semi-supervised methods are exploited to solve the problem. Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> illustrates the difference between learning from only positive labeled data and learning from both positive and unlabeled data. Semisupervised methods have one-step, two-step and iterative strategies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1: PU learning</head><p>A two-step strategy is commonly used where the first step is identifying from "U" a set of reliable negative examples, "N". In the next step, the positive and negative set is used to train the traditional binary classifier <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. The one-step strategy discriminates the positive set, "P", from the unlabeled set, "U". Weighted logistic regression <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> and biased SVM <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> are two algorithms proposed to solve PU learning. Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> proposed Dyadic Positive Unlabeled (DyPU) learning to detect positive interactions from the unlabeled data. DyPU works by giving higher scores to posi-tive pairs ("on top of") than the average score of the unlabeled pairs and it gives better performance compared to the state-of-the-art methods. An iterative, partially supervised algorithm has been proposed by Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> for text classification. Iterative methods aggregate classifiers trained on "P" and "U" to improve the performance of PU learning when the classifiers trained are unstable. As the size of the positive labeled data is very small compared to the unlabeled set, the classifiers have a higher probability of being unstable. Hence an iterative method which uses the bagging (bootstrap aggregation) SVM proposed by Mordelet and Vert <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> is used for the drug interaction prediction task.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Meta-learning</head><p>Recent works in bioinformatics have seen an increased use of ensemble-based methods.</p><p>Classification of gene expression microarray data, gene-gene interaction identification and gene function prediction are certain applications where ensemble methods have been used <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. In a typical machine learning problem, a single learning algorithm is created and evaluated against others.</p><p>Meta-learning is a technique under ensemble learning where the system tries to learn from different learning algorithms to enhance the overall prediction accuracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. It is about learning from learned knowledge. Learned knowledge from base learners, called meta-knowledge, is given as input to a meta-learner to finally predict the output. The intuition behind meta-learning is the human decision process, where a human takes the final decision combining diverse, independent opinions. The two main approaches towards meta-learning are stacked generalization and cascade generalization <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. In stacked generalization, the base learners are learnt from the same dataset and their outputs combined to form a higher-level meta-model. In cascade generalization, the original feature set is appended with the output of the base learner and given to the next base learner. This approach works sequentially. Traditional machine learning algorithms which learn from their past experience have been successfully used in various meta-learning systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35]</ref>. Abbasi et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> developed a MetaFraud system using a meta-learning framework which utilizes stacked generalization and adaptive learning for financial fraud detection. The meta-learning framework resulted in an enhanced performance, compared to state-of-the-art financial fraud detection methods. A hierarchical meta-learning approach using stacked and cascade generalizations, developed for B-cell conformational epitope prediction, outperformed other single classifiers that performed well <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>.</p><p>Stacked generalization also performed better for the medical concept extraction process <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>.</p><p>In the case of drug-drug interaction, there are different reasons why two drugs interact with each other when co-administered, and this influences the DDI prediction task. It is perhaps because the two interacting drugs have a similar chemical structure or may treat the same disease, bind to the same target, and have the same side-effects. So then, two drugs must be similar in a way for them to interact with each other inside a human body. Therefore, we propose a holistic approach which learns, from different data sources, the meta-knowledge needed for the DDI task. This metaknowledge is generated by determining the similarity between the drugs through a networkembedding algorithm and by using a PU learning-based classifier called the bagging SVM classifier.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Material and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dataset Description</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drug Feature Data</head><p>The base classifiers of the meta-learning framework use four independent drug datasets from different data sources. The datasets include the drug substructure data from DrugBank <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, the drug target interaction data from DrugBank <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, the side-effects of drugs from SIDER <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, and the treatment relationship between drugs and diseases from the work of Li and Lu <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. Each dataset is used to construct a feature network. The chemical substructure data, the drug target data, the sideeffects data and the treatment relationship data have 881 chemical substructures, 775 target proteins, 1385 side-effects and 719 diseases respectively. As we are constructing a meta-classifier without any missing values from the base classifiers, only the drugs common in all the datasets are taken into consideration. So, we get a total of 548 drugs in each dataset along with 603 chemical substructures, 578 target proteins, 1258 side-effects and 586 diseases as the input for the base classifiers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Positive DDIs</head><p>The base classifiers use the PU learning-based algorithm to identify interacting drug pairs. Therefore, we need a dataset for the positive labels, i.e. data about interacting drug pairs. A few data sources exist with drug interaction pairs developed for different purposes like NLP algorithm development <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, bioinformatics and clinical applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41]</ref>. DrugBank <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> is one such data source developed to support either pharmacovigilance or bioinformatics applications. DrugBank is chosen for this purpose because of its broad inclusion of drugs, including drugs marketed in different countries. A 2012 snapshot of DrugBank, used by Guimer? and Sales-Pardo <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, is taken as a backdated data set as a good choice for evaluating the prediction task. This DrugBank data consists of 10,878 drug pairs that interact from among the 1,116 drugs present in it. The entire set of drug pairs in this data cannot be considered as it contains drugs that are not present in the drug feature data (548 drugs). When both the drugs in the drug pair are present in the drug feature data, that par-ticular pair is considered for the positive label. This eventually ended in a positive DDI data set comprising 433 drugs and 3,299 drug pairs. The drug pairs in the unlabeled data set is calculated by determining unique drug combinations for the 548 drugs in the drug feature data. For n=548 and r=2 in , we get 1,49,878 unique combinations of drug pairs, out of which 1,46,579 pairs serve as unlabeled data. The ratio of positive labeled to unlabeled data is approximately 1:44.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposed Work</head><p>For predicting interaction between drug pairs, we propose a two-layered meta-learning framework, described in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>. The first layer of this framework, models homogeneous base classifiers (i.e.) it learns from different datasets, the same type of classifier across all the base learners. A semi-supervised learning-based classifier called the bagging SVM is used as the base classifier in this work. At the second layer, the predictions from the base classifiers are combined using a meta-classifier. The bagging SVM also acts as a meta-classifier in this work. The various factors contributing to the DDI are considered as the features and from these features, the feature networks are constructed.</p><p>The one hot-representation used in previous works <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref> has the disadvantage of being sparse and high in terms of dimension. To overcome this, the considered features are modeled as different networks and a network embedding algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> is applied to these networks to get a dense, low-dimensional representation for the drugs.  The phenotypic feature considers the response of the drug in the human body. The side effect caused by the drug is an essential phenotypic measure which is considered for creating the PFN. If two drugs have similar side-effects, there could be a mechanism-of-action (MOA) linking them and the side-effect can act as a phenotypic "biomarker" <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. The PFN has the drug node, the side-effect node and an edge representing the causal relationship between the two types of nodes. It has 548 drug nodes and 1258 side-effect nodes. Example: The drugs Amoxicillin and Methotrexate interact with each other and have several common side-effects.</p><p>Therapeutic Feature Network (TFN)</p><p>Drugs are discovered to cure a particular disease or an indication. The therapeutic feature is a direct observation on humans, thus having fewer translational issues compared to the animal models <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. The therapeutic feature takes into consideration the treatment relationship between the drug and the disease. The TFN has 548 drug nodes and 586 disease nodes. For example, the drugs Esmolol and Verapamil, used to treat a range of common indications, interact with each other.</p><p>The four FNs for the drug "Captopril" are illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>. "Captopril" has 64 substructures, so the drug node with the label "Captopril" will have 64 edges, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4b</ref>. It binds with 3 targets (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4c</ref>), treats 8 diseases (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4c</ref>), and causes 75 side-effects (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4a</ref>).</p><p>Vital network properties like the average degree and centrality measures of the four FNs are calculated and listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Representation Learning</head><p>Data representation or feature selection plays a crucial role in deciding the performance of machine learning algorithms. In representation learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, the input data is transformed into a representation that is useful and easy for machine learning algorithms to effectively exploit. This eliminates the manual feature selection process from the raw data which involves intensive human labor. The drug and drug-related nodes present in the different networks are required to get a continuous feature representation, and an algorithm called node2vec has been applied to this end.</p><p>Node2vec <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>, a scalable feature learning method designed for networks, preserves the local neighborhood of the nodes using a stochastic gradient descent (SGD). Breadth-first Sampling (BFS)</p><p>and Depth-first Sampling (DFS) strategies are used to explore the neighborhood of the nodes in the network. For each node in the network, by interpolating between homophily (DFS) and structural equivalence (BFS) using a biased random walk, a continuous feature representation is computed.</p><p>The parameters involved in node2vec are the number of features d and the node's neighborhood parameters (number of walks r, walk length l, and neighborhood size k). The likelihood of immediately revisiting a node in the walk is controlled by parameter p, and parameter q differentiates between "inward" and "outward" nodes. All these parameters can be tuned for different networks to get better representation. By default, the parameters considered for all the networks are d=128, r= 10, l =80, k=10, p=1, and q=0.5.</p><p>Feature learning for all the feature networks is based on the skip-gram architecture adapted for networks (non-linear). The node2vec algorithm is applied for each feature network to get a ddimensional feature representation for all the nodes in the network.  In inductive PU learning, the PU learner learns a function g: Y?R, from set P and U, that gives the probability of elements in Y to be positive. Here, the inductive learner is trained using P and U, but since the test data from Y may contain elements not present in both the sets, {P} U {U} is not equal to Y.</p><p>In transductive learning, {P} U {U} is equal to Y, i.e. all the instances of the test data are already known. The transductive learner learns from P and U, a function h: U?R, which gives the probability of elements in U to be positive. For the DDI prediction task, the whole set of drug pairs for which interaction has to be predicted is known during the training process and it comprises the set, U. The known interacting drug pairs constitute the positive labeled data, P. The probability of interaction between the drugs present in the set, U, is calculated using P and U. As {P} U {U} is equal to the universal set, the DDI prediction task is a transductive PU learning problem.</p><p>For the transductive PU learning task of drug interaction prediction, a semisupervised algorithm which exploits the information contained in the unlabeled distribution will perform better.</p><p>Hence, the bagging SVM technique proposed by Mordelet and Vert <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> is used as the base classifier. It is an iterative algorithm which discriminates {P} from {U} by training multiple binary classifiers from {P} and random subsamples of {U} and, finally, the predictions are averaged. The working of the bagging SVM is illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 6: Bagging SVM</head><p>For each drug pair in the unlabeled set, the prediction score is calculated using the semisupervised bagging SVM classifier, illustrated in Algorithm I. In the algorithm, and are known. The size of the bootstrap, , depends on the number of positive labeled data. is chosen such that . The number of bootstrap samples, , depends on the positive labeled , unlabeled data , and the size of the bootstrap, . From <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, it is noted that a larger and smaller would give better results. For the DDI task, we chose and .</p><p>For each drug node in the FN, the representation learning module outputs a d-dimensional vector. It is a float vector with values from -1 to +1, as node2vec uses the sigmoid activation function in the skip-gram architecture. The two data points (drugs) in the d-dimensional space will get a similar vector representation if the two drug nodes have a structural equivalence or homophily in the considered FN. To predict the interaction between the drug pairs in the constructed FN, the drug pairs should be represented in a d-dimensional space. However, the representation learning module learns a d-dimensional representation for each drug and not the drug pair. Hence, merging the two d-dimensional vectors to get a vector, or using any available distance metric would not be an effective solution to represent the drug pairs. The reason behind this is that in the ddimension vector for every drug, each value conveys information about the drug's position in the i th dimension.</p><p>Hence, combining the d dimensions to get a single numeric value to represent the drug pairs will lead to feature loss and, further, using a vector will not represent the drug pair in the ddimensional feature space. So, for each drug pair in the universal set, the absolute value of the difference is computed for each dimension in the drug's d-dimensional representation, as shown in Algorithm II. For each drug pair, Algorithm II outputs a single d-dimensional vector that is used to represent the drug pair in the d-dimensional feature space. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Meta-learning</head><p>Meta-learning is chosen for this task as different types of data influence DDIs, and metalearning is a learning methodology which exploits meta-knowledge about data to model an efficient system. Of the two meta-learning approaches, the stacking approach is used in this work. In stacking, instead of different classifiers on the same data set, the same type of classifier is trained on different data sets. Here, different data sets describe the features contributing to the DDI task (i.e.) different biomedical entities related to the drug entity. The probability of interaction between the drug pairs from each FN, along with the performance of each base classifier, constitutes the metaknowledge for the DDI task.</p><p>The algorithm for the meta-learning framework is Algorithm III. The number of features, N, given in the algorithm is a scalable factor. In this work, four important features which have high chances of contributing to the DDI task are considered. For each feature , the constructed FN acts as the unlabeled data for that feature, i.e., . Using and the labeled data , the base classifiers are trained for each feature. The bagging SVM is used as the base classifier. Each drug pair in the unlabeled data gets a score, , from each base classifier. This score is computed, based on the probability of interaction obtained from the base classifier, , and the performance of the base classifier, . In this work, for the four FNs -CFN, BFN, PFN and DFN -the performance values are , , , and respectively, and this value is constant for all the drug pairs.</p><p>The probability of interaction between the drug pairs for the FNs is a variable value. After the base classifier, the meta-classifier has to be trained using the output of the base classifiers. For this purpose, the drug pairs (labeled and unlabeled) are represented using the scores obtained from the base classifiers, as shown in Algorithm III. The bagging SVM also acts as the meta-classifier to predict the interacting drug pairs from the unlabeled data. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>The performance of the meta-learning framework using network embedding and PU learning for the DDI task is evaluated with 5-fold cross validation of the positive labeled data. As the aim of the learning task is predicting new positive DDI, and due to lack of gold standard data for negative DDI, the evaluation metrics are so chosen that they contain only true positive, false positives and false negatives values <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. Precision, Recall and F1-score are used as evaluation metrics and their equations are given below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bagging SVM</head><p>In the bagging SVM approach, the K-value decides the number of bootstrap samples to be selected, and this value varies for different datasets depending on the size of the positive and unlabeled data. Consequently, the classifiers are trained on different values of K, and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref> shows the F1-score of the base classifiers for the different values of K. For all the four classifiers, the F1-score increases with an increase in the K value, and it is constant after K=700 for all. Therefore, K=700 is chosen as the optimal value for the dataset considered. The PU learning classifier, bagging SVM, is compared with the baseline approach of oneclass SVM. The bagging SVM approach outperforms the one-class SVM for all the base classifiers and the meta-classifier using two different representation methods, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>. The considered dataset is highly imbalanced and hence the bagging SVM that learns from both the labeled and unlabeled data performs better compared to the one-class SVM. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> shows the mean precision, recall and F1-score using 5-fold cross-validation for the two approaches. When the bagging SVM is applied for one-hot representation, the F1-score increases by 9.9, 10.4, 8, 8.4 and 10.7% for the chemical, biological, phenotypic, therapeutic and meta-classifier respectively. Using the bagging SVM with network embedding results in meta-classifier having an increased F1-score of 12.7%. Among the base classifiers, the therapeutic feature-based classifier has the highest increase in the F1-score at 10.1%. The increase in the F1-score for chemical, biological and phenotypic feature-based classifiers is 9.1, 8.7 and 8.7%.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Network embedding</head><p>The network embedding technique, node2vec, which is used to represent the drug pairs is evaluated against the one-hot representation of different features. For the one-hot representation, the Jaccard similarity mentioned in Equation ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) is used to determine the similarity between the drug pairs and gives a single value as the similarity measure. The one-hot representation for all the four considered features is obtained and the Jaccard similarity applied to get a similarity score for each drug pair. Both these representations (one-hot and node2vec) are evaluated using two learning techniques, namely, the bagging SVM and one-class SVM (baseline approach). Using node2vec representation along with the one-class SVM as the learning model, the meta-classifier gets an increase of 19.6% in F1-score. For the bagging SVM approach with node2vec representation, the metaclassifier gets an increase in F1-score of 22%. Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> and Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> compare the two representations and the node2vec representation performs better for all the base classifiers as well as the metaclassifier. The significant improvement of the representation learning algorithm is attributed to its ability to learn transitive relationships between the drugs and it can be illustrated with the following examples.</p><p>Example 1: The biological base classifier with node2vec representation predicts the drugs</p><p>Bexarotene and Irbesartan to be interacting from the transitive relations between them as illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure">9a</ref>. But the same classifier with one-hot representation does not predict that particular drug pair, as there is no immediate common target site where the drugs bind.</p><p>Example 2: In the TFN, drugs Erthromycin and Ropivacaine have transitive relations between them as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">9b</ref>, and the therapeutic classifier predicts the drug pair to be interacting. As the drugs do not have immediate common neighbors, the classifier with one-hot representation does not predict the drug pair to be positive (interacting).</p><p>(1)</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref>: Transitive relations between the drug nodes</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Meta-classifier</head><p>The meta-classifier learns from each base classifier's prediction, a score as mentioned in Algorithm III. This score is dependent on the base classifier's performance and, in this work, the base classifier's performance is evaluated using the F1-score. Among the base classifiers, biological feature-based classifier performs better and it has more weightage in the meta-classifier. As can be seen from Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>, the meta-classifier performs better than the base classifiers for both one-class SVM and the bagging SVM approach. This is because, each base classifier is trained with only a single feature but the meta-classifier combines the predictions from each classifier through a second level learning. Even if a drug pair is predicted to be interacting by one base classifier with high probability but not by the other base classifiers then the meta-classifier do not predict it to be positive. Thus, the significant performance improvement of the meta-classifier is attributed to its ability to learn from the meta-knowledge of the base classifiers.</p><p>The four feature networks are integrated into a single heterogeneous network with five types of nodes (drug, substructure, target, disease, side-effect). The integrated network has a total of 3573 nodes and 1,14,786 edges. Network embedding and bagging SVM algorithms are applied to this integrated network with the same set of parameters, and without the meta-learning framework. This method achieves an F1-score of 0.84. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> demonstrates that the meta-classifier shows an improved F1-score of 6.7%. This is because, the single network considers all the features with equal weightage while the meta-classifier assigns different weights based on the base classifier's performance. And also, as the features are considered in a single network, the machine learning algorithm would learn a single hypothesis for the given problem. While the meta-learning approach has two levels of learning, it learns from a set of hypotheses generated from the different base classifiers.</p><p>Hence, the meta-classifier has more generalization ability compared to the base learners. The scalable factor of the meta-learning framework for the DDI task is evaluated by adding one more feature to the existing model. The Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) classification system, recommended by the World Health Organization (WHO), is used as the fifth feature to construct the ATC Feature Network (AFN). The classification system is used to categorize drug substances according to their therapeutic, pharmacological and chemical properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>. It is based on the assumption that drugs with similar therapeutic or pharmacological properties share a functional similarity and interact with each other. The ATC codes of the drugs are extracted from the Drug-Bank database.  The integrated single network also consists of 548 drugs and 1,49,878 unique drug pairs. It predicts a total of 13,528 drug interactions after applying the network embedding and bagging SVM algorithms. The new DDI predictions obtained from this network are validated using the same drugdrug interaction checker. The single-network-based classifier, on an average, has evidence for 44 out of 100 predictions in DrugBank, and the meta-classifier has evidence for 57 out of 100. The top 500 predictions from each classifier are examined for evidence and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10</ref> shows that the metaclassifier outperforms all other classifiers. From Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> and Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10</ref>, it is evident that using a meta-classifier which combines base classifier predictions identifies more reliable DDI pairs and performs better. Table <ref type="table">5</ref> shows the top 20 predictions of the meta-classifier with their DrugBank evidence. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case study</head><p>Each of the base classifiers predicts interaction between the drugs, based on the considered feature.</p><p>A predicted DDI which is clinically significant is taken as an example for each of the classifiers.</p><p>Chemical Base Classifier: Predictions from this base classifier output two drugs that have a probability of interaction, based on their chemical structural similarity. The drugs Phentolamine and Methylphenidate are predicted to be interacting by the chemical-based classifier and it is found that they share 80 common substructures. Phenotypic Base Classifier: The phenotypic classifier considers the clinical side-effects of a drug that could act as biomarkers for toxic effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, so side-effects are used to predict DDIs. The drugs Diclofenac and Lisinopril are predicted by the phenotypic classifier, to be interacting.</p><p>Diclofenac, a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID), is used to relieve body pain and inflammation chiefly caused by arthritis. Lisinopril, a drug under the class "angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors" is used to treat hypertension. DrugBank reports severe adverse effects when these two drugs are administered together. Serious adverse drug reactions like acute renal failure are associated with DDIs between NSAIDs and antihypertensive drugs <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>.</p><p>Therapeutic Base Classifier: The drug-disease network considered for the therapeutic classifier predicts interaction between drugs, based on their therapeutic similarity. The therapeutic base classifier predicts interaction between Rifapentine and Warfarin. Rifapentine, an antibiotic drug, is used to treat tuberculosis by stopping bacterial growth. Warfarin, an anticoagulant drug, is used to prevent blood clots. DrugBank and a study by Baciewicz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref> report that the metabolism of Warfarin can be increased when combined with Rifapentine, and there is interaction between the two drugs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations</head><p>The number of new predictions, i.e., positives from the unlabeled data identified from the proposed system is less in number. This is due to the huge difference in the ratio between the positive and the unlabeled data <ref type="bibr">(1: 44)</ref>. By increasing the number of positive DDIs from other sources like TWOSIDES <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> and KEGG <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>, thereby improving the ratio between the positive and the unlabeled data, the prediction task can predict a higher number of new interactions between the drug pairs. The number of predictions can also be increased by considering more number of features such as pathways, enzymes, transporters <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and gene ontology <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. The number of predictions from the chemical-based classifier is fewer compared to other classifiers, but the number of confirmed predictions is reasonably high. By considering other 2D molecular fingerprints and the 3D molecular structure of the drugs, such as the one used by Vilar et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>, the classifier's performance and prediction results can be improved. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Drug-drug interaction prediction is a vital task under the drug development process to assess the benefits and risks of both existing and new drugs. Given the lack of negative interaction data for the DDI prediction task and the availability of ample data sources publishing new features related to drugs, a meta-learning framework with the node2vec for drug representation and the bagging SVM as the classification algorithm is designed to predict DDIs.</p><p>The node2vec network embedding algorithm applied to the FNs gives better feature representation compared to the existing one-hot representation. The bagging SVM and the metaclassifier also demonstrate a significant performance improvement for the DDI prediction task.</p><p>While the work considers four distinct features that characterize the drug for modeling the base classifiers, the number of features and the number of base classifiers are scalable factors. Future work could be directed towards other drug related information like pathways, transporters, enzymes and gene ontology that can be incorporated into the framework. In this work, a meta-learning framework is designed to predict DDIs: however, it can also be utilized to predict other associations like drug-target, drug-disease and target-disease.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Meta-learning framework for DDI prediction</figDesc><graphic url="image-3.png" coords="8,56.70,513.25,481.90,198.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Differentiating between one-hot and network representation</figDesc><graphic url="image-4.png" coords="9,56.70,151.49,481.90,128.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Diagrammatic representation of the four feature networks</figDesc><graphic url="image-5.png" coords="11,56.70,56.70,481.90,306.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>illustrates the representation of nodes present in the FNs. Drug nodes are present in all the FNs but the same drug will get a different representation in each FN, as the neighbors of the drug node vary from one network to the other. Figure5a) shows the drug and substructure node representation in the CFN, 5b) drug and target node representation in the BFN, 5c) drug and side-effect node representation in the PFN, and 5d) drug and disease node representation in the DFN. This d-dimensional feature vector obtained for each drug node in every FN is used to train the PU learning-based base classifier to predict interactions between the drugs.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Representation of nodes in the feature network</figDesc><graphic url="image-6.png" coords="13,56.70,56.70,481.90,210.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the meta-classifier using , the representation of the set Return</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Optimal K-value for the bagging SVM 0.5 0.55 0.6 0.65 0.7 0.75 0.8 0.85 0.9</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 8 : F 1 -</head><label>81</label><figDesc>Figure 8: F 1 -score for the base and meta-classifiers</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 10 shows the prediction performance illustration of each classifier using the number of new predictions and the number of confirmed evidence from DrugBank. The newly-added ATC-based base classifier also predicts 8,537 new positive DDIs and the predictions are validated.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10: Total number of confirmed predictions for the base and meta-classifiers</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Two drugs that interact with the same target have greater chances of being a candidate for the DDI prediction task and the biological base-classifier identifies those candidates. Interaction between the drugs Simvastatin and Saquinavir is predicted by the biological classifier. Simvastatin is a lipid-lowering drug under the "statins" drug group, used to lower the blood's bad cholesterol level. Saquinavir is an antiretroviral drug under the "protease inhibitors" drug group, used to control the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). Simvastatin is a sensitive in vivo cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrate. When a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor is used along with Simvastatin, it increases the drug's exposure. Protease inhibitors are strong inhibitors of CYP3A4<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>. Therefore, co-administration of Saquinavir with Simvastatin can increase the serum concentration of simvastatin.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Top 20 DDI predictions from the meta-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="5,56.70,444.57,481.90,153.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic url="image-7.png" coords="14,92.15,160.19,481.90,274.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic url="image-8.png" coords="22,62.69,552.66,471.87,199.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic url="image-9.png" coords="33,58.20,84.30,481.90,205.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 : Network properties of the four feature networks.</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Feature Net-</cell><cell>Nodes</cell><cell>Edges</cell><cell>Average De-</cell><cell>Degree Cen-</cell><cell>Closeness</cell></row><row><cell>work</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>gree</cell><cell>trality</cell><cell>Centrality</cell></row><row><cell>CFN</cell><cell>1151</cell><cell>69,596</cell><cell>120.996</cell><cell>0.1051</cell><cell>0.4162</cell></row><row><cell>BFN</cell><cell>1126</cell><cell>1902</cell><cell>3.583</cell><cell>0.0033</cell><cell>0.0701</cell></row><row><cell>PFN</cell><cell>1806</cell><cell>41,008</cell><cell>45.487</cell><cell>0.0252</cell><cell>0.3475</cell></row><row><cell>TFN</cell><cell>1134</cell><cell>2280</cell><cell>4.007</cell><cell>0.0035</cell><cell>0.1275</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 : Performance of representation and prediction methods for different classifiers</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.9</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.7</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>F1-Score</cell><cell>0.4 0.5 0.6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Chemical</cell><cell>Biological</cell><cell>Phenotypic</cell><cell cols="2">Therapeutic</cell><cell>Meta-classifier</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">One-class SVM + One-hot</cell><cell cols="4">One-class SVM + Network Embedding</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Bagging SVM + One-hot</cell><cell cols="4">Bagging SVM + Network Embedding</cell></row><row><cell>Prediction</cell><cell>Representation</cell><cell>Classifier</cell><cell cols="2">Precision</cell><cell cols="2">Recall</cell><cell>F1-Score</cell></row><row><cell>Method</cell><cell>Method</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>One-class</cell><cell>One-hot</cell><cell>Chemical</cell><cell>0.586</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.512</cell><cell>0.546</cell></row><row><cell>SVM</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Biological</cell><cell>0.512</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.463</cell><cell>0.486</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Phenotypic</cell><cell>0.577</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">0.495</cell><cell>0.533</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 : Performance of the meta-learning framework</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Prediction method</cell><cell>Precision</cell><cell>Recall</cell><cell>F1-score</cell></row><row><cell>Network embed-</cell><cell>With the meta-learning framework</cell><cell>0.969</cell><cell>0.852</cell><cell>0.907</cell></row><row><cell>ding + Bagging</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SVM</cell><cell>Without the meta-learning frame-</cell><cell>0.902</cell><cell>0.786</cell><cell>0.84</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>work</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 : Performance of the meta-classifier after feature inclusion</head><label>4</label><figDesc>The ATC system classifies drugs hierarchically at five different levels. The AFN is constructed, based on the fourth-level ATC codes, i.e., drugs that have therapeutic, pharmacologic and chemical similarities will have the same ATC code at the fourth level. The AFN has 548 drug nodes, 387 ATC code nodes and 1206 edges. This network is used to train a separate base classifier that is incorporated into the meta-learning framework. The performance of the ATC code-based classifier and the meta-classifier after the inclusion of the AFN is given in Table4. The metaclassifier shows an improved F1-score of 0.2% after including the ATC codes as an additional feature.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Classifier</cell><cell>Precision</cell><cell>Recall</cell><cell>F1-score</cell></row><row><cell>ATC-based classifier</cell><cell>0.711</cell><cell>0.619</cell><cell>0.661</cell></row><row><cell>Meta-classifier (with five</cell><cell>0.972</cell><cell>0.853</cell><cell>0.909</cell></row><row><cell>base classifiers)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Newly-predicted DDIs</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">The 548 drugs considered have 1,49,878 unique pairs, where 3,299 pairs are positive. Of the</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">remaining 1,46,579 pairs (unlabeled), there can be new DDI pairs that can be positive, as predicted</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">by the proposed system. The four base classifiers and the meta-classifier output new, positive DDI</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">pairs from this unlabeled data. The total number of positive DDIs predicted from chemical, biologi-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">cal, phenotypic and therapeutic base classifiers is 882, 14,399, 7,668 and 14,471 respectively. The</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">meta-classifier outputs 15,395 new predictions. The validation for the newly-predicted positive</cell></row></table><note><p>DDIs is performed using DrugBank's drug-drug interaction checker.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div><p>This research did not receive a specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multiple chronic conditions chartbook</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gerteis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Rockville, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug-drug interactions and their predictors: Results from Indian elderly inpatients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kashyap</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacy practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">191</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preventable adverse drug reactions: A focus on drug interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Flockhart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Centers for Education &amp; Research on Therapeutics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">452</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug-drug interaction extraction via convolutional neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational and mathematical methods in medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery and explanation of drug-drug interactions via text mining</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Percha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pacific symposium on biocomputing. Pacific symposium on biocomputing</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>NIH Public Access</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">410</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering drug-drug interactions: a text-mining and reasoning approach based on properties of drug metabolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="547" to="553" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Literature based drug interaction prediction with clinical assessment using electronic medical records: novel myopathy associated drug interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Duke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS computational biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1002614</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting Drug-Drug Interactions with Word and Character-Level Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kavuluru</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Healthcare Informatics (ICHI), 2017 IEEE International Conference on</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug-target interaction prediction through domain-tuned network-based inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Alaimo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2004" to="2008" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network-based inference methods for drug repositioning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational and mathematical methods in medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug-Target Interaction Prediction through Label Propagation with Linear Neighborhood Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecules</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2056</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Label propagation prediction of drug-drug interactions based on clinical side effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network-based analysis and characterization of adverse drug-drug interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Takarabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of chemical information and modeling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2977" to="2985" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pharmacointeraction network models predict unknown drug-drug interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61468</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A probabilistic approach for collective similarity-based drug-drug interaction prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sridhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3175" to="3182" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards drug repositioning: a unified computational framework for integrating multiple aspects of drug similarity and disease similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">AMIA Annual Symposium Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1258" to="1267" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug-drug interaction through molecular structure similarity analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vilar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1066" to="1074" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similarity-based modeling in large-scale prediction of drug-drug interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vilar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature protocols</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2147" to="2163" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014a</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug repositioning based on comprehensive similarity measures and Bi-Random walk algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2664" to="2671" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting drug-drug interactions through large-scale similarity-based link prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fokoue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Semantic Web Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cham</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="774" to="789" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine learning-based prediction of drug-drug interactions by integrating drug phenotypic, therapeutic, chemical, and genomic properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">e2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="278" to="e286" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting drug-drug interactions through drug structural similarities and interaction networks incorporating pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics knowledge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cheminformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning classifiers from only positive and unlabeled data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Elkan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Noto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 14th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</title>
		<meeting>the 14th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="220" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DrugBank: a knowledgebase for drugs, drug actions and drug targets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wishart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic acids research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">suppl_1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="901" to="D906" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data-driven prediction of drug effects and interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Tatonetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science translational medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A bagging SVM to learn from positive and unlabeled examples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mordelet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Vert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognition Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating the support of a high-dimensional distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sch?lkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neural computation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1443" to="1471" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building text classifiers using positive and unlabeled examples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICDM 2003. Third IEEE International Conference on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003. 2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="186" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Data Mining</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning with positive and unlabeled examples using weighted logistic regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICML</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="448" to="455" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational Drug Discovery with Dyadic Positive-Unlabeled Learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2017 SIAM International Conference on Data Mining</title>
		<meeting>the 2017 SIAM International Conference on Data Mining</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="53" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Partially supervised classification of text documents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICML</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="394" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review of ensemble methods in bioinformatics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="296" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metalearning: a survey of trends and technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lemke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Artificial intelligence review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="130" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metafraud: a meta-learning framework for detecting financial fraud</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abbasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mis Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A meta learning approach to grammatical error correction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Seo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 50th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Short Papers</title>
		<meeting>the 50th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Short Papers</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="332" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A meta-learning approach for B-cell conformational epitope prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">378</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stacked generalization for medical concept extraction from clinical notes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Riloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of BioNLP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A side effect resource to capture phenotypic effects of drugs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular systems biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">343</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new method for computational drug repositioning using drug pairwise similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics and Biomedicine (BIBM), 2012 IEEE International Conference On</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Segura Bedmar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Semeval-2013 task 9: Extraction of drug-drug interactions from biomedical texts</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SemMedDB: a PubMed-scale repository of biomedical semantic predications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kilicoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3158" to="3160" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A network inference method for large-scale unsupervised identification of novel drug-drug interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guimer?</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sales-Pardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS computational biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1003374</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning network representations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Moyano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The European Physical Journal Special Topics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">226</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="518" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">node2vec: Scalable feature learning for networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 22nd ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</title>
		<meeting>the 22nd ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="855" to="864" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation learning: A review and new perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bengio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on pattern analysis and machine intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1798" to="1828" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classification of drugs using the ATC system (Anatomic, Therapeutic, Chemical Classification) and the latest changes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Skrbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medicinski arhiv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1 Suppl 2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug-drug interactions between HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors (statins) and antiviral protease inhibitors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chauvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical pharmacokinetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="815" to="831" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug interactions between antihypertensive drugs and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents: a descriptive study using the French Pharmacovigilance database</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fournier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fundamental &amp; clinical pharmacology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="230" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Update on rifampin, rifabutin, and rifapentine drug interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Baciewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current medical research and opinion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kanehisa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic acids research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene Ontology: tool for the unification of biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ashburner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">State of the art and development of a drug-drug interaction large scale predictor based on 3D pharmacophoric similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vilar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current drug metabolism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="490" to="501" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Predicting drug-drug interaction using a meta-learning framework</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Similar drugs interact with each other and the similarity calculated using network embedding algorithm</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Average prediction evidence of the meta-classifier at 57 out of 100</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
