<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Toward Dexterous Manipulation With Augmented Adaptive Synergies: The Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Della</forename><surname>Cosimo</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cristina</forename><surname>Santina</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-1067-1134</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giorg</forename><surname>Piazza</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-8635-5571</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Manuel</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Grioli</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-5310-2997</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Antonio</forename><surname>Catalano</surname></persName>
							<email>manuel.catalano@iit.it</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-1950-6186</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, IEEE</roleName><surname>Bicchi</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-8635-5571</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cosimo</forename><surname>Della</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Santina</forename><surname>Della</surname></persName>
							<email>cosimodellasantina@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Piazza</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grioli</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Catalano</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bicchi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName>Research Center &quot;Enrico Piaggio,&quot; University of Pisa, </orgName>
								<address><addrLine>Pisa 56126, Italy Genova 16163, Italy Pisa 56126, Italy, Genova 16163, Italy</addrLine></address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName> are with Soft Robotics for Human Cooperation and Rehabilitation, Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia, </orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName> Research Center &quot;Enrico Piaggio,&quot; University of Pisa, </orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName> Soft Robotics for Human Cooperation and Rehabilitation, Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia,</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Toward Dexterous Manipulation With Augmented Adaptive Synergies: The Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B414773983BBA410D7FF01C8E02EF48C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TRO.2018.2830407</idno>
					<note type="submission">received November 6, 2017; accepted March 20, 2018.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T06:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Biologically inspired robots</term>
					<term>dexterous manipulation</term>
					<term>mechanism design</term>
					<term>multifingered hands</term>
					<term>underactuated robots</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In recent years, a clear trend toward simplification emerged in the development of robotic hands. The use of soft robotic approaches has been a useful tool in this prospective, enabling complexity reduction by embodying part of grasping intelligence in the hand mechanical structure. Several hand prototypes designed according to such principles have accomplished good results in terms of grasping simplicity, robustness, and reliability. Among them, the Pisa/IIT SoftHand demonstrated the feasibility of a large variety of grasping tasks, by means of only one actuator and an opportunely designed tendon-driven differential mechanism. However, the use of a single degree of actuation prevents the execution of more complex tasks, like fine preshaping of fingers and in-hand manipulation. While possible in theory, simply doubling the Pisa/IIT SoftHand actuation system has several disadvantages, e.g., in terms of space and mechanical complexity. To overcome these limitations, we propose a novel design framework for tendon-driven mechanisms, in which the main idea is to turn transmission friction from a disturbance into a design tool. In this way, the degrees of actuation (DoAs) can be doubled with little additional complexity. By leveraging on this idea, we design a novel robotic hand, the Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2. We present here its design, modeling, control, and experimental validation. The hand demonstrates that by opportunely combining only two DoAs with hand softness, a large variety of grasping and manipulation tasks can be performed, only relying on the intelligence embodied in the mechanism. Examples include rotating objects with different shapes, opening a jar, and pouring coffee from a glass.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Here, the hand performs a pinch grasp, a power grasp of multiple objects, and it pushes a button by using the extended index. in robotics. Over the years, several design methods and prototypes have been proposed. One approach followed by many researchers consists in attempting to closely replicate the features of human hands with sophisticated designs integrating many actuators and sensors (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>). A second approach, followed mostly by designers of gripping devices for industrial or prosthetic applications, consists in developing nonanthropomorphic, simple and rugged devices, designed on purpose to solve a restricted class of tasks (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>). A third trend aspires to make hands retaining advantages of the anthropomorphic design, while drastically reducing complexity in terms of number of actuators, sensors, and lines of code to program the control. One of the most effective and widely used tools for mechanical simplification is underactuation <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, by which designers can reduce the number of degrees of actuation (DoAs) of robotic hands while maintaining a large number of degrees of freedom <ref type="bibr">(DoFs)</ref>. Notable examples of this line of research are <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</p><p>In this regard, principles from human motor control are often used as inspiration to guide hand design. Postural synergies are a valuable example of this approach. They specify a reduced set of principal directions in hand configuration space, describing the most commonly observed postures in human hand movements <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. By constraining the motion of artificial hands along these directions, simplification in programing <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and design <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> can be achieved. However, a rigidly prescriptive, purely geometric model of synergies was recognized to be not ideal for describing the extremely adaptive nature of human hands in grasping and manipulating objects. In the soft synergy model <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, the issue is addressed by considering postural synergies as only prescribing motion of a virtual reference hand toward which the physical hand is dynamically attracted. The actual hand posture emerges as an equilibrium between environment resistance to penetration and hand compliance. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, some of the authors of the present paper showed that a system of differential transmissions and compliant elements can be designed so as to implement a combination of any number of soft synergies. The idea of designing force distribution mechanisms that replicate the soft synergy model was called adaptive synergies. Its application brought to the development of Pisa/IIT SoftHand <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> [see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3(a)</ref>], an anthropomorphic robotic hand implementing one soft synergy. Even with such a small actuation space, the hand was able to realize a vast range of grasps, thanks to its physical adaptiveness and compliance.</p><p>However, while very effective in many practical conditions, Pisa/IIT SoftHand presents obvious limitations in terms of dexterity if compared to its natural counterpart. So, facing the need of augmenting the dexterity of these kind of simple hands, the following problem arises: how to increase the hand functionalities without sensibly increasing mechanical complexity?</p><p>This paper deals with this complexity-dexterity tradeoff by proposing a novel framework for the design of tendon driven underactuated hands, which, in continuity with our previous work, we will refer to as augmented adaptive synergies. The main idea behind this approach is to exploit friction effects to generate extra motions with minimal changes in the original mechanics. Using this approach, we present the design and validation of a novel self-contained robotic hand, named Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 (called hereinafter SoftHand 2). This novel hand is able to perform both precision and power grasps (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>), as well as to manipulate objects while maintaining a stable grasp through autonomous finger motions dictated by its mechanical intelligence. Note that to implement in-hand manipulation in fully actuated hands, sophisticated algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and sensing strategies <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> are generally required. In contrast, SoftHand 2 can manipulate objects of different shapes with just two DoAs, and requires only a very simple control strategy.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows. After recalling the main elements of the adaptive synergy framework in Section II, we introduce and discuss the augmented adaptive synergies framework in Section III for a generic tendon-driven mechanism. Section IV presents SoftHand 2 mechanical design.</p><p>In Section V, we derive a dynamical model of the proposed hand, to perform simulations motivating the considered control policy and corroborating the analytical results. Soft-Hand 2 performance are tested through several experiments in Section VI. The present paper extends <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, where the proposed actuation principle was preliminarily introduced and implemented in an exploratory prototype.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. BACKGROUND</head><p>The simplest definition of postural synergies is an ordered basis of the vector space of joint variables q ∈ R n , resulting from principal component analysis of the covariance matrix obtained from experimental measurements of human subjects during normal hand use <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. The eigenvectors of the covariance matrix ordered by their eigenvalues form the columns of the synergy matrix S, so that it holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">q = Sσ (1)</formula><p>where σ ∈ R n s represents the posture in the synergy basis S ∈ R n ×n s . While the complete description of the joint space would require n s = n, experimental evidence suggest that a reduced basis is sufficient to explain a large part of the covariance of grasp postures during common grasping tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. These experiments however were conducted while subjects mimed grasp, without physically interacting with objects, as hand deformations due to contact forces would confound results. As a consequence, the synergy model in ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) is adequate to describe preshaping phases of grasp, but fails to predict how grasping forces are actually generated in contact.</p><p>To address this issue, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> proposed to use the synergy model to generate reference motions for the hand. It also introduced a model of compliance of the hand to account for forces arising from resistance to interpenetration of bodies. This soft synergy model postulates that under such attraction and repulsion forces, the hand reaches the equilibrium configuration described by</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">q = Sσ -CJ T f ext (2)</formula><p>where C represents the grasp compliance and the term J T f ext collects all contact forces acting on the hand (see Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). Due to technological difficulties, the realization of an artificial hand implementing the model (2) was not obtained directly. Instead, Grioli et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> introduced the design technique of adaptive synergies, which exploits differential mechanisms and the space of self-motions to adapt to the external world. For a hand, which is actuated by means of t tendons connected to as many motors through a differential mechanism with transmission distribution matrix R, one can write a relation between the tendon positions x ∈ R t and joint variables as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Rq = x (3)</formula><p>and, by kineto-static duality, infer</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">τ = R T τ M (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">)</formula><p>where τ is the joint torque vector and τ M is the tendon tension vector. The equilibrium of the joint torques is obtained by including a linear elastic force in joint space (-Eq), and the Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Schematic of a robotic hand with adaptive synergies grasping an object. The prime movers, on the left (in green) generate motion acting on the angles σ. Those motions are mapped to the hand joint angles q through the matrix R, which collects the transmission ratios. The final posture of the hand depends on the external wrenches</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">f ext = [f T 1 , f T 2 , .</formula><p>. .] T , the internal torques τ a = [τ 1 , τ 2 , . . .] T , and the springs elasticity (matrix E collects all the stiffness in its elements e i,j ). contribution of external forces (J T f ext )</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">J T f ext = R T τ M -Eq . (<label>5</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">)</formula><p>Finally, combining (3) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">5</ref>) and solving yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">q = (-E -1 + E -1 R T (RE -1 R T ) -1 RE -1 )J T f ext + E -1 R T (RE -1 R T ) -1 x (6)</formula><p>which can be made equivalent to the soft synergies (2) by identifying the tendon position with the synergy reference variable (i.e., x = σ), and by properly designing the parameters in R and E so that</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">S = E -1 R T (RE -1 R T ) -1 = R + E C = E -1 -E -1 R T (RE -1 R T ) -1 RE -1 = P ⊥ R E -1 . (7)</formula><p>This method was used for the design of the Pisa/IIT SoftHand [see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3(a)</ref>], where the differential mechanism is obtained Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. Panel (a) presents the scheme of an adaptive finger actuated through a tendon, with main variables highlighted. Panel (b) shows a portion of the mechanism. It is composed by two tendon segments, and the pulley that separates them. q i is the ith joint angle, v j and T j are the speed and tension, respectively, of each segment of the tendon along its routing, r j,i is the radius r j of the jth pulley when it is on joint i, or 0 otherwise. (a) Finger. (b) Pulley. using a single motor (i.e., t = 1), which actuates all joints at the same time through a tendon. The physical parameters were chosen such as to implement the first soft synergy of grasp <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. With the same method, it is possible to add more synergies to the hand by adding other tendons in parallel to the first one. As a proof of concept of multisynergy hands, a prototype was presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> [see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3(b)</ref>]. However, multisynergies hands require multiple tendons to be independently routed through all hand joints, hence a large number of pulleys and an overall increase in size, weight, and complexity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. AUGMENTED ADAPTIVE SYNERGIES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. From Friction Effects to Actuation Augmentation</head><p>The ideal model presented in Section II does not account for dissipative effects that are encountered in any real mechanism.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>(a) shows a sketch of a robotic finger, driven by a unique tendon, with significant quantities marked. In a tendon-driven differential mechanism, one of the main sources of nonlinearity is the friction generated by pulleys guiding the tendon throughout the hand transmission system.</p><p>To mathematically describe the effects of friction, we consider the m + 1 tendon segments, delimited by the m pulleys. We assume inextensible tendons, and thus constant speed and tension within each segment. Let T j and v j be the tension and speed of the jth segment, and v ∈ R m +1 and T ∈ R m +1 be the two vectors collecting these terms. We refer to the jth pulley radius as r j . To write compact expressions in the following, we also define r i,j as the radius r j of the jth pulley, if the pulley is part of joint i, i.e., if a change in q i is reflected in a change of the length of the jth segment. The value of r i,j is zero otherwise. Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>(b) shows the jth portion of the transmission mechanism, composed by two successive tendon segments, and the pulley which separates them. By balancing velocities at jth pulley, we obtain m equations in m + 1 unknowns, in the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">v j = v j -1 + dl j (q) dt = v j -1 + n i=1 r j,i qi<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where v j is the velocity of the jth segment, and l j (q) its length.</p><p>Note that the length of the segment changes only if it passes through a joint. In that case, a variation of joint angle is reflected in a proportional variation of the segment length. We complete the velocity balance through a boundary equation defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">ṡ = - v 0 + v m 2<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where v 0 and v m are the velocities of first and last segments of the tendon, and ṡ is the residual sliding speed. Note that the variable s is an extra degree of freedom independent from the joint angles q, which describes the relative motion of the two ends of the tendon. Consider indeed that when all the DoFs of the hand are constrained (i.e., q ≡ 0), the tendon can still slide along its path, being all pulleys idle. Analogous considerations can be done for the balance of tensions at the jth pulley</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">T j = T j -1 -V j (v j )<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where T j is the tension on the jth segment. The tension loss V j (v j ) is due to friction on the jth pulley. We complete the tension balances through the m + 1th equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> which accounts for the total pulling force τ M applied by the motor on the synergy σ. T 0 and T m are the tensions of first and last portions of the tendon. Finally, we impose the map between tensions and joint torques, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">τ M = T 0 + T m</formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">τ i = - m +1 j =1</formula><p>r j,i T j <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> where r j,i is defined as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>, and τ i is the torque applied by the tendon on the ith joint. We rewrite the previous equations in matrix form as</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">⎧ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ MT + V (v) + eτ M = 0 Mv -R q = -2e ṡ τ = -RT T (13)</formula><p>where M ∈ R m +1×m +1 , R ∈ R n ×m +1 , and e = [0, 0, . . . , 0, 1] T ∈ R m +1 . Note that the element (j, i) of R is r j,i . Note also that V (v) is a vector function, with jth element V j (v j ).</p><p>From (13), we explicit the velocity and tension distributions v and T as <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref> with the third equation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>, the overall relation between ṡ, τ M , and joint torque vector τ yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">v = +M -1 R q -2 e v ṡ T = -M -1 V (v) -M -1 eτ M = -M -1 V (v) + e v τ M (14) where e v = -M -1 e = [1, 1, . . . 1, 1] T . Combining</formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">τ = -RT (-M -1 V (M -1 R q -e v ṡ) + e v τ M ) = R T τ M + D( q, ṡ)<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where we defined the transmission maps as</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">R T = -RT e v D( q, ṡ) = -RT (-M -1 V (M -1 R q -2 e v ṡ)).<label>(16)</label></formula><p>Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_17">15</ref>) clearly introduces the possibility of using tendon sliding ṡ as an actuation, with the nonlinear input field D( q, ṡ). This is in addition to the input τ M mapped as in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">4</ref>), de facto doubling the amount of DoA realized by each tendon.</p><p>To simplify the transmission model D( q, ṡ), it is instrumental to define a specific model for the friction force V (v). Consider initially a dynamic Coulomb-like friction model (as, e.g., described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref> where tanh(•) is intended component-wise for vectors. In Section V-A, we discuss different friction models. Assuming the system in equilibrium (i.e., q ≡ 0), and considering e v = [1, 1 . . . 1] T , (16) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">V (v) = V max tanh(v) = V max tanh(M -1 R q -e v ṡ)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">D( ṡ) = -RT (M -1 V max tanh(2e v ṡ)) = -RT M -1 V max e v tanh(2 ṡ).<label>(18)</label></formula><p>Introducing ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_17">15</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">18</ref>) in the force balance <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">J T f ext = R T u 1 + R T f u 2 -Eq (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">)</formula><p>where u 1 = τ M , u 2 = tanh(2 ṡ), and</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">R T = -RT e v R T f = -RT M -1 V max e v . (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">)</formula><p>In analogy to Section II, we define a synergy-like input</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">σ f Rq = σ R f q = σ f . (<label>21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">)</formula><p>Rewriting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">19</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">21</ref>) in matrix form, we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">⎡ ⎣ -E [R T R T f ] R R f ∅ ⎤ ⎦ ⎡ ⎣ q u 1 u 2 ⎤ ⎦ = ⎡ ⎣ J T f ext σ σ f ⎤ ⎦<label>(22)</label></formula><p>where the left-term matrix is always nonsingular. Through block inversion, the solution of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_27">22</ref>) can be written as which explicitly specifies the relationship between synergistic inputs and hand configurations, supporting our proposed idea to exploit friction to enhance the controllability of the hand.</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">q = R R f + E σ σ f + P ⊥ R,Rf E -1 J T f ext<label>(23)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Effect of Routing Changes</head><p>We consider here the possibility of changing the routing of the tendon, i.e., the order by which the tendon passes through pulleys, as an additional design parameter to shape the hand closure. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref> shows an example of two hands with the same structure but different routing.</p><p>To describe the routing, we introduce the permutation matrix P ∈ R m +1×m +1 . Its rows identify the hand pulleys, and the columns identify the tendon portions. P i,j = 1 if the jth portion of the tendon is driven by the ith pulley, P i,j = 0 otherwise. All the derivations of the previous section can be generalized by substituting v and T with their reorganized counterparts P v and P T , respectively. Thus, the overall effect is to modify <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>, into</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">⎧ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ M P T + V (P v) + eτ M = 0 M P v -R q = -2e ṡ τ = -RT P T . (<label>24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">)</formula><p>The two directions of actuation R, R f become</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">R T = -RT e v R T f = -RT P M -1 P T V max e v . (<label>25</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_32">)</formula><p>It is worth noticing that the effect of a different routing reflects just in a change of the second direction of actuation R f , leaving R unchanged.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Design Remarks</head><p>The method of Adaptive Synergies <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> was motivated by the idea of using <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> for designing parameters R, E such that a desired synergy basis S could be obtained. Here, we extended this method including the possibility of designing also the friction parameters in V max and the tendon routing P . To clarify the Augmented Adaptive Synergies approach, consider the simple example of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref>; a hand with three fingers. This hand has a total of 6 joints and 17 pulleys. They divide the tendon into 18 segments, each with constant velocity and tension. T , v, q, respectively, are tensions, velocities, and joint angles vectors</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">T = ⎡ ⎢ ⎣ T 1 . . . T 18 ⎤ ⎥ ⎦, v = ⎡ ⎢ ⎣ v 1 . . . v 18 ⎤ ⎥ ⎦, q = ⎡ ⎢ ⎣ q 1 . . . q 6 ⎤ ⎥ ⎦. (<label>26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">)</formula><p>We start by considering the routing in panel (a), which corresponds to a P equal to the identity. So to describe hand structure, we specify the following the matrices in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. Independently from the hand structure, M presents the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">M = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ -1 1 0 . . . 0 0 0 -1 1 . . . 0 0 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 0 0 0 . . . -1 1 1 0 0 . . . 0 1 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ ∈ R 18×18 . (<label>27</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">)</formula><p>The two matrices incorporating hand structure are R and V max . The transmission between tendon and joints is described by the matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">R = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ R1 ∅ ∅ ∅ R2 ∅ ∅ ∅ R3 0 0 0 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ ∈ R 18×6<label>(28)</label></formula><p>with</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">R1 = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ r 1 0 0 r 2 0 0 0 r 4 r 5 0 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ R2 = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ r 6 0 0 r 7 0 0 0 r 9 r 10 0 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ R3 = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ 0 0 0 0 r 13 0 0 r 14 0 0 0 r 16 r 17 0 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ (<label>29</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">)</formula><p>where ∅ is a zero matrix and 0 is a zero vector of opportune dimensions. The block Ri refers to the ith finger, and it contains the radii of the pulleys acting on that finger joints. The friction effects matrix V max has the diagonal form</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">V max = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ V 1 0 . . . 0 0 0 V 2 . . . 0 0 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 0 0 0 V 17 0 0 0 0 0 0 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ ∈ R 18×18<label>(30)</label></formula><p>where V i is the friction coefficient associated with the ith pulley. Note that the last row of R, V max , and M reflect ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">9</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>.</p><p>From <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>, we obtain the vectors R, R f representing the two directions of actuation</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">R T = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ r 1 + r 5 r 2 + r 4 r 6 + r 10 r 7 + r 9 r 13 + r 17 r 14 + r 16 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ (31) R T f = ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ r 1 -r 5 2 4 i=1 V i + r 1 + r 5 2 17 i=5 V i r 2 -r 4 2 3 i=2 V i + r 2 + r 4 2 17 i=4 V i -V 1 r 6 -r 10 2 9 i=6 V i + r 6 + r 10 2 17 i=10 V i - 5 i=1 V i r 7 -r 9 2 8 i=7 V i + r 7 + r 9 2 17 i=9 V i - 6 i=1 V i r 13 -r 17 2 16 i=13 V i + r 13 + r 17 2 V 17 - 12 i=1 V i r 14 -r 16 2 15 i=14 V i + r 14 + r 16 2 17 i=16 V i - 13 i=1 V i ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ . (<label>32</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">)</formula><p>From <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref>, it is clear that R can be designed through the choice of pulley radii semisum. Additionally, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref> shows that R f can be shaped independently from R through pulley radii semidifferences and friction coefficients. We consider here equal pulley radii, friction, and elastic effects, i.e., r i = r, V i = V ∀i, and E = k I. From ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_28">23</ref>), the free-closure configuration space is</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">Span ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ 1 1 1 1 1 1 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ , ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ 17 17 2 2 -19 -19 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ ⎫ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎬ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎭ . (<label>33</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">)</formula><p>The first direction is a coordinate closure of all angles, while the second one corresponds roughly to a closure of the first finger and an opening of the third, or vice versa.</p><p>As an example of independent design of closure directions, we change the friction on pulley 11 (i.e., V 11 = α V ) and the semidifference of pulley radii acting on the joint q 3 (i.e., r 6 = r + β and r 10 = rβ). The resulting free-closure configuration space is</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">Span ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ 1 1 1 1 1 1 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ , ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ 16 16 1 1 -17 -17 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ + α ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ 1 1 1 1 -2 -2 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ + β r ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ -1 -1 5 -1 -1 -1 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ ⎫ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎬ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎭<label>(34)</label></formula><p>where α ∈ (0, +∞), β ∈ (-r, +r). Hence, we can use friction to modulate differences in closure between one finger and the The hand design is self-contained, including the whole actuation system, sensors, power, and control electronics.</p><p>others, and radii variations to modulate joint closure on a same finger.</p><p>To clarify the effect of a routing change, we consider the routing in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5(b</ref>). The corresponding matrix P is</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">P = ⎡ ⎣ ∅ Π 5 × 5 ∅ Π 5 × 5 ∅ ∅ ∅ ∅ I 8 × 8 ⎤ ⎦<label>(35)</label></formula><p>where each block represents a finger, I 8 × 8 ∈ R 8 × 8 is the identity matrix, and Π 5 × 5 ∈ R 5 × 5 is the matrix with all zero elements except to the ones on the antidiagonal (i.e., Π i,6-i = 1 ∀ i ∈ {1 . . . 5}, and 0 otherwise). Hence, from <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>, tacking equal pulleys and elastic effects (i.e., r i = r, V i = V ∀i, E = k I), the following free closure configuration space results:</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">Span ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ 1 1 1 1 1 1 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ , ⎡ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎢ ⎣ 2 2 17 17 -19 -19 ⎤ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎥ ⎦ ⎫ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎬ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎭ . (<label>36</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_48">)</formula><p>Thus, the net effect of this routing change is to leave the first direction unchanged, and to modify the second, reorganizing its elements.</p><p>IV. AUGMENTED SYNERGY DRIVEN HAND: THE PISA/IIT SOFTHAND 2</p><p>We present here the Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2, an anthropomorphic robotic hand evolving the Pisa/IIT SoftHand by the introduction of a friction mediated DoA. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6</ref> shows the hand prototype, while Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref>(a) shows a sketch of the transmission system. Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 has 19 joints. Five of them are simple revolute joints, and they implement the adduction/abduction movement of each finger. The remaining 14 joints are compliant rolling-contact element (CORE) joints <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> (see appendix A for more details). This choice strongly increases the hand robustness, such as the similarity between its kinematics and one of the human hands. Elasticity is introduced in each joint as discussed in Appendix B. A single tendon moves from the palm base, through all the fingers. Two motors actuate the tendon, pulling it from its two sides. If the motors move in the same direction, the tendon length is shortened, and the SoftHand 2 closes. This corresponds to a σ command in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref>. If instead the two motors move in opposition, the tendon slides (i.e., ṡ = 0), and the hand moves according to the friction-driven DoA. This corresponds to a σ f command in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref>. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> graphically represents these two DoAs.</p><p>These two free closures are designed through the proposed augmented adaptive synergies framework. Their choice is motivated by a tradeoff between human inspiration and simplicity of implementation. For the closure related to the first degree of actuation σ, we target a coordinate closure of all fingers analogous to the first synergy of grasp in humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. This seems to be a very fundamental ingredient of human hand control, since the same synergy was discovered during analysis of haptic exploration <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> and environmental constraint exploitation <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. For the second DoA, we target a behavior similar to the one extensively described in the toy example of Section III-C. Indeed, the relative opening and closing of left fingers w.r.t. right ones (and vice versa) is found in the second and third postural synergies of grasp <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, in the second manipulation synergy in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, in the second synergy of haptic exploration <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, and in the third synergy of environmental constrain exploitation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. So the intuition that we follow here is that the implementation of a similar motion could be a key ingredient for embedding a higher level of dexterous capabilities. This was tested in extensive experiments, presented in Section VI.</p><p>We designed custom pulleys with equal radii 3.5 mm. All are made of the same material, with a friction constant approximately of v 0.3 N mm <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. We made the elastic elements of natural rubber with the addition of carbon black, to obtain k 1. The motor positions are acquired using magnetic sensors from Austrian Microsystem. Two encoders are included for each motor, as depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7(b</ref>). This choice is due to the necessity of having an absolute measurement of motor angles, robust to possible unexpected switching OFFof the electronics. The number of tics of the two encoders is selected to be coprime. The absolute angle is then derived integrating the two measurements through the Chinese remainder theorem <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>.</p><p>The firmware is implemented on a custom electronic board, mounted on the bottom part of the hand. Its schematics are openly released, and they are available online as part of the Natural Machine Motion Initiative <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. The implemented control algorithm is discussed in Section VI-A.</p><p>We designed the geometry of hand bottom part, to guarantee an easy connection with standard mechanical interfaces. It is worth noticing that, thanks to the proposed actuation principle, combined with the discussed mechanical design, SoftHand 2 is completely self-contained. Motors, electronics, and sensors are all on-board, and only the energy supply is external to the hand. This compact design allows the easy plug-and-play integration of the SoftHand 2 with robotic manipulators. Fig. <ref type="figure">8(a)</ref> shows the integration of Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 with a Kuka LWR. This was Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>. Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 presents a completely self-contained design, i.e., motors, sensors, and electronics are all on-board. This enables an easy integration in robotic manipulators. As an example, panel (a) shows SoftHand 2 mounted on Kuka LWR. Panel (b) shows instead the application of SoftHand 2 as a prosthesis. The hand is here integrated with a custom socket designed for sEMG prosthetics. made possible by the introduction of just two custom elements: an ROS node and a 3-D printed flange (both available at <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>).</p><p>Another application enabled by the hand self-contained design is the prosthetic one <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. A preliminary example is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">8(b)</ref>, where the SoftHand 2 is integrated with a socket. The mechanical interface is a standard Ottobock Quick Disconnect Wrist. Two surface electromyographic sensors (sEMGs) are integrated in the socket. We used the on-board electronics to implement sEMG signal analysis and hand control. Future work will be devoted to the further evolution of the SoftHand 2 in the prosthetic direction, which is here presented just as a proof of concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. SOFTHAND 2 DYNAMIC MODEL AND NUMERICAL SIMULATION</head><p>To achieve a more complete understanding of Pisa/IIT Soft-Hand 2 behavior, we develop in this section a numerical model, including hand specific details. We describe in the following the derivation of friction-related terms. The derivation of the other terms is reported in the appendices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Friction Terms</head><p>In Section III, we modeled friction effects through a Coulomb-like model <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. The simplicity of the model was instrumental for obtaining a closed-form solution. However, since the Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 actuation system is based on friction exploitation, we consider here a more accurate, yet still computationally tractable, model of this effect. In this way, the analytical results can be tested in a realistic simulation environment. Such model also clarifies the dependence of the actuation from both the sliding s and its derivative ṡ, informing the control strategy, as it will be discussed in the next section.</p><p>Considering the tension balance in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, we model here the tension loss V (•) as the sum of viscous and static friction. The viscous friction loss is a linear function of the tendon portion speed v i c i , where c i is the viscous friction coefficient. For static friction, we make use of the model proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, which is able to combine good accuracy and limited computational costs. The main idea is to introduce a virtual angle z j for each variable subjected to friction θ j . These variables evolve according to the dynamic</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">z + j = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ θ j + Δ max j if θ j ≤ z j -Δ max j θ j -Δ max j if θ j ≥ z j + Δ max j z j otherwise (<label>37</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_50">)</formula><p>where θ j is the angle describing the rotation of the jth pulley, z j is the virtual angle at a certain time instant, and z + j is its value in the subsequent instant. Δ j max is the friction range. Friction force on the jth pulley is (θ jz j ) κ j , where κ j takes into account the amount of friction. Note indeed that the maximum static friction torque at the jth pulley is Δ j max κ j . Combing these friction models with <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, the resulting tension balance at the jth portion is</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">T j = T j -1 -v j c j r 2 j -(θ j -z j ) κ j r 2 j (<label>38</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">)</formula><p>or, in matrix form</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">MT + Λv + Σ(θ -z) + eτ M = 0 (39)</formula><p>where Σ and Λ collect κ j r 2 j and c j r 2 j terms. θ ∈ R 117 and z ∈ R 117 are vectors collecting θ j and z j . Thus, by substituting the novel friction balance in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>, the following friction driven input field results:</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">D(θ, z, q, ṡ) = R T M -1 (Λ (M -1 R q -e v ṡ) + Σ(θ -z))</formula><p>(40) where R has the same role of R of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_18">16</ref>), and it is derived in Appendix C. To complete the model, it remains to relate θ i to joint angles. This can be done by combining r i θ i = v i dt, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>, and by dividing for pulley radii</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">θ = N (M -1 R q -e v s) (<label>41</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_56">)</formula><p>where N is the diagonal matrix having as ith diagonal element 1 r i . Combining with (40), it yields to Thus, in presence of static friction (i.e., Σ = ∅), also a constant sliding (i.e., s = 0 and ṡ ≡ 0) can serve as an actuation. It is worth noticing that in accordance to the analytical model proposed in Section III, the input field R T M -1 Λ e v is equal to R T f (V max and Λ have identical structure). Similar considerations can be drawn for Σ N M -1 e v . However, the dependency on z prevents from expressing the solution in closed form.</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">D(z, q, q, s, ṡ) = R T M -1 (Λ (M -1 R q -e v ṡ) + Σ(N (M -1 Rq -e v s) -z)). (<label>42</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_58">)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Overall Resulting Model</head><p>Including dynamics effects, a generic robotic system driven by augmented adaptive synergies can be modeled as</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">B(q)q + W (q, q) q + Γ(q) = Q(q)u + J(q) T f ext (43)</formula><p>where z dynamics is <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref>, q are hand joint angles, with their derivatives q, q. B(q) is the inertia matrix. W (q, q) collects centrifugal, Coriolis, and dissipative effects. Γ(q) collects elastic forces. J(q) T f ext collects the torque action on joints as an effect of external forces. u τ M s ṡ T collects inputs, Q(q) is the transmission ratio from u to joint torques. In the case of the Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2, these terms can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ W (q, q) C(q, q) + F + R T M -1 Λ Γ(q) G(q) -R T M -1 Σ (N M -1 R q -z) Q(q) R T M -1 1 2 M e v Σ N e v -Λ e v u τ M s ṡ T (<label>44</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_61">)</formula><p>where the derivation of B(q) and C(q, q) is described in Appendix A, the elastic field G(q) is described in Appendix B, the transmission ratio R is described in Appendix C. We consider friction on joint level as the linear function of the joint derivatives F q, with F ∈ R 19×19 diagonal. The remaining terms are friction-related terms introduced in Section V-A. The MATLAB code implementing the proposed model is available at the Natural Machine Motion Initiative web site <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Identification</head><p>As already discussed in previous sections, we fixed pulley radii r i and spring stiffnesses k i by design. Geometric dimensions are known too from the design, i.e., R i β in (46), a b c d in (50), and phalanxes lengths in Appendix A. We also make the simplifying assumption for friction coefficients c i , κ i in (38), to be equal for each pulley. We estimate these values through an identification procedure. We also estimate abduction joint stiffnesses of (47). The data set was collected through PhaseSpace system, 1 an active led based motion capture system, with a sample time of 0.021 s and submillimeter precision. We placed a led on each phalanx and five on the back of the palm. We close for five times by applying a constant force (τ M = 15 N) and no sliding (s = 0). The data were filtered with a low-pass filter with two poles in -20 Hz. The identification was performed by 1 http://www.phasespace.com/ searching for the model parameters, which generated in simulation a closing behavior as close as possible to the one measured. The considered distance measure was the 2-norm between the joint evolutions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Simulative Results</head><p>Using the proposed identified model, we performed simulations to test predictions of the analytical model of Section III. According to the Augmented Adaptive Synergy framework, a sliding with constant velocity ṡ can actuate the hand in a novel direction of actuation. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9</ref>(b), we report the results of an analogous simulation, where instead of constant ṡ, we consider a step variation of s with values ranging from -5π 2 to 5π 2 mm. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9</ref>(e) presents corresponding tension distribution on tendon. Interestingly, the effect is similar to the constant sliding. However, these simulations demonstrate how, thanks to static friction, the entire range of postures between the two extremes can be achieved statically, using as control input s.</p><p>To conclude the analysis, we present an example of how an external force affects both hand posture [in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9(c)</ref>] and tension distribution [in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">9(f)</ref>]. The input torque and sliding is the same as in the latter simulation, but we introduced here a 2 N constant force applied orthogonally to index fingertip. The most evident effect is, according to the introduced framework, that index finger remains almost completely straight (angles equal to zero), while the other fingers close more. The most affected finger is the thumb, which is near to the index and with lower inertia w.r.t. the middle, which instead closes slightly less. It is also interesting to note that the second DoA (i.e., the change of s) still generates a relative reconfiguration of the finger angles. Finally, note that, as expected, the force increases the tension in the tendon portion nearest to the index, i.e., approximately from portion 1 to portion 50.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. EXPERIMENTAL VALIDATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Control</head><p>From the simulations, it results that a step variation of the sliding s is as much effective as a step variation of sliding speed ṡ in generating limit configurations, and while it appears more effective in generating intermediate ones. We thus consider here a simple control law defining motor torques, such that desired s and σ are achieved. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">10</ref> shows the block scheme. We map sliding s to the equivalent angle by divining for motor pulley radius r. The motor angles θ 1 and θ 2 are mapped into σ and s according to the definition, i.e., as semisum and semidifference. The control action is defined by an error-based PD control, with proportional gain equals to 0.2 N rad and 0.015 N s rad (heuristically  It generates a coordinate opening-closing of all the fingers, and it can be used to establish firm grasps. The second degree (e, f, g, h) instead generates a reconfiguration of the relative posture of the fingers, and it can be used to execute more complex tasks. It resembles high-order synergies of grasping and manipulation. This DoA is driven by friction, and controlled through a sliding of the tendon.</p><p>tuned). The control is mapped back to motor inputs as semisum and semidifference. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11</ref> shows two photo sequences of SoftHand 2 movements obtained through the considered controller. In the first row s = 0, and σ moves from 0 to π 2 . Thus, hand closes according to the first soft synergy, the same implemented in the original Pisa/IIT SoftHand <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. In the second row, σ = π 2 and s moves from 5π 2 to -5π 2 mm. This is the movement that characterize SoftHand 2 w.r.t. the previous version, and that is completely conveyed by friction effects. Note that the behavior is coherent with the design framework (see Section IV) and with the one obtained in simulation (see Section V-D).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Human-Machine Interface</head><p>The SoftHand 2 can be controlled through a digital input by a computer. However, to realize a more natural control by a   human operator, we designed a mechanical interface (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12</ref>). The operator, holding the handle, can move a joystick (512 ADAFRUIT analog 2-axis joystick) using the thumb. Upward direction is translated into an increase of the σ command (i.e., first DOA), in an integral fashion. The downward direction corresponds to a decrease of σ instead. Left and right directions correspond to a similar change of s. Pressing the select button reset the hand to initial position. The handle also holds a battery pack in the lower part. Using the proposed interface, we were able to test the SoftHand 2 performances independently from automatic planning and control performances.     </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Experiments</head><p>The proposed actuation mechanism equips SoftHand 2 with various skills that we present here in several experiments. Using only the first degree of actuation σ and relying on hand adaptability, SoftHand 2 effectively performs different kinds of power grasps, as presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">13</ref>. Note that different grasps are achieved even for the same object if grasped differently, as shown in panels (c, d). In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">14</ref>, SoftHand 2 grasps two thin objects using the first DoA in panels (a, c). The grasp is correctly established, but power grasp is not fully coherent with the task (e.g., the banknote is stretched). In panel (b, d), the hand grasps the same objects using a combination of the two DoAs. Natural precision grasps are achieved in this case. As discussed above, the SoftHand 2 has a completely self-contained design, enabling easy integration with robotic manipulators. To show that, in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">15</ref>, we mount Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 on a Kuka LWR, and we perform tasks exploiting both DoAs. Panels (a, b, c, d, e, f) show two power grasps of a same object. Panels (g, h, i) show a pinch grasp. In (j, k, l), the robot performs a nonprehensile manipulation of a paper sheet using the extended index finger. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">16</ref>, the ability of closing separately the two parts of the hand is exploited to sequentially grasp two objects physically distant from each other. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">17</ref>, the operator grasps a receiver using the first DoA, and places it to the right-hand side of the phone. Then, he uses the second DoA to obtain a posture as in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">11(h</ref>). Through the extended index, he dials a phone number. Finally, a power grasp is used to grasp again the receiver as to use it. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">18</ref>, SoftHand 2 extracts a pen from its  package by exploiting all the range of postures that the second DoA provides. It is worth noticing that these tasks are all intuitively accomplished by specifying in feedforward a value of σ and s. It is the intelligence embodied in the mechanics that provides the necessary mechanical adaptation to the environment and the objects to be grasped or manipulated.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">19</ref>, we present SoftHand 2 in-hand manipulation skills. In all the examples, the object is grasped using the first DoA, and then manipulated through a feedforward input of ramp shape on the second DoA. This is done independently from the object shape and size. The hand shapes autonomously its posture and maintains the grasp during manipulation, without the need of additional reactive control. Moving to more complex daily living activities, we exploit the manipulation skills introduced by the second degree of actuation and the hand mechanical intelligence, in opening a jar in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">20</ref>, and pouring some coffee from a cup in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">21</ref>. Note that both tasks are performed without any compensation at the wrist level.</p><p>We point the reader to the video footage, which includes all the presented experiments, and additional demonstration material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, the complexity-dexterity tradeoff related to the design of multisynergistic compliant hands is faced by the introduction of a novel actuation principle, exploiting the friction inevitably encountered in tendon systems to turn it to advantage. We formalized this idea in a novel framework, called augmented adaptive synergy framework. From the application of this idea, we derived the design of the Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2, an anthropomorphic robotic hand, with two DoAs, and 19 DoFs. The physical parameters of the hand are designed so that its free motions reproduce the first synergy of grasp <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> and a reconfiguration of the fingers closely related to higher order synergies <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> [28] <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. We also presented an accurate mathematical model of the robotic hand, to perform simulations, which corroborate the analytical model, and drive the controller design. We validated the prototype in several realistic conditions, both with the hand connected to a robotic manipulator and operated through a mechanical interface. Among the various abilities shown, the capacity of performing in-hand manipulation of objects of different sizes is of particular interest. Indeed, this is here obtained without the need of any feedback, and completely relying on the intelligence embodied in the hand mechanical structure. Future work will focus on the development of high level control and planning algorithms, which can take fully advantage from the demonstrated hand capabilities. We will also investigate the possibility of combining the proposed Augmented Adaptive Synergies, with Dynamic Synergies <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, to further increase the hand capabilities.</p><p>APPENDIX A: HAND KINEMATICS Each one of the four long fingers of Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 presents three interphalangeal joints and one abduction joint, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">22</ref>. The abduction joint is a revolute joint, while interphalangeal joints are CORE joints <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. They are kinematically equivalent to an RR arm, with a virtual (i.e., no inertia) intermediate link with an equality constraint between the two joint angles [see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_21">23(a)</ref> and<ref type="figure">(b)</ref>]. Hence, the 4-joint robotic finger dynamics is equivalent to a 7R arm with standard kinematics, plus three equality constraints, which reduce the DoFs to 4. This model describes index, middle, ring, and little fingers of the Pisa/IIT SoftHand. The thumb differs slightly, since it has one phalanx less and the abduction axis is oriented differently (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref>). APPENDIX B: JOINT IMPEDANCE Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_22">24</ref> shows a schematic representation of interphalangeal elastic mechanism. The spring characteristic is considered   linear. The spring deflection w.r.t. q i is 2R i (cos (β i + q i )cos (β i )). Gear envelope radius R i is considered constant. The angle of the spring connection with respect to the segment connecting the envelope centers is referred as β i . Resulting spring energy is</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">E(q) = 4 i=2 2k i R 2 i (cos (β i + q i ) -cos (β i )) 2 . (<label>45</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_63">)</formula><p>The interphalangeal elastic field G i (q) is G i (q) = 4 k i R 2 i (cos (β i )cos (β i + q i )) sin (β i + q i ). (46) The abduction elastic mechanism is modeled as a torsional linear spring</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">G 1 (q) = k 1 (q 1 -q) (<label>47</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">)</formula><p>where q is abduction joint rest position.</p><p>APPENDIX C: TRANSMISSION RATIO Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_23">25</ref> presents the left side of the interphalangeal joint actuation system. The variation of tendon length due to the closure of ith joint l i (q) is (r j + r j +1 )q i , where r j , r j +1 are radii of the pulleys acting on the ith joint left side. Hence, from kinetostatic relationship, the torque on the ith joint due to the left side of the mechanism is equal to (r j + r j +1 )T j . Total torque is obtained adding up right and left sides τ i = (r j + r j +1 )T j + (r k + r k +1 )T k <ref type="bibr">(48)</ref> where τ i is the total torque acting on the joint, and r k , r k +1 are the radii of the two pulleys acting on the ith joint right side. Note that other tendon configurations are possible, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_24">26</ref>, with transmission ratio: 1) r j + r j +1 , 2) r jr j +1 , 3) -r j + r j +1 , 4) -r jr j +1 . This introduces an addition DoF in the mechanical design that we do not further discuss further for the sake of space.</p><p>A different structure is used to actuate the abduction joint. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_25">27</ref> shows the mechanism in various configurations, with significant quantities highlighted. We refer to l l (q 1 ) and l r (q 1 ) as the lengths of the left and right portions of the tendon. q 1 is the abduction angle.</p><p>Here, we neglect variations of l 1 (q 1 ) and l 2 (q 1 ) associated with changes of the tendon tangency point. Joint torques depend on left-hand and right-hand side tension T L , T R through two different transmission ratios, X(q 1 ) [ ∂ l 1 (q 1 ) ∂ q 1 , ∂ l 2 (q 1 ) ∂ q 1 ]. Thanks to the symmetry of the mechanism w.r.t. q 1 , we consider only configurations (a-b) in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_25">27</ref>, i.e., q 1 ≥ 0. The results are extended for q 1 &lt; 0, substituting |q 1 | to q 1 , and inverting the order of the two terms.</p><p>There is a range of values of q 1 for which there is no contact between the central pulley [i.e., the one of radius e in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_25">27(d)</ref>]  and the tendon. Outside the interval the transmission geometry changes. Thus, derivation of l 1 (q 1 ) and l 2 (q 1 ) has to be done separately for both cases. Transmission ratio is X(q 1 ) X -(q 1 ), if q 1 ≤ q contact X + (q 1 ), if q 1 &gt; q contact (49)</p><p>where X -, X + are transmission ratio in no contact and contact case, and q contact = min{q * ∈ [0, π 2 ] s.t.: X -(q * ) = X + (q * )}. Simple geometrical considerations (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_25">27</ref>) bring to the following expressions for tendon lengths:</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">l 1 (q 1 ) = -a -b -R q 1 -c -d l - 2 (q 1 ) = a -b -R q 1 c -d l + 2 (q 1 ) = a -b -R q 1 e -f + c -e f -d (50)</formula><p>where || • || is the Euclidean norm, and R q 1 is the clockwise rotation matrix of an angle q 1 . We obtain X(q) from (49) by deriving (50). X(q), together with (48), specifies completely matrix R.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 is a novel anthropomorphic robotic hand. It implements two DoAs in a compact design, thanks to a mechanism that exploits frictional effects. The hand-free motions shown in the top part of the figure are designed so to resemble the main natural postural synergies. As a result, the Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 combines good grasping performance and dexterous in-hand manipulation capabilities. A few examples are depicted in the bottom.Here, the hand performs a pinch grasp, a power grasp of multiple objects, and it pushes a button by using the extended index.</figDesc><graphic coords="1,306.45,179.65,240.00,268.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Robotic hands designed through adaptive synergies: Pisa/IIT SoftHand integrates one DoA in a compact setup, while the second hand implements four synergies at the cost of a cumbersome structure. (a) Original Pisa/IIT SoftHand. (b) Second hand.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,55.44,322.78,216.00,141.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig.5. Simple adaptive hand with main quantities highlighted. q i is the ith joint angle. v 0 , v 17 and T 0 , T 17 are the speed and the tension at the two ends of the tendon. r i is the radius of the ith pulley. We consider here two possible routings, i.e., orders in which the tendon passes through pulleys. (a) Routing 1. (b) Routing 2.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,60.94,68.64,205.44,189.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig.6. Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 evolves Pisa/IIT SoftHand through the introduction of an additional DOA, powered by a friction-based transmission system. The hand design is self-contained, including the whole actuation system, sensors, power, and control electronics.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,318.66,68.72,224.16,158.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Sketches of SoftHand 2 prototype. The red line in panel (a) highlights the tendon route. Panel (b) presents main components of SoftHand 2: (1) are the two motors, (2) are the four encoders, (3) is the control and power electronics. Panel (c) reports a 2-D section of the motor and encoder assembly. (a) Routing. (b) Exploded sketch. (c) Motor and encoder.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,58.45,68.36,473.28,167.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2 N mm . Neglecting the four long fingers abduction joints (see Section V for more details) and considering a linear elastic field, the input directions of the two DoAs results from (20) as the span of [1, . . . , 1] T N and [33, 33, 33, 17, 17, 17, 1, 1, 1, -15, -15, -15, -31, -31, -31] T N. As prescribed by (23), the freeclosure configuration space is the span of [1, . . . , 1] T and [2, 2, 2, 1, 1, 1, 0, 0, 0, -1, -1, -1, -2, -2, -2] T , compatibly with physical joint limits. Thus, both closures are in line with the desired ones. We will test the ability of the proposed design to present such behavior through accurate simulations in the next section, and experimentally in Section VI. Fig.7(a) and (b) shows two CAD views of SoftHand 2, with main components highlighted. The hand includes two MAXON DC-X 22 s 24 V motors, mounted on the back. We also included 86:1 gearboxes, characterized by 15 W of continuous output power. A single Dyneema tendon runs in the whole hand.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Effect of sliding in the steady-state posture of SoftHand 2 [Panels (a, b, c)] and corresponding distributions of tension on the tendon [Panels (d, e, f)], according to the proposed model. A constant force τ M = 6N is applied in all the cases. In panel (a, d), a constant sliding speed ṡ is considered, which ranges from -5π 2 to 5π 2</figDesc><graphic coords="9,54.95,68.56,480.00,253.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 9 (</head><label>9</label><figDesc>a) shows the final posture of Soft-Hand 2 when τ M = 6 N, and ṡ is constant with values ranging from -. 9(d) presents the corresponding tension distribution of the tendon. Results are in accord with indications of the theoretical model in Section IV, i.e., the constant sliding generates a tension redistribution, which produces a coordinated closure of ring and little, and opening of the thumb and index fingers, when ṡ &gt; 0, and vice versa when ṡ &lt; 0.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Control architecture of Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2. Two proportionalintegral controllers regulate the angles of the two motors. No measurement from the hand posture is required. The references are expressed as σ and s.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,310.66,240.52,240.00,208.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Photosequences of the two movements corresponding to the two DoAs. The first degree (a, b,c, d) resembles the first synergy of grasp. It generates a coordinate opening-closing of all the fingers, and it can be used to establish firm grasps. The second degree (e, f, g, h) instead generates a reconfiguration of the relative posture of the fingers, and it can be used to execute more complex tasks. It resembles high-order synergies of grasping and manipulation. This DoA is driven by friction, and controlled through a sliding of the tendon.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Sketch of the SoftHand 2 human-machine interface. It enables an user to easily experiment with the robotic hand. The main subsystems are highlighted in figure. The interface includes a battery, the only component not already included on-board on the hand.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,78.44,68.12,170.40,147.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13. Using the first DoA, Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2 establishes stable power grasps for all considered object shapes, with characteristics depending on the affordances of the object. (a) Cube. (b) Sphere. (c) Tetris. (d) Tetris.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,46.44,279.70,234.72,95.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14. Comparison of grasping capabilities, between one DoA and two DoAs. The grasps (a) and (c) are obtained using the first DoA of the SoftHand 2. The second DoA enables more natural grasps when grasping small and/or flat objects, as with the banknote and the credit card in panels (b) and (d). (a) Banknote. (b) Banknote. (c) Card. (d) Card.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,43.94,430.98,239.04,111.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 15 .</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Fig.<ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref>. Photosequences of tasks performed by SoftHand 2 mounted on a Kuka LWR. In (a, b, c) and (d, e, f), a same object is grasped from two different sides, achieving two different grasps. In (g, h, i), the robot performs a precision grasp, and in (j, k, l), it slides a paper through the use of the index finger.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,303.95,68.04,244.80,340.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 16 .</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Fig. 16. Two distant objects are sequentially grasped by closing separately left and right sides of the hand.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,305.96,478.72,240.96,98.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 17 .</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Fig.<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref>. SoftHand 2 grasps a receiver using both DoAs, and places it on the right-hand side of the phone. Then, the index finger is extended, and used to dial a number. Finally, the receiver is grasped as to use it.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,303.95,617.74,244.80,85.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 18 .</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Fig. 18. SoftHand 2 extracts a pen from its package, by relying on the preshaping ability provided by the second DoA.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,59.16,165.09,480.00,355.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Fig. 19 .</head><label>19</label><figDesc>Fig. 19. Examples of in-hand manipulation. A same feedforward input allows to rotate objects with different shapes, relying on the intelligence embodied in the mechanism.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 20 .</head><label>20</label><figDesc>Fig. 20. Example of in-hand manipulation. We can use SoftHand 2 for opening a jar without main compensations on the wrist level.</figDesc><graphic coords="13,54.95,68.56,480.00,85.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Fig. 21 .</head><label>21</label><figDesc>Fig. 21. Example of in-hand manipulation. Following a feedforward input, SoftHand 2 pours coffee from a cup to another.</figDesc><graphic coords="13,54.95,197.17,480.00,85.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Fig. 22 .</head><label>22</label><figDesc>Fig. 22. Finger of Pisa/IIT SoftHand 2. It can be kinematically described as a 7R arm with three equality constrains, resulting in a 4-DoFs model. (a) Side view. (b) Top view.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,49.65,68.20,236.16,161.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Fig. 23 .</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Fig. 23. Interphalangeal joint is a realization of a CORE joint. We model it as an RR arm, with a virtual (i.e., no inertia) intermediate link. The pure revolute constraint between the two phalanxes translates into an equality constraint between the two angles of the arm. (a) Rest position. (b) Flexed position.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,47.65,288.80,240.00,74.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Fig. 24 .</head><label>24</label><figDesc>Fig. 24. Schematic representation of the interphalangeal spring system, in rest (a) and flexed (b) positions. q i is the joint angle, β is the angle of the spring connection with respect to the horizontal, and R i is the envelope radium. (a) Rest position. (b) Flexed position.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,47.65,432.00,240.00,116.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Fig. 25 .</head><label>25</label><figDesc>Fig. 25. Schematic representation of interphalangeal actuation system, in its rest and flexed positions. The red lines represent the tendon. Hand closure is associated to a reduction of tendon length proportional to the radii of pulleys actuating the joint.</figDesc><graphic coords="14,349.66,68.69,162.24,151.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>Fig. 26 .</head><label>26</label><figDesc>Fig. 26. Tendon configurations in interphalangeal actuation system. The red lines represent the tendon. Each configuration enables to implement a different, even negative, transfer ratio.</figDesc><graphic coords="15,45.44,68.72,236.64,188.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head>Fig. 27 .</head><label>27</label><figDesc>Fig. 27. Actuation system of the abduction joint. In (a-c), we present the joint in different configurations, the red lines represent the tendon. In (d), we highlight significant quantities, needed to derive the tendon length. (a) q1 &gt; 0. (b) q1 = 0. (c) q1 &lt; 0. (d) Significant quantities.</figDesc><graphic coords="15,64.94,324.31,196.80,368.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,63.66,68.68,471.36,136.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>SANTINA et al.: TOWARD DEXTEROUS MANIPULATION WITH AUGMENTED ADAPTIVE SYNERGIES: THE PISA/IIT SOFTHAND 2</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The authors would like to thank A. Brando, A. Di Basco, M. Maimeri, A. Raugi, and G. Santaera for their valuable support in the development and validation of the prototype.</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper was recommended for publication by Associate Editor S. Hirai and Editor A. Billard upon evaluation of the reviewers' comments. This work was supported by the European Unions Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation Program under Grant Agreement 645599 (Soma) and 688857 (SoftPro).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Cosimo Della Santina received the B.S. degree cum laude in computer engineering and the M.S. degree cum laude in automation and robotics engineering from University of Pisa, Pisa, Italy. He is currently working toward the Ph.D. degree in robotics with Research Center E. Piaggio, University of Pisa.</p><p>His main research interests include model-based design, sensing, and control of soft robots and soft hands. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cristina</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shadow delivers first hand</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kochan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ind. Robot: Int. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The DLR hand arm system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grebenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Autom</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Autom</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3175" to="3182" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design of a highly biomimetic anthropomorphic robotic hand towards artificial limb regeneration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Todorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Autom</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Autom</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3485" to="3492" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Servo robot gripper</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zaremsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mutschler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">US Patent</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">380</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986-01">Apr. 1 1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of underactuated mechanical grippers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Montambault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gosselin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mech. Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The highly adaptive SDM hand: Design and performance evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dollar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="597" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficiency of voluntary opening hand and hook prosthetic devices, 24 years of development?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Smit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bongers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Van Der Sluis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Plettenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Rehabil. Res. Develop</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Birglen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gosselin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Laliberté</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biomechatronic design and control of an anthropomorphic artificial hand for prosthetic and robotic applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zollo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Roccella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Guglielmelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Carrozza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dario</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ASME Trans. Mech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="418" to="429" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-08">Aug. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards the design of a prosthetic underactuated hand</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Laliberté</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Baril</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Guay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gosselin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mech. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A compliant, underactuated hand for robust manipulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Odhner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="736" to="752" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel type of compliant and underactuated robotic hand for dexterous grasping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Deimel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Brock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A soft robotic hand: Design, analysis, sEMG control, and experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00170-018-1949-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Adv. Manuf. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-03">Mar. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural bases of hand synergies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Santello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Baud-Bovy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jörntell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers Comput. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<pubPlace>Art</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dexterous grasping via eigengrasps: A low-dimensional approach to a high-complexity problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ciocarlie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Goldfeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc</title>
		<meeting>null<address><addrLine>Atlana, GA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-06">Jun. 2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3270" to="3275" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inter-finger coordination and postural synergies in robot hands via mechanical implementation of principal components analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Asada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. Intell. Robots Syst</title>
		<meeting>IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. Intell. Robots Syst</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2877" to="2882" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling natural and artificial hands with synergies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bicchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gabiccini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Santello</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosoph. Trans. Roy. Soc. B: Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1581</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3153" to="3161" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive synergies: An approach to the design of under-actuated robotic hands</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Catalano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Silvestro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bicchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. Intell. Robots Syst</title>
		<meeting>IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. Intell. Robots Syst</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1251" to="1256" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive synergies for the design and control of the pisa/iit softhand</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Catalano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Farnioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Serio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Piazza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bicchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="768" to="782" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grasping and coordinated manipulation by a multifingered robot hand</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sastry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal control with learned local models: Application to dexterous manipulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Todorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Autom</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Autom</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="383" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic in-hand sliding manipulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Woodruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Umbanhowar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lynch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Robot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="778" to="795" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-08">Aug. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tactile sensing for dexterous in-hand manipulation in roboticsa review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yousef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Boukallel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Althoefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sens. Actuators A: Physical</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">167</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dexterity augmentation on a synergistic hand: The pisa/iit softhand+</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Della Santina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Catalano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bicchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE-RAS 15th Int. Conf. Humanoid Robots</title>
		<meeting>IEEE-RAS 15th Int. Conf. Humanoid Robots</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="497" to="503" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postural hand synergies for tool use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Santello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Flanders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Soechting</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10105" to="10115" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Friction models for sliding dry, boundary and mixed lubricated contacts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Söderberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Björklund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tribology Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="580" to="587" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A compliant contact-aided revolute joint</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Howell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mechanism Mach. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1273" to="1293" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidigit movement synergies of the human hand in an unconstrained haptic exploration task</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Thakur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hsiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1271" to="1281" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postural hand synergies during environmental constraint exploitation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Della</forename><surname>Santina</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers Neurorobotics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">41</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A data-driven kinematic model of the human hand with soft-tissue artifact compensation mechanism for grasp synergy analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gabiccini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Stillfried</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Marino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bianchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. Intell. Robots Syst</title>
		<meeting>IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. Intell. Robots Syst</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3738" to="3745" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of the synergies underlying complex hand manipulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Todorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ghahramani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 26th Annu. Int. Conf</title>
		<meeting>26th Annu. Int. Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4637" to="4640" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sapporo high precision ball bearings datasheet</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.sppc.co.jp/eng/download/index.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-09">Sep. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hypergraphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Duchet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Combinatorics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="432" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The quest for natural machine motion: An open platform to fast-prototyping articulated soft robots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Della</forename><surname>Santina</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Robot. Autom. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-03">Mar. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preliminary results toward a naturally controlled multisynergistic prosthetic hand</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Della Santina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Piazza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Catalano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Biechi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int. Conf. Rehabil. Robot</title>
		<meeting>Int. Conf. Rehabil. Robot</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1356" to="1363" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new computational model of friction applied to haptic rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Experimental Robot. VI</title>
		<meeting>Experimental Robot. VI</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="412" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Softhand pro-d: Matching dynamic content of natural user commands with hand embodiment for enhanced prosthesis control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Piazza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Della Santina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Catalano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Garabini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bicchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Autom</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Robot. Autom</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3516" to="3523" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
