<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">This article has been accepted for inclusion in a future issue of this journal. Content is final as presented, with the exception of pagination</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">He</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<email>wanghe@seu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210096</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Guanrong</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-1381-7418</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210096</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210096</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wenwu</forename><forename type="middle">Yu</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210096</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
							<email>wwyu@seu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210096</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
							<email>ghwen@seu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210096</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">This article has been accepted for inclusion in a future issue of this journal. Content is final as presented, with the exception of pagination</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F85A11E8B41D05E2EF1AACFFEFC24EE3</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TCSI.2018.2838087</idno>
					<note type="submission">received January 29, 2018; revised April 18, 2018; accepted May 9, 2018.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T07:19+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Finite-time consensus</term>
					<term>antagonistic interaction</term>
					<term>homogeneity</term>
					<term>multi-agent system</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper addresses the finite-time bipartite consensus problem for multi-agent systems (MASs) on a directed signed network. Some properties for signed digraphs are first investigated and two nonlinear control protocols are then designed for first-and second-order MASs, respectively, where agents may be influenced by bounded disturbances. Particularly, for MASs with second-order dynamics, a new estimation technique is developed to estimate the settling time. Simulation results are finally presented to verify the effectiveness of the proposed control protocols.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Among the topics of cooperative control, consensus problem is the most popular and also a fundamental one, which aims to manipulate the states of all the agents to reach an agreement by designing some cooperative protocols based on relative local information for arbitrary initial conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. However, one may observe that most existing works on the consensus problem are obtained based on the assumption that the relationships or interactions among the agents are all cooperative, with no conflict or competition, which leads to the nonnegativity of the weights in their communication topology. While in reality, there are counterexamples in social networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, such as two-party political systems, trust networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and so on, where the interactions may be antagonistic. To explore these phenomena, an increasing number of works focused on the collective dynamics emerging with such kind of interactions called the cluster synchronization <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Actually, such situations can be described as networks with antagonistic interactions, which can be represented by a class of signed graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> whose weights could be either positive or negative. Recently, a particularly interesting problem of cluster synchronization has been raised in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> called bipartite consensus, which means that the states of the agents reach an agreement in terms of modulus but not sign.</p><p>It is generally known that a transformation of coordinates can bridge the bipartite consensus and the usual consensus where no competition exists. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, bipartite consensus was investigated for first-order multi-agent systems on both undirected and directed signed graphs, where the convergence rate is asymptotic. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, the bipartite consensus problem for a class of linear systems was studied on undirected digraphs with asymptotic convergence rate. The work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> extended the bipartite consensus into a more general setting, called the interval bipartite consensus, for which the topological condition was relaxed. Reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> further investigated the bipartite containment tracking without requiring the spanning tree condition, which generalized the interval bipartite consensus result. In all such studies, convergence rate is an important measure for evaluating a proposed control protocol from practical considerations. Finite-time consensus protocols have better system performance with faster convergence rates and other merits such as effective disturbance rejection <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. The finite-time bipartite consensus problem for first-order multi-agents was investigated on a class of undirected signed graphs in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. As for usual consensus (which can be easily transfered to bipartite consensus), <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> considered the finite-time consensus problem for first-order multi-agents under undirected and directed graphs. Reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> considered both finite-time and fixed-time multiscale coordination for first-order multi-agents under undirected graphs. Besides, the finite-time bipartite consensus problem on directed signed graphs with higher-order dynamics still remains unsolved. The difficulty for solving such a problem partly lies in the facts that the communication over a signed directed graph is asymmetric. Furthermore, even in the usual finite-time consensus problems of higher-order multi-agent systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, the convergence time estimation is not easy to obtain. Besides, the topologies considered (in tracking problem, referred to topologies among followers) were detailed balanced in <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, and undirected in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>.</p><p>Motivated by the above discussions, this paper investigates the finite-time bipartite consensus problem on directed signed graphs for both first-and second-order multi-agent systems, where the agents may be influenced by bounded disturbances. The main contributions of this work are twofold. First, a positive lower bound for a special quadratic form constructed from Lyapunov function is obtained, based on which, the finitetime first-and second-order bipartite consensus without any leader are solved. One should notice that most existing relevant results are finite-time tracking consensus and finite-time leaderless consensus is more difficult. Besides, the finitetime first-order bipartite consensus of the considered MASs is extended to the fixed-time bipartite consensus, in which the bound of the convergence time is independent of the initial conditions. Second, the homogeneous technique is utilized to solve the finite-time bipartite consensus problem for secondorder multi-agents. Interestingly, the settling time is not trivial to estimate by the usual homogeneous theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, but can be well estimated by the proposed technique.</p><p>The rest of the paper is arranged as follows. Some basic concepts about signed graphs and some useful lemmas are presented in Section II. The finite-time first-and second-order bipartite consensus problems are discussed in Sections III and IV, respectively. In Section V, some simulations are given to verify the theoretical analysis. Finally, conclusion is drawn in Section VI.</p><p>Notations: x [α]  sign(x)|x| α , x ∈ R, α &gt; 0. When x is a vector, the function (•) [α] operates on it componentwise. Re(λ) takes the real part of λ ∈ C, where C is the set of complex numbers. λ min (B) (λ max (B)) means the minimal (maximal) eigenvalue of the symmetric real matrix B. O(x, r ) means the open ball centered at x ∈ R N with radius r &gt; 0. Furthermore, 0 1×N (0 N×1 ) means an N-dimensional row (column) vector with all elements being 0. Two matrices A, B ∈ R N×N are called similar if B = P -1 A P for some invertible matrix P ∈ R N×N , and is denoted by A ∼ B. Denote diag(a 1 , ..., a k ) as a diagonal matrix with its diagonal elements being a i , where a i ∈ R, i = 1, ..., k.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PRELIMINARIES</head><p>In this section, some basic concepts about signed graph and preliminary results on finite-time consensus are introduced.</p><p>A signed graph G = (V, E, G) involves a set of nodes V = {v 1 , v 2 , ..., v N }, a set of edges E ⊆ V × V and a signed weighted adjacency matrix G = (G i j ) N×N . Here, an edge E i j in E means a pair of nodes (v j , v i ) representing that the information flow goes from node v j to node v i . G records the coupling configuration of all edges in G. The signed weight G i j , which can be either positive or negative, is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">G i j = 0 ⇔ (v j , v i ) ∈ E. In this paper, self-loop is not considered, i.e. G ii = 0, i = 1, 2, ..., N. The graph G is undirected if (v i , v j ) ∈ E implies (v j , v i ) ∈ E, and G T = G; otherwise G is called a directed graph (digraph).</formula><p>Remark 1: In the following, an edge (a path/cycle) is always referred to an edge (a path/cycle) in a signed graph, unless otherwise indicated. A graph with nonnegative weights is called a positive graph, which is a special case of a signed graph.</p><p>Definition 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">A directed path from node v j to v i is a sequence of directed edges, (v i ,v i 1 ), (v i 1 ,v i 2 ),..., (v i l ,v j ), in the directed network with distinct nodes v i k , k = 1, 2, ..., l.</formula><p>A directed network G is strongly connected if between any pair of distinct nodes v i and v j in G, there exists a directed path, i, j = 1, 2, ..., N. A directed cycle is a directed path beginning from and ending at the same node. A directed cycle is positive if the product of all its signed edge weights is positive; otherwise, it is negative.</p><p>The Laplacian matrix L = (l i j ) N×N for a signed graph G is denoted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">l ii = N j =1, j =i |G i j |; l i j = -G i j , i = j.</formula><p>Lemma 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>: Suppose that G is a positive and strongly connected graph. Then, 0 is the algebraically simple eigenvalue of its Laplacian L, and the other eigenvalues have positive real parts. If the positive graph is undirected and connected, L has one zero eigenvalue and the others are all real and positive.</p><p>Definition 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>: A signed graph G is said to be structurally balanced if it admits a bipartition of the nodes,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">V 1 and V 2 , satisfying V 1 V 2 = V and V 1 V 2 = 0, such that G i j ≥ 0, v i , v j ∈ V q (q ∈ {1, 2}), and G i j ≤ 0, v i ∈ V q , v j ∈ V 3-q (q ∈ {1, 2}). Otherwise, it is called structurally unbalanced. Define D = {D = diag(d 1 , d 2 , ..., d N ), d i ∈ {±1}}.</formula><p>Then, the following Lemma 2 show some equivalent conditions for structural balance.</p><p>Lemma 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>: A strongly connected signed digraph G (of order N) is structurally balanced if and only if any of the following condition holds:</p><p>1) all directed cycles of G are positive; 2) ∃D ∈ D such that DG D has all nonnegative entries; 3) 0 is an eigenvalue of L, and rank(L) = N -1.</p><p>Remark 2 As for structural unbalance, one can obtain the corresponding equivalent conditions by negating these three conditions. For example, Since L is diagonally dominant, the corresponding equivalent condition 3) should be: -L is Hurwitz stable.</p><p>In the following, two useful lemmas about positive directed graphs are provided.</p><p>Lemma 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>: Consider a strongly connected positive graph, with the corresponding Laplacian matrix L p . Then, L p 1 N = 0, and there is a positive vector ξ p = (ξ p1 , ξ p2 , ..., ξ pN ) T such that ξ T p L p = 0. Lemma 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>: For a strongly connected positive graph with Laplacian matrix L p , define its general algebraic connectivity by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">a(L p ) = min x T ξ p =0,x =0 x T L p x x T p x , (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">L p = ( p L p + L T p p )/2, p = diag(ξ p1 , ξ p2 , ..., ξ pN ), ξ p = (ξ p1 , ξ p2 , ..., ξ pN ) T &gt; 0, satisfying ξ T p L p = 0, N i=1 ξ pi = 1.</formula><p>Then, a(L p ) &gt; 0. Similarly to the above two lemmas, the following two lemmas present some properties for the Laplacian matrix L of a signed digraph, which will be utilized for deducing the main results of this paper later.</p><p>Lemma 5: Suppose that L corresponds to a strongly connected, structurally balanced digraph, with adjacency matrix G. Then, ∃D ∈ D such that L D1 N = 0, and there is a positive vector ξ = (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ..., ξ N ) T such that ξ T DL = 0. Denote = diag(ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ..., ξ N ). Then, &gt; 0 and -1 &gt; 0.</p><p>Proof: Since L corresponds to a strongly connected, structurally balanced digraph, it follows from Lemma 2 that ∃D ∈ D such that DG D has all nonnegative entries, which means that DL D corresponds to a strongly connected, positive digraph. It is easy to check that DL D1 N = 0 N×1 , which leads to L D1 N = 0 N×1 because D is invertible. Then, according to Lemma 3, there exists a positive vector ξ = (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ..., ξ N ) T such that ξ T DL D = 0 1×N , which implies that ξ T DL = 0 1×N since D is invertible.</p><p>Lemma 6: For Laplacian matrix L corresponding to a strongly connected, structurally balanced digraph, define its general algebraic connectivity</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">a(L) = min x T Dξ =0,x =0 x T Lx x T x ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where L = 1 2 (L + L T ), ξ and are defined in Lemma 5. Then a(L) &gt; 0.</p><p>Proof: Similarly to the proof of Lemma 5, ∃D ∈ D such that DL D corresponds to a strongly connected, positive digraph. Then, according to Lemma 4, and since D = D, the following property holds: </p><formula xml:id="formula_8">0 &lt; a(DL D) = min y T ξ =0,y =0</formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">a(L) = min x T Dξ =0,x =0 x T Lx x T x = a(DL D) &gt; 0.<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Before going on, some useful inequalities and lemmas concerning finite-time convergence are presented.</p><p>Lemma 7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>: For any given w i ≥ 0, i = 1, 2, ..., N, and ν &gt; μ ≥ 1:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">N i=1 w ν i 1 ν ≤ N i=1 w μ i 1 μ ≤ N 1 μ -1 ν N i=1 w ν i 1 ν . (4)</formula><p>Definition 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>: A function V : R m → R is homogeneous of degree l ≥ 0 with respect to a given m-tuple of positive coefficients r = (r 1 , ..., r m ) if</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">V (λ r 1 x 1 , ..., λ r m x m ) = λ l V (x 1 , ..., x m ),<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where x 1 , ..., x m ∈ R and λ &gt; 0.</p><p>Lemma 8 <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>: Suppose V 1 and V 2 are continuous realvalued functions on R m , homogeneous with respect to a given m-tuple of positive coefficients r = (r 1 , ..., r m ) of degree l 1 &gt; 0 and l 2 &gt; 0, respectively, and V 1 is positive definite. Then, for every x ∈ R m , min</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">{z:V 1 (z)=1} V 2 (z) V l 2 l 1 1 ≤ V 2 ≤ max {z:V 1 (z)=1} V 2 (z) V l 2 l 1 1 . (<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">)</formula><p>Definition 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">Consider the system ẋ(t) = f (x(t)), f (0) = 0, x(0) = x 0 , x ∈ R k .</formula><p>The origin is said to to be globally finite-time stable if it is globally asymptotically stable and any solution x(t, x 0 ) reaches to origin in a finite time, that is x(t, x 0 ) = 0, ∀t ≥ T (x 0 ), where T : R k -→ R + ∪{0} is called the settling time. Furthermore, if the origin is globally finite-time stable and the settling time</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">T (x 0 ) satisfies T (x 0 ) ≤ T max , ∀x 0 ∈ R k , where T max &gt; 0.</formula><p>Then, the origin is said to be globally fixed-time stable.</p><p>Lemma 9 <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">Consider the system ẋ(t) = f (x(t)), f (0) = 0, x(0) = x 0 , x ∈ R k .</formula><p>Suppose that there exists a radially unbounded, positive definite continuous function V (x) : R k → R, and two real numbers c &gt; 0 and r ∈ (0, 1), such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">V (x) + c(V (x)) r ≤ 0, x ∈ R k \ {0}.</formula><p>Then, the origin is a globally finite-time stable equilibrium of this system. In addition, the finite settling time T satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">T ≤ V (x(0)) 1-r c(1-r) . Furthermore, if the continuous function V (x) satisfies V (x) + c 1 (V (x)) r 1 + c 2 (V (x)) r 2 ≤ 0, with c 1 , c 2 &gt; 0 and 0 &lt; r 1 &lt; 1 &lt; r 2 ,</formula><p>then the origin is a globally fixedtime stable equilibrium, and the settling time T is bounded by T ≤</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">1 c 1 (1-r 1 ) + 1 c 2 (r 2 -1) .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. FINITE-TIME FIRST-ORDER BIPARTITE CONSENSUS</head><p>In this section, finite-time first-order bipartite consensus problem in the presence of disturbances on a directed signed network is studied. The dynamics of agent i is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">ẋi (t) = u i (t) + d i (x i , t), i = 1, 2, ..., N,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where x i (t), u i (t), d i (x i , t) ∈ R represent the state, control input and disturbance, respectively. In the following, x i , u i and d i are used for simplicity. Definition 5: For the multi-agent system <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, the finite-time first-order bipartite consensus problem is said to be solved if there exist some control inputs u i and a finite settling time T &gt; 0, such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">lim t →T - |x i | -|x j | = 0,<label>and</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">|x i | = |x j |, ∀t ≥ T, i, j = 1, 2, .., N. (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">)</formula><p>Furthermore, if the settling time T is independent of the initial states, then the first-order bipartite consensus problem is referred to as the fixed-time problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>. Remark 3: If the agreement value is zero, i.e. x i = 0, i = 1, 2, .., N, the finite-time bipartite consensus problem reduces to the finite-time stabilization problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Finite-Time First-Order Bipartite Consensus Without Disturbance</head><p>Firstly, in this subsection, consider the nominal system without disturbance:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">ẋi = ūi , i = 1, 2, ..., N,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where ūi ∈ R is the control input to be designed. For system <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, the following general distributed protocol is proposed:</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">ūi = -a N j =1 |G i j | x i -sign(G i j )x j [α] -b N j =1 |G i j | x i -sign(G i j )x j [β] ,<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where a, b, α and β are nonnegative parameters to be determined later. Let</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">y i = N j =1 |G i j | x i -sign(G i j )x j , y = [y 1 , ..., y N ] T , x = [x 1 , ...,</formula><p>x N ] T . One then gets that y = Lx, and y ⊥ Dξ . Thus, the evolution of y satisfies ẏ = -a Ly [α] -bLy [β] .</p><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">)<label>11</label></formula><p>The following theorem validates the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>. Theorem 1: Consider the multi-agent system (9) with control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, and choose a &gt; 0, b = 0, and α ∈ (0, 1). If the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced, then the finite-time bipartite consensus can be achieved. Otherwise, if the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced, then the finitetime stabilization problem of the multi-agent system (9) can be solved with the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</p><p>Remark 4: Although for structurally unbalanced communication topology, the consensus problem degenerates to stabilization problem, it is still interesting because no agent could know whether the communication topology is structurally balanced or unbalanced. This situation could be taken as a comparison to show that structure does influence the finial convergence states.</p><p>Before giving a proof to Theorem 1, two useful lemmas are provided, for which detailed proofs are given in Appendix.</p><p>Lemma 10: Consider the Laplacian matrix L related to a strongly connected, structurally balanced digraph. Then, ∃D ∈ D such that DL D is a positive digraph Laplacian matrix. For given positive scalar a, α, and β with condition α = β, define the vector set (a, α, β) = {z : ∃y⊥Dξ and γ = γ (y) ≥ 0, s.t. z = ay [α] + γ y [β] , and z T z = 1}. Then,</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">inf z∈(a,α,β) z T Lz = k 1 &gt; 0,<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where L = (L + L T )/2, ξ and are defined in Lemma 5.</p><p>Remark 5: Consider the definition of z in Lemma 10, with a, α, and β fixed. It is clear that γ depends on the value of y. Thus γ (y) is adopted to indicate that γ depends on y. One should also notice that the positive value k 1 actually depends on the value of a, α, and β.</p><p>Lemma 11: Assume that the Laplacian matrix L corresponds to a strongly connected, structurally unbalanced digraph. Then, there exists a positive definite diagonal matrix P = diag( p 1 , p 2 , ..., p N ) such that P L + L T P &gt; 0.</p><p>With the help of the above two lemmas, Theorem 1 is now proved.</p><p>Proof: [Proof for Theorem 1] Suppose the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced. Choose the Lyapunov function</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">V = N i=1 ξ i α + 1 |y i | α+1 , (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">)</formula><p>where ξ i is defined in Lemma 5. Taking the derivatives of V along the trajectories ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_27">11</ref>) with b = 0, one obtains</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">V = N i=1 ξ i y [α] i ẏi = y [α] T -a Ly [α] = -a y [α] T L y [α] = -a||z|| 2 ȳ[α] T L ȳ[α] ≤ -ak 1 N i=1 |y i | 2α , (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_32">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">L = 1/2(L + L T ), z = y [α] ∈ (1, α, β) with γ = 0, ȳ = y/||z|| 1 α</formula><p>, and the last inequality is followed by Lemma 10.</p><p>Letting a i = |y i | 2α , ν = α+1 2α &gt; 1, μ = 1 and invoking the left inequality in Lemma 7, one gets</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">N i=1 |y i | α+1 2α 1+α = N i=1 |y i | 2α α+1 2α 2α 1+α ≤ N i=1 |y i | 2α ,</formula><p>with which, ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_31">14</ref>) can be further estimated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">V ≤ -c 1 V r 1 , (<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">c 1 = ak 1 ((α + 1)/ξ max ) r 1 , r 1 = 2α/(1 + α) and ξ max = max(ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ..., ξ N ).</formula><p>Then, it follows immediately from Lemma 9 that y reaches 0 in finite time. On the other hand, since L D1 N = 0, and rank(L) = N -1 according to Lemma 2, one can deduce from</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">y = Lx = 0 that x ∈ span{D1 N }, i.e. |x i | = |x j |, i, j = 1, 2, ..., N.</formula><p>The above analysis indicates that the bipartite consensus is achieved in finite time, and the settling time T 0 satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">T 0 ≤ V (Lx(0)) 1-r 1 c 1 (1-r 1 )</formula><p>. Suppose now the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced. Choose the following Lyapunov function for the consensus error system (9):</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">V = N i=1 p i α + 1 |y i | α+1 , (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">)</formula><p>where p i is defined in Lemma 11. By employing some similar analysis as those utilized above, one can prove that V reaches 0 in finite time, i.e. y i reaches 0 in finite time. Besides, y = Lx, and L is invertible if the strongly connected digraph is structurally unbalanced according to Remark 2, so one can conclude that the multi-agent system (9) is stabilized in finite time with the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, and the settling time T0 is estimated as T0 ≤ V (Lx(0)) 1-r 1 c1 (1-r 1 ) , where c1 = aλ min ( L )((α + 1)/ p max ) r1 , r1 = 2α/(1 + α), L = 1 2 (P L + L T P), p max = max( p 1 , p 2 , ..., p N ), and P = diag( p 1 , p 2 , ..., p N ).</p><p>Remark 6: The above settling time T 0 and T0 depend on the initial values x(0). However, the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> with a, b &gt; 0 can ensure fixed-time convergence while the settling time is independent of the initial values. The following corollary verifies this observation.</p><p>Corollary 1: Consider the multi-agent system (9) with control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>. Choose a, b &gt; 0 and 0 &lt; α &lt; 1 &lt; β. If the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced, then the fixed-time bipartite consensus can be achieved. Otherwise, if the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced, then the fixedtime stabilization problem of multi-agent system (9) can be solved with the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</p><p>Proof: Suppose the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced. Choose the Lyapunov function</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">V = N i=1 ξ i a α + 1 |y i | α+1 + b β + 1 |y i | β+1 , (<label>17</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_43">)</formula><p>where ξ i is defined in Lemma 5. Taking the derivatives for V along the trajectories <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, one obtains</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">V = N i=1</formula><p>ξ i ay [α]  i + by</p><p>[β] i ẏi =ay [α] + by [β]   T L ay [α] + by [β]   =ay [α] + by [β]   T L ay [α] + by [β]   = -</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">||z|| 2 a ȳ[α] + γ ȳ[β] T L a ȳ[α] + γ ȳ[β] ,<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where L = 1/2(L + L T ), z = ay [α] + by [β] , ȳ = y/||z|| 1 α , and γ = b||z|| (β-α)/α . By Lemma 10, one obtains</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">V ≤ -k 1 ||ay [α] + by [β] || 2 = -k 1 N i=1 a 2 |y i | 2α + 2ab|y i | α+β + b 2 |y i | 2β ≤ -k 2 N i=1 |y i | 2α + 2|y i | α+β + |y i | 2β , (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_47">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">k 2 = min(a, b) 2 k 1 .</formula><p>Then, according to the first inequality of (4) with 2N terms in Lemma 7, one gets the following inequality, where ν = β + 1 and μ = α + β:</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">N i=1 |y i | α+1 + |y i | β+1 1 1+β = N i=1 (|y i | α+1 β+1 ) β+1 + |y i | β+1 1 1+β ≤ N i=1 (|y i | α+1 β+1 ) α+β + |y i | α+β 1 α+β ≤ N i=1 |y i | 2α + |y i | 2β + |y i | α+β 1 α+β . (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_50">)</formula><p>The last inequality follows from</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">|y i | (α+1)(α+β) β+1 ≤ |y i | 2α +|y i | 2β , since 2α &lt; (α+1)(α+β) β+1 &lt; 2β is satisfied for 0 &lt; α &lt; 1 &lt; β.</formula><p>Similarly, taking ν = 2β and μ = β + 1 in the second inequality of (4) with 2N terms gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">N i=1 |y i | α+1 + |y i | β+1 1 1+β ≤ (2N) 1 β+1 -1 2β N i=1 |y i | 2β α+1 β+1 + |y i | 2β 1 2β ≤ (2N) 1 β+1 -1 2β N i=1 |y i | 2α + |y i | 2β + |y i | α+β 1 2β ,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>where the last inequality is due to 2α &lt; 2β α+1 β+1 &lt; 2β for 0 &lt; α &lt; 1 &lt; β. Then, one obtains from <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_52">21</ref>) that</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">V ≤ -k 2 N i=1 |y i | 2α + 2|y i | α+β + |y i | 2β ≤ -k 2 N i=1 |y i | 2α + |y i | α+β + |y i | 2β ≤ - 1 2 k 2 V α+β 1+β - 1 2 k 2 (2N) 1-β 1+β V 2β 1+β ≤ -ĉ 1 V r1 -ĉ2 V r2 , (<label>22</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">V = N i=1 |y i | α+1 + |y i | β+1 , ĉ1 = 1 2 k 2 α+1 max(a,b)ξ max α+β 1+β , ĉ2 = 1 2 k 2 (2N) 1-β 1+β α+1 max(a,b)ξ max 2β 1+β , r1 = α+β 1+β &lt; 1, r2 = 2β 1+β &gt; 1 and ξ max = max(ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ..., ξ N ).</formula><p>Then, it follows immediately from Lemma 9 that y i reaches 0 in fixed time. On the other hand, since L D1 N = 0 and rank(L) = N -1 according to Lemma 2, one can deduce from y = Lx = 0 that x ∈ span{D1 N }, i.e. |x i | = |x j |, i, j = 1, 2, ..., N. The above analysis indicates that the fixedtime bipartite consensus of multi-agent system (9) is achieved, and the settling time</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">T 0 satisfies T 0 ≤ 1 ĉ1 (1-r 1 ) + 1 ĉ2 ( ĉ2 -1)</formula><p>. Suppose now that the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced. Choose the following Lyapunov function for the consensus error system (9):</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">V = N i=1 p i a α + 1 |y i | α+1 + b β + 1 |y i | β+1 , (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_58">)</formula><p>where p i is defined in Lemma 11. By employing some similar analysis as those utilized on ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_28">12</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_35">15</ref>), one can prove that y i reaches 0 in fixed time. Besides, y = Lx and L is invertible if the strongly connected digraph is structurally unbalanced, according to Remark 2. Then, one can conclude that system (9) is stabilized in fixed time with the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, and the settling time T0 is estimated as T0 ≤</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">1 č1 (1-ř 1 ) + 1 č2 ( ř2 -1) , where č1 = 1 2 min(a, b) 2 λ min ( L ) α+1 max(a,b) p max ř1 , č2 = 1 2 (2N) 1-β 1+β min(a, b) 2 λ min ( L ) α+1 max(a,b) p max ř2 , ř1 = α+β 1+β &lt; 1, ř2 = 2β</formula><p>1+β &gt; 1, L = 1 2 (P L + L T P), p max = max( p 1 , p 2 , ..., p N ), and P = diag( p 1 , p 2 , ..., p N ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Finite-Time First-Order Bipartite Consensus With Bounded Disturbances</head><p>With the above discussion on the nominal system (9), a class of sliding-mode control protocol is proposed in this subsection to solve the finite-time first-order bipartite consensus problem for the multi-agent system <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, which is influenced by disturbances. Before giving the main result, one assumption is needed.</p><p>Assumption 1: The disturbance d i (x i , t) in system ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_20">7</ref>) is assumed to satisfy the following condition:</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">||d i (x i , t)|| ∞ ≤ D i , (<label>24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_61">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">D i &gt; 0 is a constant and || • || ∞ is the infinite norm of a vector, i = 1, 2, ..., N.</formula><p>Design the following sliding-mode variables:</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">s i = x i + r i , ṙi = a N j =1 |G i j | x i -sign(G i j )x j [α] +b N j =1 |G i j | x i -sign(G i j )x j [β] , (<label>25</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_64">)</formula><p>where a, b, α, and β are defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, and accordingly the sliding-mode surface is</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">{(x 1 , x 2 , ..., x N )|s i = 0, i = 1, 2, ..., N}. (<label>26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_66">)</formula><p>Theorem 2: Consider the multi-agent system (7) with Assumption 1 satisfied. Choose a &gt; 0, b = 0, and α ∈ (0, 1) for the sliding-mode variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>. If the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced, then the sliding-mode surface (26) can be reached in finite time with the following sliding-mode control used:</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">u i = ūi + u nd i , u nd i = -l i sign(s i ), (<label>27</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_68">)</formula><p>where ūi is defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> and l i &gt; D i . Thus, the finitetime bipartite consensus can be achieved. Otherwise, if the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced, then the finite-time stabilization problem of multiagent system (7) can be solved with the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>.</p><p>Proof: Taking the derivative of s i along <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> with control laws <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">ṡi = d i -l i sign(s i ), i = 1, 2, ..., N. (<label>28</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_70">)</formula><p>Choose the Lyapunov function V = 1 2 s T s with s = [s 1 , ..., s N ] T , and take the derivative of V . One obtains</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">V = N i=1 s i ṡi = N i=1 (s i d i -l i |s i |) ≤ N i=1 -(l i -D i )|s i | ≤ - l√ V , (<label>29</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_72">)</formula><p>where l = √ 2 min i=1,...,N {l i -D i }. It follows that V reaches 0 in finite time T d ≤ 2 √ V (s(0))/ l, which results in that all the states x i reach the sliding-mode surface <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref> in finite time T d . Then, s i = ṡi = 0, i = 1, 2, ..., N, for t ≥ T d . Furthermore, ṡi = 0 means that the nominal system (9) holds thereafter. According to Theorem 1, the finite-time firstorder bipartite consensus can be reached if the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced, and the finite-time first-order stabilization can be solved if the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced.</p><p>Corollary 2: Consider the multi-agent system (7) with Assumption 1 satisfied. Choose a, b &gt; 0 and 0 &lt; α &lt; 1 &lt; β for the sliding-mode variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>. If the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced, then the sliding-mode surface ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_65">26</ref>) can be reached in fixed time with the following sliding-mode control used:</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">u i = ūi + u xd i , u xd i = -a i s [α i ] i -b i s [β i ] i -l i sign(s i ), (<label>30</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_74">)</formula><p>where ūi is defined in (10), a i , b i &gt; 0, 0 &lt; α i &lt; 1 &lt; β i , and l i &gt; D i . Thus, the bipartite consensus can be achieved in fixed time. Otherwise, if the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced, then the fixedtime stabilization problem of multi-agent system (7) can be solved with the control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref>.</p><p>Proof: Choosing V i = 1 2 s 2 i and taking the derivative of V i , one gets</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">Vi = -a i |s i | α i +1 -b i |s i | β i +1 -l i |s i | + s i d i ≤ - √ 2a i V α i +1 2 - √ 2b i V β i +1 2 . (<label>31</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_76">)</formula><p>It follows that V i reaches 0 in fixed time 1) . With similar arguments as in the proof for Theorem 2, one can prove the claims in this corollary.</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">T di ≤ √ 2 a i (1-α i ) + √ 2 b i (β i -</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. FINITE-TIME SECOND-ORDER BIPARTITE CONSENSUS</head><p>In this section, the finite-time second-order bipartite consensus problem with disturbances on a directed signed network is discussed. Suppose each agent is described by the following second-order dynamics:</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">ẋi (t) = v i (t), vi (t) = u i (t) + di (x i , v i , t), i = 1, 2, ..., N,<label>(32)</label></formula><p>where x i (t), v i (t), di (x i , v i , t) ∈ R represent the position, velocity and disturbance of the i th agent, respectively, and u i (t) ∈ R is the control protocol for agent i . In the following, x i , v i , u i and di are used for simplicity.</p><p>Definition 6: For the multi-agent system <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>, the finitetime second-order bipartite consensus problem is said to be solved if and only if there exist some control inputs u i , a finite settling time T &gt; 0, and δ i ∈ {±1}, i = 1, 2, ..., N, such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">lim t →T -|δ i • (x i , v i ) -δ j • (x j , v j )| = 0, δ i • (x i , v i ) = δ j • (x j , v j ), t ≥ T, i, j = 1, ..., N. (<label>33</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_80">)</formula><p>If the agreement value is zero, i.e. x i = v i = 0, i = 1, 2, .., N, the finite-time stabilization problem is solved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Finite-Time Second-Order Bipartite Consensus Without Disturbance</head><p>In this subsection, the nominal system without disturbance is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">ẋi (t) = v i (t), vi (t) = ūi (t), i = 1, 2, ..., N,<label>(34)</label></formula><p>where ūi (t) ∈ R is the control input to the nominal system. With a bit abuse of index notations (a, b, α, and β), consider the following control protocol for the nominal system (34):</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">ūi = -a N j =1 |G i j | x i -sign(G i j )x j [α] -b N j =1 |G i j | v i -sign(G i j )v j [β] , (<label>35</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">)</formula><p>where a, b are some positive constants to be determined later, and α ∈ (0, 1], β = 2α 1+α . Denote x = [x 1 , ..., x N ] T , v = [v 1 , ..., v N ] T , and let e x = Lx and e v = Lv. Then, one obtains the error system ėx = e v , ėv = -a L(e x ) [α] -bL(e v ) [β] .</p><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">)<label>36</label></formula><p>The following theorem provides a sufficient condition for achieving the finite-time second-order bipartite consensus. Theorem 3: Consider system (34) with controller <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>. Assume that the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced, a and b satisfy a(L)•b 2 &gt; a, and α is chosen properly. Then, the finite-time secondorder bipartite consensus can be achieved. Besides, when the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced, the finite-time second-order consensus can be achieved if λ min ( L ) • b 2 &gt; a and α is chosen properly, where L = 1 2 (P L + L T P) and P is defined in Lemma 11. Proof: Define w = e T x , (e</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">[2/(1+α)] v</formula><p>) T T and denote e = (e T</p><p>x , e T v ) T . If the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced, choose the Lyapunov function</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">V (α, e) = 1 2 w T w, (<label>37</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_87">)</formula><p>where = 2a L a b a b , is defined in Lemma 5, and L = (L+L T )/2. One can prove that, for any α ∈ (0, 1], V (α, e) is positive definite. In fact, according to Lemma 6, V (α, e) ≥ 2a a(L)e T x e x +2 a b e T x e</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">[2/(1+α)] v + e [2/(1+α)] v T e [2/(1+α)] v = ( a b e x +e [2/(1+α)] v ) T ( a b e x +e [2/(1+α)] v )+(2a a(L)-a 2 b 2 )e T x e x . Since â(L) • b 2 &gt; a, one gets that V (α, e) ≥ 0, and V (α, e) = 0 ⇔ e = 0.</formula><p>Computing the derivative of V (α, e), one obtains 1) α = 1:</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">V (1, e) = - 1 2 e T + T T e = -(e T x , e T v ) a 2 b L 0 N×N 0 N×N b L -a b e x e v ,<label>(38)</label></formula><p>2) α ∈ (0, 1):</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">V (α, e) = ω T e v diag |e v | 1-α 1+α</formula><p>a Le [α]  x -bLe</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">[β] v , (<label>39</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_92">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_93">where = 0 N×N -I N a L bL . It is obvious that V (α, e) is continuous in (0, 1) and left-continuous at α = 1. Note that V is continuous in (e x , e v ) ∈ R N × R N . Furthermore, when a(L)•b 2 &gt; a, e x ⊥Dξ</formula><p>, and e v ⊥Dξ , where D and ξ are defined in Lemma 5, one gets that V (1, e) ≤ 0 and V (1, e) = 0 if and only if y = 0, i.e. e x = 0 and e v = 0.</p><p>Let</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">N (η) = {e|V (α, e) = 1, α ∈ [η, 1]} and Nα = {e|V (α, e) = 1}</formula><p>, where η ∈ (0, 1). Notice that V (α, e) is radially unbounded and continuous, so N (η) is bounded and closed, thus is compact. In the following, it will be proved that there exists α 0 ∈ (0, 1) such that V (α 0 , e) &lt; 0, ∀e ∈ Nα 0 .</p><p>Firstly, consider V (1, e). According to the definition of N (η) and V (α, e), there exists δ such that O(0 N , δ) ∩ N (η) = ∅. Besides, e x ⊥Dξ and e v ⊥Dξ , so one gets that V (1, e) ≤ -a 2 b a(L)e T x e x -(b a(L) -a b )e T v e v , implying that there exists ε 0 such that V (1, e) ≤ -ε 0 , ∀e ∈ N (η).</p><p>Since V (α, e) is continuous in both α and e, ∀e ∈ N (η),</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">∃(1 -ε e , 1] × O(e, δ e ), s.t. V ≤ -ε 0 2 . It is obvious that {O(e, δ e )|e ∈ N (η)} is an open covering of N (η). Since N (η)</formula><p>is compact, there exist e 1 , ..., e n such that the sets O(e i , δ e i ), i = 1, ..., n, for some finite number n, cover N (η). Consider the corresponding sets {(1 -</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">ε e i , 1]|i = 1, ..., n}. One can conclude that ∀α ∈ ∩ i=1,...,n (1 -ε e i , 1], V (α, e) ≤ -ε 0 2 , ∀e ∈ N (η). Thus, there exists α 0 ∈ (0, 1) such that V (α 0 , e) &lt; 0, ∀e ∈ Nα 0 .</formula><p>Secondly, it is easy to verify the following: 1. V (α 0 , e x , e v ) is homogeneous over (e x , e v ), with dilation (2, ..., 2, 1 + α 0 , ..., 1 + α 0 ) of degree 4;</p><p>2. V (α 0 , e x , e v ) is homogeneous over (e x , e v ), with dilation (2, ..., 2, 1 + α 0 , ..., 1 + α 0 ) of degree 3 + α;</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">3. ∪ λ≥0 {(λ 2 e x , λ 1+α 0 e v )|V (α 0 , e x , e v ) = 1, e T x Dξ = 0, e T v Dξ = 0} = {(e x , e v ) ∈ R N × R N |e T x Dξ = 0, e T v Dξ = 0}.</formula><p>In fact, it is easy to see that V (α 0 , e x , e v ) and V (α 0 , e x , e v ) satisfy condition (3) both with dilation (2, ..., 2, 1 +α 0 , ..., 1 + α 0 ), and the degrees are 4 and 3 + α 0 , respectively. As for the last item, if (e x , e v ) = 0, letting λ = 0, one has (λ 2 e x , λ 1+α 0 e v ) = 0. Besides, e x ⊥Dξ ⇔ λ 2 e x ⊥Dξ , and e v ⊥Dξ ⇔ λ 1+α 0 e v ⊥Dξ for λ = 0. If e x , e v = 0 and e T</p><p>x Dξ = 0, e T v Dξ = 0, then V (α 0 , e x , e v ) &gt; 0. Considering item 1 and taking λ = - 1  4 , one has λ 4 V (α 0 , e x , e v ) = V (α 0 , λ 2 e x , λ 1+α 0 e v ) = 1. So, item 3 is also true.</p><p>With items 2 and 3, and V (α 0 , e) &lt; 0, ∀e ∈ Nα 0 , one has that -V (α 0 , e) is positive definite. According to Lemma 8, one has</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">-C 1 V 3+α 0 4 ≥ V ≥ -C 2 V 3+α 0 4 ,<label>(40)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">C 1 = -max z∈ Nα 0 V (α 0 , z) and C 2 = -min z∈ Nα 0 V (α 0 , z).</formula><p>Then, according to Lemma 9, V reaches 0 in finite time, which implies that e x and e v reach 0 in finite time. Similarly to the discussion in the proof of Theorem 1, one can obtain that x, v ∈ span{D1 N }, which meets the condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>. So, the finite-time second-order bipartite consensus is achieved, and the settling time is estimated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_100">T 1 ≤ V α 0 , Lx(0), Lv(0) 1-α 0 4 /(C 1 1-α 0 4</formula><p>). If the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced, define the following Lyapunov function: show that there exists α 0 ∈ (0, 1) such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">V (α, e) = 1 2 w T w,<label>(41) where</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_102">V ≤ -C 1 V 3+α 0 4 ,<label>(42)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">C 1 = -max z∈ N α 0 V (α 0 , z) and N α 0 = {e| V (α 0 , e) = 1}.</formula><p>So, V reaches 0 in finite time, implying that e x = Lx and e v = Lv both reach 0 in finite time. Since L is invertible according to Remark 2, x and v reach 0 in finite time, which means that the finite-time second-order consensus is achieved. Furthermore, the settling time is estimated as T1 ≤ V α 0 , Lx(0), Lv(0)</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">1-α 0 4 /(C 1 1-α 0 4</formula><p>). Remark 7: In Theorem 3, the existence of α 0 (or α 0 ) is essential, since it ensures the derivatives of the constructed homogeneous Lyapunov function V (or V ) be negative definite. This idea is inspired by the work <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>, while it is more complicated here in the setting of multi-agent systems. Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> firstly proposed the concept called generalized algebraic connectivity of strongly connected networks with positive weights, which provides a general way to deal with directed networks. The Lyapunov function constructed here partly generates from this concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Finite-Time Second-Order Bipartite Consensus With Bounded Disturbances</head><p>With the discussion for the second-order nominal system <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(34)</ref> in the above subsection, it is ready to solve the finite-time second-order bipartite consensus problem for the multi-agent system <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>, which is influenced by disturbances.</p><p>Assumption 2: <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref> The disturbances di (x i , , v i , t) in system (32) satisfy the following condition:</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">|| di (x i , v i , t)|| ∞ ≤ Di ,<label>(43)</label></formula><p>where Di &gt; 0 is a constant and || • || ∞ is the infinite form of a vector, i = 1, 2, ..., N.</p><p>Design the following sliding-mode variables:</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">si = v i + ri , ṙi = a N j =1 |G i j | x i -sign(G i j )x j [α] +b N j =1 |G i j | v i -sign(G i j )v j [β] ,<label>(44)</label></formula><p>where a, b, α, and β are defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> and, accordingly, the sliding-mode surface is</p><formula xml:id="formula_107">{(x 1 , ..., x N , v 1 , ..., v N )| si = 0, i = 1, 2, ..., N}. (<label>45</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_108">)</formula><p>Theorem 4: Consider the multi-agent system (7) with Assumption 2 satisfied. Choose a, b &gt; 0, α ∈ (0, 1], and β = 2α 1+α for the sliding-mode variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref>. Then, the slidingmode surface ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_106">44</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_107">45</ref>) can be reached in finite time with the following sliding-mode controllers:</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">u i = ūi + u d i , u d i = -li sign(s i ), (<label>46</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_110">)</formula><p>where ūi is defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>, and li &gt; Di . Furthermore, when the communication topology is strongly connected and structurally balanced, the finite-time bipartite consensus of the multi-agent system (32) can be achieved if a(L) • b 2 &gt; a and α is chosen as in Theorem 3. Otherwise, when the communication topology is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced, the finite-time stabilization problem of the multiagent system (32) can be solved if λ min ( L ) • b 2 &gt; a, and α is chosen as in Theorem 3, where L = 1 2 (P L + L T P) and P is defined in Lemma 11.</p><p>Proof: Taking the derivative of si along (32) with controllers <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(46)</ref> and variables <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref>, one gets</p><formula xml:id="formula_111">ṡi = di -li sign(s i ), i = 1, 2, ..., N. (<label>47</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_112">)</formula><p>Choose the Lyapunov function V = 1 2 s T s with s = [s 1 , ..., sN ] T , and then take the derivative of V . One obtains</p><formula xml:id="formula_113">V = N i=1 si ṡi = N i=1 (s i di -li |s i |) ≤ N i=1 -( li -Di )|s i | ≤ - l√ V , (<label>48</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_114">)</formula><p>where l = √ 2 min i=1,...,N { li -Di }. It follows that V reaches 0 in finite time Td ≤ 2 V (s(0))/ l, which results in that all the states x i and v i reach the sliding-mode surface <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref> in finite time Td . Thus, si = ṡi = 0, i = 1, 2, ..., N, for t ≥ Td . Furthermore, ṡi = 0 means that the nominal system (34) holds thereafter. According to Theorem 3, the finite-time secondorder bipartite consensus can be reached if the communication Remark 8: Notice that a positive graph is a special situation of a signed graph, so all the above conclusions can be drawn when the communication topology is a positive digraph.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. SIMULATION EXAMPLES</head><p>In this section, two examples are provided to verify the theoretical analysis. Consider a multi-agent system consisting of 5 agents, with the corresponding communication topologies illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>, where Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_115">G b = ⎛ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎝ 0 0 0 0 1.5 1 0 0 0 0 0 -1 0 0 0 0 0 3 0 0 0 -2 0 -1.2 0 ⎞ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ ⎠</formula><p>, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Example 1</head><p>Consider the following first-order multi-agent system with bounded disturbances:</p><formula xml:id="formula_116">ẋi = u i + sin(t + i ), i = 1, 2, ..., 5,<label>(49)</label></formula><p>where the bound of the disturbances is D i = 1. Firstly, consider the communication topology shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1(a)</ref>. The control protocol takes the form ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_67">27</ref>) with ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">10</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>, and the parameters are chosen as a = 1, b = 0, α = 0.8, and l i = 1.5. Furthermore, randomly set the initial states as [x 1 (0), ..., x 5 (0)] = [1.1, -9.2, 4.5, -6, 10]. The trajectories of the 5 agents are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>. One can observe that the bipartite consensus is achieved after about 40s. Furthermore, agents 1, 2 and 5 meet the same values, and agents 3 and 4 reach the opposite values, which is coincident with the fact that the agents in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref>(a) can be divided into two clusters,   V 1 = {1, 2, 5} and V 2 = {3, 4}, where the edges in each cluster are positive weighted, while the edges between the two clusters take negative weights. Accordingly, consider the fixed-time control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref> with ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">10</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_63">25</ref> Then, consider the communication topology shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1(b</ref>). The control protocol still takes the form <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> with <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>, and the parameters are chosen as a = 1, b = 0, α = 0.8, and l = 1.5. Set randomly the initial states as [x 1 (0), ..., x 5 (0)] = [-8, 3, 7, -4, -6]. The trajectories of the 5 agents are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4</ref>, which become stable after about 30s. Accordingly, consider the fixed-time control protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref> with ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">10</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_63">25</ref>), and the parameters are taken as a   α i = 0.9, and β i = 1.1. Take the same initial conditions as [x 1 (0), ..., x 5 (0)] = [-8, 3, 7, -4, -6]. The trajectories of the 5 agents are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">5</ref>. It shows that all the agents reach stable after about 13s, which is faster than the finite-time control protocol above.</p><formula xml:id="formula_117">= 1, b = 0.1, α = 0.8, β = 1.1, l i = 1.1, a i = b i = 0.1,</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Example 2</head><p>Consider the following second-order multi-agent system with bounded disturbances:</p><formula xml:id="formula_118">ẋi = v i , vi = u i + cos(t -i ), i = 1, 2, ..., 5,<label>(50)</label></formula><p>where the bound of the disturbance is Di = 1. First, consider the communication topology depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1(a)</ref>. The control protocol takes the form ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_109">46</ref>) with ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_82">35</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_106">44</ref> One can observe that all the agents achieve the second-order consensus after about 35s.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, the finite-time bipartite consensus problem for signed digraphs has been studied. Some useful properties of signed digraphs have been revealed. One kind of nonlinear control protocol has been designed for first-order multiagent systems, which solves the finite-time bipartite consensus problem. Furthermore, with some properly chosen parameters, the proposed control protocol can ensure the first-order multi-agent system to achieve fixed-time bipartite consensus. Another homogeneity-based nonlinear control protocol has been designed for second-order multi-agent systems, to reach finite-time bipartite consensus for which the convergence time has been estimated.</p><p>Although the estimation of the settling time for secondorder multi-agent systems is given in an accurate mathematical formulation, it is not easy to compute. Thus, in the future, some efficient algorithms will be developed. Furthermore, multi-agent systems with nonlinear dynamics as well as some practical applications of bipartite consensus will be investigated. z T Lz = 0. Then, ∃{z l } ⊆ (a, α, β), s.t. lim l→∞ (z l ) T Lz l = 0. In addition, z l can be expressed as z l = a(y l ) [α] + γ l (y l ) [β] . Notice that ||z l || = 1, and 0 is the algebraically simple eigenvalue of L with D1 N being the corresponding eigenvector, there exists a subset -ε &gt; 0. So the j th element of z l i takes the same sign as d j with l i being large enough. On the other hand, z l i = a(y l i ) [α] + γ l i (y l i ) [β] , one gets that y l i j take the same sign of d j , which makes Dy l i a positive vector. This is a contradiction with the fact that y T Dξ = 0. So, inf (</p><formula xml:id="formula_119">{z l i } ⊆ {z l } such that z l i → 1 √ N D1 N or -1 √ N D1 N .</formula><p>Before proving Lemma 11, a useful property is presented. Proposition 1: Suppose a signed digraph G is structurally unbalanced, strongly connected, and weight-balanced. Then, the Laplacian matrix L satisfies L + L T &gt; 0.</p><p>Proof for Proposition 1: Denote the corresponding adjacency matrix and Laplacian matrix with G = G i j N×N and L, respectively. Let C r be the diagonal matrix with the i -th diagonal element C r i being</p><formula xml:id="formula_121">N j =1 G i j . Let L = 1 2 (L + L T ) = C r -1 2 (G + G T ) = C r -G u .</formula><p>It is easy to see that L = C r -G. One can also rewrite L = Cr + L u , where L u corresponds to the Laplacian matrix of the undirected graph G(G u ) generated by G u . Besides, Cr is the redundant diagonal matrix with its i -th diagonal element being C r i -1 2 j =1 |G i j + G j i | ≥ 0. If G i j G j i ≥ 0, i, j = 1, ..., N (called digon sign-symmetric), the result becomes Proposition 3 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. In the following, just consider that digon sign-symmetry is not satisfied. Then, there exist i 1 = i 2 such that G i 1 i 2 G i 2 i 1 &lt; 0. It is easy to see that C r i k -1 </p><formula xml:id="formula_122">)<label>52</label></formula><p>Consider L = p L. It is easy to check that L is the Laplacian matrix corresponding to a signed digraph Ḡ, which shares the same edge directions and signs of weights with the signed digraph G, except for the weight values. Furthermore, the signed digraph Ḡ is weight-balanced because of <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52)</ref>. Thus, according to Proposition 1, one has that p L + L T p &gt; 0.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>equality is due to the properties that DD = I N and DD = . Substituting x = Dy into the above equation, it follows that</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Strongly connected communication topologies with 5 agents.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) is strongly connected and structurally balanced, while Fig. 1(b) is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced. The weights are indicated on the edges. The adjacency matrices for Figs. 1(a) and 1(b) are G a =</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Trajectories of 5 agents with control protocol (27), on the structurally balanced digraph shown in Fig. 1(a).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Trajectories of 5 agents with fixed-time control protocol (30), on the structurally balanced digraph shown in Fig. 1(a).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Trajectories of 5 agents with control protocol (27), on the structurally unbalanced digraph shown in Fig. 1(b).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>), and the parameters are taken asa = 1, b = 0.1, α = 0.8, β = 1.1, l i = 1.1, a i = b i = 0.1, α i = 0.9,and βi = 1.1. Take the same initial conditions as [x 1 (0), ..., x 5 (0)] = [1.1, -9.2, 4.5, -6, 10].The trajectories of the 5 agents are shown in Fig.3. It is easy to observe that agents 1, 2 and 5 meet the same values, and agents 3 and 4 reach the opposite values. Besides, the consensus reaching time is about 14s, which is much faster than the finite-time control protocol above.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Trajectories of 5 agents with fixed-time control protocol (30), on the structurally unbalanced digraph shown in Fig. 1(b).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Trajectories of 5 agents with control protocol (46), on the structurally balanced digraph shown in Fig. 1(a).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Trajectories of 5 agents with control protocol (46), on the structurally unbalanced digraph shown in Fig. 1(a).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>), and the parameters are chosen as a = 1, b = 5, α = 0.97, β = 2α/(1 + α) and li = 1.5. Set randomly the initial states as [x 1 (0), ..., x 5 (0)] =[15, -12, -5, 3, -7]   and [v 1 (0), ..., v 5 (0)] =[7, 3, -5, -4, 10]. The trajectories of the states and velocities of 5 agents are shown in Fig.6. One can observe that agents 1, 2, 5 reach the same displacement and velocity, while the displacement and velocity of agents 3 and 4 meet the opposite values after about 20s.Then, consider the communication topology depicted in Fig.1(b). The control protocol takes the form<ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>, and the parameters are chosen as a = 0.9, b = 6, α = 0.98, and β = 2α/(1 + α). Set randomly the initial states as [x 1 (0), ..., x 5 (0)] = [20, -10, -2, -7, 8] and [v 1 (0), ..., v 5 (0)] = [-1, 4, 6, 7, -2]. The trajectories of the states and velocities of 5 agents are shown in Fig.7.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>APPENDIXA.</head><label></label><figDesc>Proof of Lemma 10 Noticing the facts of D L D1 N = 0, D L D being symmetric, all the diagonal elements of D L D being positive, and all the off-diagonal elements of D L D being non-positive, one can take D L D as the Laplacian matrix corresponding to a connected undirected positive graph. Then, it follows from Lemma 1 that D L D has a simple zero eigenvalue, and the others are positive. Since L ∼ D L D, it immediately follows that L ≥ 0, which leads to inf z∈(a,α,β) z T Lz ≥ 0. The rest of the proof is conducted by contradiction. Suppose that inf z∈(a,α,β)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Without loss of generality, suppose that z l → 1 √ N D1 N . Denote D = diag{d 1 , ..., d N }, d i = ±1, i = 1, 2, ..., N. Then,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>11 Definition 7 :</head><label>117</label><figDesc>z∈(a,α,β) z T Lz = k 1 &gt; 0.B. Proof of LemmaA signed digraph G is said to be weight balanced, if the adjacency matrix G satisfies N k=1 |G ik | = N k=1 |G ki |, ∀i = 1, 2, ..., N.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>2 Nj 1 N</head><label>21</label><figDesc>=1 |G i k j + G j i k | &gt; 0, k = 1, 2.Since G is weight balanced, and not digon signsymmetric, Cr has at least one positive element. If G(G u ) is connected and structurally unbalanced, then L u &gt; 0, which follows that L = L u + Cr &gt; 0. If G(G u ) is connected and structurally balanced, then there exists D ∈ D such that DL u D corresponds to a positive graph. It also follows that L = D(D Cr D + DL u D)D &gt; 0. Now consider the situation that G(G u ) is not connected. This could only happen when the node pair set X = (i, j ): |G i j | + |G j i | &gt; 0, G i j + G j i = 0 is nonempty. Then G(G u ) can be divided into m connected components: G(G u 1 ), ..., G(G u m ). Denote the corresponding Laplacian matrices as L u i , i = 1, ..., m. Without loss of generality, one has L u = diag(L u 1 , ..., L u m ).Cr can be correspondingly rewritten as Cr = diag( Cr 1 , ..., Cr m ). It is easy to see that each G(G u i ) has at least one node that belongs to the endpoint of the node pair in set X. Thus each Cr i has at least one positive diagonal element. For each connected component, applying the above argument, one hasL u i + Cr i &gt; 0, i = 1, ..., m. Then L = diag(L u 1 + Cr 1 , ..., L u m + Cr m ) &gt; 0. This completes the proof.Suppose the digraph G is strongly connected but structurally unbalanced. Its adjacency matrix and Laplacian matrix are denoted by G and L, respectively. Then, define the corresponding positive digraph G p by G p i j = |G i j |, i, j = 1, 2, ..., N, which maintains the directions, but has nonnegative weights. Here, G p = (G p i j ) N×N is the adjacency matrix of G p . The Laplacian matrix L p of G p is defined correspondingly. Then, G p is a strongly connected digraph. According to Lemma 3 in<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, there exists a positive vector ξ p = (ξ p 1 , ξ p 2 , ..., ξ p N ) T such that L T p ξ p = 0. Let p = diag= 0 N = p L p 1 N .(</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under Grants 61673107, 61722303, and 61673104, in part by the National Ten Thousand Talent Program for Young Top-Notch Talents under Grant W2070082, in part by the General Joint Fund of the Equipment Advance Research Program of Ministry of Education under Grant 6141A020223, in part by the Jiangsu Provincial Key Laboratory of Networked Collective Intelligence under Grant BM2017002, in part by the Scientific Research Foundation of the Graduate School of Southeast University, in part by the Hong Kong Research Grants Council through the GRF under Grant CityU 11200317, in part by the Natural Science Foundation of Jiangsu Province of China under Grant BK20170079, and in part by the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities of China under Grant 2242018k1G004. This paper was recommended by Associate Editor G</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Swarming behaviors in multi-agent systems with nonlinear dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lü</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-T</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chaos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flocking for multi-agent dynamic systems: Algorithms and theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Olfati-Saber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-03">Mar. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some necessary and sufficient conditions for second-order consensus in multi-agent dynamical systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1089" to="1095" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-06">Jun. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus and collision avoidance control algorithms for multiple AUVs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3359" to="3367" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-11">Nov. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic synchronization of a leader-follower network of uncertain euler-Lagrange systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Klotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Kan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pasiliao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Control Netw. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-06">Jun. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus algorithm for multi-agent systems with double-integrator dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1706" to="1712" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-08">Aug. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus seeking in multiagent systems under dynamically changing interaction topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Beard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="655" to="661" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-05">May 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed finite-time average consensus in digraphs in the presence of time delays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Charalambous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hadjicostis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Control Netw. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="370" to="381" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">Dec. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asynchronous max-consensus protocol with time delays: Convergence results and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Giannini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Petitti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Paola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rizzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Circuits Syst. I, Reg. Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="264" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-02">Feb. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reverse group consensus of multi-agent systems in the cooperation-competition network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Xuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Circuits Syst. I, Reg. Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2036" to="2047" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-11">Nov. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leaderfollowing coordination of nonlinear agents under time-varying communication topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Priscoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Isidori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Marconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pietrabissa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Control Netw. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="393" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">Dec. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information flow and cooperative control of vehicle formations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fax</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1465" to="1476" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-09">Sep. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opinion dynamics in social networks with hostile camps: Consensus vs. Polarization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Proskurnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Matveev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1524" to="1536" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-06">Jun. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural balance and opinion separation in trust-mistrust social networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Control Netw. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-03">Mar. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Easley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kleinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Networks, Crowds, and Markets: Reasoning About a Highly Connected World</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, U.K.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social Network Analysis: Methods Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wasserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Faust</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge U.K.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rigid patterns of synchrony for equilibria and periodic cycles in network dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golubitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chaos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94803" to="94804" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Symmetry Perspective: From Equilibrium to Chaos Phase Space Physical Space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golubitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Birkhäuser Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Basel, Switzerland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic distributed control for networks with cooperativeantagonistic interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TAC.2017.2763536</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control, to be published</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploiting nodes symmetries to control synchronization and consensus patterns in multiagent systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Di Bernardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Control Syst. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-10">Oct. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symmetries, stability, and control in nonlinear systems and networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Slotine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E, Stat. Phys. Plasmas Fluids Relat. Interdiscip. Top</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41929" to="41930" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Signed graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zaslavsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Discrete Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="1982-01">Jan. 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus problems on networks with antagonistic interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Altafini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="935" to="946" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-04">Apr. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the consensus and bipartite consensus in high-order multi-agent dynamical systems with antagonistic interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Valcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Misra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="94" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-04">Apr. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interval bipartite consensus of networked agents associated with signed digraphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3755" to="3770" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-12">Dec. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bipartite containment tracking of signed networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="282" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-05">May 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus problems for networks of dynamic agents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="950" to="955" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-04">Apr. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus for multiagent systems with cooperative and antagonistic interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Neural Netw. Learn. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="762" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-04">Apr. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear finite-time bipartite consensus protocol for multi-agent systems associated with signed graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2074" to="2085" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-10">Oct. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finitetime consensus for switching network topologies with disturbances</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Franceschelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Giua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pisano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Usai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nonlinear Anal. Hybrid Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus with disturbance rejection by discontinuous local interactions in directed graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Franceschelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pisano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Giua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Usai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1133" to="1138" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-04">Apr. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust consensus algorithms for multiscale coordination control of multivehicle systems with disturbances</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1107" to="1119" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-02">Feb. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus of second-order leaderfollowing multi-agent systems without velocity measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Lett. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">377</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus of doubleintegrator multi-agent systems with time-varying directed topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Adv. Comput. Intell. Intell. Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="254" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus for leaderfollowing second-order multi-agent networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Circuits Syst. I, Reg. Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2646" to="2654" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-11">Nov. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time synchronization of a class of second-order nonlinear multi-agent systems using output feedback control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Circuits Syst. I, Reg. Papers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1778" to="1788" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-06">Jun. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus control for second-order multi-agent systems without velocity measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>You</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Syst. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="346" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Second-order consensus for nonlinear leader-following multi-agent systems via dynamic output feedback control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Robust Nonlinear Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="344" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed finite-time cooperative control of multiple high-order nonholonomic mobile robots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Neural Netw. Learn. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2998" to="3006" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-12">Dec. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus of multiagent systems with a switching protocol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Neural Netw. Learn. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="853" to="862" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-04">Apr. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus for multi-agent networks with second-order agent dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 17th World Congr</title>
		<meeting>17th World Congr</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15185" to="15190" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Second-order consensus for multi-agent systems with directed topologies and nonlinear dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kurths</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst. Man, Cybern. B, Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="881" to="891" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-06">Jun. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Second-order consensus in multiagent systems via distributed sliding mode control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1872" to="1881" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-08">Aug. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Distributed Cooperative Control of Multi-Agent Systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Singapore</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time stability of continuous autonomous systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bhat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Control Optim</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="751" to="766" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-01">Jan. 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear fixed-time control protocol for uniform allocation of agents on a segment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Parsegov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Polyakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Shcherbakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Doklady Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-12">Dec. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geometric homogeneity with applications to finite-time stability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bhat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Control, Signals, Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-06">Jun. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time stabilization and stabilizability of a class of controllable systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Syst. Control Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-01">Jan. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Equivalence constants for l p norms of matrices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Linear Multilinear Algebra</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time consensus for second-order multiagent systems with disturbances by integral sliding mode</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="165" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-04">Apr. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fixed-time consensus tracking of multi-agent systems under a directed communication topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 12th IEEE Int. Conf. Control Autom</title>
		<meeting>12th IEEE Int. Conf. Control Autom</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-06">Jun. 2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="191" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed robust fixed-time consensus for nonlinear and disturbed multiagent systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst., Man, Cybern. A, Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1464" to="1473" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-07">Jul. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time observers: Application to secure communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Perruquetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Floquet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Moulay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Autom. Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="356" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-02">Feb. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algebraic connectivity of graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fiedler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Czechoslovak Math. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="298" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
