<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Collaborative Multi-agent Reinforcement Learning Anti-jamming Algorithm in Wireless Networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fuqiang</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Luliang</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Collaborative Multi-agent Reinforcement Learning Anti-jamming Algorithm in Wireless Networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8FF56D2C5F4E4AE2A342C0F79AB1E84E</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/LWC.2019.2904486</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-27T04:54+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Anti-jamming</term>
					<term>multi-agent reinforcement learning</term>
					<term>Q-learning</term>
					<term>Markov game</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In this letter, we investigate the anti-jamming defense problem in multi-user scenarios, where the coordination among users is taken into consideration. The Markov game framework is employed to model and analyze the anti-jamming defense problem, and a collaborative multi-agent anti-jamming algorithm (CMAA) is proposed to obtain the optimal antijamming strategy. In sweep jamming scenarios, on the one hand, the proposed CMAA can tackle the external malicious jamming. On the other hand, it can effectively cope with the mutual interference among users. Moreover, we consider the impact of sensing errors due to miss detection and false alarm. Simulation results show that the proposed CMAA is superior to both sensing based method and independent Q-learning method, and has the highest normalized rate.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Jamming attack is a serious threat in wireless networks, and various anti-jamming methods have been developed in recent years <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Due to factors of the jammers' activities, the quality of channels varies between "good" and "poor" dynamically. The Markov decision process (MDP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> is a suitable paradigm to model and analyze the anti-jamming defense problem. Unfortunately, it is difficult to obtain the state transition probability function in an adversarial environment. In these scenarios, reinforcement learning (RL) techniques are available, such as the classic Q-learning method <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Based on the Q-learning method, the anti-jamming decisionmaking problem in single-user scenarios were investigated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Then, the authors in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> extended it to the multi-user scenarios, and they resorted to the Markov game framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, which is the extension of the Markov decision process and can characterize the relationship among multiple users. Moreover, the corresponding multi-user reinforcement learning anti-jamming algorithm was designed. However, each user employed a standard Q-learning method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, and the coordination among users was not considered. Based on our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, the cooperative anti-jamming problem was investigated in UAV communications networks in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, and the mobility of UAV was exploited. It is noted that miss detection and false alarm were not considered in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, and they are common in practical wireless networks. In order to achieve better anti-jamming performance, the coordination among users is necessary. Through collaborative learning, on the one hand, it can tackle the external malicious jamming, and on the other hand, it can effectively cope with the mutual interference caused by competition among users. In this letter, a collaborative anti-jamming framework is formulated, in which the "coordination" and "competition" are simultaneously considered. To model and analyze the anti-jamming defense problem, the Markov game framework is adopted, and a collaborative multi-agent reinforcement learning antijamming algorithm is proposed. The main contributions of this letter are given as follows:</p><p>• Based on the Markov game, the anti-jamming defense problem is investigated in multi-user scenarios, and the coordination among users is considered. • We develop a collaborative multi-agent reinforcement learning anti-jamming algorithm to obtain the optimal anti-jamming strategy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. SYSTEM MODEL AND PROBLEM FORMULATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. System Model</head><p>As illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, there are N users and one jammer in the considered model. The users have intelligent capabilities that include spectrum sensing, learning and decision-making, and thus, they are referred to as cognitive users in this letter. The cognitive user set is denoted as N = {1, • • • , N }, and the available channel set is defined as M = {1, • • • , M }. The number of available channels is M (N &lt; M ). The coordination among cognitive users can be achieved through information exchange. It is noted that the jamming pattern is the sweep jamming, and one channel is jammed at each time slot. The jamming channel set is represented as C = {1, • • • , C}. In this letter, we assume that the available channel set is the same as the jamming channel set. If two or more users select the same channel, it will lead to the mutual interference. In order to realize the reliable transmission, it is necessary to simultaneously consider the external malicious jamming and mutual interference due to competition among users. In this letter, the mutual interference refers to the co-channel interference among users, and the strategy is the selection of available channels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Problem formulation</head><p>The anti-jamming defense problem can be formulated as a Markov game <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, which is the extension of the Markov decision process in multi-user scenarios. Mathematically, it can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">G = {S, A 1 , • • • , A N , f, r 1 , • • • , r N },</formula><p>where S denotes the set of states, A n , n = 1, • • • , N is the set of the strategies, f represents the state transition model, and r n , n = 1, • • • , N is the reward. In this letter, we consider sensing errors due to miss detection and false alarm, and the miss detection probability and false alarm probability of channel m are denoted as P m,md and P m,f a , respectively. Referring to <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, the state can be defined as s = {a, fjx }, where fjx is the observed jamming channel, a = (a 1 , a 2 , • • • , a N ) represents a joint action profile, and the set of the joint action profiles is</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">A= ⊗ A n , n = 1, • • • , N ,</formula><p>where ⊗ represents the Cartesian product. Similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, the global reward can be defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">R = ∑ N n=1 r n (s, a),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where s ∈ S denotes a state. It is assumed that the jamming channel is denoted as f jx , the selected channel of cognitive user n is represented as f n,x , and the reward of cognitive user n at time slot t can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">r n (s, a, t) = { 1, if f n,x ̸ = f jx &amp;f n,x ̸ = f m,x (m ∈ N /n) , 0, otherwise.<label>(2)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. COLLABORATIVE MULTI-AGENT ANTI-JAMMING ALGORITHM</head><p>In this letter, we consider the two characteristics "coordination" and "competition" among users simultaneously. In wireless network, the coordination has various meanings, such as relay and information exchange. Here, the coordination is realized by information exchange through a common control channel <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Based on the coordination among users, the method of "decision-feedback-adjustment" is applied to obtain the optimal anti-jamming strategy.</p><p>To solve the formulated anti-jamming Markov game, a multi-agent Q-learning algorithm is proposed. Similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, cognitive user n updates its Q values according to the following rules:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Algorithm 1: Collaborative Multi-agent Anti-jamming Algorithm (CMAA) Initiate: S, Q n , n ∈ N . Loop: t = 0, • • • , T</formula><p>Each user observes its current state s(t) = {a(t), f jx (t)}, and selects a channel according to the following rules:</p><p>• User n randomly chooses a channel profile a ∈ A with probability ε;</p><p>• User n chooses a channel profile a * ∈ argmax</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">∑ N n=1 Q n (s ′ , a ′ ) with probability 1 -ε. Each user measures its payoff r n (s, a).</formula><p>The state is transferred into s(t+1) = {a(t+1), f jx (t+ 1)}, and Q values are updated according to the rules in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>. End loop</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">Q n (s, a) = (1 -λ)Q n (s, a) + λ [r n + γV n (s ′ )] , (3) V n (s ′ ) = Q n (s ′ , a * ) , (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">)</formula><p>where λ is the learning rate, and s ′ represents the next state s(t + 1) after executing action a at state s(t), a * denotes the best joint action, and it can be given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">a * ∈ arg max a ′ N ∑ n=1 Q n (s ′ , a ′ ),<label>(5)</label></formula><p>It is noted that the multi-agent Q-learning algorithm in (3) is decentralized, and each user updates its Q values separately. However, for the problem in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>, it is necessary to solve a global coordination game, which has common payoff <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Q (s, a) = N ∑ n=1 Q n (s, a).<label>(6)</label></formula><p>The exchanged information between users is only the Qvalue, and each user broadcasts its current Q value to other users at the end of each time slot. The exploration rate ε ∈ (0, 1) is introduced to avoid falling into a local optimum. Users randomly select a joint action a ∈ A with probability ε, and users select the joint action a * ∈ argmax ∑ N n=1 Q n (s ′ , a ′ ) with probability 1 -ε. Based on the above analysis, a collaborative multi-agent anti-jamming algorithm (CMAA) is proposed, and its implementation procedure is shown in Algorithm 1. The convergence condition of the proposed Algorithm 1 is either that the Q-table is no longer updated, or that its change is small. Motivated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, we analyze the computational complexity of Algorithm 1. In one time slot, according to equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>, each cognitive user selects the joint action, and its computational complexity can be expressed as O(F 1 ), in which F 1 denotes a constant. For each cognitive user, it updates its Q values according to equation (3), and its computational complexity can be given by O(F 2 ), in which F 2 represents another constant. In our system, it is assumed that there are N users, and the number of time slots is T num . Then, the computational complexity of Algorithm 1 can be given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">C = N ∑ n=1 T num [O(F 1 ) + O(F 2 )]. (<label>7</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">)</formula><p>Similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, the wideband spectrum sensing is adopted to sense the jammer's activities, and all Q values are updated simultaneously. A transmission slot structure diagram is presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. At the end of current slot, each user obtains a reward, and updates its strategy according to the received reward.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. NUMERICAL RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS</head><p>In this subsection, we present some simulation results. A system with two cognitive users and one jammer is considered, in which five channels are available. t Rx , t W BSS , t ACK , and t Learning denote the transmission time, wideband sensing time, ACK time, and learning time, respectively. In this letter, we have P 1,md = • • • = P M,md = P md and P 1,f a = • • • = P M,f a = P f a to analyze the impact of false alarm and miss detection. The jammer begins to jam the transmission at time slot t = 0.2ms. Referring to <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, the simulation parameters are given as: λ = 0.8, γ = 0.6, ε = 0.2, t Rx = 0.98ms, t W BSS +t ACK +t Learning = 0.2ms. Moreover, the dwelling time of the sweeping jammer on each channel is t dwell = 2.28ms, the number of time slots for simulations is K = 10000, and the simulation time is</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">T = K * (t Rx + t W BSS +t ACK +t Learning ).</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> respectively show the time-frequency information at the initial and convergent state. As indicated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, at the initial stage, the cognitive users employ random actions, and the signals of cognitive users and jammer are overlapped. Moreover, the signals among users are also overlapped. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> shows the time-frequency information of the proposed CMAA at convergent stage. As can be seen from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>, at convergent stage, the signals of cognitive users can avoid the signal of the jammer. Meanwhile, the signals among cognitive users can effectively cope with the mutual interference, and the actions of cognitive users are coordinated.</p><p>To validate the proposed CMAA, we compare it with the following two methods:  • Sensing based method: In this method, the users cannot learn the actions of the jammer, and channels are selected based on the sensing results. Moreover, we resort to a coordination approach, as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, in which user n (n &gt; 1) selects its channel a * n until the previous users 1, • • • , n-1 broadcast their chosen channels in the ordering. Then, user n broadcasts its channel.</p><p>• Independent Q-earning <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>: Each user adopts a standard Q-learning method. The coordination among users is not considered, and other users are treated as part of its environment.</p><p>In this section, the normalized rate is introduced to validate the performance of the proposed CMAA, and it can be defined as ρ = P K succ /P N 0 , where P K succ represents the number of packets for successful transmission, and P N 0 denotes the length of packet statistics, which means that the normalized ρ is calculated after P N 0 packets are transmitted. In this simulation, we have P N 0 = 20. Then, the following results are obtained by making 200 independent runs and then taking the mean. Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> shows the performance of the normalized rate, it can be seen that the proposed CMAA can converge in about 80 update numbers. Also, the proposed CMAA is superior to both  sensing based method and independent Q-learning method. Moreover, the proposed CMAA has the highest normalized rate ρ. The reason is that the sensing based method cannot learn the actions of the jammer, and channels are chosen based on the sensing results. Meanwhile, the independent Q-learning method does not consider the coordination among users, and each user chooses its channel independently. For the proposed CMAA, it can not only learn the actions of the jammer, but also consider the coordination among users.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref> show the impact of false alarm probability and miss detection probability. Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows that the normalized rate decreases with growing miss detection probability. The reason is that higher miss detection probability leads to more invalid transmission. In addition, miss detection makes it more difficult for cognitive users to learn jamming rules. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref>, as the false alarm probability increases, the normalized rate decreases. The reason is that false alarm causes the waste of channels. Moreover, false alarm also makes it more difficult for cognitive users to learn jamming rules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this letter, we consider the "coordination" and "competition" simultaneously, and the Markov game framework is employed to model and analyze the anti-jamming defense problem. Then, a collaborative multi-agent anti-jamming algorithm (CMAA) is proposed to obtain the optimal anti-jamming strategy. Through collaborative learning, it can cope with the external malicious jamming and the mutual interference caused by competition among users simultaneously. In addition, we consider the impact of miss detection and false alarm. Finally, simulation results are presented. Compared with the sensing based method and independent Q-learning method, the proposed CMAA has the highest normalized rate. Note that we consider a system with two users and one jammer in our simulation. For a system with more users, it is also applicable. In future work, the deep reinforcement learning approach may be a good candidate to obtain faster convergence speed in multi-user scenarios.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FFig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. System model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Illustration of the transmission slot structure.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Time-frequency information at initial state.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,322.24,256.29,230.68,50.03" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Time-frequency information at convergent state.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,322.24,356.35,230.68,50.03" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. The impact of false alarm probability.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Jamming and anti-jamming techniques in wireless networks: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Ad Hoc and Ubiquitous Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stackelberg game approaches for anti-jamming defence in wireless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Anpalagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-12">Dec. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coping with a smart jammer in wireless networks: A stackelberg game approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Xue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Richa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4038" to="4047" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-08">Aug. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anti-jamming transmission stackelberg game with observation errors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="952" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-06">Jun. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A gametheoretical learning approach for anti-jamming dynamic spectrum access in dense wireless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Anpalagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Tech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1646" to="1656" />
			<date type="published" when="2019-02">Feb. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Markov decision processes with their applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Springer US</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Q-learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J C H</forename><surname>Watkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="292" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Jamming mitigation in cognitive radio networks using a modified Q-learning algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Slimeni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Scheers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chtourou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. International Conference on Military Comunications and Information Systems (ICMCIS)</title>
		<meeting>International Conference on Military Comunications and Information Systems (ICMCIS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cooperative Q-learning based channel selection for cognitive radio networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Slimeni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chtourou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Scheers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11276-018-1737-9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Wireless Netw</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>to be published</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reinforcement learning based antijamming with wideband autonomous cognitive radios</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Machuzak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jayaweera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE International Conference on Communications in China (ICCC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE International Conference on Communications in China (ICCC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-agent reinforcement learning based cognitive anti-jamming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aref</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jayaweera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Machuzak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel cognitive anti-jamming stochastic game</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aref</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jayaweera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Cognitive Communications for Aerospace Applications Workshop (CCAA)</title>
		<meeting>Cognitive Communications for Aerospace Applications Workshop (CCAA)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A cognitive anti-jamming and interference-avoidance stochastic game</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aref</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jayaweera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Informatics and Cognitive Computing (IC-CI*CC)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Informatics and Cognitive Computing (IC-CI*CC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="520" to="527" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive survey of multiagent reinforcement learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Busoniu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Babuska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Schutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Systems, Man, and Cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-03">Mar. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A collaborative multi-agent reinforcement learning antijamming algorithm in wireless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1809.04374</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interference-aware cooperative antijamming distributed channel selection in UAV communication networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-10">Oct. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opportunistic spectrum access in cognitive radio networks: Global optimization using local interaction games</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Topics Signal Pocess</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="194" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-04">Apr. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A concise introduction to multiagent systems and distributed artificial intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vlassis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Morgan and Claypool Publishers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opportunistic spectrum access with spatial reuse: Graphical game and uncoupled learning solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wirel. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4814" to="4826" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-10">Oct. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
