<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time Convergence Adaptive Fuzzy Control for Dual-Arm Robot with Unknown Kinematics and Dynamics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chenguang</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
							<email>cyang@ieee.org</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
							<email>long.cheng@ia.ac.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Automation Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with Key Laboratory of Autonomous Systems and Networked Control</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South China University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510640</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Kunming University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>650500</postCode>
									<settlement>Kunming</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology of China</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>230026</postCode>
									<settlement>Hefei</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Key Laboratory of Complex Systems and Intelligence Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100190</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">School of Artificial Intelligence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100049</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">School of Automation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Guangdong University of Technology on leave from Concordia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>510006, H3G 1M8</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou, Montreal</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country>China, Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time Convergence Adaptive Fuzzy Control for Dual-Arm Robot with Unknown Kinematics and Dynamics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">95C172ABCB5B75C57C66015FE19F7989</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TFUZZ.2018.2864940</idno>
					<note type="submission">This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TFUZZ.2018.2864940, IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T15:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Fuzzy logic system (FLS)</term>
					<term>dual-arm robots</term>
					<term>Uncertain kinematics</term>
					<term>Finite-Time (FT) convergence</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Due to strongly coupled nonlinearities of or the grasped dual-arm robot and the internal forces generated by grasped objects, the dual-arm robot control with uncertain kinematics and dynamics becomes a challenging problem. In this paper, an adaptive fuzzy control scheme is developed for a dual arm robot, where an approximate Jacobian matrix (AJM) was applied to address the uncertain kinematic control, while decentralized fuzzy logic controller (FLC) was constructed to compensate for uncertain dynamics of the robotic arms and the manipulated object. Also, a novel finite-time convergence parameter adaptation (FCPA) technique was developed for the estimation of kinematic parameters and fuzzy logic weights, such that the estimation was guaranteed to converge to small neighborhoods around their ideal values in a finite time. Moreover, a partial persistent excitation (PPE) property of Gaussian membership based fuzzy basis function (GFBF) was established to relax the conventional persistent excitation (PE) condition. This enables the designer to re-use these learned weight values next time without relearning. Extensive simulation studies have been carried out based on a dual-arm robot to illustrate the effectiveness of the proposed approach.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>In recent decades, there has been a pronounced tendency to focus the studies of coordinated dual-arm robots in robotics and automation communities <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. With a bimanual cooperation, the dual-arm robots can accomplish complex tasks, such as cooperative load transporting and coordinate manipulation. But difficulties of the controller designs are also increased significantly since an additional arm not only leads to complicated structure and mechanism, but also adds strong coupled nonlinearities as well as the internal forces generated by the grasped object. To address these problems, coordinate control of dual arm robots has been widely investigated <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Early work of the dual-arm coordinate position tracking control was presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. A decentralized adaptive control algorithm was proposed for multiple redundant cooperative manipulators to address the position tracking and internal forces regulation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, the coordination problem of redundant robot systems was addressed by using the dual neural network with a multicriteria to minimize the energy cost. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, an adaptive neural control for the humanoid robot was presented to deal with unknown output nonlinearities by employing a smooth adaptive inverse technique.</p><p>It is worth mentioning that, many existing dual-arm robot coordinated control schemes were developed under the assumption that the robot kinematics are fully known. However, in realistic operational scenarios, kinematic uncertainties are widely existed. For example, when a dual arm robot equips with replaceable tools or grasps an unknown object, the system parameters may be changed and lead to unknown kinematic parameters. Recently, the robot tracking control with uncertain kinematics for single-arm robots has been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. An adaptive set-point control scheme of robots with uncertain kinematics and gravitational force was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, where the exact knowledge of kinematics and Jacobian matrix was not required. This scheme has been extended to the robot tracking control <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, without using knowledge of robotic kinematics, dynamics and actuator model. A neural network controller combining with the (approximate Jacobian matrix) AJM scheme was also presented to deal with the robot tracking in the absence of kinematics and dynamics <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. The uncertain kinematics control of a single arm robot was well addressed in the above-mentioned works, however, few literature has investigated the control of the dual-arm robot where accurate kinematic parameters are unavailable. Without precise kinematic information, the task space position can not be accurately converted to joint inputs, and therefore the control performance of the dual-arm robot may be greatly limited.</p><p>On the other hand, dynamic uncertainties of the dual-arm robot widely exists as well, let alone various unknown factors of the operating environment and the objects under manipulation. These uncertainties may cause degeneration of the control performance or even incur instable system states. To deal with this problem, especially the unstructured model uncertainties, model free control design approaches have been extensively studied <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. It is worth mentioning that, among these control approaches, fuzzy logic systems was characterized as a powerful approximator by using linguistic knowledge representations and fuzzy rules, and has been wildly used to deal with uncertainties <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. To address the strictfeedback control of single-input-single-output (SISO) systems, a FLS was constructed for the compensation of uncertain nonlinearities in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. To compensate for the unknown system dynamics of a class of nonlinear systems, a backstepping based adaptive controller was developed by utilizing the universal approximation ability of FLS <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, to enhance the control performance of a humanoid robot in the presence of unknown actuator backlash and uncertain dynamics, a decentralized controller was designed by using the adaptive FLS and a smooth backlash inverse. In the above mentioned works, however, only ultimate boundedness of the weights estimation error can be guaranteed and the convergence of the weights was not analysed. The FLS is required to online adjust the learned weights to transform the expert linguistic knowledge into adaptive learning ability of the control system. Without convergence, the weight values need to re-learn every time when the FLS runs again even if repeating the same task. It would be more desirable to guarantee fast and accurate convergence of estimated parameters to improve the control performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>.</p><p>In this paper, we develop a dual arm robot control scheme by using the AJM technique and the adaptive FLS, such that the robot can be well controlled in the absence of robot dynamics and kinematics. The proposed control scheme can guarantee the convergence of the tracking errors in a finitetime, in addition to the parameter estimation. It has been reported that the estimation performance can be improved if the adaptation law contains the information of the estimation errors <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. An adaptive estimation technique was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, where the parameter estimation errors were used to ensure the convergence of the estimated parameters. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, an optimal control strategy was applied in a nonlinear system by using the dynamic programming algorithm to ensure the finite-time convergence. Inspired by the concept of 'direct' parameters estimation <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, in this paper, a finite-time adaptive estimation algorithm is developed by introducing a leakage term driven by parameter estimation errors, such that the estimated kinematic parameters can converge to small neighborhoods of their optimal values in finite time.</p><p>It should be noted that persistent excitation (PE) condition is important to guarantee the convergence of estimated parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. However, for conventional FLS, the requirement of the PE condition is restricted and not easy to be satisfied. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>, a partial persistent excitation (PPE) is proposed to relax the PE condition of the neural network control, which proved that the PE condition of certain regression subvectors of radical basis functions along with a recurrent trajectory (e.g., periodic and periodic-like orbits) could be rigorously guaranteed <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. Inspired by this work, in this paper, the PPE condition of FLS is investigated to replace the conventionally used PE condition. Based on the PPE condition, an adaptive weights updating scheme is further developed by introducing an auxiliary framework to express the weights errors. Under the PPE condition, the finite-time convergence of partial FLS weight estimated and accurate approximation of unknown dynamics are guaranteed.</p><p>The main contributions of the proposed control scheme could be summarized as follows:</p><p>• Construction of an adaptive fuzzy logic control scheme for the coordinated robot arms with neither a priori knowledge of system dynamics nor information of the kinematic parameters. • Design a novel parameters adaptation framework by applying a set of auxiliary filtered matrices, such that the parameter estimation errors could be appropriately expressed without using the robot joint accelerations. • Relaxing the PE condition by introducing the concepts of the PPE and SLA of the FLS, such that the weights could converge to their optimal values when tracks a periodic trajectory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. MODELLING PROCEDURE OF THE ROBOT AND PRELIMILARIES A. Kinematics Modeling of the Dual-arm Robot</head><p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, the dual arm robot is commanded to grasp a common object to follow a reference trajectory. Assume that the end-effector of each arm grasps the object rigidly so that no relative motion occurs between the endeffectors and the object. Then, the object's position and orientation vector can be calculated by the joint variable of each arm as below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">x = f kinei (q i ), i = 1, 2<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where x ∈ R N0 is the position of the object, N 0 is the object's degree of freedom (DOF), q i denotes the joint angle of the ith arm. The subscript "i" denotes the "left" and "right" robotic arm, respectively. Differentiate (1) with respect to time yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ẋ = J i (q i , φ i ) qi<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where φ i ∈ R hi denotes the kinematic parameters of the ith arm, and h i denotes the number of the D-H parameters. J i (q i , φ i ) ∈ R No×Ni is the Jacobian matrix which satisfies the following property. Property 1: <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> The Jacobian matrix J i (q i , φ i ) can be formulated with a linearly parametrized form as</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">J i (q i , φ i )ξ i = R i (q i , ξ i )φ i<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where R i (q i , ξ i ) ∈ R No×hi is the regressor matrix of kinematics with respect to q i and ξ i , ξ i is a known vector. Without loss of generality, we assume that φ i is bounded by known vectors φ i and φ i , as φ i ≥ φ i ≥ φ i , where φ i and φ i denote the lower and upper bounds of φ i , respectively.</p><p>From Property 1, we can derive that J i (q i , φ i )ξ i = J i (q i , φi )ξ i + J i (q i , φi )ξ i , where φ i = φi + φi , φi is the estimated kinematic parameters and φi is the estimation error. This property is useful in the identification of the kinematic parameters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Dynamics Modeling of Dual-arm Robot</head><p>The dynamic model of the ith robotic arm is given by Lagrangian method as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">H i (q i )q i + D i (q i , qi ) qi + G i (q i ) = τ i + J T ei (q i )F ei<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">H i (q i ) ∈ R Ni×Ni , D i (q i , qi ) ∈ R Ni×Ni , G i (q i ) ∈ R Ni</formula><p>are the inertial matrix, Coriolis matrix and gravity term, respectively. N i denotes the DOF of ith robotic arm. J T ei (q i ) is the Jacobian matrix of ith robotic arm, while τ i ∈ R Ni is the joint torque, F ei ∈ R N0 is the external force exerted at the ith end-effector. The dynamics of the object can be described as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">H o (x)ẍ + D o (x, ẋ) ẋ + G o (x) = F o<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where H o (x) ∈ R N0×N0 denotes the inertial matrix of the object; D o (x, ẋ) ∈ R N0×N0 is the Coriolis and centrifugal matrix; G o (x) ∈ R N0×N0 is the object's gravity term, while F o ∈ R N0 denotes the result force exerted on the object. As shown from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, the force F o can be represented by two force vectors as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">F o = -F oe1 -F oe2<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where F oei ∈ R N0 is the interaction force applied by the object on the ith end-effector. The relationship between F oei and F ei is described as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">F oei = J T oei (x)F ei<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where J oei (x) ∈ R N0×N0 is the manipulated Jacobian matrix from the ith manipulator's end-effector to the mass center of the object. The force F oei can be decomposed to an external force and an internal force, such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">F oei = f i + f oi<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where the external forces f oi only contribute to the motion of the object, while the internal forces</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">f i satisfy f 1 + f 2 = 0 [n] .</formula><p>The combination of equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">5</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">6</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">8</ref>) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">H o (x)ẍ + D o (x, ẋ) ẋ + G o (x) = -f o1 -f o2<label>(9)</label></formula><p>The external force f oi could be represented as below <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">f oi = -C i (t) H o (x)ẍ + D o (x, ẋ) ẋ + G o (x)<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where C i (t) is a positive definite N 0 × N 0 diagonal matrix denoting the object load distribution onto the ith robotic arm, with C 1 (t) + C 2 (t) = I N0 , I N0 ∈ R N0×N0 is an identity matrix. Substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">9</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">10</ref>) into (8) we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">f i = F oei -C i (t)(f o1 + f o2 )<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Let us combine (4), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">5</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">6</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">8</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> and the kinematic equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>) -( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">2</ref>), the dynamics of the ith robotic arm could be reformulated as below</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">τ i = H i (q i )q i + D i (q i , qi ) qi + G i (q i ) -J T i (q i , φ i )f i (12) where H i = H i +C i H o , H o = J T i M o J i , D i = D i +C i (H D + D o ), D o = J T i D o J i , H D = J T i H o Ji , G i = G i +C i G o , G o = J T i G o , J ei = J oei J i .</formula><p>To facilitate the analysis, a number of useful properties and assumptions are given as below Property 2: <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> The matrix 2D i (q i , qi ) -[ Ḣi (q i ) -Ċi (t)H o (q i , qi )] is skew-symmetric and satisfies that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">∂ T 2D i (q i , qi ) -Ḣi (q i ) -Ċi (t)H o (q i , qi ) ∂ = 0, ∀∂ Property 3: [7]</formula><p>The term Ċi (t)H 0 (q i ) is uniformly continuous and bounded by a known constant as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">Ċi (t)H 0 (q i ) ≤ 2 , ∀t ≥ 0</formula><p>where is a positive constant.</p><p>Assumption 1: The Jacobian matrices of the robotic arms are of full rank during the operation.</p><p>Assumption 2: The robot grasp the object tightly such that no relative motion or rotation occurs between the object and grasper. In addition, the rigid object would not be deformed by the applied forces.</p><p>Assumption 3: The reference task space trajectory x d and its time derivative ẋd are continuous and bounded.</p><p>C. Preliminaries 1) Fuzzy logic system (FLS): FLS has been widely applied in the control of nonlinear systems by its powerful ability to approximate complex systems and no requirement of a priori experience of system dynamics. Considering the unknown nonlinear function F (z) ∈ R m , and the measurable scalar input z ∈ R n , with n and m being the dimensions of the input and output, respectively, we employ a multi-input-multioutput (MIMO) FLS to approximated an unknown nonlinear system F (z) with the following steps <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> i) Fuzzification: Fuzzification maps a real scalar input z into fuzzy linguistic terms by using membership functions. ii) Fuzzy IF-THEN rules: The Fuzzy IF-THEN rules are adopted to relate an input set to an output set with the Mamdani min-implication as below Rule l,</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">(l = 1, 2, • • • , L): If z 1 is A l 1 , z 2 is A l 2 , • • • , z n is A l n , then y 1 is B l 1 , y 2 is B l 2 , • • • , y m is B l m , where z = [z 1 , • • • , z n ] ∈ R n and y = [y 1 , • • • , y m ] ∈ R m are the</formula><p>premise variables with respect to the input and output, A l i and B l j are fuzzy sets, i = 1, • • • , n, j = 1, • • • , m, and L is the number of the rules. iii) Fuzzy inference engine and defuzzification: Combining the singleton fuzzifier, sum-product inference, and center-average defuzzifier, the defuzzification can be performed as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">y j (z) = L l=1 Φ l j n i=1 µ A l i (z i ) L l=1 n i=1 µ A l i (z i )<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">µ A l i (z i ) is the membership function of linguistic variable A l i (z i ), Φ l j =max yj (z)∈R {µ B l j (Φ l )} is the point at which µ B l j (Φ l j ) achieves its maximum value. Let p l (z) = n i=1 µ A l i (zi) L l=1 n i=1 µ A l i (zi) , P (z) = [p 1 (z), p 2 (z), • • • , p L (z)] T ∈ R L , W j = [Φ 1 j , Φ 2 j , • • • , Φ L j ] T ∈ R L , W = [W 1 , W 2 , • • • , W m ] ∈ R L×m .</formula><p>Then, the fuzzy logic systems can be rewritten as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">y(z) = W T P (z)<label>(14)</label></formula><p>Lemma 1: <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> Let f j (z) ∈ R be a continuous function defined on a compact set Ω j , then for any given constant j , there exists a FLS such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">sup fj (z)∈Ωj |f j (z) -y j (z)| ≤ j<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">y j = W T j P (z). In terms of Lemma 1, F (z) = [f 1 (z), f 2 (z), • • • , f m (z)] ∈ R m can be formulated as F (z) = W T P (z) + ε (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">)</formula><p>where W ∈ R L×m is the optimal weight matrix, P ∈ R L is the fuzzy basis vector, ε ∈ R m is the approximation error, and L is the number of fuzzy rules.</p><p>2) Spatially localized approximation (SLA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>: The SLA means that for any bounded trajectory z which remains in a compact set Ω, the unknown function f (z) can be approximated by a limited number of fuzzy rules in a local region (close to the trajectory z) as,</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">f (z) = W * T ξ P ξ (z) + ε ξ (z)<label>(17)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">P ξ (z) = [p 1 ξ (z), • • • , p L ξ (z)] T ∈ R L ξ denotes a subvector of P , with L ξ &lt; L, |p lξ | &gt; ς with ς being a small positive constant, W * ξ = [W * T j1 , • • • , W * T jξ ]</formula><p>T represents the corresponding weight matrix, and ε ξ is the construction error which satisfies ||ε ξ (z) -ε(z)|| ≤ σ, with σ being a small value.</p><p>3) Partial PE condition: In the parameter estimation, the PE condition is important to ensure the convergence of estimated parameters. The definition of PE condition could be described as below.</p><p>Definition 1: <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> A vector or matrix P (t) is called persistently excited if there exist two constant T &gt; 0 and &gt; 0, such that t+T t P T (r)P (r) dr ≥ I, ∀t ≥ 0 Note that for FLS, the PE condition is relatively strict and not easy to be satisfied. To relax the PE condition, we introduce a partial PE condition for the FLS with the Gaussian membership function, which is established by the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 1: Consider a periodic trajectory Z(t), which is continuous on a compact set Ω, and Ż(t) is bounded. For an FLS W T P (Z) with P (Z) chosen to be Gaussian fuzzy membership functions, and the centers placed on a regular lattice (large enough to cover the compact set Ω), the regressor subvector P ξ (Z(t)) could satisfy the PE condition.</p><p>Proof: See the Appendix I. Remark 1: In the previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, the SLA of the radical basis function based neural network (RBFNN) was well established, such that the accurate approximation can be achieved by a limited number of neural nodes. This property has been widely employed in the identification of system dynamics such as robotic manipulators <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>, unmanned surface vessels <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, faults detection system <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, etc. Inspired by the above discussion, in this paper, we investigate the partial PE property of the FLS. We have proved that the partial PE condition of FLS holds if the inputs trajectory is periodic. Which means that the partial PE condition of FLS could be more easy to satisfy.</p><p>Remark 2: Theorem 1 shows that for the GFBFs whose centers are close to the periodic trajectory, the PE condition could be relaxed to partial PE condition, and hence the convergence of the estimated weights is more easy to satisfy. On the other hand, for the GFBFs whose centers are far away from the tracking trajectory, the weights are only slightly updated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. CONTROL DESIGN</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Control Design for the Closed-Loop Robot System</head><p>Step 1: Define the tracking error as e x = x(t) -x d (t). Taking its differentiation with respect to time, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">ėx = ẋ(t) -ẋd (t) = J i (q i , φ i ) qi -ẋd<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where ẋ = J i (q i , φ i ) qi holds according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. Then, an auxiliary controller qdi is designed as below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">qdi = J + i (q i , φi )( ẋd -K e e x -α fi )<label>(19)</label></formula><p>where J + i (q i , φi ) is the Moore-Penrose inverse of J i (q i , φi ), K e is the control gain, α fi is an auxiliary term defined by α fi = β fi Λ Fi , with β fi being a positive constant, and Λ Fi is a leakage term which will be designed later. The combination of (3) ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">18</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">19</ref>) yields, ėx = -K e e x + J i (q i , φ i )e qi + R i (q i , qdi ) φi -α fi <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> where e qi = qi -qdi .</p><p>Step 2: Substituting equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_25">18</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">19</ref>) into (12), we have  </p><formula xml:id="formula_27">H i (q i ) ėqi + D i (q i , qi )e qi = τ i -H i (q i )q di -D i (q i , qi ) qdi -G i (q i ) + J i (q i , φ i )f i<label>(21)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_28">F i (z i ) = H i (q i )q di + D i (q i , qi ) qdi + G i (q i )<label>(22)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">z i = [q T di , qT di , q T i , qT i ] T . Since H i (q i ), D i (q i , qi</formula><p>) and G i (q i ) are not available, we use an FLS to approximate <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> as</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">F i (z i ) = W T Fi P Fi + ε Fi (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_31">)</formula><p>where W Fi ∈ R σ F i ×Ni is the optimal FLS weight matrix, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">P Fi (z i ) = [P Fi 1 (z i ), P Fi 2 (z i ), • • • , P Fiσ F i (z i )] T ∈ R σ F i</formula><p>is the fuzzy basis vector, σ Fi is the number of fuzzy rules, and ε Fi ∈ R Ni is the construction error.</p><p>Then, the controller τ i can be designed as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">τ i = Fi (e qi )-K i e qi -J T i (q i , φi )(e x -K fi Λ fi +f di )+Υ i (e qi ) (24) where K i is the selected control gain, Fi (z i ) = Ŵ T Fi P Fi (z i ), and ŴFi ∈ R σ F i ×Ni is the estimation of W Fi , f di is the desired internal force. The robust term Υ i (e qi ) is designed as Υ i (e qi ) = -β i eq i ||eq i ||</formula><p>e qi = 0 0 otherwise , and β i is a selected positive constant. And Λ fi is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">Λ fi = t 0 fi dt, fi = f i -f di .</formula><p>The overall control scheme is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p><p>Substituting <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref> and ( <ref type="formula">24</ref>) into ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_27">21</ref>), the closed-loop error dynamics of the dual-arm robot can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">H i (q i ) ėqi + D i (q i , qi )e qi = -K i e qi -J T i (q i , φi )e x + Υ i (e qi ) + J T i (q i , φ i )f i -J T i (q i , φi )(f di -K fi Λ fi ) + ε Fi + W T Fi S Fi (z i )<label>(25)</label></formula><p>where WFi = ŴFi -W Fi .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Finite-Time Kinematic Parameter Estimation Design</head><p>In this section, we will preform the parameters estimation design of the unknown system parameters.</p><p>1) FCPA design of the kinematic parameters: In order to derive the parameter estimation of φi , we define an auxiliary matrix U i ∈ R hi×hi , and two vectors</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">T i ∈ R Ni , P i ∈ R Ni as      Ui = -ζ i U i + R i (q i , qi ) T R i (q i , qi ) U i (0) = 0 Ṫi = -ζ i T i + R i (q i , qi ) T ẋ T i (0) = 0 P i = T i -U i φi<label>(26)</label></formula><p>where ζ i is a positive constant that introduces a forgetting factor for the filter matrix. Which can be designed to make a trade-off of the robustness and the convergence rate.</p><p>By integrating on both sides of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_36">26</ref>) with respect to time, the solution of U i and T i can be derived as</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">       U i (t) = t 0 e -ζi(t-r) R i (q i (r), qi (r)) T R i (q i (r), qi (r))dr T i (t) = t 0 e -ζi(t-r) R i (q i (r), qi (r)) T ẋ(r)dr (27)</formula><p>Remark 3: From the analysis in Section II, we have ẋ = R(q i , qi )φ i . Comparing the structure between T i and U i in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>, we can derive that T i = U i φ i . Then, P i can be represented by P i = U i φ i -U i φi = U i φi . In this sense, the term P i contains the information of estimation error of φ i . This is important to improve the estimation performance.</p><p>Then, the updating law for φi is designed by using the following projection algorithm,</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">( φi ) k =                      -λ i R T i (q i , qdi )e x + κ i U T i P i ||P i || + N i k if (φ i ) k ≤ ( φi ) k ≤ (φ i ) k ; or if ( φi ) k = (φ i ) k and (φ i F ) k ≤ 0; or if ( φi ) k = (φ i ) k and (φ i F ) k ≥ 0; 0 otherwise. (<label>28</label></formula><p>) where λ i and κ i are positive constants to be specified by the designer, (•) k denotes the kth element of the vector (•), N i is a leakage term which will be designed later,</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">φ i F = -R T i (q i , qdi )e x -κ i U T i Pi</formula><p>||Pi|| -N i , and φ i and φ i are the known lower bound and upper bound of the real value of φ i , respectively.</p><p>2) FCPA design of the FLS weights: In order to achieve the FT estimation of the FLS weight parameters without using the joint acceleration qi , the following functions have been designed</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">Ξ i (z ci ) = H i e qi Ψ i (z di ) = -Ḣi e qi + D i (q i , qi )e qi -J T i (q i , φ i )f i<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">z ci = [q T i , qT i , qT di ] T , z di = [q T i , qT i , qT di , f T i ] T</formula><p>. By combining <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>, and considering that Ξ(z ci ) = H i ėqi + Ḣi e qi , the closed-loop dual-arm robot system (12) can be represented as</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">F i (z i ) + Ξi (z ci ) + Ψ i (z di ) = τ i<label>(30)</label></formula><p>Since Ξ i (z ci ) and Ψ i (z di ) are not available, the following FLS is constructed for Ξ i and Ψ i as</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">Ξ i (z ci ) = W T Ξi P Ξi + ε Ξi Ψ i (z di ) = W T Ψi P Ψi + ε Ψi (<label>31</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">)</formula><p>where W Ξi ∈ R σΞ×Ni and W Ψi ∈ R σΨ i ×Ni are the optimal weight matrix, P Ξi ∈ R σΞ i and P Ψi ∈ R σΨ i are the fuzzy basis vectors, and ε Ψi and ε Ξi are the construction errors.</p><p>Inspired by the work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, we introduce a stable linear filter (•) f = 1 bis+1 (•), b i &gt; 0 on both sides of (30) as follows,</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">F if (z i ) + Ξif (z ci ) + Ψ if (z di ) = W T Fi P Fif + W T Ξi ṖΞif + W T Ψi P Ψif + ε Fif + εΞif + ε Ψif = τ if<label>(32)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">P Fif ∈ R σ F i , P Ξif ∈ R σΞ i , P Ψif ∈ R σΨ i , ε Fif ∈ R Ni , ε Ξif ∈ R Ni , ε Ψif ∈ R Ni and τ if ∈ R Ni</formula><p>are the filtered version of P Ξi , P Ψi , P Fi , ε Fi , ε Ξi , ε Ψi and τ i , respectively, and given as follows,</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">         b i ṖFif + P Fif = P Fi b i εFif + ε Fif = ε Fi b i ṖΞif + P Ξif = P Ξi b i ṖΨif + P Ψif = P Ψi b i εΞif + ε Ξif = ε Ξi b i εΨif + ε Ψif = ε Ψi b i τif + τ if = τ i (33)</formula><p>where b i is a positive constant, P Fi (0) = 0, ε Fi (0) = 0, P Ξif (0) = 0, P Ψif (0) = 0, ε Ξif (0) = 0, ε Ψif (0) = 0 and τ i (0) = 0. Then, the filtered dynamics can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">τ if = W T i S i (Z i ) + ε i (<label>34</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">W i = [W T Fi , ψ T i ] T ∈ R σi×Ni , ψ i = [W T Ξi , W T Ψi ] T ∈ R σ Y i ×Ni are the optimal weight matrix of FLS, S i (Z i ) = [P T F if (z i ), P T Yi (c i )] T ∈ R σi , and P Yi (c i ) = [ P T Ξ i -P T Ξ i f bi , P T Ψif ] T ∈ R σ Y i</formula><p>is the fuzzy basis function, σ i = σ Fi + σ Yi with σ Yi being the number of fuzzy rules;</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">ε i = ε F if + ε Yi ∈ R Ni , ε Yi = εΞ i -ε Ξ i f bi</formula><p>+ ε Ψif ∈ R Ψi are the approximation errors. To derive the parameters estimation of W i , we design the auxiliary filter matrices</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">L i ∈ R σ Y i ×σ Y i , Q i ∈ R σ Y i ×Ni and V i ∈ R σ Y i ×Ni as      Li = -δ i L i + S i (z i )S T i (z i ) L i (0) = 0 Qi = -δ i Q i + S i (z i )τ T if Q i (0) = 0 V i = L i Ŵi -Q i (35)</formula><p>where δ i is a positive constant. The solution of L i and Q i are derived by integrating on both sides of <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">       L i (t) = t 0 e -δi(t-r) S i (z i (r))S i (z i (r)) T dr Q i (t) = t 0</formula><p>e -δi(t-r) S i (z i (r)) T τ i dr <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref> From the definition of V i , L i and Q i in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref>, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">V i = L i Ŵi -L i W i + χ i = L i Wi + χ i<label>(37)</label></formula><p>where χ i = -t 0 exp -δ i (t -r) S i (z i (r))ε i (r)dr. Since ε i and the basis function S i (z i ) are bounded, the χ i is also bounded and satisfies that χ i ≤ χi , where χi is the upper bound of χ i . Then, the FLS weight updating law Ẇi is designed as below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">Ẇi = -Γ i (M i S Fi (z i )e T qi + γ i L T i V i ||V i || )<label>(38)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">M i = I σ F i ×σ F i 0 σ Y i ×σ F i</formula><p>and γ i is a positive constant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Stability Analysis</head><p>The stability analysis of the proposed control algorithm is established by the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 2: Consider the dual-arm robot system grasping a common object in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>. Assume that the regressor matrices R i (q i , qi ) and P i (Z i ) satisfy the PE condition. Then, the adaptive control input τ di developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> with the auxiliary controllers qdi in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>, as well as the parameter adaptation law <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref> and the FLS weight adaptation law in <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref> can guarantee that (i) all the signals in the closed-loop system are uniformly ultimately bounded. (ii) the tracking error e x converges to a residual set around zero. (iii) the estimate error and Wi could converge to a small neighbourhood around zero.</p><p>Proof: Consider the following Lyapunov function for the dual-arm robot</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">V i = V i1 + V i2 + V i3<label>(39)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">V i1 = 1 2 e T x e x + 1 2λ i φT i φi<label>(40)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">V i2 = 1 2 e T qi H i e qi + 1 2 β i Λ T fi Λ fi<label>(41)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_60">V i3 = 1 2 tr W T i Γ -1 i Wi<label>(42)</label></formula><p>and φi = φ i -φi , β i is a positive constant. The differentiation of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_58">40</ref>) with respect to time gives us</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">Vi1 = e T x ėx + 1 λ i φT i φi<label>(43)</label></formula><p>Substituting equation ( <ref type="formula">20</ref>) and the updating law ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_38">28</ref>) into <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(43)</ref>, yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">Vi1 = e T x -K e e x + J i (q i , φ i )e qi + R i (q i , qdi ) φi -α fi + 1 λ i φT i φi = -e T</formula><p>x K e e x + e T x J i (q i , φi )e qi + e T x J i (q i , φi )e qi -e T x α fi</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">-φT i R T i (q i , qi )e x + κ i U T i P i ||P i || + N i + e T x R i (q i , qdi ) φi<label>(44)</label></formula><p>As mentioned above, P i can be represented by P i = U i φi . Then (44) can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">Vi1 = -e T x K e e x + e T x J i (q i , φi )e qi -κ i φT i U T i U i φi ||U i φi || -φT i N i -e T x α fi<label>(45)</label></formula><p>Taking the derivative of V i2 with respect to time yields,</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">Vi2 = e T qi H i ėqi + 1 2 e T qi Ḣi e qi + β i Λ T fi fi<label>(46)</label></formula><p>the error dynamics of the closed-loop system (25) into (46), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">= e T qi -K i e qi + Υ i (e qi ) + W T Fi S Fi (z i ) + ε Fi +e T qi -J T i (q i , φi )(e x + f di -K fi Λ fi ) + J T i (q i , φ i )f i + 1 2 e T qi Ḣi e qi -e T qi D i (q i , qi )e qi + β i Λ T fi fi<label>(47)</label></formula><p>In terms of the Properties 2 and 3 of the dual-arm robot, and employing the inequality e T qi 2D i (q i , qi ) -Ḣi (q i ) e qi ≤ i e T qi e qi , (47) can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">Vi2 ≤ -K i -i e T qi e qi + e T qi W T Fi S Fi (z i ) + e T qi ε Fi -e T qi J T i (q i , φi )e x + e T qi J T i (q i , φ i )f i -β i ||e qi || -e T qi J T i (q i , φi ) f di -K fi Λ fi + β fi Λ T fi fi<label>(48)</label></formula><p>Note that J i (q i , φ i )e qi = ėx +K e e x -R i (q i , qdi ) φi +α fi and J i (q i , φi )e qi = ėx + K e e x -R i (q i , qi ) φi + α fi hold according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>, then, the combination of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_64">45</ref>) and (48) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">Vi1 + Vi2 ≤ -e T x K e e x -K i -i e T qi e qi -β i ||e qi || -κ i ||U i φi || -φT i N i + ėx + K e e x + α fi T (f i -f di + K fi Λ fi ) -φi T R T i (q i , qdi )f i + φi T R T i (q i , qi )f di + e T qi W T Fi S Fi (z i ) -φi T R T i (q i , qi )K fi Λ fi + e T qi ε Fi + β fi Λ T fi fi -e T x β fi Λ Fi<label>(49)</label></formula><p>Let us design N i to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">N i = R T i (q i , qi )f di -R T i (q i , qdi )f i - R T i (q i , qi )K fi</formula><p>Λ fi and substitute it into (49), yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">Vi1 + Vi2 ≤ -e T x K e e x -K i -i e T qi e qi -β i ||e qi || -κ i ||U i φi || + ėx + K e e x + α fi T ( fi + K fi Λ fi ) + e T qi W T Fi S Fi (z i ) + e T qi ε Fi + β fi Λ T fi fi -e T x β fi Λ Fi<label>(50)</label></formula><p>Then, let us consider the convergence of the FLS weight errors. Taking the derivative of the V i3 in (42), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">Vi3 = tr W T i Γ -1 i Ẇi = -e T qi W T Fi S Fi (z i ) -tr γ i W T i L T i V i ||V i || = -e T qi W T Fi S Fi (z i ) -γ i ||L i || 2 ||V i || || Wi || 2 -γ i C i<label>(51)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">C i = tr( W T i L T i χ i /||V i ||</formula><p>) is a bounded term. Combining Vi1 , Vi2 and Vi3 , and according to the definition of V i in (39), we can obtain the time derivation of V i as below</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">Vi = Vi1 + Vi2 + Vi3 ≤ -e T x K e e x -K i -i e T qi e qi -β i ||e qi || -κ i ||U i φi || + ėx + K e e x + α fi T ( fi + K fi Λ fi ) + e T qi W T Fi S Fi (z i ) + e T qi ε Fi + β fi Λ T fi fi -e T x β fi Λ Fi -e T qi W T Fi S Fi (z i ) -γ i ||L i || 2 ||V i || || Wi || 2 -γ i C i (52)</formula><p>Let us consider the following inequalities,</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">e T qi ε Fi ≤ 1 2 e T qi e qi + 1 2 ε T Fi ε Fi ,<label>(53)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_75">-e T x β fi Λ Fi ≤ β fi 2 e T x e x + β fi 2 Λ T Fi Λ Fi (54)</formula><p>Substituting ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_74">53</ref>) into (52), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">Vi ≤ -e T x (K e - β fi 2 )e x -(K i -i - 1 2 )e T qi e qi -β i ||e qi || -κ i ||U i φi || + ėx + K e e x + α fi T ( fi + K fi Λ fi ) -γ i C i + 1 2 ε T Fi ε Fi + β fi Λ T fi fi + β fi 2 Λ T fi Λ fi -γ i ||L i || 2 ||V i || || Wi || 2<label>(55)</label></formula><p>Let α fi = -β fi Λ fi , and</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">K f1 = K f2 = K f , β f1 = β f2 = β f</formula><p>with K f and β f being a positive constants. Then, considering the property of internal forces errors f1 + f2 = 0, Λ 1 +Λ 2 = 0, and taking the Lyapunov function</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">V = V 1 +V 2 = 2 i=1 (V i1 + V i2 + V i3 ), we have V = 2 i=1 Vi1 + Vi2 + Vi3 ≤ -e T x (2K e -β f )e x - 2 i=1 (K i -i - 1 2 )e T qi e qi + 2 i=1 -κ i ||U i φi || -β i ||e qi || + β fi Λ T fi fi + 2 i=1 -β fi Λ T fi fi -β fi Λ T fi K f Λ fi + β fi 2 Λ T fi Λ fi - 2 i=1 γ i ||L i || 2 ||V i || || Wi || 2 + γ i C i - 1 2 ε T Fi ε Fi ≤ -e T x (2K e -β fi )e x - 2 i=1 (K i -i -<label>1</label></formula><p>2 )e T qi e qi</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">+ 2 i=1 -β fi Λ T fi (K f - 1 2 )Λ fi - 2 i=1 γ i ||L i || 2 ||V i || || Wi || 2 - 1 2 ε T Fi ε Fi + γ i C i<label>(56)</label></formula><p>If the gains K i and K e are selected to satisfy <ref type="formula" target="#formula_79">56</ref>) and the definition of V in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_57">39</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_58">40</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_59">41</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_60">42</ref>), we can derive that</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">K i ≥ i + 1 2 and K e ≥ 1 2 β f , γ i is chosen to be γ i ≥ ||(L -1 i ) T Γ -1 i ω i ||, then, from (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_81">V ≤ -ηV + µ (<label>57</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_82">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_83">η = min[λ max 2K e -β fi , λ max Ki-i -I Hi , γ i ||Li|| 2 ||Vi|| , β fi (K f -1 2 )], µ = 1 2 2 i=1 ε T Fi ε Fi + γ i C i , i = 1, 2.</formula><p>According to the results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, we can derive that the tracking errors and estimation errors could converge to a small neighborhood near zero. This completes the proof.</p><p>Theorem 2 shows that the tracking error qi could converge to a small neighborhood of zero. For the estimated parameters Ŵi , however, they may not converge to their optimal values since the PE condition of FLS is not easy to satisfy. According to SLA in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>, the FLS in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_30">23</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_43">31</ref>) can be expressed using localized Gaussian fuzzy basis functions as</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">     F ijξ (z i ) = W T F ijξ P F ijξ + ε F ijξ Ξ ijξ (z ci ) = W T Ξ ijξ P Ξ ijξ + ε Ξ ijξ Ψ ijξ (z di ) = W T Ψ ijξ P Ψ ijξ + ε Ψ ijξ<label>(58)</label></formula><p>where P (•) ijξ and W (•) ijξ are the subvectors of P (•) and W (•) , whose centers are close to the reference trajectory ϕ iξ = {z iξ , z ciξ , z diξ }. Then (34) can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">τ ij = W T ijξ P ijξ (Z i ) + ε ijξ , where W ijξ = [W T F ijξ , W T Ξ ijξ , W T Ψ ijξ ] T , P ijξ (Z i ) = [P T F ijf ξ , (P T Ξij ξ -P T Ξ ijf ξ )/2, P T Ψ ijf ξ ] T .</formula><p>Since the elements in P (•) ijξ are activated, we can obtain that the regerossers P Fij ξ , P Ξij ξ , P Ψij ξ and P ijξ satisfy the PE condition. For the subvector of FLS weight Ŵijξ , its adaptation law can be designed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">Ẇijξ = -Γ ijξ (P F ijξ e T qij + γ i L T ijξ V ijξ ||V ijξ || ) (<label>59</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_87">)</formula><p>where P F ijξ , V ijξ and L ijξ are elements of the 'subvertor' version of P Fi , V i and L i . Similar to ( <ref type="formula">35</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">36</ref>), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">L ijξ (t) = t 0 e -δi(t-r) P ijξ (Z i (r))P T ijξ (Z i (r))dr Q ijξ (t) = t 0 e -δi(t-r) P T ijξ (Z i (r))τ ij dr V ijξ (t) = L ijξ Wijξ + χ ijξ (<label>60</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_89">)</formula><p>where χ ijξ = -t 0 exp -δ i (t -r) P ijξ (Z i (r))ε ijξ (r)dr. Theorem 3: Consider the dual-arm robot system in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> and provide the auxiliary controllers qdi in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>. Then, for any recurrent trajectory ϕ ξ (Z i ) starting from the initial condition Z i (0) ∈ Ω 0 (where Ω 0 is a properly chosen compact set), the adaptive control input τ i developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> with the parameter adaptation law in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref> and the FLS weight adaptation law in (59) can guarantee that, (i) the tracking error e x exponentially converges to a small residual set around zero in finite time. (ii) the estimation error φ1 , φ2 , could converge to a small neighbourhood around zero in finite time. (iii) the estimated parameters Ŵi converge to small neighborhoods of their optimal values in finite time.</p><p>Proof: Let us consider the following Lyapunov function for the robotic arm i,</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">L i = V i1 + V i2 + V i3ξ<label>(61)</label></formula><p>where V i1 and V i2 are as defined in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_58">40</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_59">41</ref>) in the proof of Theorem 2, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">V i3 ξ = 1 2 Ni j=1 V T ijξ (L -1 ijξ ) T Γ -1 ijξ L -1 ijξ V ijξ<label>(62)</label></formula><p>where Γ iξ is the 'subvertor' version of Γ i . Then considering the L -1 ijξ V ijξ in V i3ξ , the derivation with respect to time gives</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">∂L -1 ijξ V ijξ ∂t = Ẇijξ -L -1 ijξ Lijξ L -1 ijξ χ ijξ + L -1 ijξ χijξ<label>(63)</label></formula><p>Since P ijξ (Z i ) is PE and Z i is bounded, we can obtain that L -1 ijξ and L-1 ijξ are bounded, then L -1 ijξ is also bounded.</p><p>Then, taking the derivative of V i3ξ with respect to time and substituting (63) in it, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">Vi3ξ = Ni j=1 V T ijξ L -1 ijξ Γ -1 ijξ ( Ẇijξ + ω ij )<label>(64)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">ω ij = -L -1 ijξ Lijξ L -1 ijξ χ ijξ + L -1</formula><p>ijξ χijξ . Then, substituting the updating law (59) into (64), and considering V ijξ = L ijξ Wijξ + χ ijξ , we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">Vi3ξ = Ni j=1 V T ijξ (L -1 ijξ ) T -P T F ijξ e qij -γ i L T ijξ V ijξ ||V ijξ || + Γ -1 ijξ ω ij ≤ Ni j=1 -V T ijξ (L -1 ijξ ) T P F ijξ e qij + V T ijξ L -1 ijξ T Γ -1 ijξ ω ij + Ni j=1 -γ i V T ijξ (L -1 ijξ ) T L ijξ V ijξ ||V ijξ || ≤ Ni j=1 -W T ijξ P F ijξ e qij + ρ ij ||e qij || - Ni j=1 (γ i -||(L -1 ijξ ) T Γ -1 ijξ ω ij ||)||V ijξ ||<label>(65)</label></formula><p>where ρ ij is a positive parameter defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">ρ ij = ||χ T ijξ (L -1 ijξ ) T P T F ijξ (z i )||.</formula><p>According to the definition of χ ijξ , it can be proved that χ ijξ and χijξ are all bounded in terms of the boundness of P ijξ (Z i ) and ε ij , which have been established in Theorem 2. L -1 ijξ is also bounded according to the satisfaction of PPE condition of P ijξ (Z i ). Therefore, we can derive that ρ ij and ω ij are bounded, hence the term ||(L -1 ijξ ) T Γ -1 ijξ ω ij || is also bounded.</p><p>Combining Vi1 , Vi2 and Vi3ξ , we can obtain the time derivation of the Lyapunov function</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">L = L 1 + L 2 as below L = 2 i=1 Vi1 + Vi2 + Vi3ξ ≤ -e T x (2K e -β fi )e x - 2 i=1 (K i -i - 1 2 )e T qi e qi + 2 i=1 -κ i ||U i φi || - 2 i=1 (β i -ρ i )||e qi || + 2 i=1 -β fi Λ T fi K f Λ fi + β fi 2 Λ T fi Λ fi + 1 2 ε T Fi ε Fi - 2 i=1 Ni j=1 (γ i -||(L -1 ijξ ) T Γ -1 ijξ ω ij ||)||V ijξ || ≤ 2 i=1 -κ i ||U i φi || - 2 i=1 (β i -ρ i )||e qi || + 2 i=1 - Ni j=1 (γ i -||L -1T ijξ Γ -1 ijξ ω ij ||)||V ijξ || + 1 2 ε T Fi ε Fi ≤ -η 1 √ L + µ 1<label>(66)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">ρ i = max(ρ i1 , ρ i2 , • • • , ρ iNi ), γ i is chosen to be γ i ≥ ||L -1T ijξ Γ -1 ijξ ω ij ||, β i is chosen to be β i ≥ ρ i , η 1 = √ 2 min λ max γi-||L -1T iξ Γ -1 iξ ωi|| λmin(Γ -1 iξ ) , (β i - ρ i )/ λ min H i , κ i ||U i || √ λ i , µ 1 = 1 2 2 i=1 ε T Fi ε Fi , i = 1, 2.</formula><p>Following the results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> and according to (66), the tracking errors and the parameter estimation errors could converge to a small neighbourhood near zero in finite time. This completes the proof.</p><p>Remark 4: Note that for parameters estimation, the PE (or partial PE) condition should be fulfilled to guarantee the convergence of the estimation errors. Also, in practical robot control implementations, some unknown factors such as friction, actuator nonlinearities, non-rigid grasping and external disturbances may exist. These factors could affect the parameters estimation performance and may degrade the control performance. Further investigation together with experimental studies will be made in our future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. SIMULATION STUDY</head><p>To illustrate the effectiveness of the proposed control scheme, simulation studies are carried out based on a model of a dual-arm robot with 3 joints for each arm, and in the scenario that a common object is firmly held in between the arms. The robot dynamic model for each arm is described as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">H i (q i )q i + D i (q i , qi ) qi + G i (q i ) = τ i + J T</formula><p>ei (q i )F ei where the manipulator inertial matrix H i (q i ) and Coriolis matrix D(q i qi ) are described as</p><formula xml:id="formula_100">H i (q i ) = H T i (q i ) =   H 11 * * H 21 H 22 * H 31 H 32 H 33   D i (q i ) =   D 11 D 12 D 13 D 21 D 22 D 23 D 31 D 32 D 33   G i (q i ) =   G 11 G 21 G 31   with H 11 = p 1 + 2p 4 l 1 c 2 + 2p 5 (l 2 c 3 + l 1 c 23 ), H 21 = p 2 + p 4 l 1 c 2 + p 5 (2l 2 c 3 + l 1 c 23 ), H 22 = p 2 + 2p 5 l 2 c 3 , H 31 = p 3 + p 5 (l 2 c 3 + l 1 c 23 ), H 32 = p 3 + p 5 l 2 c 3 , H 33 = p 3 , D 11 = l 1 (p 4 s 2 + p 5 s 12 ), D 12 = l 2 p 5 s 3 -l 1 p 4 s 2 , D 13 = -p 5 (l 2 s 3 + l 1 s 12 ), D 21 = l 1 (p 4 s 2 + p 5 s 12 ), D 22 = l 2 p 5 s 3 , D 23 = -l 2 p 5 s 3 , D 31 = -l 1 p 5 s 12 , D 32 = V , D 33 = 0, G 11 = 0, G 21 = 0, G 31 = 0.</formula><p>And s j = sin(q ij ), c j = cos(q ij ), s j1j2 = sin(q ij1 + q ij2 ), c j1j2 = cos(q ij1 + q ij2 ), s 123 = sin(q i1 + q i2 + q i2 ), c 123 = cos(q i1 + q i2 + q i2 ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">p 1 = I 1 + I 2 + I 3 + l 2 1 (m 1 + m 2 + m 3 ) + 2l 1 m 1 l c2 + l 2 2 (m 2 + m 3 ) + 2l 2 m 2 l c2 , p 2 = I 2 + I 3 + l 2 2 (m 1 + m 2 ) + 2l 2 m 2 l c2 , p 3 = I 3 , p 4 = m 3 l c2 + l 2 (m 2 + m 3 ), p 5 = m 3 l c3 .</formula><p>The motion dynamic of the object is described as</p><formula xml:id="formula_102">H o ẍ + D o ẋ + G o (x) = F o (<label>67</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_103">)</formula><p>where  For the fuzzy logic system, Gaussian membership functions are selected for each input dimension. The Gaussian membership functions are continuously differentiable and have the advantage for the theoretical analysis of FLS. We choose parameter -3, -2, -1, 0.5, 1.5, 1, 2 for the central points and π for the standard deviations for the FLS. The initial FLS weights are chosen to be Ŵ1 (0) = 0, Ŵ2 (0) = 0, which will be updated with the FT estimated law (59). The adaptation gains are chosen to be</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">H o =   1 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0.1   , C o = G o = 0.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_105">ζ 1 = ζ 2 = 5, δ 1 = δ 2 = 1.5, κ 1 = κ 2 = 0.05, λ 1 = λ 2 = 5, Γ 1 = Γ 2 = 1.5 and b 1 = b 2 = 0.001.</formula><p>And the control gains are selected to be positive definite matrix as K e = diag{5, 5, 3}, and K i = diag{20, 10, 9}.</p><p>We employ the proposed controller <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> into the dual-arm robot system to achieve the control goal without using a priori knowledge of both the kinematics and dynamics of the robot. The simulation results are performed in Figs. <ref type="bibr">3-17.</ref> An overlook of the tracking performance is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, where the grasped object is controlled to follow the periodic tracking trajectories in the phase plane. dashed line '-') and all tracking errors converge to zeros, even in the presence of kinematic and dynamic uncertainties.</p><p>To verify the superiority of the proposed control method, comparison studies have been further carried out based on a model based controller <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and a conventional PD controller. The comparative results are depicted in Figs. <ref type="figure">7</ref><ref type="figure">8</ref><ref type="figure">9</ref>. From the figures, we can find that the proposed controller (24) obtained the best control performance and tracking errors are much smaller than the other two methods.</p><p>The parameters estimation performance is shown in Figs. <ref type="bibr">10-11.</ref> From the figures, we can observe that the estimated kinematic parameters of both arm converge to their real values (blue dash line '-') in a short period of time (less than a periodic). Additionally, the profile of the auxiliary term P 1 , P 2 and the minimum eigenvalue of the auxiliary matrix U 1 , U 2 are also depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">12</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">13</ref>, respectively. It is shown that both σ 1 = λ min (U 1 ) and σ 2 = λ min (U 2 ) are great than zero. This implies that the PE condition is satisfied during the estimation, which has been further verified in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">12</ref>, where both P 1 and P 2 (which contain the information of estimation errors) have approached to zero. Therefore the validity of the kinematics identification is demonstrated. In comparison to the work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, our proposed method ensures not only the convergence of the tracking errors, but also the finite-time convergence of the estimated parameters.</p><p>Simulation results of the proposed fuzzy logic control are depicted in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">14</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">15</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">16</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">17</ref>. The weights of the fuzzy logic system are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">14</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">15</ref>. From the figures, we can see that the weights of the fuzzy logic systems of both arms are converged with a fast rate. It should also be emphasized that not all of the FLS weights have converged to relatively larger value, and a number of weights only converge to the small Estimation performance of the kinematic parameters l 21 , l 22 , l 23 and lo neighborhood around zero. This is consistent with the partial PE condition and only part of the fuzzy weights are activated and updated by the adaptive law, while for the Gaussian membership functions, whose centers are far away from the FLS inputs, the corresponding FLS weights are not activated and hence will remain in their initial conditions. A comparative study of the FLS weights estimation using gradient descent adaptation is shown in Figs. <ref type="bibr">16-17.</ref> It can be observed that some weights diverge in the estimation and not all the weights are converged to their optimal values.</p><p>The simulation results have illustrated that our proposed controller can successfully track the desired trajectory in the presence of uncertain kinematics and dynamics with the guarantee of FT convergence of the estimated weights.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we have developed an adaptive fuzzy control scheme for the coordinated robot arms in the presence of system uncertainties. To guarantee the estimated parameters converge to the optimal values, the partial PE property of fuzzy basis function has been investigated. An FCPA technique is developed for the estimation of both the unknown kinematics parameters and FLS weights. We have shown that, under the partial PE condition, the estimated parameters are able to converge to a small neighborhood of their actual values in a finitesuch that they could be re-used next time with improved computational efficiency and control performance. Extensive simulation studies have been carried out to illustrate that the manipulated object is able to track well a desired trajectory in the presence of uncertain kinematics and dynamics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. APPENDIX</head><p>Before proceeding to prove Theorem 1, let us introduce some useful definitions and lemmas as below.</p><p>Definition 2: <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> A uniformly bounded piecewise continuous vector function P ∈ R m is said to be PE if there   where ξ l = [ξ l1 , ξ l2 , • • • , ξ lN ] T . And (70) can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">p l (Z) = ϕ l (Z) ϕ l + ϕ 2 + • • • + ϕ L<label>(71)</label></formula><p>In comparison to the equations ( <ref type="formula">68</ref>) and (71), if ρ and ς are chosen to been the same, we can deduce that ϕ l is functional equivalent to a RBF. Then, according to Lemma 2, for the RBF ϕ = [ϕ 1 , ϕ 2 , • • • , ϕ L ] T , there exist an arbitrary selected constant vector c ∈ R L , and positive constants α 1 , α 2 , such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_107">α 1 ||c|| 2 ≤ t0+T0 t0 |ϕ(Z(t)) T c| 2 dµ(τ ) ≤ α 2 ||c|| 2<label>(72)</label></formula><p>The ϕ l is bounded with the boundedness of Z according to (71). And from (72) we can also easily obtain that there exist a ϕ l (Z(t)) among ϕ 1 , • • • , ϕ L , such that ϕ l (Z(t)) &gt; 0 in the time interval [t 0 , t 0 + T 0 ]. Let ϕ u = ϕ 1 + • • • + ϕ L , then we have φu ≤ ϕ u ≤ ϕ u with φu and ϕ u are the upper and lower bound of ϕ u , which are positive constants, respectively.</p><p>Then, combining (71), (72) and the definition of P ξ , we have From above analysis and Definition 2, we can conclude that for any periodic trajectory Z(t) the corresponding regressor subvector of FLS P ξ (Z(t)) is persistently exciting. This completes the proof.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. An overlook of the dual-arm robot manipulated an object</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Control strategy of the dual arm robot with uncertain dynamics and kinematics</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Trajectory tracking performance in phase plane</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .Fig. 9 .</head><label>4569</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Trajectory tracking performance in x direction</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10.Estimation performance of the kinematic parameters l 11 , l 12 , l 13 and lo</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig.</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 17.FLS Weights W 2 with conventional adaptation law</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>17</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Fig. 17.FLS Weights W 2 with conventional adaptation law</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>2 ,li ρ 2 =</head><label>22</label><figDesc>Fig. 17.FLS Weights W 2 with conventional adaptation law</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>2 u 2 u</head><label>22</label><figDesc>t0+T0 t0 |P ξ (Z(τ )) T c| 2 dµ(τ ) = t0+T0 t0 |ϕ(Z(τ )) T c| 2 ϕ dµ(τ ) ≤ t0+T0 t0 |ϕ(Z(τ )) T c| 2 ϕ dµ(τ ) ≤ α P 2 ||c|| 2(73)andt0+T0 t0 |P ξ (Z(τ )) T c| 2 dµ(τ ) ≥ t0+T0 t0 |ϕ(Z(τ )) T c| 2 φ2 u dµ(τ ) ≥ α P 1 ||c|| 2 (74) with α P 1 = α 1 / φ2 u , α P 2 = α 2 /ϕ 2 u .Therefore, from (73) and (74), we have that for every constant vector c ∈ R L ,α P 1 ||c|| 2 ≤ t0+T0 t0 |P ξ (Z(τ )) T c| 2 dµ(τ ) ≤ α P 2 ||c|| 2 (75)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Adaptive Fuzzy Control for Robot Arm I Robot Controller Robotic Arm 1 Dual Arm Robot System FT Kinematic Learning Fuzzy Logic System Common Object</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Trajectory 𝒙𝒙𝒅𝒅, ẋ𝒙𝒅𝒅</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>𝝉𝝉 𝟏𝟏</cell><cell></cell><cell>𝑞𝑞1, q𝑞1, 𝑓𝑓1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ẋ𝑥1 , q𝑞1 , 𝑓𝑓 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>𝑥𝑥, ẋ𝑥</cell></row><row><cell>𝑧𝑧 1 , 𝑓𝑓 1</cell><cell>Stable</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Filter</cell><cell>𝝉𝝉 𝟐𝟐</cell><cell>Robotic Arm 2</cell><cell>𝑞𝑞2, q𝑞2, 𝑓𝑓2</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">𝑒𝑒 𝑞𝑞1 , 𝑧𝑧 1 , 𝜏𝜏 1</cell><cell>Adaptive FLS</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Weights Learning</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was partially supported by National Nature Science Foundation (NSFC) under Grant 61473120, 61573174, 61633016 and 61811530281, Science and Technology Planning Project of Guangzhou 201607010006, State Key Laboratory of Robotics and System (HIT) Grant SKLRS-2017-KF-13, the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities 2017ZD057, the Research Fund for Young Top-Notch Talent of National Ten Thousand Talent Program, the Beijing Municipal Natural Science Foundation under Grant 4162066, and the Major Science and Technology Project of Beijing under Grant Z181100003118006.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An adaptive control scheme for coordinated multimanipulator systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-H</forename><surname>Jean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L.-C</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="231" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Robotics and Automation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control of two industrial manipulators rigidly holding an egg</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-H</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Schutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Control Systems, IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control of upper-limb power-assist exoskeleton using a human-robot interface based on motion intention recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Huo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mohammed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Amirat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1257" to="1270" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teleoperation control based on combination of wave variable and neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-Y</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics: Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2125" to="2136" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haptic identification by elm-controlled uncertain manipulator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-Y</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics: Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2398" to="2409" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized adaptive and nonadaptive position/force controllers for redundant manipulators in cooperations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of Robotics Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive robust fuzzy control for dual arm robot with unknown input deadzone nonlinearity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nonlinear Dynamics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1301" to="1314" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicriteria optimization for coordination of redundant robots using a dual neural network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-G</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Systems, Man, and Cybernetics, Part B: Cybernetics, IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1075" to="1087" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized robust adaptive control for the multiagent system consensus problem using neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-G</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Systems, Man, and Cybernetics, Part B: Cybernetics, IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="636" to="647" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural control of bimanual robots with guaranteed global stability and motion precision</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-Y</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1162" to="1171" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive neural control for dual-arm coordination of humanoid robot with unknown nonlinearities in output mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="518" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cybernetics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive neural network tracking control for manipulators with uncertain kinematics, dynamics and actuator model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-G</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2312" to="2318" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive vision and force tracking control for robots with constraint uncertainty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cheah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J E</forename><surname>Slotine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mechatronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="399" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-06">June 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate jacobian control for robots with uncertain kinematics and dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cheah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hirano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kawamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Robotics and Automation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="692" to="702" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-08">Aug 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive jacobian tracking control of robots with uncertainties in kinematic, dynamic and actuator models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Cheah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Slotine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1024" to="1029" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Automatic Control</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust model-based online fault detection for mating process of electric connectors in robotic wiring harness assembly systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Di</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fukuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsuno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Control Systems Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1207" to="1215" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximation-free control for vehicle active suspensions with hydraulic actuator</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive neural impedance control of a robotic manipulator with input saturation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics: Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="334" to="344" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-03">March 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Active adaptive estimation and control for vehicle suspensions with prescribed performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Control Systems Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Actuator backlash compensation and accurate parameter estimation for active vibration isolation system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L P</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1643" to="1654" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-03">March 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based intelligent fault detection and diagnosis for mating electric connectors in robotic wiring harness assembly systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fukuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsuno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mechatronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive nonlinear crane control with load hoisting/lowering and unknown parameters: Design and experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mechatronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new antiswing control method for underactuated cranes with unmodeled uncertainties: Theoretical design and hardware experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="453" to="465" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interface design of a physical human-robot interaction system for human impedance adaptive skill transfer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-Y</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct adaptive fuzzy control of nonlinear strict-feedback systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0005109809000946" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1530" to="1535" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Posture estimation and human support using wearable sensors and walking-aid robot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mohammed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Robotics and Autonomous Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy approximation-based adaptive backstepping optimal control for a class of nonlinear discrete-time systems with dead-zone</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct adaptive fuzzy tracking control of marine vehicles with fully unknown parametric dynamics and uncertainties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Control Systems Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive robust online constructive fuzzy control of a complex surface vehicle system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Er</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interval type-2 fuzzy logic modeling and control of a mobile two-wheeled inverted pendulum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy neural network-based adaptive control for a class of uncertain nonlinear stochastic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L P</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="593" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive fuzzy output tracking control for a class of uncertain nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-C</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0165011408005836" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuzzy Sets and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2727" to="2754" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized robust fuzzy adaptive control of humanoid robot manipulation with unknown actuator backlash</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="605" to="616" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finite-time parameter estimation in adaptive control of nonlinear systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Adetola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Guay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="807" to="811" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Composite adaptive control for eulerclagrange systems with additive disturbances</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Patre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mackunis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Automatica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="140" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust adaptive finite-time parameter estimation and control for robotic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Mahyuddin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Barber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Robust and Nonlinear Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3045" to="3071" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Online adaptive optimal control for continuous-time nonlinear systems with completely unknown dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving transient performance of adaptive control via a modified reference model and novel adaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Robust and Nonlinear Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1351" to="1372" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Deterministic learning theory for identification, recognition, and control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel hybrid adaptive controller for manipulation in complex perturbation environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Culverhouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cangelosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Burdet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plos One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deterministic learning and rapid dynamical pattern recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="617" to="630" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural learning control of marine surface vessels with guaranteed transient tracking performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1717" to="1727" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-03">March 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid detection of small oscillation faults via deterministic learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1284" to="1296" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive observer-based parameter estimation with application to road gradient and vehicle mass estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Mahyuddin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Barber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2851" to="2863" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chenguang Yang (M&apos;10-SM&apos;16) received the B.Eng. degree in measurement and control from Northwestern Polytechnical University</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carnigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Yang was a recipient of the Best Paper Award in the IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON ROBOTICS and a number of international conferences. Yiming Jiang received the B.S. degree in automation from the Hunan University</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London, U.K; Changsha, China; Guangzhou, China; Guangzhou, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990. 1990. 2010. 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2083" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Guangdong University of Technology ; South China University of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>His research interests include robotics, intelligent control and human-robot interaction</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
