<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">IMAGE RESTORATION: WAVELET FRAME SHRINKAGE, NONLINEAR EVOLUTION PDES, AND BEYOND *</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-03-30">March 30, 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bin</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
							<email>dongbin@math.pku.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Corresponding author. Beijing International Center for Mathematical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Peking Univer-sity</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100871</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Qingtang</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
							<email>jiangq@umsl.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Missouri-St. Louis</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63121</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zuowei</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National University of Singapore</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>10 Lower Kent Ridge Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>119076</postCode>
									<settlement>Singapore</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">IMAGE RESTORATION: WAVELET FRAME SHRINKAGE, NONLINEAR EVOLUTION PDES, AND BEYOND *</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-03-30">March 30, 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">13D7BABFCD4566725297E13D5965BCAD</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1137/15M1037457</idno>
					<note type="submission">* Received by the editors August 31, 2015; accepted for publication (in revised form) January 6, 2017;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T15:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>image restoration</term>
					<term>nonlinear diffusion</term>
					<term>wavelet frames</term>
					<term>wavelet frame shrinkage AMS subject classifications. 35A15</term>
					<term>42C40</term>
					<term>45Q05</term>
					<term>65K10</term>
					<term>68U10</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In the past few decades, mathematics based approaches have been widely adopted in various image restoration problems; the partial differential equation (PDE) based approach (e.g., the total variation model [L.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>and the PDE based approach quite often end up solving a similar numerical problem, and their numerical behaviors are often comparable, although different approaches have advantages in different applications. Since all these different approaches are modeling the same type of problem with success, it is natural to ask whether the wavelet frame based approach is fundamentally connected with PDE methods when we trace them all the way back to their roots. A fundamental connection between a wavelet frame based approach and a general variation model (with TV model <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[55]</ref> as a special case) was established in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref>. It was shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref> that a special type of wavelet frame model using generic wavelet frame systems can be regarded as an approximation of the variational model in the discrete setting.</p><p>Motivated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[46]</ref>, this paper establishes a fundamental connection between wavelet frame shrinkage and nonlinear evolution PDEs, provides interpretations and analytical studies of this connection, and proposes new algorithms for image restoration based on the new understandings. This connection automatically gives the wavelet frame based approach a geometric explanation through nonlinear PDEs, and, at the same time, it equips the PDE based approach with a time frequency analysis by the nature of the two approaches. Together with the results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref>, we now have a better picture of how the wavelet frame based approach can be used to interpret the general PDE based approach and how it can be used as a new and useful tool in numerical analysis to discretize and solve various variational and PDE models. Some earlier results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[64,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">65,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">66]</ref> showed the correspondence between Haar wavelet shrinkage and second-order nonlinear diffusions. This work was recently generalized to wavelet frame shrinkage and higher order nonlinear diffusions for the one-dimensional case in <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[46]</ref>. However, it is not clear how two-dimensional (2D) wavelet frame shrinkage can be related to nonlinear PDEs. Can we theoretically justify such a connection? Furthermore, can we observe something new and something we could not see without establishing a relation between them? These important questions have yet to be answered. As we will see, this fundamental connection between wavelet based shrinkage and nonlinear evolution PDEs provides answers to all these questions.</p><p>The key idea of the wavelet frame based approach is to apply shrinkage (especially soft-thresholding) to wavelet frame coefficients iteratively, so that it converges to an optimal solution of some objective functional. The bridge between the wavelet frame based approach and the PDE based approach is established when we see that a proper choice of numerical scheme of solving nonlinear evolution PDEs can be viewed as applying a properly chosen shrinkage operator on wavelet frame coefficients iteratively. Corresponding optimal properties are also discussed. Furthermore, the asymptotic analysis, i.e., when the image resolution goes to infinity, will be given for a few important cases. The connection between the wavelet frame based and PDE based approaches will become clear once we show the following.</p><p>First, we show that we can approximate a generic nonlinear evolution PDE (of parabolic or hyperbolic type) using iterative (discrete) wavelet frame shrinkage by properly choosing the underlying wavelet frame systems and carefully designing the associated shrinkage operator. Such a nonlinear evolution PDE includes the nonlinear parabolic equation called the Perona-Malik (PM) equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref>, the nonlinear hyperbolic equation known as the Osher-Rudin shock filter <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[50]</ref>, and many others as examples. Our key observations are the connections between the (discrete) wavelet frame decomposition and differential operators (that were observed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref>), and between the (discrete) wavelet frame reconstruction and divergence operators. The approximations by wavelet frame transforms is fundamentally different from the widely used finite difference approximation and the well-known wavelet Galerkin methods, in that Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php a discrete approximation to nonlinear evolution PDEs in a rather general setting. Differences between our approach and some existing numerical methods for PDEs, such as finite difference methods and wavelet Galerkin methods, are discussed at the end of section 2. Generic connections between wavelet frame shrinkage and nonlinear evolution PDEs are established in section 3. In section 3.1, we start with generic derivations for the correspondence of wavelet frame shrinkage to nonlinear diffusion equations. We will show how the commonly used PDE models for image restoration can be derived from iterative shrinkage of wavelet frame coefficients. In section 3.2, we present some new high order diffusion equations that correspond to the B-spline tight wavelet frame systems which are commonly used in image restoration. In the same section, we also study the rotation-invariant high order diffusion equation and its associated frame filter banks. In section 3.3, we show that some of the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithms, i.e., iterative soft-thresholding, commonly used in image restoration lead to new nonlinear diffusion equations. We also discuss how we can borrow the idea of anisotropy of the PM nonlinear diffusion to design new iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithms which are adaptive to local image features. In section 4, we prove the convergence of the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm to the solution of a second-order nonlinear diffusion equation as mesh-size goes to zero. We also address stability and convergence of generic iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithms. Finally, numerical experiments are presented in section 5.</p><p>2. Preliminaries and main ideas. This section starts with an overview of wavelet frames, including some basic concepts of wavelet frames such as vanishing moments, and generic iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithms. Then, we provide some of the general ideas of how wavelet frame shrinkage algorithms can be regarded as discrete approximations to nonlinear evolution PDEs. Finally, we point out the fundamental differences between the wavelet frame based approach to solving nonlinear evolution PDEs and the existing methods such as finite difference methods and wavelet Galerkin methods, especially in the context of image restoration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Review of wavelet frames.</head><p>In this subsection, we first briefly introduce the concept of wavelet frames. The interested reader should consult <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">22]</ref> for theories of frames and wavelet frames, <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[56]</ref> for a short survey on the theory and applications of frames, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[31]</ref> for a more detailed survey.</p><p>A set X = {g j : j</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">∈ Z} ⊂ L 2 (R d ), with d ∈ N, is called a frame of L 2 (R d ) if A f 2 L2(R d ) ≤ j∈Z | f, g j | 2 ≤ B f 2 L2(R d ) for all f ∈ L 2 (R d ),</formula><p>where •, • is the inner product of L 2 (R d ). We call X a tight frame if it is a frame with A = B = 1. For any given frame X of L 2 (R d ), there exists another frame</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">X = { g j : j ∈ Z} of L 2 (R d ) such that f = j∈Z f, g j g j for all f ∈ L 2 (R d ).</formula><p>We call X a dual frame of X. We shall call the pair (X, X) bi-frames. For given Ψ := {ψ 1 , . . . , ψ L } ⊂ L 2 (R d ), the corresponding quasi-affine system X(Ψ) generated by Ψ is defined by the collection of the dilations and the shifts of Ψ as (2.1) X(Ψ) = {ψ ,n,k : 1 ≤ ≤ L; n ∈ Z, k ∈ Z d }, Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php When X(Ψ) forms a (tight) frame of L 2 (R d ), each function ψ , = 1, . . . , L, is called a (tight) framelet, and the whole system X(Ψ) is called a (tight) wavelet frame system.</p><p>The construction of framelets Ψ is usually based on a multiresolution analysis (MRA) that is generated by some refinable function φ with refinement mask p ∈ 2 (Z d ) and its dual MRA generated by φ with refinement mask p ∈ 2 (Z d ) satisfying</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">φ = 2 d k∈Z d p[k]φ(2 • -k) and φ = 2 d k∈Z d p[k] φ(2 • -k).</formula><p>The idea of an MRA based construction of bi-framelets Ψ = {ψ 1 , . . . , ψ L } and Ψ = { ψ 1 , . . . , ψ L } is to find masks q ( ) and q( ) , which are finite sequences on Z d , such that, for = 1, 2, . . . , L,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(2.2) ψ = 2 d k∈Z d q ( ) [k]φ(2 • -k) and ψ = 2 d k∈Z d q ( ) [k] φ(2 • -k).</formula><p>For a sequence {p[k]} k∈Z 2 of real numbers, we use p(ω) to denote its (two-scale) symbol (it is also called a filter here):</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">p(ω) = k∈Z 2 p[k]e -ikω .</formula><p>When p is a sequence with finitely many nonzero terms, its corresponding two-scale symbol p(ω) is a trigonometric polynomial, and we shall call it a finite impulse response (FIR) filter.</p><p>The mixed extension principle (MEP) of <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[54]</ref> provides a general theory of the construction of MRA based wavelet bi-frames. Given two sets of FIR filters {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q(1) , . . . , q(L) }, the MEP says that as long as we have <ref type="bibr">(2.3)</ref> p(ω) p(ω)+ L =1 q ( ) (ω) q ( ) (ω) = 1 and p(ω) p(ω + ν)+ L =1 q ( ) (ω) q ( ) (ω + ν) = 0 for all ν ∈ {0, π} d \ {0} and ω ∈ [-π, π] d , the quasi-affine systems X(Ψ) and X( Ψ) with Ψ and Ψ given by (2.2) form a pair of bi-frames in L 2 (R d ). In particular, when p = p and q ( ) = q ( ) for = 1, . . . , L, the MEP (2.3) becomes the following unitary extension principle (UEP) discovered in <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[53]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(2.4) | p(ω)| 2 + L =1</formula><p>| q ( ) (ω)| 2 = 1 and p(ω) p(ω + ν)+ L =1 q ( ) (ω) q ( ) (ω + ν) = 0, and the system X(Ψ) is a tight frame of L 2 (R d ). We call {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } a pair of bi-frame filter banks if they satisfy <ref type="bibr">(2.3)</ref>. p is called the lowpass filter, and q ( ) , q ( ) are called the highpass filters. If {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } satisfies (2.4), then it is called a tight frame filter bank. Note that some of the filter banks we use in later sections only satisfy the first identity of (2.3) or <ref type="bibr">(2.4)</ref>, and they shall be Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN called undecimated bi-frame filter banks or undecimated tight frame filter banks. In this case the system generated by the functions associated to these filters does not form a frame or tight frame for L 2 (R d ). However, these filters do form frames or tight frames (undecimated) for sequence space 2 (Z d ). Since image data are elements in In the discrete setting, let an image f be a d-dimensional array. We denote by</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">I d := R N1×N2×•••×N d the</formula><p>set of all d-dimensional images. We will further assume that all images are square images, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">N 1 = N 2 = • • • = N d = N ,</formula><p>and they all have supports in the open unit d-dimensional cube Ω = (0, 1) d . For simplicity, we will focus on d = 2 throughout the rest of this paper. We denote the 2D fast Lev-level wavelet frame transform/decomposition with {q (0) , q (1) , . . . , q (L) } (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[31]</ref>) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">(2.5) W u = {W l, u : 0 ≤ l ≤ Lev -1, 0 ≤ ≤ L}, u ∈ I 2 .</formula><p>We will mostly consider the case Lev = 1 in this paper, and, in that case, W = W 0, . However, all results we have can be generalized to Lev &gt; 1 without much difficulty.</p><p>In some of our analytical results and numerical experiments, we also use multilevel wavelet frame decomposition for better image restoration quality. The fast wavelet frame transform W is a linear operator with W l, u ∈ I 2 denoting the frame coefficients of u at level l and band . Furthermore, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">W l, u := q l, [-•] u,</formula><p>where denotes the convolution operator with a certain boundary condition, e.g., periodic boundary condition, and q l, is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">(2.6) q l, = ql, ql-1,0 • • • q0,0 with ql, [k] = q [2 -l k], k ∈ 2 l Z 2 , 0, k / ∈ 2 l Z 2 .</formula><p>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php Notice that q 0, = q , and we let q 0 = p for convenience. Similarly, we can define W u and W l, u. We denote the inverse wavelet frame transform (or wavelet frame reconstruction) as W , which is the adjoint operator of W , and by the MEP, we have the perfect reconstruction formula</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">(2.7) u = W W u for all u ∈ I 2 .</formula><p>In particular, when W is the transform for a tight frame system, the UEP gives us u = W W u for all u ∈ I 2 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Vanishing moments.</head><p>The concept of vanishing moments of wavelet frames and their associated FIR filters is closely related to the orders of differential operators and their corresponding finite difference operators. The correspondence between the vanishing moments of wavelet frames and the orders of differential operators was crucial to the analysis of <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref>. In this subsection, a key observation, which is given in Lemma 2.3, is the connection between the vanishing moments of FIR filters and the order of finite difference operators (and the orders of approximation as well).</p><p>For an FIR highpass filter q, let q(ω) = k∈Z 2 q[k]e -ikω be its two-scale symbol. Throughout this paper, for a multi-index α</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">= (α 1 , α 2 ) ∈ Z 2 + and ω ∈ R 2 , denote α! = α 1 !α 2 !, |α| = α 1 + α 2 , ∂ α ∂ω α = ∂ α1+α2 ∂ω α2 2 ∂ω α1 1 .</formula><p>We say q (and q(ω)) have vanishing moments of order α = (α 1 , α 2 ), where α ∈ Z<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> + , provided that</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">k∈Z 2 k β q[k] = i |β| ∂ β ∂ω β q(ω) ω=0 = 0</formula><p>for all β ∈ Z 2 + with |β| &lt; |α| and for all β ∈ Z 2 + with |β| = |α| but β = α. By convention, we say that q has the vanishing moment of order (0, 0) if k q[k] = 0. We also say q has total vanishing moments of order</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">K with K ∈ Z + if (2.8) k∈Z 2 k β q[k] = i |β| ∂ β ∂ω β q(ω) ω=0 = 0 for all β ∈ Z 2 + with |β| &lt; K. Suppose K ≥ 1. If (2.8) holds for all β ∈ Z 2 + with |β| &lt; K except for β = β 0 with certain β 0 ∈ Z 2</formula><p>+ and |β 0 | = J &lt; K, then we say q has total vanishing moments of order K\{J + 1}.</p><p>Clearly, if q has vanishing moments of order α, then it has total vanishing moments of order at least |α|, and it has total vanishing moments of order K\{|α| + 1} with</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">K ≥ |α| + 1. It is obvious that if k1∈Z k β1 1 q[k 1 , k 2 ] = 0 for all 0 ≤ β 1 &lt; α 1 , k 2 ∈ Z, and k2∈Z k β2 2 q[k 1 , k 2 ] = 0 for all 0 ≤ β 2 &lt; α 2 , k 1 ∈ Z,</formula><p>then q has vanishing moments of order α = (α 1 , α 2 ). To have a better understanding of the concept of vanishing moments, let us look at two examples.</p><p>Let q 1 (ω) = e iω1 -e -iω1 . Then</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">q 1 (0) = 0, ∂ ∂ω 1 q 1 (0) = 2i = 0, ∂ ∂ω 2 q 1 (0) = 0.</formula><p>Thus q 1 (ω) has vanishing moments of order (1, 0). In addition, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">∂ 2 ∂ω 2 1 q 1 (0) = 0, ∂ 2 ∂ω 1 ∂ω 2 q 1 (0) = 0, ∂ 2 ∂ω 2</formula><p>BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN Therefore, q 1 has total vanishing moments of order 3\{|(1, 0)| + 1}, or 3\{2} (it does not have total vanishing moments of order 4\{2} since</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">∂ 3 ∂ω 3 1 q 1 (0) = -2i = 0).</formula><p>Let q 2 (ω) = (e iω1 -e -iω1 )(1 -e -iω2 ) 2 . Then ∂ β ∂ω β q 2 (0) = 0 for |β| &lt; 3 and β = (3, 0), (2, 1), (0, 3), and ∂ 3 ∂ω1∂ω 2 2 q 2 (0) = -4i = 0. Thus q 2 has vanishing moments of order (1, 2). Observe that ∂ 4 ∂ω1∂ω 3 2 q 2 (0) = -4 = 0. Therefore, q 2 has total vanishing moments of order 4\{4} (instead of 5 \ {4}).</p><p>Lemma 2.3. Let q be an FIR highpass filter with vanishing moments of order α ∈ Z 2 + . Then for a smooth function F (x) on R 2 , we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">1 ε |α| k∈Z 2 q[k]F (x + εk) = C α ∂ α ∂x α F (x) + O(ε) as ε → 0, (2.9)</formula><p>where C α is the constant defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">(2.10) C α = 1 α! k∈Z 2 k α q[k] = i |α| α! ∂ α ∂ω α q(ω) ω=0 .</formula><p>If, in addition, q has total vanishing moments of order K\{|α|+1} for some K &gt; |α|, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">1 ε |α| k∈Z 2 q[k]F (x + εk) = C α ∂ α ∂x α F (x) + O(ε K-|α| ) as ε → 0. (2.11)</formula><p>Proof. The proof is by straightforward calculation based on Taylor's expansion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Wavelet frame filter banks.</head><p>For any nonlinear evolution PDE considered in this paper, we can simply use the filter bank of one of the tensor-product B-spline wavelet frame systems constructed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[53]</ref>, as long as the highest order of vanishing moments of the highpass filters is no lower than half of the order of the PDE. All we need to do is choose appropriate parameters for each of the highpass filters such that the ones that are inactive in the given PDE, i.e. the filters whose associated differential operators do not appear in the PDE, converge to zero asymptotically. One may also simply set those parameters to zero. However, choosing a parameter that asymptotically goes to zero sometimes leads to better image restoration results. This idea first appeared in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref>. We will also present some specific choices of the parameters associated to the inactive highpass filters in Corollaries 3.3 and 3.7. Numerical examples showing the benefit of having inactive highpass filters in the filter bank are given in section 5.</p><p>However, using B-spline type filter banks for all nonlinear evolution PDEs may not always be efficient, especially when we have too many inactive filters. We need to compute the decomposition transform associated to those inactive filters in any case; otherwise the first identity of (2.3) is violated, and we will not have the perfect reconstruction (2.7). In some applications, when image quality is less of a concern than computation efficiency, it is desirable to specifically construct a filter bank for a given PDE that has as few filters as possible. Therefore, we list some of the FIR filter banks that will be used in later sections. As we will see, these filters can be used to Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php discretize different types of nonlinear evolution PDEs, especially nonlinear diffusion equations.</p><p>Let {a, b (1) , b (2) } be a piecewise linear B-spline tight frame filter bank of <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[53]</ref> (given by Example 2.2):</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">a(ω) = 1 2 + 1 4 (e -iω + e iω ) = 1 4 e iω (1 + e -iω ) 2 , b (1) (ω) = √ 2 4 (e iω -e -iω ), b (2) (ω) = 1 2 - 1 4 (e -iω + e iω ) = 1 4 e iω (1 -e -iω ) 2 .</formula><p>(2.12)</p><p>By the tensor product, we can construct the separable 2D piecewise linear B-spline tight frame filter bank from (2.12), which is commonly used in image denoising, image inpainting, and other areas. We note that all filter banks in this subsection except for (2.14) are undecimated bi-frame or tight frame filter banks, which means they only satisfy the first equation of (2.3) or (2.4).</p><p>Example 2.4. Let a, b (1) , and b (2) be given as in <ref type="bibr">(2.12)</ref>. The separable 2D piecewise linear B-spline tight frame filter bank p, q (1) , . . . , q (8) , with ω = (ω 1 , ω 2 ), is given by (2.13)</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">p(ω) = a(ω 1 ) a(ω 2 ), q (1) (ω) = b (1) (ω 1 ) a(ω 2 ), q (2) (ω) = a(ω 1 ) b (1) (ω 2 ), q (3) (ω) = b (2) (ω 1 ) a(ω 2 ), q (4) (ω) = b (1) (ω 1 ) b (1) (ω 2 ), q (5) (ω) = a(ω 1 ) b (2) (ω 2 ), q (6) (ω) = b (2) (ω 1 ) b (1) (ω 2 ), q (7) (ω) = b (1) (ω 1 ) b (2) (ω 2 ), q (8) (ω) = b (2) (ω 1 ) b (2) (ω 2 ).</formula><p>It is straightforward to obtain the following orders of vanishing moments of q (1) , . . . , q (8) : β1 = (1, 0), β2 = (0, 1), β3 = (2, 0), β4 = (1, 1), β5 = (0, 2), β6 = (2, 1), β7 = (1, 2), β8 = (2, 2). These filters will be used to discretize nonlinear diffusion equation <ref type="bibr">(3.28)</ref>.</p><p>We can construct a type of tight frame filter bank similar to (2.14) with fewer highpass filters.</p><p>Example 2.5. Let a be given in <ref type="bibr">(2.12)</ref>. A separable 2D piecewise linear B-spline tight frame filter bank with fewer highpass filters is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">p(ω) = a(ω1) a(ω2), q (1) (ω) = √ 2 16 e iω 1 -e -iω 1 1 + e -iω 2 2 e iω 2 , q (2) (ω) = √ 2 8 e iω 1 + e -iω 1 e iω 2 -e -iω 2 , q (3) (ω) = 1 16 1 -e -iω 1 2 1 + e -iω 2 2 e iω 1 e iω 2 , q (4) (ω) = √ 2 8 e iω 1 -e -iω 1 e iω 2 -e -iω 2 , q (5) (ω) = 1 4 1 -e -iω 2 2 e iω 2 .</formula><p>(2.14)</p><p>These filters will be used to discretize nonlinear diffusion equations (3.31) and <ref type="bibr">(3.32)</ref>.</p><p>Furthermore, we can construct tight frame filter banks which result in the rotationinvariant diffusion equations of arbitrary orders.</p><p>Example 2.6. The lowpass and highpass filters are given, respectively, by <ref type="bibr">(2.15</ref>) </p><formula xml:id="formula_25">p(ω) = 1 2 2m 1 + e -iω1 m 1 + e -iω2 m e i[m/2](ω1+ω2) , m ≥ 1,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">(s,k) (ω) (2.16) = 1 2 2m-k m s s k e i[ m-k 2 ]ω1 e i[m/2]ω2 1 + e -iω1 m-s 1 + e -iω2 m-k • 1 -e -iω1 s-k 1 -e -iω2 k .</formula><p>These filters will be used to discretize the rotation-invariant nonlinear diffusion equation <ref type="bibr">(3.37)</ref>. Now, we present filter banks that will be used for the diffusion equations of the PM and TV models, image inpainting diffusion, and shock filtering.</p><p>Example 2.7. The following bi-frame filter bank is constructed for the PM diffusion (3.20):</p><p>(2.17)</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">       p(ω) = p(ω) = 1 4 1 + e -iω1 1 + e -iω2 , q (1) (ω) = 1 2 1 -e -iω1 , q<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_28">(ω) = 1 16 1 -e -iω1 6 + e iω2 + e -iω2 , q (2) (ω) = 1 2 1 -e -iω2 , q<label>(2)</label></formula><p>(ω) = 1 16 1 -e -iω2 6 + e iω1 + e -iω1 . Example 2.8. The following bi-frame filter bank is constructed for the image inpainting diffusion (3.23):</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">(2.18)            p(ω) = p(ω) = 1 4 (1 + e -iω 1 )(1 + e -iω 2 ), q (1) (ω) = 1 2 (1 -e -iω 1 ), q (2) (ω) = -1 2 (1 -e -iω 2 ), q (3) (ω) = -1 32 (1 -e -iω 1 ) 2 e iω 1 (6 + e -iω 2 + e iω 2 ), q (4) (ω) = -1 32 (1 -e -iω 2</formula><p>) 2 e iω 2 (6 + e -iω 1 + e iω 1 ), q</p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">(ω) = 1 2 (e iω 2 -1), q<label>(2)</label></formula><p>(ω) = 1 2 (e iω 1 -1), q</p><p>(ω) = q (4)</p><p>(ω) = 1.</p><p>Example 2.9. The following bi-frame filter bank is constructed for the nonlinear hyperbolic equation of shock filters (3.27):</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">(2.19)                      p(ω) = p(ω) = 1 16 (1 + e -iω 1 ) 2 (1 + e -iω 2 ) 2 e iω 1 e iω 2 , q (1) (ω) = 1 8 (e iω 1 -e -iω 1 )(1 + e -iω 2 ) 2 e iω 2 , q (2) (ω) = 1 8 (e iω 2 -e -iω 2 )(1 + e -iω 1 ) 2 e iω 1 , q (3) (ω) = -1 32 (1 -e -iω 1</formula><p>) 2 e iω 1 (6 + e -iω 2 + e iω 2 ), q (4) (ω) = -1 32 (1 -e -iω 2 ) 2 e iω 2 (6 + e -iω 1 + e iω 1 ), q</p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">(ω) = 1</formula><p>64 (e iω 1 -e -iω 1 )(6 + e -iω 2 + e iω 2 ), q</p><p>(ω) = 1 64 (e iω 2 -e -iω 2 )(6 + e -iω 1 + e iω 1 ), q</p><p>(3)</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">(ω) = q (4) (ω) = 1.</formula><p>Finally, we note that the filter bank that can be used to discretize a given PDE is not uniquely determined, even though we do not allow inactive highpass filters in the filter bank. For example, other than (2.18), we can use the following filter bank for the image inpainting diffusion (3.23):</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">p(ω) = p(ω) = 1 16 (1 + e -iω 1 ) 2 (1 + e -iω 2 ) 2 e iω 1 e iω 2 , q (1) (ω) = 1 2 (e iω 1 -e -iω 1 ), q (2) (ω) = - 1 2 (e iω 2 -e -iω 2 ), q (3) (ω) = - 1 512</formula><p>(1 -e -iω 1 ) 2 e iω 1 (6 + e -iω 1 + e iω 1 )(22 + 4e -iω 2 + 4e iω 2 + e -i2ω 2 + e i2ω 2 ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">q (4) (ω) = - 1 512</formula><p>(1 -e -iω 2 ) 2 e iω 2 (6 + e -iω 2 + e iω 2 )(22 + 4e -iω 1 + 4e iω 1 + e -i2ω 1 + e i2ω 1 ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">q (1) (ω) = 1 2 (e iω 2 -e -iω 2 ), q<label>(2)</label></formula><p>(ω) = 1 2 (e iω 1 -e -iω 1 ), q</p><p>(ω) = q (4)</p><p>(ω) = 1. 2.4. Iterative wavelet frame shrinkage. Iterative wavelet frame shrinkage (especially soft-and hard-thresholding) is the key ingredient of the wavelet frame based approach for image restoration in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b73">70,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">28]</ref>. In this section, we review the formula for more general iterative wavelet frame shrinkage, which goes beyond soft-and hard-thresholding, and rewrite it in a compact form that will be repeatedly used in later sections.</p><p>Let {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } be a pair of FIR filters that satisfy the first equation of (2.3). Let {u 0 j } j∈Z 2 be the initial data. The (one-level) wavelet frame transform based denoising consists of the following processes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">L n = j∈Z 2 p[j]u 0 j+n , H ( ) n = j∈Z 2 q ( ) [j]u 0 j+n , n ∈ Z 2 , 1 ≤ ≤ L, u 1 j = n∈Z 2 p[j -n]L n + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n]S (H ( ) n ), j ∈ Z 2 ,<label>(2.20)</label></formula><p>where S , 1 ≤ ≤ L, are the shrinkage functions. The first step in (2.20) is called the analysis process, and the second is called the synthesis process after shrinkage.</p><p>L n and H ( ) n are the lowpass and highpass outputs of u 0 . The shrinkage functions we consider in this paper are not limited to the well-known soft-thresholding that is frequently used in image restoration. As we shall see in later sections, different shrinkage operators will correspond to different PDEs. Proposition 2.10. Let {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } be a pair of biframe filter banks, and let u 1 j be the resulting signal given by (2.20) after one-step frame shrinkage of u 0 j with these filter banks. Then</p><p>(2.21)</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">u 1 j = u 0 j + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n] S (ξ) -ξ ξ=H ( ) n , j ∈ Z 2 ,</formula><p>where H</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">( )</formula><p>n is defined by (2.20). Proof. Since {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } satisfy the first equation of (2.3), u 0 j can be recovered from the synthesis algorithm (2.20) with S (ξ) = ξ, namely,</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">u 0 j = n∈Z 2 p[j -n]L n + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n]H ( ) n , j ∈ Z 2 .</formula><p>Thus, The frame shrinkage process (2.20) can be applied iteratively:</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">u 1 j = n∈Z 2 p[j -n]L n + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n]S (H ( ) n ) = u 0 j - L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n]H ( ) n + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n]S (H ( ) n ) = u 0 j + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n] S (ξ) -ξ ξ=H ( ) n , j ∈ Z 2 .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_45">H ( ),k-1 n = j∈Z 2 q ( ) [j]u k-1 j+n , 1 ≤ ≤ L; u k j = u k-1 j + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n] S (H ( ),k-1 n ) -H ( ),k-1 n , k = 1, 2, . . . .<label>(2.22)</label></formula><p>In this paper we will also consider the channel-mixed frame shrinkage (coupled frame shrinkage):</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">(2.23) u 1 j = n∈Z 2 p[j -n]L n + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n]S (H (1) n , H (2) n , . . . , H (L) n ), j ∈ Z 2 ,</formula><p>where S , 1 ≤ ≤ L, n ∈ Z 2 are functions of several variables. If u 1 j , j ∈ Z 2 , are given by (2.23) after channel-mixed shrinkage, then one can obtain similarly to the proof of Proposition 2.10 that</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">(2.24) u 1 j = u 0 j + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n] S (H (1) n , H (2) n , . . . , H (L) n ) -H ( ) n , j ∈ Z 2 .</formula><p>The channel-mixed frame shrinkage process can also be applied iteratively:</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">H ( ),k-1 n = j∈Z 2 q ( ) [j]u k-1 j+n , 1 ≤ ≤ L, u k j = u k-1 j + L =1 n∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -n] S (H (1),k-1 n , . . . , H (L),k-1 n ) -H ( ),k-1 n , k = 1, 2, . . . .<label>(2.25)</label></formula><p>Although the choice of shrinking functions S can be general, they need to be meaningfully chosen. In this paper, we will focus on a few specific shrinkage operators which are closed-form solutions of certain optimization problems. Next, we rewrite (2.22) and (2.25) in operator form. Let W u =: d be the wavelet frame decomposition of u defined by (2.5), and let W d be the reconstruction operator using a duel wavelet frame. We have W W = I. For simplicity, we assume the level of decomposition is 1, i.e., Lev = 1 in (2.5). For a given wavelet frame</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">coefficient d = {d ,n : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L} and threshold α(d) = {α ,n (d) : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L}, define the multiplicative shrinkage operator S α (d) as (2.26) S α (d) = {S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n (1 -α ,n (d)) : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L}. Note that S α ,n (d ,n ) in (2.26) denotes (S α (d))</formula><p>,n , whose value may depend on more values than merely d ,n (see, e.g., (3.17)). Similarly, we denote the anisotropic and isotropic soft-thresholding operators as T 1 α and T 2 α , respectively, where (2.27)</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">T 1 α (d) = T 1 α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n |d ,n | max{|d ,n | -α ,n (d), 0} : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L and</formula><p>(2.28) </p><formula xml:id="formula_51">T 2 α (d) = T 2 α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n R ,n max R ,n -α ,n (d), 0 : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">u k = W S α k-1 (W u k-1 ), k = 1, 2, . . . ,</formula><p>which shall be referred to as the iterative multiplicative wavelet frame shrinkage (algorithm), and</p><p>(2.30)</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">u k = W T ℘ α k-1 (W u k-1 ), k = 1, 2, . . . , ℘ = 1, 2,</formula><p>which shall be referred to as the iterative (anisotropic/isotropic) wavelet frame softthresholding (algorithm). Here, Consider the quadratic optimization problem</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">α k-1 = {α ,n (d k-1 ) : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L} with d k-1 = W u k-1 .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_55">min d 1 2 d -W u 2 2 + 1 2 α 1 -α • d 2 2</formula><p>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">where d = {d ,n : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L} and α 1-α • d := { α ,n 1-α ,n d ,n : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L}. We first observe that S α (W u) = arg min d 1 2 d -W u 2 2 + 1 2 α 1 -α • d 2 2</formula><p>, which is easy to derive by simple differentiation. Also, we have (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">8]</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">T ℘ α (W u) = arg min d 1 2 d -W u 2 2 + α • d 1,℘ , ℘ = 1, 2,</formula><p>where α When we have a tight frame system, i.e., W = W , by [9, Proposition 3], we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">• d := α ,n d ,n : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L , (<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">(2.33) 1 2 d -W u 2 2 = 1 2 W d -u 2 2 + 1 2 (I -W W )d 2 2 .</formula><p>Therefore, the iteration (2.29) has the following optimality property:</p><p>(2.34)</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">u k =          W arg min d 1 2 d -W u k-1 2 2 + 1 2 α k-1 1-α k-1 • d 2 2</formula><p>bi-frame,</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">W arg min d 1 2 W d -u k-1 2 2 + 1 2 (I -W W )d 2 2 + 1 2 α k-1 1-α k-1 • d 2 2</formula><p>tight frame.</p><p>Similarly, the iteration (2.30) has the following optimality property:</p><p>(2.35)</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">u k =          W arg min d 1 2 d -W u k-1 2 2 + α k-1 • d 1,℘ bi-frame, W arg min d 1 2 W d -u k-1 2 2 + 1 2 (I -W W )d 2 2 + α k-1 • d 1,℘ tight frame.</formula><p>Judging from the formulas of the shrinkage operator, the parameter α k-1 depends only on the wavelet frame coefficients d k-1 . The first optimization problem in (2.35) is a synthesis based model <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">39]</ref>, and the second optimization problem is a balanced model <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">7]</ref>.</p><p>2.5. Wavelet frame shrinkage and nonlinear evolution PDEs. In this subsection, we discuss how wavelet frame shrinkage is related to nonlinear evolution PDEs in general. We shall focus on the motivation of such a connection and leave the details to later sections. We will also discuss the similarities and differences between our approach and some of the existing approaches, i.e., the finite difference and wavelet Galerkin methods.</p><p>Throughout this paper, all the evolution PDEs we shall consider take the following general form:</p><p>(2.36)</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">u t = L =1 ∂ α ∂x α Φ (Du, u), with D = ∂ β1 ∂x β1 , . . . , ∂ β L ∂x β L ,</formula><p>where we assume the PDE is defined on R 2 for the moment, and |α |, |β | ≥ 0 for all 1 ≤ ≤ L. Note that (2.36) includes diffusion, hyperbolic, and Hamilton-Jacobi equations as special cases. In this paper, we shall focus on nonlinear diffusions. However, we will also discuss a nonlinear hyperbolic equation used for image restoration called the shock filter <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[50]</ref>. Given a pair of bi-frame filter banks {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) }, and their associated transforms W and W , we have W W = I. We split the low and high frequency components of W and W according to the notation in (2.5) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">W low = W 0 and W high = {W : 1 ≤ ≤ L}.</formula><p>We define W low and W high similarly. Assuming that q ( ) and q ( ) have vanishing moments of orders β and α , respectively, our key observation is based on the following Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php relations, which can be derived using Lemma 2.3 by choosing λ and λ properly:</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">(2.37) λ • W high u ≈ (Du) and λ • W high • v L =1 ≈ - L =1 ∂ α ∂x α v , where u = u | and v = (v ) | for some smooth functions u and v , f | denotes the restriction of f on Z 2 , λ•W high u = {λ W u : 1 ≤ ≤ L}, and λ• W high • v L =1 = L =1 λ W v .</formula><p>Note that the first approximation of (2.37) was observed earlier in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref>, while both approximations of (2.37) in the one-dimensional setting were used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[46]</ref>. Using the observation (2.37), we can discretize (2.36) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">(2.38) u k = u k-1 -τ λ • W high • Φ (λ • W high u k-1 , u k-1 ) L =1 ,</formula><p>where u k j denotes an approximation to the value u(hj, τ k) of u(x, t) at (hj, τ k), where h and τ are the spatial step size and the time step size. Recall that from Proposition 2.10 and the iterative shrinkage formula (2.24) that follows, we have the following general expression of the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm:</p><p>(2.39)</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">u k = u k-1 -W high • W high u k-1 -S (W high u k-1 ) L =1 .</formula><p>Comparing (2.38) with (2.39), we will show that, if the shrinkage operator S is properly chosen, the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm will match (2.38) in the sense that u k = u k for all k ≥ 1 as long as u 0 = u 0 . This implies that (2.39), and its equivalent operator form (2.29), is a discrete approximation of the evolution PDE (2.36) if the shrinkage operator is properly chosen. On the other hand, for some type of given shrinkage, such as the soft-thresholding operator, we will work our way backward and find the associated (new) evolution PDEs. The main ideas here will be followed and carried out in detail in sections 3.1 and 3.2 to establish the connections between the nonlinear evolution PDEs (especially the nonlinear diffusions) and the wavelet frame based approach for image restorations. Furthermore, in section 3.3, we will discuss how we can further generalize such a relation, and how new evolution PDEs and iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithms can be created.</p><p>2.5.1. Difference from finite difference approach. The main advantage of wavelet frame based discretization of PDEs is that it equips the nonlinear diffusion PDE approach with a space-frequency analysis and multiscale analysis through the multiresolution analysis associated to wavelet frames. This is impossible to achieve by other finite difference methods. This provides a new angle from which to understand the nonlinear PDE approach. It further provides new types of nonlinear PDEs motivated by the wavelet frame based approach. On the other hand, as we will see in this paper, the PDE based approach in turn gives the wavelet frame based approach a geometric explanation and motivates us to develop new wavelet frame based methods which are different from the already available wavelet frame methods, which are mainly based on the sparse approximation of underlying solutions in the wavelet domain. We elaborate on some of the details as follows.</p><p>1. Finite difference methods and our approach are different in how discrete data is sampled from the unknown function. For a standard finite difference method, discrete data u is sampled from its continuum counterpart u normally by u = R h u, where R h is the restriction of u on a certain grid with Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN mesh-size h. However, the wavelet frame based approach samples u using the associated refinable function, which generates the underlying MRA of the wavelet frame system, as u = T h u with (T h u) k := 2 n u, φ n,k (see (4.9)). The sampling used by the wavelet frame based approach is more general and better than that used by finite difference methods in the following sense. (a) When u is continuous, the two samplings are equal to each other asymptotically (see Lemma 4.9 for details). (b) When u ∈ L 2 (R 2 ), the sampling T h u is still well defined, while R h u is not. More importantly, with the samples of u, the sampled values of various differentiations of u can be obtained by applying a standard wavelet decomposition on T h u. In this way, we are able to directly link the sampled values of derivatives to wavelet frame coefficients, which can be used to analyze various properties of the underlying solution, e.g., singularities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">For standard finite difference approximation of the operator</head><formula xml:id="formula_68">D = ( ∂ β ∂x β ) L =1 (differentiation) and L =1 ∂ α ∂x α (divergence)</formula><p>, there is not a bi-frame structure for the finite differencing of differentiation and divergence. However, when we use wavelet frame transform to discretize differentiation and divergence, λ • W high approximates the differentiation and λ • W high approximates the divergence. By augmenting the associated lowpass filter, we always have W W = I. This property is used extensively, and without it, we would not be able to rewrite the standard iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm (2.20) as (2.21) (see the proof of Proposition 2.10). In other words, we would not have the general iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm (2.39) that can be used to link with <ref type="bibr">(2.38)</ref>. Note that if we start with a certain finite difference scheme, we can complete the corresponding system to a certain biframe system. Therefore, implicitly, the finite difference method is also frame based, although it may not have the MRA structure and wavelet frames associated to it. However, the completion to a bi-frame system is not considered by finite difference methods. 3. Finally, the advantage of the discretization by wavelet frame transforms over the finite difference methods is the multiresolution structure of wavelet frames, or the multiple decomposition levels of wavelet frame transform. This automatically casts a multiscale analysis and space-frequency analysis to the PDE based approach. The multilevel decomposition allows us to detect singularities of the underlying solution and its directives in the presence of noise.</p><p>The ability to detect singularities enables us to activate wavelet frame bands and the associated shrinkage algorithms adaptively according to the orders of singularities. These advantages of discretization by wavelet frame transforms over finite difference methods will be illustrated in our numerical simulations in section 5 (Tables <ref type="table">1</ref> and<ref type="table">2</ref>), where multiple decomposition levels are used.</p><p>2.5.2. Difference from wavelet Galerkin. The basic idea of the wavelet Galerkin method [1, <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">52]</ref> is to represent the solution by a linear combination of a refinable function φ for an orthonormal wavelet system. One can form the weak form of the given PDE using refinable functions as test functions and then obtain a linear system with a stiffness matrix, or an iterative scheme associated to the linear system, which has entries like ∂φ α ∂x α , ∂ β φ ∂x β called connection coefficients. The key idea of the wavelet Galerkin method is to make the stiffness matrix sparse in the wavelet domain. In order to make this idea work, the wavelet system used has to be close Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php in some way to the eigenfunctions of the differential operator. However, it is hard to design such a wavelet system in general.</p><p>Our approach here never tries to make the stiffness matrix sparse. Instead, our methods are based on the properties of the underlying solutions. One example of such properties is that the underlying solutions for many differential equations considered in this paper are piecewise smooth functions, which can be sparsely approximated by a wide range of wavelet systems. Iterative algorithms are derived by carefully designing shrinkage operators based on prior knowledge of the underlying solutions. Such prior knowledge can be obtained either from the given data or by a prior analysis of the underlying solution. For example, when soft-thresholding is used, we assume that the underlying solution has a good sparse approximation in the wavelet frame domain.</p><p>Finally, to solve a given PDE using the wavelet Galerkin method, one needs to compute the connection coefficients first, which is an additional complication in solving PDEs, especially given the fact that many refinable functions do not have analytic forms. Our approach, however, is much easier to implement in practice. We can use the exact same algorithmic structure to solve a large class of (nonlinear) PDEs. We do not need to alter the fast wavelet frame transforms; we simply need to choose the right shrinkage operator and proper parameters λ and λ, which can be calculated analytically. In other words, ease of implementation and flexibility in solving general nonlinear PDEs are the major advantages of our approach over the wavelet Galerkin method.</p><p>3. Wavelet frame shrinkage and nonlinear evolution equations. This section establishes connections between the wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm (2.29) and the nonlinear evolution PDE of the form (2.36). As illustrated in the previous section, discretization of the PDE (2.36) using wavelet frame transforms can be written as <ref type="bibr">(2.38)</ref>, and the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage can be written as <ref type="bibr">(2.39)</ref>. The connections can be made by comparing the formulas (2.38) and <ref type="bibr">(2.39)</ref>. This is the key observation that we shall rely on in this section. As a further illustration of the observation, we use a specific evolution PDE and the Haar framelet as an example. For the rest of this section, however, we shall discuss the connections in generic settings.</p><p>Consider the following PDE:</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">u t = ∂Φ 1 ∂x 1 ∂u ∂x 1 , ∂u ∂x 2 , u + ∂Φ 2 ∂x 2 ∂u ∂x 1 , ∂u ∂x 2 , u .</formula><p>If we choose tensor-product Haar framelets to discretize the involved differential operators, a discrete form of the above PDE can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">u k = u k-1 -τ λ 1 W 1 Φ 1 (λ 1 W 1 u k-1 , λ 2 W 2 u k-1 , u k-1 ) -τ λ 2 W 2 Φ 2 (λ 1 W 1 u k-1 , λ 2 W 2 u k-1 , u k-1 ).</formula><p>For the same wavelet frame system, the iterative shrinkage algorithm (2.29) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">u k = u k-1 -W 1 W 1 u k-1 -S 1 (W 1 u k-1 , W 2 u k-1 , u k-1 ) -W 2 W 2 u k-1 -S 2 (W 1 u k-1 , W 2 u k-1 , u k-1 ) .</formula><p>Comparing the above two formulas, to link the two iterative algorithms, we can simply define S , = 1, 2, as a pointwise defined operator such that, for ξ , ζ ∈ R, as long as the ratio Φ (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ζ)/ξ is well defined. In particular, when Φ ( ∂u ∂x1 , ∂u ∂x2 , u) = g (|∇u| 2 , u) ∂u ∂x (nonlinear diffusion), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">S (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ζ) := ξ -τ λ Φ (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ζ) = ξ 1 -τ λ Φ (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ζ)/ξ ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_73">S (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ζ) = ξ 1 -τ λ g (ξ 2 1 + ξ 2 2 , ζ) .</formula><p>The parameters λ and λ are chosen so that λ W ≈ ∂ ∂x and λ W ≈ ∂ ∂x . 3.1. Wavelet frame shrinkage derived from PDEs. In this section, we focus on the relation between the iterative multiplicative wavelet frame shrinkage and nonlinear diffusion equations. A nonlinear hyperbolic equation known as the shock filter <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[50]</ref> will also be studied; this can be cast (formally) into the form of a nonlinear diffusion. In fact, the arguments we use to link wavelet frame shrinkage with nonlinear diffusions can be applied to general nonlinear evolution equations <ref type="bibr">(2.36)</ref>. Therefore, in the rest of this paper, we will mostly focus on nonlinear diffusions.</p><p>We will show that, with proper choice of the shrinkage functions, the wavelet frame shrinkage (2.22) (or, equivalently, (2.29)) is a discretization of the following nonlinear diffusion equation for u = u(x, t), x ∈ R 2 , t ≥ 0:</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">(3.1) u t = L =1 (-1) 1+|α | ∂ α ∂x α g ∂ β u ∂x β 2 ∂ β u ∂x β , with g : R → R + smooth and f being the initial function u(x, 0) = f (x), x ∈ R 2 .</formula><p>More precisely, let {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } be a pair of bi-frame filter banks. With u 0 j = f (hj), the sequence u k j generated by (2.22) (or, equivalently, from (2.29)) approximates u(hj, kτ ), where h and τ are the spatial and temporal step sizes, provided that S in (2.22) satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">(3.2) S (ξ) = ξ 1 - τ C ( ) α C ( ) β h |α|+|β | g ξ 2 (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | , ξ ∈ R, 1 ≤ ≤ L,</formula><p>or, equivalently, the shrinkage operator S α in (2.26) satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n (1 -α ,n (d ,n )) (3.3) = d ,n 1 - τ C ( ) α C ( ) β h |α |+|β | g d 2 ,n (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | , 1 ≤ ≤ L,</formula><p>where α , β in Z 2 + are the vanishing moment orders of q ( ) , q ( ) , and C ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">α , C ( )</formula><p>β are defined by <ref type="bibr">(2.10)</ref>.</p><p>In this section we will also consider the channel-mixed nonlinear diffusion</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">(3.4) u t = L =1 (-1) 1+|α | ∂ α ∂x α g ∂ β1 u ∂x β1 , ∂ β2 u ∂x β2 , . . . , ∂ β L u ∂x β L ∂ β u ∂x β ,</formula><p>with g : R L → R + smooth, and show how to design some tight frame and biframe filter banks and choose appropriate shrinking functions/operators such that the iterative frame shrinkage (2.25)/(2.29) is a discretization of (3.4). Finally, applying similar techniques, we will show how can we design tight frame and bi-frame filter banks and the associated shrinking functions/operators to discretize the PM equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref>, the Bertalmio-Sapiro-Caselles-Ballester image inpainting diffusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[5]</ref>, and a nonlinear hyperbolic equation known as the Osher-Rudin shock filter <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[50]</ref>. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php 3.1.1. Shrinkage for nonlinear diffusions. In this subsection, we discuss the correspondence between frame shrinkage and high order nonlinear diffusion. Let p, q ( ) , 1 ≤ ≤ L, be a tight frame filter bank. Suppose q ( ) , 1 ≤ ≤ L, have vanishing moments of orders β with C ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">β = 0, where C ( )</formula><p>β are the constants defined by (2.10) with q = q ( ) , respectively. We will show that, with properly chosen shrinkage functions, the iterative shrinkage <ref type="bibr">(2.22)</ref> or equivalently (2.29) is a discretization of the high order nonlinear diffusion equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">(3.5) u t = L =1 (-1) 1+|β | ∂ β ∂x β g ∂ β u ∂x β 2 ∂ β u ∂x β for u = u(x, t), x ∈ R 2 , t ≥ 0, with u(x, 0) = f (x)</formula><p>and some smooth diffusivity function g : R → R + .</p><p>Recall that h and τ denote the spatial step size and the time step size. Lemma 2.3 ensures that we can use FIR filter q ( ) to approximate partial derivatives</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">∂ β ∂x β u(x, t) and ∂ β ∂x β G (x, t), where G (x, t) := g ∂ β u ∂x β 2 ∂ β u ∂x β .</formula><p>Indeed,</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">∂ β ∂x β u(hj, τ k) ≈ 1 C ( ) β 1 h |β | n∈Z 2 q ( ) [n]u(hj + hn, τ k),<label>(3.6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">∂ β ∂x β G (hj, τ k) ≈ (-1) |β | C ( ) β 1 h |β | m∈Z 2 q ( ) [m]G (hj -hm, kτ ) (3.7) = (-1) |β | C ( ) β 1 h |β | m∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -m]G (hm, kτ ),</formula><p>where (2.9) with ε = h and ε = -h has been used in <ref type="bibr">(3.6</ref>) and (3.7), respectively.</p><p>Let u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 . From (3.5), <ref type="bibr">(3.6)</ref>, and (3.7) with k = 0, u 1 j , j ∈ Z 2 , defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">u 1 j -u 0 j τ = - L =1 1 C ( ) β h |β | m q ( ) [j -m]g 1 C ( ) β h |β | n q ( ) [n] u 0 n+m 2 • 1 C ( ) β h |β | n q ( ) [n] u 0 n+m</formula><p>give approximated values of the solution u(x, t) at (hj, τ ), j ∈ Z 2 . The above equation can be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">(3.8) u 1 j = u 0 j -τ L =1 1 C ( ) β h |β | m∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -m]g 1 C ( ) β h |β | H ( ) m 2 1 C ( ) β h |β | H ( ) m , j ∈ Z 2 ,</formula><p>where H</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">( ) m is defined by (2.20): H ( ) m = n q ( ) [n] u 0 n+m = n q ( ) [n]f (h(n + m)</formula><p>). Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php Repeating the above process, we have u 1 j , u 2 j , . . . , which are approximated values of the solution u(x, t) at (hj, 2τ ), (hj, 3τ ), . . . , respectively. More precisely, assume we have u k-1 j , approximated values of u(x, t) at (hj, τ (k -1)), j ∈ Z 2 . Then from</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">(3.6), ∂ β ∂x β u(hj, τ (k -1)) ≈ 1/(C ( ) β h |β | ) n∈Z 2 q ( ) [n] u k-1 n+j .</formula><p>This, together with (3.7), implies that</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">∂ β ∂x β G (hj, τ (k -1)) ≈ (-1) |β | C ( ) β 1 h |β | m q ( ) [j -m]g 1 C ( ) β h |β | n q ( ) [n] u k-1 n+m 2 1 C ( ) β h |β | n q ( ) [n] u k-1 n+m .</formula><p>Thus, u k j , j ∈ Z 2 , defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">u k j -u k-1 j τ = - L =1 1 C ( ) β h |β | m q ( ) [j -m]g 1 C ( ) β h |β | n q ( ) [n] u k-1 n+m 2 • 1 C ( ) β h |β | n q ( ) [n] u k-1 n+m</formula><p>give approximated values of the solution u(x, t) at (hj, τ k), j ∈ Z 2 . Hence the highpass filters q ( ) , 1 ≤ ≤ L, give a discretization of (3.5), which can be rewritten as follows: for j ∈ Z 2 ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">u k j = u k-1 j -τ L =1 1 C ( ) β h |β | m q ( ) [j -m]g 1 C ( ) β h |β | H ( ),k-1 m 2 (3.9) • 1 C ( ) β h |β | H ( ),k-1 m , k = 1, 2, . . . ,</formula><p>where H ( ),k-1 , 1 ≤ ≤ L, are the highpass outputs of u k-1 j defined by (2.20) with u 0 replaced by u k-1 .</p><p>Let u k be the resulting sequences of the wavelet frame shrinkage (2.22) with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 . Comparing (2.22) and (3.9), we have that u k j = u k j , j ∈ Z 2 , for all k ≥ 2 as long as u 0 = u 0 and (3.10)</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">S (ξ) = ξ 1 - τ (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | g ξ 2 (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | , ξ ∈ R, 1 ≤ ≤ L.</formula><p>If u k is generated from (2.29), the equivalent operator form of (2.22), then condition (3.10) can be translated equivalently to</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">(3.11) S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n (1-α ,n (d ,n )) = d ,n 1- τ (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | g d 2 ,n (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | , 1 ≤ ≤ L.</formula><p>In other words, the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm (2.22)/(2.29) generates the exact same sequence as (3.9) provided that u 0 = u 0 and (3.10)/(3.11) is satisfied, where (3.9) is in fact a discretization of the nonlinear diffusion (3.5). In the following theorem, we summarize this result on the relation between the wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm (2.22)/(2.29) and the high-order nonlinear diffusion (3.5). Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php Theorem 3.1. Let u k be the resulting sequence from the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage (2.22)/ (2.29) with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , and using a tight frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } with q ( ) having vanishing moment β . Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) the solution of (3.5) provided that the shrinkage functions satisfy (2.22)/ <ref type="bibr">(3.11)</ref>. Furthermore, if the α given in (3.11) satisfies (2.31), we have that both the optimality properties in (2.34) hold for u k . Remark 3.2. In Theorem 3.1 and many other results in this paper, the statement that "u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) the solution of a given PDE" means that the discretization by (2.29) is consistent with the given PDE. Since all the consistency proofs are very similar to each other, we present a detailed proof of consistency for a specific PDE later in Proposition 4.3, which can be easily modified to a proof for Theorem 3.1, as well as all other consistency results in this paper. To show that u k indeed converges to the solution of the given PDE, we need it to be well-posed and the algorithm to be stable, in addition to consistency. A complete proof of convergence of the discretization given by (2.29) to a specific PDE is given in section 4. Although the analysis is only applied to one particular PDE, one can easily see from the proofs in section 4 that, as long as the given PDE is well-posed, we can always show convergence of (2.29) with properly chosen shrinkage functions.</p><p>With Theorem 3.1, we have the following easy corollary.</p><p>Corollary 3.3. Let u k be the resulting signal from the iterative multiplicative wavelet frame shrinkage (2.29) with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , and using a tight frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) }, with L &gt; 2, q ( ) having vanishing moment β . Let L be an integer with 2 ≤ L &lt; L. Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) the solution of (3.12)</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">u t = L =1 (-1) 1+|β | ∂ β ∂x β g ∂ β u ∂x β 2 ∂ β u ∂x β ,</formula><p>provided that the shrinkage operator of (2.29) is chosen as</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">(3.13) S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n (1-α ,n (d ,n )) =      d ,n 1 - τ (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | g (d ,n ) 2 (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | for 1 ≤ ≤ L, d ,n 1 - C(0) τ h s g C(1) (d ,n ) 2 h 2|β | for L &lt; ≤ L,</formula><p>where C(0) , C(1) ≥ 0 and s &lt; 2|β |. Furthermore, if the α given in (3.13) satisfies (2.31), we have that both the optimality properties in (2.34) hold for u k . Remark 3.4. Theorem 3.1 and Corollary 3.3 imply that we can use the tight frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q ( L) } or {p, q (1) , q (2) , . . . , q (L) } with L &gt; L to approximate the same PDE (3.12). Numerically, the discretization by Corollary 3.3 can produce better image restoration results than the discretization by Theorem 3.1. This is in fact consistent with our earlier findings in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref>, where we discretize variational models using B-spline tight wavelet frames.</p><p>Similarly, when a pair of bi-frame filter banks {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } are used for frame shrinkage, the formulas used to discretize partial derivatives </p><formula xml:id="formula_95">∂ β ∂x β u(hj, τ k) ≈ 1 C ( ) β 1 h |β | n∈Z 2 q ( ) [n]u(hj + hn, τ k), ∂ β ∂x β G (hj, τ k) ≈ (-1) |β | C ( ) α 1 h |β | m∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -m]G (hm, τ k),</formula><p>where C ( )</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">β and C ( )</formula><p>α are the constants defined by (2.10) with q = q ( ) and q = q ( ) , respectively. Then u k j with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">u k j = u k-1 j -τ L =1 1 C ( ) α h |β | m∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -m]g 1 C ( ) β h |β | H ( ),k-1 m 2 (3.14) • 1 C ( ) β h |β | H ( ),k-1 m for k = 1, 2, .</formula><p>. . provides a discretization of the diffusion equation (3.1), where H ( ),k-1 , 1 ≤ ≤ L, are the highpass outputs of u k-1 defined by (2.20) with u 0 replaced by u k-1 . Let u k be the resulting sequences from wavelet frame shrinkage (2.22) with</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 . Comparing (2.22) with (3.14), we have u k = u k for k ≥ 1 if (3.</formula><p>2) holds. Therefore, in this case, the wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm (2.22) (or its equivalent form (2.29)) approximates the nonlinear diffusion (3.14). Theorem 3.5. Let u k be the resulting sequences from wavelet frame shrinkage (2.22)/ (2.29) with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , and using a bi-frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } with q ( ) (resp., q ( ) ) having vanishing moment β (resp., α ). Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) the solution of (3.1) provided that (3.2)/ (3.3) is satisfied. Furthermore, if the α given in (3.3) satisfies (2.31), we have that the first optimality property in (2.34) holds for u k .</p><p>Similarly, one can easily derive the correspondence between the wavelet frame shrinkage and diffusion of <ref type="bibr">(3.4)</ref>. In this case, the discretization scheme for (3.4) with a bi-frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } is, for k = 1, 2, . . . , <ref type="bibr">(3.15</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">u k j = u k-1 j -τ L =1 1 C ( ) α h |β | m∈Z 2 q ( ) [j -m]g H (1),k-1 m C (1)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_100">β 1 h |β 1 | , . . . , H (L),k-1 m C (L) β L h |β L | H ( ),k-1 m C ( ) β h |β |</formula><p>, where u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , and H ( ),k-1 , 1 ≤ ≤ L, are the highpass outputs of u k-1 with q ( ) . Theorem 3.6. Let u k be the resulting sequence from the wavelet frame shrinkage (2.25)/ (2.29) with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , and using a bi-frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , • • • , q (L) } with q ( ) (resp., q ( ) ) having vanishing moment β (resp., α ). Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) the solution of (3.4) provided that the shrinkage functions S of Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php </p><formula xml:id="formula_101">S (ξ 1 , . . . , ξ L ) = ξ - τ ξ C ( ) α C ( ) β h |α |+|β | g ξ 1 C (1) β1 h |β1| , . . . , ξ L C (L) β L h |β L | , ξ 1 , . . . , ξ L ∈ R, 1 ≤ ≤ L,</formula><p>or equivalently the shrinkage operator of (2.29) is chosen as</p><formula xml:id="formula_102">S α ,n (d) (d 1,n , . . . , d L,n ) = d ,n 1 -α ,n (d 1,n , . . . , d L,n ) = d ,n 1 - τ C ( ) α C ( ) β h |α |+|β | g d 1,n C (1) β1 h |β1| , . . . , d L,n C (L) β L h |β L | (3.17)</formula><p>for 1 ≤ ≤ L. Furthermore, if the α given in (3.17) satisfies (2.31), we have that the first optimality property in (2.34) holds for u k .</p><p>With Theorem 3.6, we have the following easy corollary.</p><p>Corollary 3.7. Let u k be the resulting signal from the iterative multiplicative wavelet frame shrinkage (2.29) with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , and using a bi-frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } with L &gt; L ≥ 2, q ( ) (resp., q ( ) ) having vanishing moment β (resp., α ). Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) the solution of</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">(3.18) u t = L =1 (-1) 1+|α | ∂ α ∂x α g ∂ β1 u ∂x β1 , ∂ β2 u ∂x β2 ∂ β u ∂x β ,</formula><p>provided that the shrinkage operator of (2.29) is chosen as</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n 1 -α ,n (d1,n, . . . , dL,n) =        d ,n 1 - τ C ( ) α C ( ) β h |α |+|β | g d 1,n C (1) β 1 h |β 1 | , d 2,n C (2) β 2 h |β 2 | for 1 ≤ ≤ L, d ,n 1 - C(0) τ h s g C(1) d 1,n h |β 1 | , C(2) d 2,n h |β 2 | , . . . , C(L) d L,n h |β L | for L &lt; ≤ L,<label>(3.19)</label></formula><p>where C(j) ≥ 0, j = 0, 1, . . . , L, and s &lt; |α | + |β |. Furthermore, if the α given in (3.19) satisfies (2.31), we have that the first optimality property in (2.34) holds for u k . Remark 3.8. Theorem 3.6 and Corollary 3.7 imply that we can use a bi-frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q ( L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q ( L) } or {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } and { p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } with L &gt; L to approximate the same PDE <ref type="bibr">(3.18)</ref>. Numerically, the discretization by Corollary 3.7 can produce better image restoration results than the discretization by Theorem 3.6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2.">PDE models for image restoration.</head><p>In this subsection we show how iterative wavelet frame shrinkage can be used to discretize some PDE models commonly used in image restoration. We will consider the PM equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref> and a modified TV equation, the Bertalmio-Sapiro-Caselles-Ballester image inpainting diffusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[5]</ref>, and the Osher-Rudin shock filter <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[50]</ref>. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php 1. PM and TV models. The most commonly used diffusion equation is <ref type="bibr">(3.20)</ref> u t = div g(| u| 2 ) u , namely,</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">u t = ∂ ∂x 1 g ∂u ∂x 1 2 + ∂u ∂x 2 2 ∂u ∂x 1 + ∂ ∂x 2 g ∂u ∂x 1 2 + ∂u ∂x 2 2 ∂u ∂x 2 ,</formula><p>where g is the diffusivity function.</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">If g(x 2 ) = c 1+(x/λ) 2 , where c &gt; 0, λ &gt; 0 are constants, (3.20) is the PM model; it is the (modified) TV model if g(x 2 ) = c √ ε 2 +x 2 ,</formula><p>where c &gt; 0, ε &gt; 0 are constants.</p><p>Let {p, q (1) , q (2) } and { p, q (1) , q (2) } be a pair of bi-frame filter banks defined by (2.17). Then q (1) , q (1) have vanishing moment of order (1, 0) and q (2) , q (2) have vanishing moment of order (0, 1) with C</p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_107">(1,0) = C (1) (1,0) = C (2) (0,1) = C (2) (0,1) = -1 2 . Thus, by Theorem 3.6 with g 1 (ξ 1 , ξ 2 ) = g 2 (ξ 1 , ξ 2 ) = g(ξ 2 1 + ξ 2 2 ), if S1(ξ1, ξ2) = ξ1 - 4τ ξ1 h 2 g 4(ξ 2 1 + ξ 2 2 ) h 2 , S2(ξ1, ξ2) = ξ2 - 4τ ξ2 h 2 g 4(ξ 2 1 + ξ 2 2 ) h 2 , (3.21)</formula><p>or equivalently</p><formula xml:id="formula_108">(3.22) S α ,n (d) (d 1,n , d 2,n ) = d ,n 1 - 4τ h 2 g 4(d 1,n ) 2 + 4(d 2,n ) 2 h 2 , = 1, 2,</formula><p>then the iterative channel-mixed frame shrinkage (2.25)/(2.29) results in a discretization of the PM equation.</p><p>2. Image inpainting diffusion. The (slightly modified) diffusion equation for image inpainting is</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">u t = ( u) • u ⊥ + ε u, (x, t) ∈ D × (0, T )</formula><p>with initial condition u(x, 0) = f ext , x ∈ Ω, an extension of f from D to Ω\D, where ε &gt; 0 and</p><formula xml:id="formula_110">u ⊥ = -∂ ∂y ∂ ∂x</formula><p>.</p><p>We consider the more general equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_111">(3.23) u t = g( u) • u ⊥ + ε u,</formula><p>where g is a smooth function on R. Equation (3.23) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_112">(3.24) u t = ∂ ∂y g( u) ∂u ∂x + ∂ ∂x -g( u) ∂u ∂y + ε u.</formula><p>Thus (3.23), or equivalently <ref type="bibr">(3.24)</ref>, can be expressed in the form of (3.4) with L = 4,</p><formula xml:id="formula_113">β 1 = (1, 0), β 2 = (0, 1), β 3 = (2, 0), β 4 = (0, 2), α 1 = (0, 1), α 2 = (1, 0), α 3 = (0, 0), α 4 = (0, 0),</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_114">g 1 (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 ) = g(ξ 3 + ξ 4 ), g 2 (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 ) = -g(ξ 3 + ξ 4 ), g 3 (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 ) = g 4 (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 ) = -ε.</formula><p>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php Therefore, in order for the wavelet frame shrinkage to be in correspondence to the diffusion equation <ref type="bibr">(3.24)</ref>, the analysis highpass filters q (1) , . . . , q (4) need to have vanishing moments of orders (1, 0), (0, 1), (2, 0), (0, 2), respectively. The synthesis highpass filters q (1) and q (2) should have vanishing moments of orders (0, 1) and (1, 0), respectively, and filters q (3) and q (4) are just the delta filter which have vanishing moment of (0, 0) order.</p><p>The bi-frame filters needed to discretize (3.24) are given by (2.18). Indeed, the highpass filters q (1) , q (2) , q (3) , q (4) and q (1) , q (2) , q (3) , q (4) have vanishing moments of orders (1, 0), (0, 1), (2, 0), (0, 2) and (0, 1), (1, 0), (0, 0), (0, 0), respectively. One can easily obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_115">C (1) (1,0) = - 1 2 , C<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_116">(0,1) = 1 2 , C<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_117">(2,0) = C (4) (0,2) = - 1 4 , C<label>(1)</label></formula><p>(0,1) = C</p><p>(1,0) = -</p><formula xml:id="formula_119">1 2 , C<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_120">(0,0) = C<label>(4)</label></formula><p>(0,0) = 1.</p><p>Thus by Theorem 3.6, if the shrinkage functions S of (2.25) and the diffusion function g satisfy</p><formula xml:id="formula_121">S (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 ) = ξ - 4τ ξ h 2 g - 4ξ 3 + 4ξ 4 h 2 for = 1, 2, S (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 ) = ξ 1 - 4τ ε h 2 for = 3, 4,</formula><p>or equivalently if the shrinkage operator S α of (2.29) satisfies </p><formula xml:id="formula_122">S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n 1 -4τ h 2 g - 4d3,n+4d4,n h 2 for = 1, 2, d ,n 1 -4τ ε h 2 for = 3,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_123">u t + | u|F (L(u)) = 0, (x, t) ∈ Ω × (0, T ),</formula><p>with initial condition u(x, 0) = f (x), x ∈ Ω, where F is a Lipschitz continuous function satisfying F (0) = 0, sign(x)F (x) &gt; 0 for x = 0.</p><p>The simplest example for</p><formula xml:id="formula_124">F is F (x) = x. A desirable choice for L(u) is (3.26) L(u) = u 2 x u xx + 2u x u y u xy + u 2 y u yy | u| 2 ,</formula><p>which is the second derivative of u in the direction of n = u | u| . Here we consider the case F (x) = x and show that the wavelet frame shrinkage is connected with the shock filtering of (3.25) with L(u) given by <ref type="bibr">(3.26)</ref>. In this case (3.25) is </p><formula xml:id="formula_125">u t = - u 2 x u xx +</formula><formula xml:id="formula_126">) ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 -g(| u| 2 ) ∂ 2 u ∂y 2 ,</formula><p>where g(x) = -√ x, x ≥ 0. Thus (3.27) is an equation in the form of (3.4) with L = 4,</p><formula xml:id="formula_127">β 1 = (1, 0), β 2 = (0, 1), β 3 = (2, 0), β 4 = (0, 2),</formula><p>α 1 = (1, 0), α 2 = (0, 1), α 3 = (0, 0), α 4 = (0, 0), and</p><formula xml:id="formula_128">g 1 = g 2 = g 3 = g 4 = g(ξ 2 1 + ξ 2 2</formula><p>). Therefore, in order that the frame shrinkage corresponds to the diffusion with (3.24), the analysis highpass filters q (1) , . . . , q (4)  have vanishing moments of orders (1, 0), (0, 1), (2, 0), (0, 2), respectively, while the synthesis highpass filters q (1) and q (2) should have vanishing moments of orders (0, 1) and (1, 0), respectively, and q (3) and q (4) are just the delta filters, which have vanishing moment of (0, 0) order.</p><p>The filter bank that satisfies the above requirements is given by (2.19). Indeed, the highpass filters q (1) , q (2) , q (3) , q (4) and q (1) , q (2) , q (3) , q (4) have vanishing moments of orders (1, 0), (0, 1), (2, 0), (0, 2) and (1, 0), (0, 1), (0, 0), (0, 0), respectively. We have</p><formula xml:id="formula_129">C (1) (1,0) = C (2) (0,1) = -1, C<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_130">(2,0) = C (4) (0,2) = - 1 4 , C<label>(1)</label></formula><p>(0,1) = C</p><p>(1,0) = -</p><formula xml:id="formula_132">1 4 , C<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_133">(0,0) = C<label>(4)</label></formula><p>(0,0) = 1.</p><p>Thus, by Theorem 3.6, if the shrinkage functions S of (2.25) and the diffusion function g satisfy</p><formula xml:id="formula_134">S (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 ) = ξ - 4τ ξ h 2 g ξ 2 1 + ξ 2 2 h 2 for = 1, 2, S (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 ) = ξ + 4τ ξ h 2 g ξ 2 1 + ξ 2 2 h 2 for = 3, 4,</formula><p>or equivalently if the shrinkage operator S α of (2.29) satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_135">S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) =    d ,n 1 -4τ h 2 g (d1,n) 2 +(d2,n) 2 h 2 for = 1, 2, d ,n 1 + 4τ h 2 g (d1,n) 2 +(d2,n) 2 h 2 for = 3, 4,</formula><p>then, with the filters given by (2.19), the sequence from the wavelet frame shrinkage (2.25)/(2.29) is a discretization of (3.27).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.2.</head><p>PDEs derived from wavelet frame shrinkage. In the previous section, we showed, in generic settings, how to construct the wavelet frame system and choose appropriate shrinkage functions so that the wavelet frame shrinkage is a discrete approximation of a given PDE. In this section we present several specific (new) high order diffusion equations that are derived from wavelet frame shrinkage (2.29) using some specific B-spline tight wavelet frame systems. Note that our techniques can be generalized easily to many other wavelet frame systems, and other (possibly new) nonlinear evolution PDEs can be derived similarly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.2.1.</head><p>Diffusions from B-spline filter banks. Let {p, q (1) , . . . , q (8) } be the separable spline tight frame filter bank given in <ref type="bibr">(2.14)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_136">∂u ∂x2 - ∂ 2 ∂x 2 1 g3 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 1 2 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 1 (3.28) - ∂ 2 ∂x1∂x2 g4 ∂ 2 u ∂x1∂x2 2 ∂ 2 u ∂x1∂x2 - ∂ 2 ∂x 2 2 g5 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 2 2 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 2 + ∂ 3 ∂x 2 1 ∂x2 g6 ∂ 3 u ∂x 2 1 ∂x2 2 ∂ 3 u ∂x 2 1 ∂x2 + ∂ 3 ∂x1∂x 2 2 g7 ∂ 3 u ∂x1∂x 2 2 2 ∂ 3 u ∂x1∂x 2 2 - ∂ 4 ∂x 2 1 ∂x 2 2 g8 ∂ 4 u ∂x 2 1 ∂x 2 2 2 ∂ 4 u ∂x 2 1 ∂x 2 2 ,</formula><p>with the initial condition u(x, 0) = f (x), x ∈ R<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> . More precisely, with C</p><p>(1) </p><formula xml:id="formula_137">β 1 = C<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_138">β 2 = - √ 2 2 , C<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_139">β 3 = - 1 4 , C<label>(4)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_140">β 4 = 1 2 , C<label>(5)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_141">β 5 = - 1 4 , C<label>(6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_142">β 6 = C<label>(7)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_143">β 7 = √ 2 8 , C<label>(8)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_144">β</formula><formula xml:id="formula_145">S (ξ) = ξ 1 - 2τ h 2 g 2ξ 2 h 2 for = 1, 2, S (ξ) = ξ 1 - 16τ h 4 g 16ξ 2 h 4 for = 3, 5, S (ξ) = ξ 1 - 32τ h 4 g 32ξ 2 h 4 for = 6, 7, S 4 (ξ) = ξ 1 - 4τ h 4 g 4 4ξ 2 h 4 , S 8 (ξ) = ξ 1 - 256τ h 8 g 8 256ξ 2 h 8 ,</formula><p>or equivalently the shrinkage operator satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_146">S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n 1 - 2τ h 2 g 2(d ,n ) 2 h 2 for = 1, 2, S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n 1 - 16τ h 4 g 16(d ,n ) 2 h 4 for = 3, 5, S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n 1 - 32τ h 6 g 32(d ,n ) 2 h 6 for = 6, 7, S α4,n(d) (d 4,n ) = d 4,n 1 - 4τ h 4 g 4 4(d 4,n ) 2 h 4 , S α8,n(d) (d 8,n ) = d 8,n 1 - 256τ h 8 g 8 256(d 8,n ) 2 h 8 .</formula><p>Next we construct wavelet frame filter banks with fewer highpass filters, while the lowpass filter is still the same: p(ω) = a(ω 1 )a(ω 2 ). Denote</p><formula xml:id="formula_147">(3.29) ξ = cos ω 1 2 2 , η = cos ω 2 2 2 .</formula><p>Observe that</p><formula xml:id="formula_148">ξ = 1 + e -iω1 2 2 , 1 -ξ = sin ω 1 2 2 = 1 -e -iω1<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_149">2 , η = 1 + e -iω2 2 2 , 1 -η = sin ω 2 2 2 = 1 -e -iω2 2 and that 4ξ(1 -ξ) = (sin ω 1 ) 2 = e iω1 -e -iω1 2 2 , (1 -2ξ) 2 = (cos ω 1 ) 2 = e iω1 + e -iω1 2 2 , 4η(1 -η) = (sin ω 2 ) 2 = e iω2 -e -iω2 2 2 , (1 -2η) 2 = (cos ω 2 ) 2 = e iω2 + e -iω2<label>2 2</label></formula><p>.</p><p>From |p(ω)| 2 = ξ 2 η 2 and</p><formula xml:id="formula_150">1 = η + (1 -η) 2 = η 2 + 2η(1 -η) + (1 -η) 2 = ξ + (1 -ξ) 2 η 2 + 2 (1 -2ξ) 2 + 4ξ(1 -ξ) η(1 -η) + (1 -η) 2 = ξ 2 η 2 + 2ξ(1 -ξ)η 2 + (1 -ξ) 2 η 2 + 2(1 -2ξ) 2 η(1 -η) + 8ξ(1 -ξ)η(1 -η) + (1 -η) 2 ,</formula><p>we know that q ( ) , 1 ≤ ≤ 5 given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_151">| q (1) (ω)| 2 = 2ξ(1 -ξ)η 2 = 1 2 sin ω 1 ) 2 cos ω 2 2 4 , | q (2) (ω)| 2 = 2(1 -2ξ) 2 η(1 -η) = 1 2 cos ω 1 ) 2 sin ω 2 2 , | q (3) (ω)| 2 = (1 -ξ) 2 η 2 = sin ω 1 2 4 cos ω 2 2 4 , | q (4) (ω)| 2 = 8ξ(1 -ξ)η(1 -η) = 1 2 sin ω 1 2 sin ω 2 2 , | q (5) (ω)| 2 = (1 -η) 2 = sin ω 2 2 4 ,</formula><p>which are the filters given by (2.14), together with the lowpass filter p, form a tight frame filter bank. The highpass filters q (1) , . . . , q (5) have the vanishing moments of orders</p><formula xml:id="formula_152">β 1 = (1, 0), β 2 = (0, 1), β 3 = (2, 0), β 4 = (1, 1), β 5 = (0, 2),</formula><p>respectively, and one can obtain the constants C ( ) β in (2.10) with q = q ( ) :</p><formula xml:id="formula_153">C (1) (1,0) = C (2) (0,1) = - √ 2 2 , C<label>(3)</label></formula><p>(2,0) = C</p><p>(5)</p><formula xml:id="formula_154">(0,2) = 1 4 , C<label>(4)</label></formula><p>(1,1) =</p><formula xml:id="formula_155">√ 2 2 . (3.30)</formula><p>The nonlinear diffusion equation corresponding to this Ron-Shen-type tight frame filter bank is</p><formula xml:id="formula_156">ut= ∂ ∂x1 g1 ∂u ∂x1 2 ∂u ∂x1 + ∂ ∂x2 g2 ∂u ∂x2 2 ∂u ∂x2 - ∂ 2 ∂x 2 1 g3 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 1 2 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 1 (3.31) - ∂ 2 ∂x1∂x2 g4 ∂ 2 u ∂x1∂x2 2 ∂ 2 u ∂x1∂x2 - ∂ 2 ∂x 2 2 g5 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 2 2 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 2 ,</formula><p>with u(x, 0) = f (x), x ∈ R 2 . From Theorem 3.1, we have the conclusion in the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 3.9. Let u k be the resulting signal from the wavelet frame shrinkage (2.22)/ (2.29) with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , and using the spline tight frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q (5) } given in (2.14). Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) the solution of (3.31), provided that the shrinkage functions S of (2.22) are chosen as</p><formula xml:id="formula_157">S (ξ) = ξ 1 - 2τ h 2 g 2ξ 2 h 2 for = 1, 2, S (ξ) = ξ 1 - 16τ h 4 g 16ξ 2 h 4 for = 3, 5, S 4 (ξ) = ξ 1 - 2τ h 4 g 4 2ξ 2 h 4 , ξ ∈ R,</formula><p>or equivalently the shrinkage operator S α of (2.29) is chosen as</p><formula xml:id="formula_158">S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n 1 -α ,n (d ,n ) =          d ,n 1 -2τ h 2 g 2(d ,n ) 2 h 2 for = 1, 2, d ,n 1 -16τ h 4 g 16(d ,n ) 2 h 4 for = 3, 5, d 4,n 1 -2τ h 4 g 4 2(d4,n) 2 h 4 for = 4.</formula><p>Furthermore, if the α given above satisfies (2.31), both the optimality properties in (2.34) hold for u k .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2.">Rotation-invariant diffusions.</head><p>For some applications, the rotationinvariant diffusion is preferred. In this subsection we will show that the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage (2.25)/(2.29) corresponds rotation-invariant diffusion if we choose the threshold α for S α properly. In particular, the rotation-invariant diffusion equation corresponding to the spline tight frame filter banks (2.14) is</p><formula xml:id="formula_159">(3.32) ut= ∂ ∂x1 g1 ∂u ∂x1 2 + ∂u ∂x2 2 ∂u ∂x1 + ∂ ∂x2 g1 ∂u ∂x1 2 + ∂u ∂x2 2 ∂u ∂x2 - ∂ 2 ∂x 2 1 g2 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 1 2 + ∂ 2 u ∂x1∂x2 2 + ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 2 2 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 1 - ∂ 2 ∂x 2 2 g2 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 1 2 + ∂ 2 u ∂x1∂x2 2 + ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 2 2 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 2 - ∂ 2 ∂x1∂x2 g2 ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 1 2 + ∂ 2 u ∂x1∂x2 2 + ∂ 2 u ∂x 2 2 2 ∂ 2 u ∂x1∂x2 ,</formula><p>with the initial condition u(x, 0) = f (x), x ∈ R 2 , where g 1 and g 2 are functions on R.</p><p>Theorem 3.10. Let u k be the resulting signal from the wavelet frame shrinkage (2.25)/ (2.29) with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , and using the spline type tight frame filter bank {p, q (1) , . . . , q (5) } given in <ref type="bibr">(2.14)</ref>. Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) the solution of (3.32), provided that the shrinkage functions S of (2.25) satisfy</p><formula xml:id="formula_160">S (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 , ξ 5 ) = ξ 1 - 2τ h 2 g 1 2 h 2 (ξ 2 1 + ξ 2 2 ) for = 1, 2, S (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 , ξ 5 ) = ξ 1 - 16τ h 4 g 2 2 h 4 (8ξ 2 3 + ξ 2 4 + 8ξ 2 5 ) for = 3, 5, (3.33) S 4 (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , ξ 3 , ξ 4 , ξ 5 ) = ξ 4 1 - 2τ h 4 g 2 2 h 4 (8ξ 2 3 + ξ 2 4 + 8ξ 2 5 ) ,</formula><p>or equivalently the shrinkage operator S α of (2.29) is chosen as Next we construct tight filters which result in higher order rotation-invariant diffusion. The scaling functions for the tight filter banks are the tensor products of the B-spline of an arbitrary order m with the two-scale symbol given by (2.15). Recall from (3.29) that ξ and η denote cos ω1 </p><formula xml:id="formula_161">S α ,n (d) (d ,n ) = d ,n 1 -α ,n (d ,n ) =          d ,n 1 -2τ h 2 g 2(d 1,n ) 2 +2(d 2,n ) 2 h 2 for = 1, 2, d ,n 1 -16τ h 4 g 16(d 3,n ) 2 +2(d 4,n ) 2 +16(d 5,n ) 2 h 4 for = 3, 5, d ,n 1 -2τ h 4 g 16(d 3,n ) 2 +2(d 4,n ) 2 +16(d</formula><formula xml:id="formula_162">= η + (1 -η) m = m r=0 m r η m-r (1 -η) r = m r=0 m r ξ + (1 -ξ) m-r η m-r (1 -η) r = m r=0 m r m-r j=0 m -r j ξ m-r-j (1 -ξ) r η m-r (1 -η) r = m r=0 m r m s=r m -r s -r ξ m-s η m-r (1 -ξ) s-r (1 -η) r (by s = r + j) = m s=0 s r=0 m s s r ξ m-s η m-r (1 -ξ) s-r (1 -η) r = ξ m η m + m s=1 s r=0 m s s r ξ m-s η m-r (1 -ξ) s-r (1 -η) r ,</formula><p>we may choose tight frame highpass filters q (s,r) (ω), 1 ≤ s ≤ m, 0 ≤ r ≤ s, by</p><formula xml:id="formula_163">q (s,r) (ω) 2 = m s s r cos ω 1 2 2(m-s) cos ω 2 2 2(m-r) sin ω 1 2 2(s-r) sin ω 2 2 2r ,</formula><p>or by <ref type="bibr">(2.16)</ref>. Highpass filter q (s,r) has vanishing moment of order (s -r, s). Let C s,r denote the constants in (2.10) with q = q (s,r) . Then it is not difficult to obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_164">(3.35) C s,r = (-1) s 2 2m-r m s s r .</formula><p>We consider the iterative channel-mixed shrinkage defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_165">(3.36) u k j = n∈Z 2 p[j -n]L k-1 n + m s=1 s r=0 n∈Z 2 q (s,r) [j -n]Ss,r(H (s,0),k-1 n , H (s,2),k-1 n , . . . , H (s,s),k-1 n ),</formula><p>where u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , L k-1 , and H (s,r),k-1 are the lowpass and highpass outputs of u k-1 with lowpass filter p and highpass filters q (s,r) , and for an s with 1 ≤ s ≤ m, each of S s,r , 0 ≤ r ≤ s, is a function of s + 1 variables. Note that (3.36) can be cast in the form of the generic iterative wavelet frame shrinkage (2.29). However, for notational convenience, we shall use the current form.</p><p>We can show as in the previous section that the tight frame filter bank given by (2.15) and (2.16) corresponds to the following general high order rotation-invariant Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php nonlinear diffusion:</p><formula xml:id="formula_166">(3.37) u t = m s=1 (-1) 1+s |α|=s ∂ α ∂x α g s |β|=s ∂ β u ∂x β 2 ∂ α u ∂x α ,</formula><p>where m ≥ 1, and g s : R → R + is smooth.</p><p>Theorem 3.11. Let u k be the resulting signal from the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage (3.36) with u 0 j = f (hj), j ∈ Z 2 , and using the tight frame filter bank {p, q (s,r) , 1 ≤ s ≤ m, 0 ≤ r ≤ s} given by (2.15) and (2.16). Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, τ k) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) the solution of (3.37), provided that Ss,r(ξ0, ξ1, . . . , ξs</p><formula xml:id="formula_167">) = ξr 1 - τ C s,k 2 h 2s gs 1 h 2s s j=0 1 (Cs,j) 2 ξ 2 j , r = 0, 1, . . . , s, (3.38) for 1 ≤ s ≤ m.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Further development.</head><p>Up to this point, we have already known that given a certain nonlinear evolution equation, we can choose a wavelet frame system and the threshold α in S α properly such that (2.29) is an iterative finite difference scheme solving the given equation. On the other hand, new nonlinear diffusion equations can be derived using the iterative shrinkage (2.29) with certain wavelet frame filter banks and proper choices of the threshold α for S α . In this section, we focus on the discussion of the iterative shrinkage (2.30) and also on other type of iterative shrinkage that originated from (2.29) and <ref type="bibr">(2.30)</ref>. The main goal of this section is to:</p><p>1. show that the iterative wavelet frame soft-thresholding algorithms commonly used in image restoration can lead to new nonlinear diffusion equations; 2. show that by borrowing ideas from some of the algorithms used in image restoration, we can design new iterative multiplicative wavelet shrinkage algorithms which can also be understood as a discretization of a certain nonlinear diffusion equation; 3. discuss how we can borrow the idea of anisotropy of the PM nonlinear diffusion to design a new iterative wavelet frame soft-thresholding algorithm which is adaptive to local image features.</p><p>3.3.1. Nonlinear diffusions from soft-thresholding. Throughout this subsection, we assume that W is the transform of a tight frame system, i.e., W W = I. We will find the corresponding diffusion equations to the iterative soft-thresholding algorithms in (2.30) with various choices of thresholds.</p><p>We start with the soft-thresholding operator with ℘ = 1 given by (2.27). We will show that the diffusion equation corresponding to the iterative shrinkage algorithm (2.30) takes the form of (3.5) with some specific diffusivity functions g . The connection between the diffusivity functions g and the shrinkage operator is given by (3.10). In fact, the specific expression for g can be solved from (3.10) by equating S α = T 1 α and choosing an appropriate α. Indeed, for T 1 θ (ξ) = ξ |ξ| max{|ξ| -θ , 0}, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_168">τ (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | g ξ 2 (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | = 1 - max{|ξ| -θ , 0} |ξ| = min 1, θ |ξ| .</formula><p>Thus the diffusivity function g in (3.5) satisfies Now, we discuss how we should choose the threshold θ properly such that when h, τ → 0, g (ξ) is a function independent of h and τ . Note that it is reasonable to assume that there exists C &gt; 0 such that h 2m /τ = C (see Proposition 4.6 in section 4), where m is the largest number among</p><formula xml:id="formula_169">g (ξ 2 ) = min (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | τ , C<label>(</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_170">|β 1 |, . . . , |β L |. If we choose θ = τ |ξ| C ( ) β h |β | g (ξ 2</formula><p>), with some smooth function g : R → R + , then we have the following formula for the diffusivity functions g : (3.39)</p><formula xml:id="formula_171">g (ξ 2 ) = min (C ( ) β ) 2 C h 2(m-|β |) , g (ξ) = min (C ( ) β ) 2 C, g (ξ 2 ) for |β | = m, g (ξ 2 ) for 1 ≤ |β | &lt; m</formula><p>whenever h is small enough. Then we have the following result.</p><p>Theorem 3.12. Let {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } be a given tight frame filter bank, and let q ( ) have vanishing moment β with the associated constant C </p><formula xml:id="formula_172">α(d) = α ,n (d ,n ) = τ |d ,n | C ( ) β h |β | g ((d ,n ) 2 ) : 1 ≤ ≤ L, n ∈ Z 2 ,</formula><p>with g : R → R + being some smooth function; and we set h 2m /τ = C for some constant C &gt; 0 with h and τ sufficiently small. Let u k be generated from the iterative soft-thresholding algorithm (2.30) with ℘ = 1. Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) being the solution of the diffusion equation (3.5) with the diffusivity functions given by (3.39).</p><p>Note that in Theorem 3.12, the threshold α depends on the wavelet frame coefficient d, which means that the threshold in the iterative soft-thresholding algorithm (2.30) will be changing along with the iteration. However, the threshold used in the literature of wavelet or wavelet frame based image restoration is generally chosen independently of the iteration. The following corollary, which is a special case of Theorem 3.12, describes the type of differential equation that is approximated by the iterative soft-thresholding (2.30) when the threshold α is independent of the iteration. Corollary 3.13. Under the same assumptions and notation as Theorem 3.12, if we choose the threshold α as</p><formula xml:id="formula_173">α = α ,n = τ λ C ( ) β h |β | 1 ≤ ≤ L, n ∈ Z 2</formula><p>for some constants λ &gt; 0, then u k generated from (2.30) with ℘ = 1 approximates the solution of the diffusion equation (3.5) with the diffusivity functions given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_174">g (ξ 2 ) = min (C ( ) β ) 2 C, λ |ξ| for |β | = m, λ |ξ| for 1 ≤ |β | &lt; m.</formula><p>In particular, when L = 2, β 1 = (1, 0), β 2 = (0, 1), and C</p><p>(1) For example, we can use any B-spline tight frame filter bank, such as the piecewise linear framelets. We only need to properly adjust the threshold in a way similar to that described in Corollary 3.3, i.e., introducing an additional power of h so that the terms corresponding to higher order derivatives vanish as h → 0. 2. The diffusion <ref type="bibr">(3.40)</ref> resembles the (anisotropic version of) mean curvature flow for λ 1 = λ 2 ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_175">β1 = C (2) β2 = C β (e.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_176">u t = λ ∂ ∂x 1 u x1 |u x1 | + ∂ ∂x 2 u x2 |u x2 | ,</formula><p>except that the flow induced by iterative soft-thresholding, i.e., <ref type="bibr">(3.40)</ref>, is more regular in the sense that the diffusivity is bounded above.</p><p>For ℘ = 2, we consider the following rotation-invariant diffusion:</p><p>(3.41)</p><formula xml:id="formula_177">u t = L =1 (-1) 1+|β | ∂ β ∂x β g |β |=|β | ∂ β u ∂x β 2 ∂ β u ∂x β .</formula><p>Here, for a given β , the summation</p><formula xml:id="formula_178">|β |=|β | = { : |β |=|β |} .</formula><p>The relation between the shrinkage operator and the diffusivity functions g is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_179">(3.42) S (ξ ) = ξ 1 - τ C ( ) β 2 h 2|β | g 1 h 2|β | |β |=|β | ξ 2 C ( ) β 2 , 1 ≤ ≤ L.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Now, for</head><formula xml:id="formula_180">T 2 θ (ξ ) = ξ |β |=|β | |ξ | 2 1 2 max |β |=|β | |ξ | 2 1 2 -θ , 0 , we have τ (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | g |β |=|β | ξ 2 (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | = 1- T 2 θ (ξ ) ξ = min 1, θ |β |=|β | |ξ | 2 1 2 , or g |β |=|β | ξ 2 = min (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2|β | τ , (<label>C</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_181">( ) β ) 2 h |β | θ τ |β |=|β | C ( ) β ξ 2 1 2 .</formula><p>Following the same idea as the case ℘ = 1 and assuming h 2m /τ = C for some C &gt; 0, we can choose</p><formula xml:id="formula_182">θ = τ |β |=|β | C ( ) β ξ 2 1 2 (C ( ) β ) 2 h |β | g |β |=|β | ξ 2 , so that (3.43) g |β |=|β | ξ 2 =    min (C ( ) β ) 2 C, g |β |=|β | ξ 2 for |β | = m, g |β |=|β | ξ 2 for |β | &lt; m</formula><p>whenever h is small enough. Then, we have the following result. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN Theorem 3.15. Let {p, q (1) , . . . , q (L) } be a given tight frame filter bank, and let q ( ) have vanishing moment β with the associated constant C ( ) β given by (2.10) and m = max {|β | : 1 ≤ ≤ L}. Assume that the threshold α(d) for wavelet frame coefficients d takes the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_183">α(d) = α ,n (d ,n ) = τ |β |=|β | C ( ) β d ,n<label>2 1 2 (C ( )</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_184">β ) 2 h |β | g |β |=|β | (d ,n ) 2 : 1 ≤ ≤ L, n ∈ Z 2 ,</formula><p>with g : R → R + being some smooth function; and we set h 2m /τ = C for some constant C &gt; 0 with h and τ sufficiently small. Let u k be generated from the iterative soft-thresholding algorithm (2.30) with ℘ = 2 and the threshold given above. Then, u k is a discrete approximation of {u(hj, kτ ) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} with u(x, t) being the solution of the diffusion equation (3.41) with the diffusivity functions given by (3.43).</p><p>Similar to Corollary 3.13 is the following corollary, which is a special case of Theorem 3.15.</p><p>Corollary 3.16. Under the same assumptions and notation as Theorem 3.15, if we choose the threshold α as</p><formula xml:id="formula_185">α = α ,n = τ λ C ( ) β h |β | : 1 ≤ ≤ L, n ∈ Z 2</formula><p>for some constants λ &gt; 0, then u k generated from (2.30) with ℘ = 2 approximates the solution of the diffusion equation (3.5) with the diffusivity functions given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_186">g (ξ 2 ) =      min (C ( ) β ) 2 C, λ |β |=|β | C ( ) β ξ 2 1/2 for |β | = m, λ |β |=|β | C ( ) β ξ 2 1/2 for 1 ≤ |β | &lt; m.</formula><p>In particular, when L = 2, β 1 = (1, 0), β 2 = (0, 1), and C</p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_187">β1 = C<label>(2)</label></formula><p>β2 = C β (e.g., the Haar framelets), the corresponding diffusion equation to (2.30) is</p><formula xml:id="formula_188">(3.44) u t = ∂ ∂x 1 min C, λ 1 /C β |∇u| u x1 + ∂ ∂x 2 min C, λ 2 /C β |∇u| u x2 , with C = (C β ) 2 C.</formula><p>Remark 3.17. The diffusion (3.44) resembles the well-known mean curvature flow (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">58]</ref>) for λ 1 = λ 2 ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_189">u t = λ ∂ ∂x 1 u x1 |∇u| + ∂ ∂x 2 u x2 |∇u| ,</formula><p>except that the flow induced by iterative soft-thresholding, i.e., <ref type="bibr">(3.44)</ref>, is more regular in the sense that the diffusivity is bounded above. In other words, the iterative isotropic soft-thresholding algorithm with threshold given in Corollary 3.16 solves a regularized mean curvature flow. The mean curvature flow has been used in image restoration as a regularizer that removes noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">61]</ref>. Since the equation becomes singular when |∇u| ≈ 0, a regularized diffusivity was used to replace |∇u|, which is |∇u| := |∇u| 2 + 2 . However, such regularization reduces the ability of the PDE model to preserve edges. It is known in the literature that soft-thresholding of wavelet frame coefficients can well preserve edges. Therefore, Corollary 3.16 reveals that (3.44) is a better regularization of the mean curvature flow than using |∇u| in place of |∇u|. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php 3.3.2. Image-restoration embedded diffusion. Other than the balanced and synthesis based model, the analysis based model (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">59]</ref>) is also frequently used in image restoration. This subsection shows that, inspired by algorithms solving the analysis based model, a new class of nonlinear diffusions, with the underlying image restoration model embedded, can be derived.</p><p>Due to the diffusive nature of the diffusion equations, one drawback of the nonlinear diffusions we have seen so far is that, when t → ∞, noise and all image features will vanish. For a good diffusion equation, image features diffuse more slowly than noise or other artifacts. Therefore, in practice, an appropriate stopping time should be chosen for these diffusion equations. Also, since these diffusion equations do not have an idea of what image restoration problem they are solving, they are not guaranteed to produce relevant image restoration results. Therefore, we need to properly place the model of the underlying image restoration into the diffusion equations.</p><p>Image restoration is usually cast as the following linear inverse problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_190">(3.45) Au = f + η,</formula><p>where f is the observed image, η is additive noise, and A is a linear operator corresponding to an image restoration problem (i.e., A = I for denoising, A = (a * ) for deblurring, etc.). In a discrete setting, we shall denote A, u, and f as A, u, and f , respectively. Since A is usually ill posed, regularization based methods are usually adopted to find a reasonable solution. In the literature, various types of regularization have been used, including the TV model <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[55]</ref>, and the wavelet or wavelet frame based approach, which includes a synthesis based approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">39]</ref>, an analysis based approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">59]</ref>, and a balanced approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">7]</ref>.</p><p>Here, we shall focus on the following analysis based model that was recently proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[37]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_191">(3.46) min u H λ (W u) + µ 2 Au -f 2 2 + µ 2 2 A Au -A f 2 D ,</formula><p>where H λ is the Huber function (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[37]</ref> for details) and u 2 D = u, Du with D = (I -µA A) -1 . Two algorithms solving (3.46) were proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[37]</ref>: one is based on the proximal forward-backward splitting (PFBS) algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">7]</ref>; the other is based on the accelerated proximal gradient (APG) algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[57]</ref> (also known as FISTA <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[4]</ref>). Throughout the rest of this subsection, we assume again that W is a tight frame, i.e., W W = I.</p><p>Start with the PFBS algorithm that solves (3.46), (3.47)</p><formula xml:id="formula_192">u k = (I -µA A)W T λ (W u k-1 ) + µA f , k = 1, 2, . . . ,</formula><p>where T λ is the soft-thresholding operator defined by either (2.27) or (2.28). Then, comparing the PFBS algorithm (3.47) with (2.29), it is natural to generalize (2.29) to the following algorithm:</p><formula xml:id="formula_193">(3.48) u k = (I -µA A)W S α k-1 (W u k-1 ) + µA f , k = 1, 2, . . . .</formula><p>It is not clear which energy function the algorithm (3.48) tries to minimize, since the threshold value α k-1 = α(W u k-1 ) depends on W u k-1 , which is changing along with the iteration. However, if α k = α for all k, then it is not hard to show (similarly as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[37]</ref>) that (3.48) is a PFBS algorithm that solves the following optimization Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_194">min u 1 2 √ α • W u 2 2 + µ 2 Au -f 2 2 + µ 2 2 A Au -A f 2 D .</formula><p>Therefore, when α k changes with k, algorithm (3.48) can be understood as an attempt to solve</p><formula xml:id="formula_195">(3.49) min u 1 2 α(W u) • W u 2 2 + µ 2 Au -f 2 2 + µ 2 2 A Au -A f 2 D .</formula><p>Indeed, at each iteration k, if we let α(W u) = α(W u k-1 ) in (3.49) and conduct one step of PFBS, we obtain the algorithm <ref type="bibr">(3.48)</ref>. Now, we discuss the formulas of the nonlinear diffusions to which the algorithms (3.48) correspond. Once we have them, the corresponding diffusions to the algorithm (3.47) are automatically given by Theorems 3.12 and 3.15. We assume that the continuum and discrete versions of the operator A satisfy the following consistency property:</p><formula xml:id="formula_196">(3.50) Av = Av + O(h) and A v = A v + O(h),</formula><p>where v j = v(jh) for j ∈ Z 2 and v smooth enough. For the equations in (3.50) and below, their meaning is that the left-hand side (in sequence space) of the equation is a discretization of the smooth function on the right-hand side of the equation. We choose µ = κτ with some constant κ &gt; 0. When the shrinkage given by (3.17) is used, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_197">µA AW S α (W u) = κτ A Au + O(τ h) + O(τ 2 ).</formula><p>Then, assuming (3.50), choosing the shrinkage given by (3.17) and following a similar derivation as in section 3.1, we can obtain that the PDE approximated by algorithm (3.48) takes the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_198">(3.51) u t = L =1 (-1) 1+|β | ∂ β ∂x β g u, ∂ β1 u ∂x β1 , . . . , ∂ β L u ∂x β L ∂ β ∂x β u -κA (Au -f ).</formula><p>In particular, when L = 2 with β 1 = (1, 0), β 2 = (0, 1) and g 1 = g 2 = g(ξ 2 1 + ξ 2 2 ), we have the following second-order nonlinear diffusion:</p><formula xml:id="formula_199">u t = div g |∇u| 2 ∇u -κA (Au -f ),</formula><p>which was considered in <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[63]</ref>. Now, recall the APG algorithm that solves (3.46) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[37]</ref>. Given some initial guess v 0 and v 1 , and letting t 0 = 1, t -1 = 0, the algorithm reads</p><formula xml:id="formula_200">v k = u k-1 + t k-2 -1 t k-1 (u k-1 -u k-2 ), u k = (I -µA A)W T λ (W v k ) + µA f , k = 1, 2, . . . ,<label>(3.52)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_201">t k = 1+ √ 1+4(t k-1 ) 2 2</formula><p>. Following a similar argument as before, we have the following algorithm that generalizes (2.29): (3.53) </p><formula xml:id="formula_202">u k = (I-µA A)W S α k-1 (1+γ k-1 )W u k-1 -γ k-1 W u k-2 +µA f , k = 1,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_203">γ k-1 = t k-2 -1 t k-1 .</formula><p>The algorithm (3.53) (resp., <ref type="bibr">(3.52)</ref>) is different from the PFBS algorithm (3.48) (resp., <ref type="bibr">(3.47)</ref>) in that it has both u k-1 and u k-2 involved in the iteration and the weighting given by t k is changing along with the iteration. These differences makes APG require a much smaller number of iterations to converge than the PFBS algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">4]</ref>. The corresponding differential equation to the APG algorithm (3.53) will also be quite different from that of the PFBS algorithm <ref type="bibr">(3.48)</ref>. Once we find the corresponding nonlinear PDE to <ref type="bibr">(3.53)</ref>, the corresponding diffusions to the algorithm (3.52) are automatically given by Theorems 3.12 and 3.15.</p><p>We first have the following lemma about the asymptotical properties of t k and γ k , whose proof is provided at the end of this subsection. Lemma 3.18. Let t k , γ k , k = 2, 3, . . ., be the sequences defined by 2  2</p><formula xml:id="formula_204">t k = 1+ √ 1+4(t k-1 )</formula><p>with t 1 = 1, and γ k = (t k-1 -1)/t k . Then</p><formula xml:id="formula_205">(3.54) t k k = 1 2 + O log k k and (3.55) 1 -γ k = 3 k + O log k k 2 .</formula><p>For u k j = u(jh, τ k) with u smooth enough, Taylor's expansion with respect to the time variable at t = τ (k -1) gives us</p><formula xml:id="formula_206">(1 + γ k-1 )u k-1 j -γ k-1 u k-2 j = u(jh, τ (k -1)) + O(τ ), (3.56) u k -(1 + γ k-1 )u k-1 j + γ k-1 u k-2 j = (1 -γ k-1 )τ u t (jh, τ (k -1)) +τ 2 1 + γ k-1 2 u tt (jh, τ (k -1)) + O(τ 3 ).</formula><p>What makes algorithm (3.53) different from <ref type="bibr">(3.48)</ref> is that u k-2 is also involved in the expression, which means we have u at three time steps present in the algorithm. This suggests to us that, with a slightly different choice of the shrinkage operator, the corresponding PDE of algorithm (3.53) can be second-order in time. However, such correspondence turns out to be slightly different from all other correspondences we have established so far. Suppose k is some large integer of size O( 1 τ ), i.e., k = C 1 /τ for some C 1 &gt; 0. This is a reasonable assumption if we assume that the time interval [0, T ] is divided uniformly with size τ , and we focus on the behavior of (3.53) for large k. By Lemma 3.18, 1+γ k 2 → 1 as k → ∞. Assume that (3.50) holds, and we take µ = τ 2 κ with some κ &gt; 0 and choose the following shrinkage function: (3.57)</p><formula xml:id="formula_207">S α ,n (d) (d 1,n , . . . , d L,n ) = d ,n 1 - τ 2 C ( ) α C ( ) β h |α |+|β | g d 1,n C (1) β1 h |β1| , . . . , d L,n C (L) β L h |β L |</formula><p>for 1 ≤ ≤ L. We can see from (3.56) and Lemma 3.18 that, when τ and h are asymptotically small and k = O( 1 τ ), the algorithm (3.53) behaves asymptotically like the following nonlinear evolution PDE that is second-order in time: (3.58)</p><formula xml:id="formula_208">u tt + Cu t = L =1 (-1) 1+|β | ∂ β ∂x β g u, ∂ β1 u ∂x β1 , . . . , ∂ β L u ∂x β L ∂ β ∂x β u -κA (Au -f</formula><p>), Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php where C = 3/(kτ ), the positive constant term in (1 -γ k-1 )/τ = 3 kτ + O( log k k 2 τ ). For example, when k = C 1 /τ , then C = 3/C 1 . During the review process, we were made aware that a discovery similar to (3.58) was made in <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[60]</ref> without partial differentials on the right-hand side. </p><formula xml:id="formula_209">a k = 1 + 1 + a 2 k-1 , we have 1 + a k-1 &lt; a k &lt; 2 + a k-1 , k ≥ 2.</formula><p>Thus,</p><formula xml:id="formula_210">(k -1) + a 1 &lt; • • • &lt; 1 + 1 + a k-2 &lt; a k &lt; 2 + 2 + a k-2 &lt; • • • &lt; 2(k -1) + a 1 ,</formula><p>and hence, we have </p><formula xml:id="formula_211">a n+1 = 1 + 1 + a 2 n = 1 + a n 1 + (1/a n ) 2 = 1 + a n 1 + 1 2 1 a 2 n - 1 8 1 a 4 n + O( 1 n 6 ) = 1 + a n + 1 2 1 a n - 1 8 1 a 3 n + O 1 n 5 .</formula><p>Thus, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_212">(3.61) a n+1 -a n = 1 + 1 2 1 a n + O 1 n 3 , n ≥ 1, which leads to a k -a 1 = k-1 n=1 (a n+1 -a n ) = k -1 + 1 2 k-1 n=1 1 a n + O(1) = k -1 + O(log k),</formula><p>where the last last equality follows from (3.60) and the fact </p><formula xml:id="formula_213">-γ k = 1 - a k-1 -2 a k = a k -a k-1 a k + 2 a k = 1 + 1/(2a k-1 ) + O(1/k 3 ) a k + 2 a k = 3 a k + O 1 k 2 = 3 k + O(log k) + O 1 k 2 = 3 k + O log k k 2 .</formula><p>This shows (3.55).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.3.3.</head><p>Adaptive thresholding for wavelet frame shrinkage. Most of the iterative wavelet (frame) shrinkage algorithms for image restoration use one, or a few, fixed thresholds for all coefficients. Since the original image to be restored can be sparsely approximated by wavelet frames, the threshold should be chosen such that the wavelet frame coefficients corresponding to features of the image, such as edges, are above the threshold. The rest of the coefficients are set to zero, which does not hamper the restoration quality since the representation is sparse and thus most of the small nonzero coefficients correspond to noise instead of signal.</p><p>However, for a given natural image, it contains components with varied regularity. Therefore, a threshold should be chosen according to the following criteria:</p><p>1. A large threshold should be chosen where the image is regular, while a small threshold should be chosen around singularities, and the value of such a threshold should depend on the type of the singularities. 2. The threshold near singularities not only should be moderately small but also should be chosen such that we only introduce smoothing along the level sets of the image and do not introducing any smoothing or even sharpening in the directions normal to the level sets. 3. Since the restored image changes along with the iteration, the threshold should also be modified properly to incorporate the updated information of local regularities of the image. Therefore, to get a desirable image restoration through iterative wavelet frame shrinkage, we need a thresholding strategy satisfying the above three conditions.</p><p>It is not obvious how to design such a thresholding strategy from only the perspective of wavelet frame transform. However, since we have the connection between wavelet frame shrinkage and nonlinear diffusions, we can borrow ideas from nonlinear diffusions, e.g., anisotropic diffusions, and use them to design a self-adaptive thresholding strategy for iterative wavelet shrinkage.</p><p>Take the PM equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref> as an example. This anisotropic diffusion equation reads</p><formula xml:id="formula_214">u t = div g(|∇u| 2 )∇u ,</formula><p>where g is a function satisfying</p><formula xml:id="formula_215">(3.62)      g : [0, ∞) → (0, ∞) decreasing; g(0) = 1; g(x) → 0 as x → ∞; g(x) + 2xg (x) &gt; 0 for x ≤ K; g(x) + 2xg (x) &lt; 0 for x &gt; K.</formula><p>One example of g is g(x) = 1 1+x p /K for some constant K &gt; 0 and p &gt; 1/2. The diffusion coefficient of the PM equation is g(|∇u| 2 ), which controls the amount of diffusion at each location. By the specific assumption on g, we can see that at smooth regions (|∇u| is small), g(|∇u| 2 ) is large, which means more diffusion is allowed; while Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN near singularities (|∇u| is large), g(|∇u| 2 ) is small, meaning less diffusion is allowed. If we rewrite the PM equation as (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_216">u t = g(|∇u| 2 )u T T + g(|∇u| 2 )u N N , with g(x) = g(x) + 2xg (x), N = ∇u |∇u| ,<label>and</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_217">T = N ⊥ , |T | = 1,</formula><p>we can see that around singularities, the amount of diffusion across the singularities may be negative. A negative diffusivity means that we have a locally backward diffusion, and hence the singularities such as edges are enhanced, which is desirable for image restoration.</p><p>An alternative way of interpreting such anisotropic diffusion is that the diffusion at different locations of an image stops at a different time or even moves in opposite directions: diffusion in regions with singularities stops earlier to prevent smearing or even moves backward to enhance sharp features, while diffusion in smooth regions stops late in order to remove a sufficient amount of noise and other oscillatory artifacts.</p><p>Following the idea of the PM equation, we can choose the threshold α for T ℘ α in the iterative wavelet frame soft-thresholding algorithm (2.30) to be adaptive to local features of the given image. Also, when we have a specific image restoration model (3.45) available, we can embed the model within the algorithm similarly to <ref type="bibr">(3.48)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">(3.53)</ref>. Now, we present the following iterative wavelet frame soft-thresholding algorithm with adaptive thresholds:</p><formula xml:id="formula_218">(3.63) u k = (I -µA A)W T ℘ θ k-1 (W u k-1 ) + µA f , with ℘ = 1 or 2,</formula><p>where u 0 = f the initial data (e.g., the observed noisy image) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_219">θ k := θ(Gσ * W u k ) := θ(d k ) (3.64) := α0,n = 0; α ,n (d k ) = C g h -2s |β |=|β | (d k ,n ) 2 : n ∈ Z 2 , 1 ≤ ≤ L</formula><p>with C ≥ 0 being some fixed constant and g (x) satisfying the first two conditions of (3.62), d k = G σ * W u k , where G σ denotes a discretized Gaussian with variance σ and s satisfying</p><formula xml:id="formula_220">s = |β | for ∈ : |β | = min 1≤ ≤L {|β |} , s ≤ |β | otherwise.</formula><p>The reasons we require g to satisfy only the first two sets of conditions of (3.62), i.e., we do not require the diffusivity to have a backward-diffusion mechanism, are that (1) in contrast to the shrinkage operator S, the soft-thresholding operator already has an edge-sharpening effect, and (2) when the observed image f is blurred by the blurring operator A, the presence of the image restoration model in (3.63) (second term) also has a sharpening effect.</p><p>Similarly, we can have the following iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithm with adaptive thresholding that resembles <ref type="bibr">(3.53)</ref>, which is an accelerated version of (3.63): (3.65)</p><formula xml:id="formula_221">u k = (I-µA A)W T ℘ θ k-1 (1 + γ k-1 )W u k-1 -γ k-1 W u k-2</formula><p>+µA f , ℘ = 1 or 2, Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php where γ k-1 = t k-2 -1 t k-1 , t -1 = 0, t 0 = 1, and θ k is given by either <ref type="bibr">(3.64)</ref> or</p><formula xml:id="formula_222">θ k := θ G σ * (1 + γ k-1 )W u k -γ k-1 W u k-1 .</formula><p>4. Convergence analysis. This section provides convergence analysis of the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage (2.29) for a second-order quasilinear parabolic equation and the convergence of the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage algorithms (2.29) and (2.30) for generic thresholds.</p><p>Consider the following second-order nonlinear diffusion equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_223">(4.1)        ∂u ∂t = ∂ ∂x1 g 1 ∂u ∂x1 2 ∂u ∂x1 + ∂ ∂x2 g 2 ∂u ∂x2 2 ∂u ∂x2</formula><p>in Ω × (0, t e ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_224">u = 0 on ∂Ω × (0, t e ), u(x, 0) = u 0 (x)</formula><p>in Ω,</p><p>where Ω = (0, 1) 2 ⊂ R 2 , t e &gt; 0, and the initial data u 0 (x) ∈ L 2 (Ω). We shall show that under suitable assumptions, we have that (2.29) converges to the solution of (4.1) with a certain order of accuracy which depends on the choice of the corresponding wavelet frame system. Note that we can obtain similar convergence analyses for most of the nonlinear diffusions considered in this paper, provided that the given diffusion is well-posed. For simplicity and clarity, we shall focus on the diffusion (4.1). We will also analyze the stability and convergence of the following generic iterative wavelet frame shrinkage:</p><formula xml:id="formula_225">(4.2) u k = W S α k-1 (W u k-1 ), 2 -shrinkage, W T θ k-1 (W u k-1 ), 1 -shrinkage, with α k := α(d k ), θ k := θ(d k )</formula><p>, where d k := W u k . In order to include most of the iterative shrinkage formulas we have discussed in the previous sections, we assume the thresholding functions S α (d) and T θ (d) take the following forms:</p><formula xml:id="formula_226">(4.3)          S α (d) = S α ,n (d ,n ) = d ,n (1 -α ,n (d)) : 0 ≤ ≤ L, n ∈ Z 2 , T θ (d) = T θ ,n (d ,n ) = d ,n w max w -θ ,n (d), 0 ; w = w(d 1,n , . . . , d L,n ) : 0 ≤ ≤ L, n ∈ Z 2 , with (4.4)    α(d) = α ,n (d) = g (d 1,n , . . . , d L,n , h, τ ) : 0 ≤ ≤ L, n ∈ Z 2 , θ(d) = θ ,n (d) = w g (d 1,n , . . . , d L,n , h, τ ) : 0 ≤ ≤ L, n ∈ Z 2 .</formula><p>We shall prove that, under suitable assumptions on the function g , the iteration (4.2) has a subsequence that converges weakly to a function in L 2 (Ω) as h, τ → 0 and k = O( 1 τ ) → ∞; and such convergence is stable. 4.1. Convergence of <ref type="bibr">(2.29)</ref>. This subsection focuses on the convergence of the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage (2.29), with a proper choice of thresholds, to a solution of the nonlinear diffusion equation (4.1) as τ, h → 0. To prove convergence of (2.29), we need to first make sure the corresponding PDE (4.1) is well-posed, for which we shall make the following assumptions. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN Assumption 4.1. We assume that, for each = 1, 2, g (ξ) ∈ C ∞ (R) are nonnegative functions satisfying 0 &lt; ξg (ξ 2 ) ≤ B, ξ ∈ R, where B is a positive constant.</p><p>Under Assumption 4.1, it is clear from the theory of nonlinear semigroups and monotone operators <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[6]</ref> that the quasilinear parabolic equation (4.1) is well-posed, i.e., there exists a unique solution for each given initial data, and it is continuously dependent on the initial data with respect to the L 2 -norm (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[34]</ref> for a proof). With well-posedness of the differential equation, Lax's equivalent theorem implies that, to prove convergence of (2.29), we only need to show consistency and stability of this iterative method. For convenience, we shall also make the following assumptions on the underlying wavelet frame systems of (2.29). Note that the assumptions below are satisfied by all tensor-product B-spline tight frame systems constructed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[53]</ref>.</p><p>Assumption 4.2. We shall consider the discretization given by a tensor-product tight frame system with FIR filters {q ( ) : 0 ≤ ≤ L}, where q (0) = p and L ≥ 2. Assume that each q ( ) with 1 ≤ ≤ L has vanishing moments of order β and has total vanishing moments of order K \{|β | + 1} with 1 ≤ |β | &lt; K . In particular, we require that β 1 = (1, 0), β 2 = (0, 1), and K 1 = K 2 .</p><p>4.1.1. Consistency. To show consistency, we need to show that for any given u ∈ C ∞ (R 2 ), when the algorithm (2.29) is applied to {u(hj, τ k) : j ∈ Z 2 , k = 1, 2, . . .} we will recover the PDE (4.1) plus the local truncation error which decreases to zero with a certain order of τ and h.</p><p>Lemma 2.3 implies that, for any u ∈ C ∞ (R 2 ) and h &gt; 0 small enough, we have, for 1 ≤ ≤ L,</p><formula xml:id="formula_227">(4.5) 1 h |β | j∈Z 2 q ( ) [j]u(hm ± hj) = C ( ) β ∂ β u(hm) ∂x β + O(h K -|β | ).</formula><p>For example, when the Haar wavelet frame system is used, we have K 1 = K 2 = 2; when the piecewise linear wavelet frame system is used, we have K 1 = K 2 = 3. By Theorem 3.5 and Corollary 3.3, we can take the following threshold α for the shrinkage operator S α (d) that is in correspondence with the diffusivity functions of (4.1):</p><formula xml:id="formula_228">(4.6)    α ,n (d ,n ) = τ (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2 g (d ,n ) 2 (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2 for = 1, 2, α ,n (d ,n ) = 0 for 3 ≤ ≤ L.</formula><p>Then, we have the following consistency result stating that the iterative shrinkage method (2.29) using a tight wavelet frame satisfying Assumption 4.2 is consistent of order O(τ ) + Proof. We need to show that for any u ∈ C ∞ (R 2 ), we have  </p><formula xml:id="formula_229">u k+1 j -u k j -τ 2 =1 1 C ( ) β h |β | m q ( ) [j -m]g 1 C ( ) β h |β | n q ( ) [n]u k n+m 2 • 1 C ( ) β h |β | n q ( ) [n]u k n+m = τ u k t,j + 2 =1 g (u k β ) 2 u k β β ,j + O(τ 2 ) + 2 =1 O(τ h K -|β | ),</formula><formula xml:id="formula_230">4.7) S α (d) = {d ,n (1 -α ,n (d ,n )) : n ∈ Z 2 , 0 ≤ ≤ L}</formula><p>with α ,n given in (4.6). Now, we address the stability condition for our iterative multiplicative shrinkage algorithm (2.29) as follows.</p><p>Assumption 4.5. Given the shrinkage operator S α (d) in (4.7), we assume that α ,n (ξ) is differentiable for each and n, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_231">ξ 1 -α ,n (ξ) = 1 -α ,n (ξ) -ξα ,n (ξ) ≤ 1 for all 0 ≤ ≤ L and n ∈ Z 2 .</formula><p>The following proposition shows that the stability requirements in Assumption 4.5 can be easily achieved in practice by assuming τ = O(h 2 ). Proposition 4.6. Suppose Assumption 4.1 holds for the diffusivity functions of (4.1). Given the choice of thresholding α in (4.6), the stability requirements in Assumption 4.5 can be achieved by taking τ = Ch 2 for some C independent of τ and h.</p><p>Proof. First, observe that</p><formula xml:id="formula_232">(4.8) 1 -α ,n (ξ) -ξα ,n (ξ) ≤ 1 ⇔ 0 ≤ α ,n (ξ) + ξα ,n (ξ) ≤ 2. Let C := τ (C ( ) β ) 2 h 2 . Then, we have α ,n (ξ) = Cg Cξ 2 /τ ⇒ α ,n (ξ) = 2 C 2 ξ τ g Cξ 2 τ .</formula><p>Therefore,</p><formula xml:id="formula_233">α ,n (ξ) + ξα ,n (ξ) = Cg Cξ 2 τ + 2 C 2 ξ 2 τ g Cξ 2 τ = C g Cξ 2 τ + 2 Cξ 2 τ g Cξ 2 τ .</formula><p>Recall the assumption we imposed in Assumption 4.1:</p><formula xml:id="formula_234">0 &lt; (ξg (ξ 2 )) = g (ξ 2 ) + 2ξ 2 g (ξ 2 ) ≤ B.</formula><p>Thus, (4.8) is satisfied, whence we have C ≤ 2 B , which yields the condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_235">τ = Ch 2 with C ≤ 2(C ( ) β ) 2 /B.</formula><p>This concludes the proof.</p><p>Assume that the computation domain Ω = (0, 1) 2 is discretized by a dyadic grid</p><formula xml:id="formula_236">{2 -n k : 0 &lt; k 1 , k 2 &lt; 2 n , n ≥ 1}.</formula><p>Therefore, the mesh-size for spatial discretization is h = 2 -n . We denote the index set </p><formula xml:id="formula_237">O 2 h ⊂ Z 2 as O 2 h := {k ∈ Z 2 : 0 &lt; k 1 , k 2 &lt; 2 n }.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_238">h : L 2 (Ω) → 2 (Z 2 ) as (4.9) (T h u) k := 2 n u, φ n,k , with k ∈ O 2 h ,</formula><p>where φ n,k = 2 n φ(2 n • -k). When a wavelet frame system associated to a refinable function φ is used in the shrinkage algorithms, the underlying sampling is given by the operator T h . We denote the space 2,h (O 2 h ) as the collection of all vectors supported on the index set O 2 h equipped with the following norm:</p><formula xml:id="formula_239">v 2 2,h (O 2 h ) = j∈O 2 h |v j | 2 h 2 .</formula><p>Note that we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_240">T h u 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ C u L2(Ω)</formula><p>with some C independent of h (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref>).</p><p>Given a t ∈ (0, t e ), let K = t/τ . We define the discrete operator M h,τ :</p><formula xml:id="formula_241">2,h (O 2 h ) → 2,h (O 2 h ) as M h,τ v := K k=0 W S α k W v for v ∈ 2,h (O 2 h ).</formula><p>Note that the shrinkage operator S α (d) defined in (2.26) is nonlinear in d, since α depends on d (see (4.7)). Thus the product above means a product of compositions of nonlinear operators.</p><p>Definition 4.7. We say that the discrete algorithm (2.29) is stable if for any &gt; 0 there exist δ &gt; 0 independent of τ, h, such that for any u, v ∈ L 2 (Ω) with u -v L2(Ω) &lt; δ, we have </p><formula xml:id="formula_242">M h,τ T h v -M h,τ T h u 2,h (O 2 h ) &lt; ; i.e.,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_243">Proof. Note that W 2,h (O 2 h ) = W 2,h (O<label>2</label></formula><p>h ) ≤ 1, which is in fact true for all tight wavelet frame systems. We have </p><formula xml:id="formula_244">M h,τ T h v -M h,τ T h u 2,h (O 2 h ) = K k=0 W S α k W T h v - K k=0 W S α k W T h u 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ S α K W K-1 k=0 W S α k W T h v -S α K W K-1 k=0 W S α k W T h u 2,h (O 2 h ) . Let d K v = W K-1 k=0 W S α k W T h v and d K u = W K-1 k=0 W S α k W T h u.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Then, we have</head><formula xml:id="formula_245">M h,τ T h v -M h,τ T h u 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ S α K (d K v ) -S α K (d K u ) 2,h (O 2 h ) = d K v • (1 -α(d K v )) -d K u • (1 -α(d K u )) 2,h (O 2 h ) (Assumption 4.5) ≤ d K v -d K u 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ S α K-1 (d K-1 v ) -S α K-1 (d K-1 u ) 2,h (O 2 h ) • • • ≤ T h v -T h u 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ C v -u L 2 (Ω) .</formula><p>This shows that {M h,τ T h } h,τ is indeed equicontinuous on L 2 (Ω).</p><p>4.1.3. Convergence. We show that well-posedness + consistency + stability ⇒ convergence. We first establish the following lemma regarding the consistency between the sampling T h and the pointwise sampling for smooth functions. Given u ∈ C(Ω), we denote the pointwise sampling operator R h u as</p><formula xml:id="formula_246">(4.10) (R h u) k = u(hk), k ∈ O 2 h .</formula><p>Then we have the following lemma.</p><p>Lemma 4.9. Let φ be a tensor-product B-spline refinable function; then we have, for every u ∈ C(Ω), (4.11)</p><formula xml:id="formula_247">T h u -R h u 2,h (O 2 h ) → 0 as h → 0. Proof. We first note that • 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ • 1(O 2 h )</formula><p>. Thus, we focus on showing that (4.12)</p><p>T h u -R h u 1 (O 2 h ) → 0 as h → 0.</p><p>Let k be the rectangular domain [ k1 2 n , k1+1</p><p>2 n ] × [ k2 2 n , k2+1</p><p>2 n ] with k ∈ O 2 h . Then we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_248">T h u -R h u 1(O 2 h ) = k∈O 2 h 2 n u, φ n,k -u(2 -n k) 2 -2n = Ω k∈O 2 h 2 n u, φ n,k -u(2 -n k) χ k dx = Ω k∈O 2 h 2 n u, φ n,k χ k -u(2 -n k)χ k dx.</formula><p>By <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr">Lemma 4</ref>.1], for every u ∈ L 1 (Ω) ⊃ C(Ω) we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_249">Ω k∈O 2 h 2 n u, φ n,k χ k (x) -u(x) dx → 0 as n → ∞.</formula><p>On the other hand, the fact that for every u ∈ C(Ω)</p><formula xml:id="formula_250">Ω k∈O 2 h u(2 -n k)χ k -u(x) dx → 0 as n → ∞</formula><p>is well known in real analysis. We then have (4.12) by triangular inequality. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php Given any v ∈ L 2 (Ω) and a t ∈ (0, t e ), we define an operator M : L 2 (Ω) → L 2 (Ω) as u(x, t) = M (v), where u(•, t) ∈ L 2 (Ω) is a solution of (4.1) with u 0 = v. Since the PDE (4.1) is well-posed w.r.t. the L 2 -norm <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[34]</ref>, then for any &gt; 0, there exists δ &gt; 0 such that for any u -v L2(Ω) &lt; δ, we have M u -M v L2(Ω) &lt; . In other words, M is well defined and continuous on L 2 (Ω). Proof. Given any u ∈ L 2 (Ω) and a given δ &gt; 0, we can always find v ∈ C ∞ (Ω) such that u -v L2(Ω) &lt; δ. Then by triangular inequality we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_251">T h M u -M h,τ T h u 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ T h M u -T h M v 2,h (O 2 h ) + T h M v -M h,τ T h v 2,h (O 2 h ) + M h,τ T h v -M h,τ T h u 2,h (O 2 h )</formula><p>, where the three terms on the right-hand side of the inequality correspond to wellposedness, consistency, and stability, respectively. Note that T h M u-T h M v 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ C T M u -M v L2(Ω) . Thus, the first term above can be made arbitrarily small for a properly chosen v due to well-posedness of the problem M . The same argument holds for the last term above as well, due to stability in Proposition 4.8. We now show that</p><formula xml:id="formula_252">T h M v -M h,τ T h v 2,h (O 2</formula><p>h ) → 0 as h, τ → 0. Indeed, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_253">T h M v -M h,τ T h v 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ T h M v -R h M v 2,h (O 2 h ) + R h M v -M h,τ R h v 2,h (O 2 h ) + M h,τ T h v -M h,τ R h v 2,h (O 2 h )</formula><p>. By <ref type="bibr">(4.11)</ref> and that M v ∈ C ∞ (Ω), the first term goes to zero. By our previous consistency analysis in Proposition 4.3, we have that the second term goes to zero as well. Finally, following a similar proof of stability in Proposition 4.8, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_254">M h,τ T h v -M h,τ R h v 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ T h v -R h v 2,h (O<label>2</label></formula><p>h ) → 0. This concludes the proof of this theorem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.2.</head><p>Behavior of the generic wavelet frame shrinkage (4.2). We will analyze the asymptotic behavior of the iterative wavelet frame shrinkage (4.2) under suitable assumptions, which are given as follows.</p><p>Assumption 4.12. We make the following assumptions on the wavelet frame system we use and the threshold function g = g (ξ 1 , . . . , ξ L , h, τ ):</p><p>1. Let W be the transform operator of a tensor-product wavelet frame system constructed from a univariate B-spline function, and assume that W is the transform operator of the canonical duel system. 2. We assume that, for each 0 ≤ ≤ L, g ∈ C 1 (R L ), 0 ≤ g ≤ 1, and ∂ ∂ξ j ξ 1 -g (ξ 1 , . . . , ξ L , h, τ ) ≤ 1 for all 1 ≤ j ≤ L, for every (ξ 1 , . . . , ξ L ) ∈ R L , and h, τ &gt; 0 small enough. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN Similarly to before, we assume Ω = (0, 1) 2 is discretized by the dyadic grids {k2 -n : 0 &lt; k 1 , k 2 &lt; 2 n , n ≥ 1}. Then, h = 2 -n and τ = O(2 -np ) for some p &gt; 0. The value p comes naturally from the second assumption of Assumption 4.12 (e.g., p = 2 in section 4.1). We define the adjoint operator of T h as T * h : 2,h (O 2 h ) → L 2 (Ω):</p><formula xml:id="formula_255">T * h v = 2 -n j∈O 2 h v j φ n,j .</formula><p>We note that T h u 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ C T u L2(Ω) and T * h u L2(Ω) ≤ C T u 2,h (O 2 h ) . With Assumption 4.12, we have the following theorem. Theorem 4.13. Suppose all requirements in Assumption 4.12 are satisfied. For any given artificial time t &gt; 0, let K = t/τ be the stopping iteration of (4.2).</p><p>1. For any given initial data v ∈ L 2 (Ω), we denote the K step iterative procedure based on the first formula of (4.2) as a nonlinear operator T * h M S h T h : L 2 (Ω) → L 2 (Ω):</p><formula xml:id="formula_256">T * h M S h T h v := T * h K k=0 W S α k W T h v.</formula><p>Then, for every v ∈ L 2 (Ω), the sequence {T * h M S h T h v} h has a weakly converging subsequence in L 2 (Ω). Furthermore, the iterative algorithm (4.2) is stable in the following sense: for any &gt; 0, there is a δ &gt; 0 independent of h, such that for any u -v L2(Ω) &lt; δ, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_257">T * h M S h T h u -T * h M S h T h v L2(Ω) &lt; . 2.</formula><p>Denote the K step iterative procedure based on the second formula of (4.2) as a nonlinear operator T * h M T h T h : L 2 (Ω) → L 2 (Ω):</p><formula xml:id="formula_258">T * h M T h T h v := T * h K k=0 W T θ k W T h v.</formula><p>The conclusions in 1 also hold for T * h M T h T h . Proof. We shall only prove part 1, since the proof of part 2 is similar. Note that from the first set of assumptions of Assumption 4.12, we have W 2,h (O 2 h ) = C W and W 2,h (O 2 h ) = 1 C W . Therefore, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_259">T * h M S h T h v L2(Ω) ≤ C T C W S α k W K-1 k=0 W S α k W T h v 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ C T C W W K-1 k=0 W S α k W T h v 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ C T K-1 k=0 W S α k W T h v 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ • • • ≤ C T T h v 2,h (O 2 h ) ≤ C 2 T v L2(Ω)</formula><p>, where the second inequality follows from the assumption 0 ≤ g ≤ 1. This shows that {T * h M S h T h v} h is bounded; hence it has a weakly converging subsequence in L 2 (Ω). On the other hand, using the second inequality of 2 of Assumption 4.12 and following a derivation similar to that in the proof of equicontinuity in Proposition 4.8, we can easily show that, for any u, v ∈ L 2 (Ω) and some constant C &gt; 0, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_260">T * h M S h T h u -T * h M S h T h v L2(Ω) ≤ C u -v L2(Ω)</formula><p>, which gives us the stability. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php 5. Numerical simulations and comparisons. In this section, we conduct numerical experiments using some of the algorithms we discussed in earlier sections. Recall the general image restoration model</p><formula xml:id="formula_261">Au = f + η,</formula><p>where f is the observed image and η is assumed to be Gaussian white noise. We take image deblurring as the specific image restoration problem, where A is the convolution operator with the kernel generated in MATLAB by "fspecial('gaussian',11,1.5)." The test images and their blurry noisy counterparts are presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>. To measure the quality of the restored image, we use the peak signal-to-noise ratio (PSNR) value defined by PSNR := -20 log 10 u -u 2 N ,</p><p>where u and u are the original and restored images, respectively, and N is the total number of pixels in u.</p><p>We will compare performance of some of the algorithms discussed earlier in this paper for image deblurring. For convenience of the readers, we list these algorithms here. Note that all the parameters that are not specifically mentioned below are chosen manually for optimal image restoration quality. For Algorithm 1 and 2, we stop our iteration when we have the highest PSNR values of the restored images. For the rest of the algorithms, since we have image restoration model embedded in the algorithms, we can let the iteration run until convergence. In our experiments, we adopt the following stopping criterion for algorithms 3-6:</p><formula xml:id="formula_262">u k -u k-1</formula><p>BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN All of the following algorithms are implemented on a Windows laptop with Intel Core i7 processor (1.73 GHz) and 8GB memory.</p><p>List of algorithms used for comparison.</p><p>1. PM equation with standard discretization (PM-SD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_263">u t = div g(|G σ * ∇u| 2 )∇u (PM).</formula><p>We take g(ξ) = 1 1+ξ/K . 2. PM equation discretized by Haar (PM-Haar) and piecewise linear (PM-Linear) B-spline wavelet frame systems:</p><formula xml:id="formula_264">u k = W S α k-1 (W u k-1</formula><p>).</p><p>Here we choose the level of decomposition Lev = 1 for W . The shrinkage operator S α k-1 (d k-1 ) = {S α ,n (d k-1 ) (d k-1 ) : 1 ≤ ≤ L} is chosen as in (3.21) for = 1, 2 with g(ξ) = 1/(1 + ξ/K). We choose S α ,n for 3 ≤ ≤ L as in Corollary 3.7 with s = |α 1 | + |β 1 | = 2 and g C</p><p>(1) </p><formula xml:id="formula_265">1 ξ 1 h |β1| , C<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_266">u k = (I -µA A)W T 2 λ (W u k-1 ) + µA f .</formula><p>Here we choose the level of decomposition Lev = 3 for W and λ is some fixed threshold. 4. Adaptive multiplicative-thresholding by Haar (AMT-Haar) and piecewise linear (AMT-Linear) B-spline wavelet frame systems:</p><p>u k = (I -µA A)W S α k-1 (W u k-1 ) + µA f .</p><p>Here we choose the level of decomposition Lev = 3 for W . We take S α k-1 (W u k-1 ) = {S α l, ,n (W l u k-1 ) (W l u k-1 ) : 0 ≤ l ≤ Lev -1, 1 ≤ ≤ L}, where W l u = {W l, u : 1 ≤ ≤ L}. The shrinkage operator S α l, ,n is chosen the same as in 2 for l = 0 and S α l, ,n = S α 0, ,n for l &gt; 0. 5. Adaptive soft-thresholding by Haar (AST-Haar) and piecewise linear (AST-Linear) B-spline wavelet frame systems:</p><formula xml:id="formula_267">u k = (I -µA A)W T 2 θ k-1 (W u k-1</formula><p>) + µA f . Here, the threshold θ k-1 = θ l, (W l,1 u k-1 , W l,2 u k-1 , . . . , W l,L u k-1 ) : 0 ≤ l ≤ Lev -1, 1 ≤ ≤ L is chosen as θ l, (ξ 1 , ξ 2 , . . . , ξ L ) = C g</p><formula xml:id="formula_268">|β |=|β | ξ 2 C ( ) β h β</formula><p>for all l = 0, 1, . . . , Lev -1. Here we choose g = 1/(1 + x 0.25 /K), Lev = 3, and C &gt; 0 as some fixed constants. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>2 2 and cos ω2 2 2</head><label>22</label><figDesc>, respectively. Thus from the fact p(ω) 2 = ξ m η m and the identity 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>β</head><label></label><figDesc>given by (2.10) and m = max {|β | : 1 ≤ ≤ L}. Assume that the threshold α(d) for wavelet frame coefficients d takes the form</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>( 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>60) k &lt; a k &lt; 2k, k = 2, 3, . . . . From (3.59) again, for n ≥ 1,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>k n=1 1 n</head><label>1</label><figDesc>= O(log k). Therefore, we have a k /k = 1 + O(log k/k). This shows that (3.54) holds. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php Applying (3.61) with n = k -1, we have 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>2 =1</head><label>2</label><figDesc>O(h K -|β | ). Proposition 4.3. The numerical algorithm (2.29) with a tight wavelet frame system satisfying Assumption 4.2 is consistent of order O(τ )+O(h K -|β | ) to the diffusion equation (4.1) provided that the thresholds are chosen as (4.6).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Definition 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">10</ref>. A method M h,τ is said to converge to M if for any v ∈ L 2 (Ω) we haveT h M v -M h,τ T h v 2,h (O 2 h ) → 0 as τ, h → 0.Theorem 4.11. With Assumptions 4.1-4.5 and assuming that M v ∈ C ∞ (Ω) whenever v ∈ C ∞ (Ω), the iterative algorithm (2.29) with threshold (4.6) converges to the nonlinear diffusion (4.1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Test images: Original (first row) and observed (second row). The PSNR values of the observed images are 23.4519 (Barbara), 22.4428 (Boat), and 22.5482 (Peppers). The image size of "Barbara" is 195 × 195, and both "Boat" and "Peppers" are of size 256 × 256.</figDesc><graphic coords="50,76.90,215.80,114.80,114.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Iterative soft-thresholding algorithm by Haar (IST-Haar) and piecewise linear (IST-Linear) B-spline wavelet frame systems:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</figDesc><table><row><cell>BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN</cell></row><row><cell>and</cell></row><row><cell>q</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</figDesc><table><row><cell>BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php where R ,n= ( |β |=|β | |d ,n | 2 ) Observe that R ,n = R ,n if |β | = |β |.For all shrinkage operators, we always fix the threshold α 0,n = 0, which means we never penalize the low frequency coefficients d 0,n .</figDesc><table><row><cell>1 2 . With the notation in (2.5) and choosing the shrinking functions S as S α and α , we can rewrite both (2.22) and (2.25) as T ℘</cell></row><row><cell>(2.29)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Here we regroup β , 1 ≤ ≤ L, according to the order of vanishing moments |β | of highpass filter q ( ) , and we assume the largest number among |β 1 |, . . . , |β L | is m.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>m</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>.32)</cell><cell>d 1,1 :=</cell><cell>|d ,n |, and d 1,2 =</cell><cell>|d ,n | 2</cell><cell>2 .</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>,n</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>l=1 |β |=l</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN are</figDesc><table /><note><p>∂ β ∂x β u(x, t) and ∂ β ∂x β G (x, t) in the diffusion equation (3.1), where G (x, t) = g (( ∂ β u ∂x β ) 2 ) ∂ β u ∂x β ,</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2u x u y u xy + u 2 y u yy | u| , Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="7">BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">which can be written as</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(3.27) u t =</cell><cell>∂ ∂x</cell><cell>g(| u| 2 )</cell><cell>∂u ∂x</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>∂ ∂y</cell><cell>g(| u| 2 )</cell><cell>∂u ∂y</cell><cell>-g(| u| 2</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. The corresponding nonlinear Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">diffusion equation is</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ut=</cell><cell>∂ ∂x1</cell><cell>g1</cell><cell>∂u ∂x1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>∂u ∂x1</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>∂ ∂x2</cell><cell>g2</cell><cell>∂x2 ∂u</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN Furthermore, if the α given in (3.34) satisfies (2.31), both the optimality properties in (2.34) hold for u k .</figDesc><table><row><cell>(3.34)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>h 4</cell><cell>5,n ) 2</cell><cell>for = 4.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN</figDesc><table /><note><p><p>)</p>β h |β | θ τ |ξ| .</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php with C = (C β ) 2 C. Remark 3.14. 1. To have (2.30) approximate the second-order nonlinear diffusion (3.40), we do not have to use Haar framelets.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>g., the</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">Haar framelets), the corresponding diffusion equation to (2.30) is</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(3.40)</cell><cell>u t =</cell><cell>∂ ∂x 1</cell><cell>min C,</cell><cell>λ 1 |u x1 |</cell><cell>u x1 +</cell><cell>∂ ∂x 2</cell><cell>min C,</cell><cell>λ 2 |u x2 |</cell><cell>u x2 ,</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2, . . . , Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</figDesc><table><row><cell>where</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>What makes the nonlinear diffusion(3.51)  different from those we have seen in earlier sections is that (1) we have the underlying image restoration model embedded in the PDEs, which leads to better image restoration results as supported by our numerical simulations;<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(2)</ref> it is now safe to seek the steady state solution, i.e., u(x, ∞), which makes the determination of stopping easier.We end this subsection by providing the proof of Lemma 3.18. Proof of Lemma 3.18. For simplicity of presentation, denote a k = 2t k , k = 1, 2, . . . .</figDesc><table><row><cell>Remark 3.19.</cell></row><row><cell>1. Both of the algorithms (3.47) and (3.48) discretize the PDE (3.51). For</cell></row><row><cell>different types of shrinkage, we have different diffusivity functions g (see,</cell></row><row><cell>e.g., the previous subsection for the form of g that corresponds to the soft-</cell></row><row><cell>thresholding).</cell></row><row><cell>2. From</cell></row><row><cell>(3.59)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN 4.1.2. Stability. Similarly to standard finite difference discretization of nonlinear diffusions, the temporal step size τ and the spatial step size h should satisfy a certain stability condition. For the diffusivity functions in (4.1), the multiplicative shrinkage operator S α defined in (2.26) takes the following form:</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php Given any function u ∈ L 2 (Ω), and a compactly supported tensor-product B-spline function φ ∈ L 2 (R 2 ), we define the sampling operator T</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the set of operators {M h,τ T h } h,τ is equicontinuous.Now we show that {Mh,τ T h } h,τ is indeed equicontinuous if Assumptions 4.2 and 4.5 are satisfied. Proposition 4.8. Algorithm (2.29), with threshold satisfying (4.6), is stable if Assumptions 4.2 and 4.5 are satisfied.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php BIN DONG, QINGTANG JIANG, AND ZUOWEI SHEN</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0"><p>q 1 (0) = 0. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>, Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_2"><p>/ f 2 &lt; 10 -5 . Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_3"><p>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>. http://www.siam.org/journals/mms/15-1/M103745.html</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The first author was supported by the Thousand Talent Plan of China.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>where u k j = u(hj, τ k) and u k t,j = u t (jh, τ k), u k β := ∂ β u(x, τ k) ∂x β , and u k β ,m :=</p><p>Then by <ref type="bibr">(4.5)</ref>,</p><p>). Applying <ref type="bibr">(4.5)</ref> to G , we have 1</p><p>where the second to the last equality follows from the fact that G is differentiable.</p><p>. Therefore, we have</p><p>This concludes the proof of the proposition.</p><p>Remark 4.4. 1. Note from Corollary 3.3 that, instead of setting the thresholds α ,n to zeros for 3 ≤ ≤ L, we can take the choices of α given by (3.13). The proof of consistency for these cases is very similar to that of Proposition 4.3. 2. The order of consistency we have just derived may not optimal. Optimal order of consistency can be obtained by a more careful local truncation error analysis. However, finding an (optimal) order of approximation of the solutions of PDEs is not what we want to focus on in this paper. Although the analysis in this section can be modified to reveal the order of approximation, we will only prove convergence without addressing the order of convergence.</p><p>The reason is that in image restoration, or image processing and analysis in general, all data are discrete to begin with, and most data do not have, nor do they need, a corresponding continuum version. Therefore, in this section, we show convergence only to rigorously justify that wavelet frame shrinkage is indeed a discretization of the corresponding PDE. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php 6. Image-restoration embedded diffusion with standard discretization (IRED-SD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref>: Our results in Table <ref type="table">1</ref> show that the discretization provided by wavelet frame shrinkage is better than the standard discretization by <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref> in terms of restoration quality. The results in Table <ref type="table">2</ref> show that with the image restoration model being properly incorporated into the algorithms, better results can be obtained. More importantly, the new algorithms AMT and AST outperform the IST algorithm that is commonly used in wavelet frame based image restoration problems. In addition, the AMT algorithm, which is a discretization of IRED, generates better results than the standard discretization of IRED.</p><p>In section 3.3.2, we proposed an accelerated version of AMT and IRED. The accelerated algorithm and PDE produce results of quality similar to those of their corresponding nonaccelerated versions, while the total number of iterations and computation time are greatly reduced. For the same image deblurring problem and with the same stopping criterion, we implemented the accelerated (APG) version of AMT and IRED following the generic formulas of (3.53) and (3.58). To be more precise, we implement the following accelerated AMT (A-AMT)</p><p>where the shrinkage operator S α is chosen exactly the same as that of Algorithm 4 above. The accelerated IRED takes the form</p><p>which is discretized by the standard finite differencing <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[51]</ref>. We shall call the A-IRED discretized by such finite differencing A-IRED-FD. The parameters for A-AMT are chosen exactly the same as AMT, and we choose C = 0.2 for A-IRED. A comparison of efficiency is summarized in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>. Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13. Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright; see http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">PSNR values of the restored images by algorithms 3-6: IST-Haar, IST-Linear</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Qingtang</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AST-Linear, and IRED-SD</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>AMT-Linear</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Table 3 Comparisons for image deconvolution</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A-Amt-Linear Ired-Fd A-Ired-Fd</forename><surname>Amt-Linear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>sec) PSNR Barbara 23.38</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Time (sec.) PSNR Time (sec) PSNR Time (sec) PSNR Time</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Image</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelet Galerkin solutions for one-dimensional partial differential equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Amaratunga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Internat. J. Numer. Methods Engrg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2703" to="2716" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parabolic equations for curves on surfaces: Part II. Intersections, blow-up and generalized solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Angenent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Aubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kornprobst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mathematical Problems in Image Processing: Partial Differential Equations and the Calculus of Variations</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fast iterative shrinkage-thresholding algorithm for linear inverse problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Teboulle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/080716542</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/080716542" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Imaging Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image inpainting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bertalmio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Caselles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ballester</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 27th Annual Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques</title>
		<meeting>the 27th Annual Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques<address><addrLine>New York, Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="424" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Brezis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Opérateurs Maximaux Monotones et Semi-groupes de Contractions dans les Spaces de Hilbert</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>North-Holland, Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convergence analysis of tight framelet approach for missing data recovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Comput. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image restorations: Total variation, wavelet frames and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Math. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1033" to="1089" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data-driven tight frame construction and image denoising</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Comput. Harmon. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Framelet based deconvolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framelet-based image inpainting algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Comput. Harmon. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="149" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Simultaneous cartoon and texture inpainting, Inverse Problems Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="395" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Split Bregman methods and frame based image restoration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-F</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/090753504</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/090753504" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multiscale Model. Simul</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Restoration of chopped and nodded images by framelets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-F</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/040615298</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/040615298" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1205" to="1227" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image selective smoothing and edge detection by nonlinear diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Catté</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-L</forename><surname>Lions</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Morel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Coll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/0729012</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/0729012" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Numer. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deconvolution: A wavelet frame approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Numer. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="587" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framelet algorithm for enhancing video stills</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Comput. Harmon. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelet algorithms for high-resolution image reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/S1064827500383123</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/S1064827500383123" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1408" to="1432" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tight frame: An efficient way for high-resolution image reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Riemenschneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Comput. Harmon. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="115" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Signal recovery by proximal forward-backward splitting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Combettes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wajs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/050626090</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/050626090" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multiscale Model. Simul</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1168" to="1200" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ten Lectures on Wavelets, CBMS-NSF Regional Conf</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Daubechies</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ser. in Appl. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<pubPlace>SIAM, Philadelphia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MRA-based constructions of wavelet frames</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Daubechies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Framelets</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Comput. Harmon. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright</title>
		<idno>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iteratively solving linear inverse problems under general convex constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Daubechies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Teschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Vese</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inverse Problems Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Denoising and Enhancement of Digital Images-Variational Methods, Integrodifferential Equations, and Wavelets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Didas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<pubPlace>Saarbrücken, Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Saarland University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ph.D. Dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Properties of higher order nonlinear diffusion filtering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Didas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weickert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Burgeth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Imaging Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelet frame based blind image inpainting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Comput. Harmon. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="279" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">X-ray CT image reconstruction via wavelet frame based regularization and Radon domain inpainting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="349" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An efficient algorithm for 0 minimization in wavelet frame based image restoration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="350" to="368" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frame based segmentation for medical images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun. Math. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="559" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frame based surface reconstruction from unorganized points</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">230</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8247" to="8255" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MRA-based wavelet frames and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mathematics in Image Processing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Providence, RI</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AMS</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="158" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">De-noising by soft-thresholding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Donoho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="627" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous cartoon and texture image inpainting using morphological component analysis (MCA)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Elad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Starck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Querre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Donoho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Comput. Harmon. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Partial Differential Equations</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Providence, RI</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AMS</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fadili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Starck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://spars05.irisa.fr/ACTES/PS1-1.pdf" />
		<title level="m">Sparse representations and Bayesian image inpainting</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Rennes, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings of SPARS</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inpainting and zooming using sparse representations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fadili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Starck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Murtagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelet frame based algorithm for 3D reconstruction in electron microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/130914474</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/130914474" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="B45" to="B69" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An EM algorithm for wavelet-based image restoration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Figueiredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="906" to="916" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A bound optimization approach to wavelet-based image deconvolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Figueiredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Image Processing</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE International Conference on Image Processing<address><addrLine>Genoa, Italy; Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005. 2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="782" to="785" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison principle and convexity preserving properties for singular degenerate parabolic equations on unbounded domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Giga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ishii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-H</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indiana Univ. Math. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geometric evolutions of phase-boundaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Giga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">On the Evolution of Phase-Boundaries</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gurtin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mcfadden</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelet solutions of linear and nonlinear elliptic, parabolic and hyperbolic problems in one space dimension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Glowinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lawton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ravachol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tenenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computing Methods in Applied Sciences and Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990. 1990</date>
			<pubPlace>Paris; SIAM, Philadelphia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The split Bregman algorithm for L1-regularized problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/080725891</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/080725891" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Imaging Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A vector thermodynamics for anisotropic surfaces, I: Fundamentals and application to plane surface junctions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Cahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="368" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GPU-based iterative cone-beam CT reconstruction using tight frame regularization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Med. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3787" to="3807" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correspondence between frame shrinkage and high-order nonlinear diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Numer. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evaluation of connection coefficients of compactly supported wavelets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Latto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Resnikoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tenenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the French-USA Workshop on Wavelets and Turbulence</title>
		<meeting>the French-USA Workshop on Wavelets and Turbulence<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="89" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Copyright © by SIAM. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Qingtang</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Downloaded 04/02/17 to 134.148.10.13</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.siam.org/journals/ojsa.php" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Redistribution subject to SIAM license or copyright</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Noise removal using fourth-order partial differential equation with applications to medical magnetic resonance images in space and time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lysaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lundervold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1579" to="1590" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Explicit algorithms for a new time dependent model based on level set motion for nonlinear deblurring and noise removal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marquina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/S1064827599351751</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/S1064827599351751" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feature-oriented image enhancement using shock filters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Rudin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/0727053</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/0727053" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Numer. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="919" to="940" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scale-space and edge detection using anisotropic diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Perona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intel</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="629" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelets and the numerical solution of partial differential equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Affine systems in L 2 (R d ): The analysis of the analysis operators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Funct. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="408" to="447" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Affine systems in L 2 (R d ) II: Dual systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Fourier Anal. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="617" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear total variation based noise removal algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rudin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Osher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fatemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelet frames and image restorations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Congress of Mathematicians</title>
		<meeting>the International Congress of Mathematicians<address><addrLine>Hyderabad, India</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2834" to="2863" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An accelerated proximal gradient algorithm for frame-based image restoration via the balanced approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-C</forename><surname>Toh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/090779437</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/090779437" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Imaging Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="596" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interface motion in models with stochastic dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Spohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Stat. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1081" to="1132" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image decomposition via the combination of sparse representations and a variational approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Starck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Elad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Donoho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1570" to="1582" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A differential equation for modeling Nesterov&apos;s accelerated gradient method: Theory and insights</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Candes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mach. Learn. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">153</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iterative methods for total variation denoising</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Vogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Oman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/0917016</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/0917016" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized Perona-Malik equation for image restoration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Process. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="167" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variational deblurring of images with uncertain and spatially variant blurs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Welk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Theis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weickert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pattern Recognition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="492" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correspondences between wavelet shrinkage and nonlinear diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mrázek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weickert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Steidl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Scale-Space Methods in Computer Vision</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Griffin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lillholm</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="116" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Lecture Notes in Comput. Sci. 2695</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From two-dimensional nonlinear diffusion to coupled Haar wavelet shrinkage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mrázek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weickert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Vis. Commun. Image Represent</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the equivalence of soft wavelet shrinkage, total variation diffusion, total variation regularization, and SIDEs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Steidl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weickert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mrázek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Welk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1137/S0036142903422429</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1137/S0036142903422429" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Numer. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="686" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Anisotropic Diffusion in Image Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weickert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>B. G. Teubner</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<pubPlace>Stuttgart, Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image enhancement using fourth order partial differential equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>You</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kaveh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 32nd Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers</title>
		<meeting>the 32nd Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers<address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1677" to="1681" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fourth-order partial differential equations for noise removal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>You</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kaveh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1723" to="1730" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">0 minimization of wavelet frame based image restoration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Comp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="995" to="1015" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
