<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Multiscale Convolutional Neural Networks for Fault Diagnosis of Wind Turbine Gearbox</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Multiscale Convolutional Neural Networks for Fault Diagnosis of Wind Turbine Gearbox</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">49B93C621C0A8137994883520524A3E8</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TIE.2018.2844805</idno>
					<note type="submission">This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TIE.2018.2844805, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T13:11+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Intelligent fault diagnosis</term>
					<term>multiscale feature extraction</term>
					<term>convolutional neural network (CNN)</term>
					<term>deep learning</term>
					<term>classification</term>
					<term>wind turbine (WT) gearbox</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This paper proposes a novel intelligent fault diagnosis method to automatically identify different health conditions of wind turbine (WT) gearbox. Unlike traditional approaches where feature extraction and classification are separately designed and performed, this study aims to automatically learn effective fault features directly from raw vibration signals while classify the type of faults in a single framework, thus providing an end-to-end learning based fault diagnosis system for WT gearbox without additional signal processing and diagnostic expertise. Considering the multiscale characteristics inherent in vibration signals of a gearbox, a new multiscale convolutional neural network (MSCNN) architecture is proposed to perform multiscale feature extraction and classification simultaneously. The proposed MSCNN incorporates multiscale learning into the traditional CNN architecture, which has two merits: (1) high-level fault features can be effectively learned by the hierarchical learning structure with multiple pairs of convolutional and pooling layers and (2) multiscale learning scheme can capture complementary and rich diagnosis information at different scales. This greatly improves the feature learning ability and enables better diagnosis performance. The proposed MSCNN approach is evaluated through experiments on a WT gearbox test rig. Experimental results and comprehensive comparison analysis with respect to the traditional CNN and traditional multiscale feature extractors have demonstrated the superiority of the proposed method.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>I N recent years, wind energy has experienced a remarkable expansion in response to the increase of worldwide energy demand <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, and accordingly, wind turbines (WTs) have been Guoqian Jiang and Ping Xie are with the School of Electrical Engineering, Yanshan University, Qinhuangdao 066004, China(e-mail: jgqysu@gmail.com, pingx@ysu.edu.cn). This work was conducted when Guoqian Jiang was a joint Ph.D. student at the Department of Electrical, Computer and Biomedical Engineering, University of Rhode Island, Kingston, RI 02881, USA .</p><p>Haibo He is with the Department of Electrical, Computer and Biomedical Engineering, University of Rhode Island, Kingston, RI 02881, USA (e-mail: he@ele.uri.edu).</p><p>Jun Yan is with the Concordia Institute for Information Systems Engineering, Concordia University, Montr éal, Qu ébec, Canada. (e-mail: jun.yan@concordia.ca).</p><p>extensively installed both onshore and offshore. Usually, these turbines are located in remote areas and are exposed to harsh environments, suffering from constantly varying loads and experiencing extreme operational temperature and humidity changes. As a result, they are prone to failures and result in high operation and maintenance (O&amp;M) costs. Gearbox, as a critical component in WTs, often suffers from various failures, such as bearing damage, tooth breakage and gear crack, and has shown high failure rates and resulted in high maintenance costs <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> due to its long downtimes and complex repair procedures. Statistically, maintenance cost caused by the gearbox is about 13% of the overall WT cost <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Therefore, condition monitoring and fault diagnosis of WT gearbox have gained considerable attentions from both academia and industry <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>Generally, a fault diagnosis system is defined from a pattern recognition perspective. It consists of three general steps: data acquisition, feature extraction, and fault classification, among which the latter two are of significant importance and greatly affect the final diagnosis accuracy. The main objective of feature extraction is to extract representative features which can characterize the health conditions of the underlying machine and also help the downstream fault recognition task. Up to now, numerous feature extraction methods have been reported and discussed. For example, Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> utilized the correlation coefficient analysis in the time domain and the windowed Fourier transform in the frequency domain to extract fault features and combined with several data mining methods to identify different failure stages of a WT gearbox. Du et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> proposed a novel sparse feature identification framework based on the union of redundant dictionary to diagnose multiple faults occurred in a WT gearbox. Yang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> proposed an improved spline-kernelled chirplet transform to extract fault-related frequency features for detecting faults in a WT drive train under the time-varying operational conditions. Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> integrated ensemble empirical mode decomposition (EEMD) with independent component analysis (ICA) to separate fault components for diagnosis of bearing failures in a WT. To sum up, various signal processing methods, including classical spectral analysis, wavelet transform <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, empirical mode decomposition (EMD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, manifold learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, sparse representation <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and other variants, have been applied to extract effective fault-related features from vibration signals from different perspectives. Then these extracted features are fed into some shallow machine learning algorithms including logistic regression and support vector machine (SVM). It has been shown that the extracted features or representations 0278-0046 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p><p>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: <ref type="bibr">DOI</ref>  define the upper-bound performances of machine learning algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. These traditional shallow learning models can only provide limited diagnosis ability. In summary, traditional intelligent fault diagnosis methods still have some obvious drawbacks as follows:</p><p>1) Feature extraction and classification are separately designed and performed, both of which affect the final diagnosis performance. This is a divide and conquer strategy that cannot be optimized simultaneously. 2) All extracted features are naturally hand-crafted, requiring much prior knowledge about signal processing techniques and diagnostic expertise, which is time-consuming and labor-intensive. 3) Most of the existing methods are domain-specific and cannot be updated online and generalize well to new diagnosis domains, thus a general-purpose approach is highly desirable.</p><p>Alternatively, to address above drawbacks, deep learning may provide a promising and effective solution for intelligent fault diagnosis. Deep learning attempts to model high-level representations of data and predict/classify patterns via multiple stacked layers of nonlinear information processing units in a hierarchical architecture <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. In recent years, deep learning has been emerged as a powerful tool and successfully applied in various domains such as computer vision, speech recognition, natural language processing, and health informatics. Motivated by these successful achievements, deep learning has been recently introduced to the field of fault diagnosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Different deep models such as stacked denoising autoencoders (SDA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, deep belief network (DBN) <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, sparse filtering <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, convolutional neural networks (CNNs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> and recurrent neural network (RNN) <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> have demonstrated state-of-the-art diagnosis performance compared to traditional approaches relying on hand-crafted features.</p><p>In this paper, our goal is to develop an end-to-end fault diagnosis system based on CNNs, which is motivated by its excellent feature learning ability. The desirable system can automatically learn and discover discriminative features from raw temporal vibration signals and then classify different health conditions of the WT gearbox. However, in practice, WT gearboxes usually work in variable operation conditions, especially under different speeds or loads. Thus, vibration signals measured from the gearbox are characterized with nonlinearity and nonstationarity caused by varying speeds and loads, along with strong environment noises. Therefore, it is quite challenging to extract useful fault features from raw vibration signals for fault diagnosis. On the other hand, it is well known that WT gearboxes are complex mechanical systems consisting of bearings, gears, shafts and other mechanical components, and are usually coupled with other subsystems, such as generators. Thus, measured vibration signals using sensors installed on the house of the gearbox will contain multiple intrinsic oscillatory modes due to the interaction and coupling effects among different components and subsystems. Various mechanical rotating and reciprocating frequencies will complicate the measured vibration signals. As a result, vibration signals usually exhibit multi-scale charac-teristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and contain complex patterns at multiple time scales, which has been discussed in literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Such inherent multiscale characteristics cannot be captured by the traditional CNN architecture due to the lack of multiscale feature extraction ability. To overcome the limitation, this paper proposes a new multiscale convolutional neural network (MSCNN) architecture. This architecture is developed on top of the traditional CNN but incorporates the idea of multiscale learning and provides a more efficient and applicable way to extract fault signatures from multiple scales. As a result, it will enhance the feature learning capability and therefore improve the fault diagnosis performance. The main contributions of this paper are summarized as follows: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. RELATED WORKS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Overview of CNNs</head><p>CNNs are a specialized kind of multilayer perceptrons (MLPs) neural network, which is biologically inspired to mimic the behavior of the mammalian visual cortex <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. CNNs were originally proposed by Lecun et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> for handwritten digits classification. Up to now, CNN has been extensively applied in various application domains including automatic speech recognition and natural language processing. It has been shown that CNN can deal with various types of signals, including 1D signals and sequences, 2D images and 3D videos, due to their powerful ability of automatic feature extraction and classification. Different from the traditional fully-connected neural networks, there are three key architectural ideas <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> behind CNNs, i.e., local connectivity, shared weights and spatial pooling. These properties allow CNNs to optimize fewer parameters, learn more robust translationinvariant features and achieve better generalization on many recognition tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. CNNs for Fault Diagnosis</head><p>In recent years, motivated by the success of CNNs in a variety of classification and recognition tasks, CNNs have also been investigated in the field of fault diagnosis, especially for rotating machineries such as bearings and gearboxes. Different from 2D image data, sensory signals, such as vibration and current signals collected from the underlying machines, are naturally 1D time series sampled by sensors with a certain time interval. To apply the 2D CNN for fault diagnosis, some signal preprocessing or transformation procedures are required before input to the 2D CNN model. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, Chen et al. adopted a 2D-CNN for gearbox fault diagnosis, in which the input matrix with a size of 16 × 16 for CNN is reshaped by a vector containing 256 statistic features including RMS values, standard deviation, skewness, kurtosis, rotating frequency, and applied load. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, a 2D-CNN model was utilized to recognize four different conditions of rotating machinery, where the input of CNN is discrete Fourier transform of two-channel vibration signals from two accelerometer sensors. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, the vibration signals were first processed using wavelet transform to form spectrogram images of size 32×32 and then these images were fed into a CNN model to learn the invariant representation and recognize the fault status of the rotor system.</p><p>In the case of raw sensory signals, 1D CNN was recently developed on raw current signals for motor bearing fault detection <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, where two major blocks (i.e. feature extraction and classification) of a traditional fault detection approach were integrated together. Also, Abdeljaber et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. PROPOSED MSCNN-BASED FAULT DIAGNOSIS SYSTEM FOR WT GEARBOX</head><p>This paper focuses on the fault diagnosis of the WT gearbox under varying operational conditions. In such cases, for vibration signals measured under different speeds or loads, different conditions of the gearbox will have a considerable internal variability, which further challenges the class separability when simply extracting the fault signatures in a single scale with CNN. We argue that a more thorough and wide understanding of the signals, such as in multiple time or frequency scales, is required to enhance feature extraction and classification performance. In addition, faults occurred in gearbox components will introduce low-frequency impulse components and demodulated components. However, these fault signatures are easily masked by those inherent highfrequency components with dominant amplitudes or those strong background noises. To better extract fault signatures and capture multiscale characteristics of raw vibration signals, this paper proposes a new MSCNN architecture to incorporate multiscale feature learning into the traditional CNN architecture. The overall architecture of the proposed MSCNN is illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>. A key advantage of the proposed new architecture is to automatically learn high-level robust and useful fault features at different time scales directly from complex raw vibration signals in a parallel way through the hierarchical learning. It works in an end-to-end learning manner. Generally, it consists of three sequential stages: a multiscale coarse-grained stage, a multiscale feature learning stage and a classification stage. A. MSCNN Architecture 1) Multiscale Coarse-grained Layer: The key idea of the proposed MSCNN is to incorporate multiscale feature learning ability into the traditional CNN architecture. In a recent study <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, the down-sampling and smoothing are simultaneously used to implement multiscale operations of a raw time series input. Motivated by the work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, but differently, in this paper, we introduce a simple coarse-grained procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> to represent the raw vibration signals at multiple time scales. The coarse-grained process has been successfully used for quantifying the complexity of complex physiologic time series <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> and recently for vibration time series signals <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> measured from mechanical systems.</p><p>Given a measured vibration signal</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">x = {x 1 , x 2 , • • • , x N }</formula><p>, where x i is the value at time stamp i, and there are N timestamps for each signal. We construct consecutive coarsegrained signals {y (s) } by averaging the data points in the original signal x with a non-overlapping window of increasing length s (also called the scale factor). Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> illustrates a coarse-grained procedure for scales s = 2 and s = 3. Each element of a coarse-grained signal is calculated by using the following equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">y (s) j = 1 s js i=(j-1)s+1 x i , 1 ≤ j ≤ N s<label>(1)</label></formula><p>In fact, the coarse-grained operation is naturally to perform smoothing and down-sampling of the original signals simultaneously. In other words, this operation can also be y2 (2)  y3 (2)   y2 (3)   s=1 Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Illustration of the coarse-grained procedure for s = 2, 3.</p><p>considered as a simple low-pass filtering process through moving average with a non-overlapped window, thus those high frequency perturbations and random noises will be filtered to some extent. Compared to the multiscale transformation used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, the coarse-grained operation is simple to implement and can reduce the model complexity and computational cost. The input of the first convolutional layer (C1) is a coarsegrained signal with length L = N/s. We slide the filter with a window size of m over the whole input signal to extract local features. Accordingly, the output z i of the i-node in the feature map is defined by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">z i = σ(w T y i:i+m-1 + b)<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where w ∈ R m represents the filter vector, b denotes the bias term, y i:i+m-1 is a m-length sub-signal of input signal y starting from the i-th time step, and σ(•) is a nonlinear activation function. In this study, we choose Rectified Linear Units (ReLU) <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> σ(x) = max(0, x) as the nonlinear activation function to prevent the vanishing gradient problem and accelerate the convergence of model. As defined in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">2</ref>), the output scalar z i can be viewed as the activation of the filter on the corresponding sub-signal. By sliding the filter from the beginning time step to the ending time step, the feature map of the j-th filter can be denoted as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">z j = [z 1 , z 2 , • • • , z L-m+1 ]<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Afterwards, the pooling layers (P1) are further applied to the feature maps generated by the convolutional layer (C1), thus enabling to extract the most important and location-invariant features. In this paper, the max-pooling with a pooling length of p is adopted for calculating the local max value over the input feature map. Then the k-th pooled feature map can be obtained as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">h k = [h 1 , h 2 , • • • , h L-m p +1 ]<label>(4)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">h j = max (j-1)p+1≤i≤jp {z i }<label>(5)</label></formula><p>After the first pair of convolutional layer (C1) and maxpooling layer (P1), we obtain K 1 new feature maps. Then 0278-0046 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. these feature maps will act as the input of the second pair of convolutional layer (C2) and max-pooling layer (P2), and repeat the same operations in Eqs. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">2</ref>)-( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">5</ref>). Supposing that K 2 filters are used and learned in the second pair, the output of the pooling layer (P2) is K 2 new pooled feature maps, in which the k-th one can be denoted as h k .</p><p>Then, for each coarse-grained signal {y (s) }, we can obtain its corresponding representation q (s) learned through two alternating convolutional layers and pooling layers, which is the concatenation of all feature maps represented as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">q (s) = [h 1 , h 2 , • • • , h K2 ]<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Finally, we simply concatenate the learned representations of each coarse-grained signal to obtain a final multiscale representation of the raw input signal in a long vector, which is denoted as: q = [q (1) , q (2) , q (3) ]</p><p>Obviously, compared to the representation learned from raw vibration signal on only one single scale, the learned multiscale representations may contain complementary and rich fault pattern features at multiple time scales. Thus, they can provide complementary discriminability among different conditions to a significant extent and enable better fault classification ability.</p><p>3) Classification: The classification task for the WT gearbox fault diagnosis studied in this paper is a multiclass classification problem. The multiscale representation q obtained in the feature extraction stage is directly fed to two additional layers. The first is a fully-connected layer with ReLU units. In the output layer, we use a softmax function <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> that outputs a conditional probability for each class. Assuming that there are n classes of gearbox health conditions for the input sample x, its corresponding output probability O j ∈ [0, 1] for class j is calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">O j = e (θ (j) x) n j=1 e (θ (j) x) , j = 1, 2, • • • , n<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where θ is the model parameter to learn and n j=1 O j = 1. It will be automatically optimized based on training samples.</p><p>Similar to the traditional CNN, MSCNN is trained using gradient descent through the back propagation (BP) algorithm. The input of MSCNN is the raw temporal vibration signals, and the output is the prediction of the gearbox conditions with different class labels indicating different health conditions. For MSCNN training, we adopt the cross-entropy between the predicted class labels and the true class labels as the loss function. The Adam optimization algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> is empolyed to minimize the loss function for its efficient computation and little memory. We also use a dropout technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> on fully-connected layers in the classification stage of our MSCNN architecture to prevent overfitting. With the dropout technique, individual nodes are randomly removed with a certain probability, typically 0.5, at each training epoch. Also, this technique significantly improves the speed of training.</p><p>It is worth noting that our proposed MSCNN architecture is general and flexible, which may have different scales and different depths (i.e., pairs of convolutional layers and pooling layers). Specifically, MSCNN can effectively learn high-level fault features by using the hierarchical learning structure with multiple pairs of convolutional layers and pooling layers and capture complementary and rich diagnosis information at different scales. An MSCNN model with more scales and more layers can learn more robust and abstract fault features from more time scales, and is expected to have improved diagnosis performance. However, there is certain restriction relationship between the length of the input sample, the number of scales and the depth. As is shown in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">1</ref>), with the increase of the scale factor s, the length of coarse-grained signal decreases. Therefore, if more scales are considered, the longer input signal will be required to ensure that every coarse-grained signal contains enough information for feature extraction using convolutional layers and pooling layers. On the other hand, the pooling operation will also reduce the length of the extracted feature maps. Therefore, the deeper model also requires the longer input signal. In practical applications, we should make a suitable choice about the number of scales and the depth depending on the length of the input signal, which will be discussed in detail in Section IV.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. MSCNN-based Fault Diagnosis</head><p>In this section, an end-to-end fault diagnosis system based on the proposed MSCNN architecture is presented. The flowchart is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> and the general procedures are summarized as follows.</p><p>1)</p><p>Step 1: Collect vibration data from different health conditions of the WT gearbox using the data acquisition (DAQ) system. For each condition, we segment the whole signal into several small segments to obtain data samples for model training and testing.  extraction algorithms, our proposed MSCNN-based fault diagnosis system has several important merits as follows: 1) Multiscale. MSCNN incorporates the multiscale learning and learns useful fault features at different time scales in a parallel manner, thus obtaining multiscale representations containing more rich and complementary diagnosis information and enabling better fault diagnosis performance. 2) End-to-end. MSCNN provides an end-to-end fault diagnosis system which is directly fed with raw input data through a deep network architecture and outputs the final fault classification results. Also, it builds and captures the complex mapping relationship between raw temporal vibration signals and health condition labels. 3) General-purpose. More importantly, instead of extracting those hand-crafted features which are generally specific for certain diagnosis object, MSCNN only depends on the raw temporal signals without any complex timeconsuming transformation, domain knowledge and expert experience, and therefore is a general-purpose approach. Thus, it can be easily extended to deal with fault diagnosis problems of other industrial systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CASE STUDY</head><p>In this section, the proposed MSCNN framework is evaluated using experiments on a WT gearbox test rig. We start with the description of the test rig and experiments, and then the detailed results are shown and discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Test Rig and Data Acquisition</head><p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>, an experimental WT gearbox test rig has been set up to illustrate the effectiveness of MSCNN for fault diagnosis. This test rig is designed to simulate the operation of a real WT system. A 3-kW induction motor coupled with a speed reducer with a ratio of 40:1 is operated by the speed controller, and is used to emulate the dynamics of a WT rotor to generate a lower shaft speed. Then the lower speed at the output shaft of the reducer will increase through a two-stage parallel gearbox with total ratio 1:20 to drive a 3-kW threephase permanent magnet synchronous generator (PMSG) for power generation. Finally, the generated power was consumed by the load bank.</p><p>In this test rig, various common periodic and irregular faults occurred in the gearbox, such as chipped tooth, broken tooth, cracked gear, bearing outer race damage, can be simulated. In this study, eight health conditions of the gearbox, including one normal, three gear faults, three bearing faults and a shaft fault, are tested. All considered fault conditions occurred on the second stage (i.e, the high-speed end) of the tested gearbox, which is commonly encountered in the large-scale WT gearbox. In each experiment, a damaged component is installed inside the tested gearbox and other components remain normal. Each experiment is conducted under different operation conditions, i.e., five motor driving speeds and two loads. Vibration signals were acquired using a piezoelectric accelerometer (PCB 352C33) mounted on the end cover of the second stage of the gearbox by a data acquisition (DAQ) system with a sampling frequency of 10 kHz. The detailed description of the dataset and condition labels is summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">I</ref>, where eight health conditions are listed. In this dataset, the same health condition under different speeds and loads is treated as one class. There are 2600 samples for each health condition under ten operation conditions, and each sample contains 2000 data points. Therefore, the dataset totally contains 2600×8 = 20800 samples for eight health conditions. We adopted the 10-fold cross-validation method for performance evaluation, which is commonly used in literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. We split the original vibration dataset into 10 equal sized subsets. Of the 10 subsets, a single subset is retained as the testing set for testing the model, and the remaining 9 subsets are used as the training set. The cross-validation process is then repeated 10 times, with each of the 10 subsets used exactly once as the testing set. The average classification results of the testing set over ten folds are reported.</p><p>0278-0046 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Performance Metrics</head><p>The fault diagnosis problem studied in this paper is naturally multi-class classification (8 classes in our case). For performance evaluation and comparison, F 1 score <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> is adopted in this study. It is a commonly used comprehensive metric to the performance of a classification method, which is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">F 1 = 2T P 2T P + F P + F N<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where T P (true positive) is correctly classified as positive samples, F P (false positive) is misclassified as positive samples, T N (true negative) is correctly classified as negative samples and F N (false negative) is misclassified as negative samples. In the following studies, F 1 score for each class (health condition) calculated with the proposed method and the compared methods will be reported. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Multiscale Learning Evaluation: MSCNN vs. CNN</head><p>We first evaluate the performance of our proposed method by using the collected gearbox dataset. In order to extract more rich fault pattern features helpful for classification from raw signal, four scales are considered in our proposed MSCNN framework. The input size of MSCNN is 2000, i.e., the length of a vibration signal sample. The number of filters for two convolutional layers C1 and C2 are 16 and 32, respectively. The same filter length of 100 for all filters is used for capturing enough information from a local region of the input signal. The pooling length for two pooling layers P1 and P2 is set to 2. In the classification stage, the number of neurons in fully-connected hidden layer is chosen as 1024. The output size of MSCNN is 8, corresonding to the number of considered health conditions of the gearbox. Our proposed MSCNN is trained from scratch using the training set described in Section IV-A. As mentioned earlier, MSCNN is optimized by Adam gradient descent optimization algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> with a mini-batch size of 50 samples. The number of training epochs is 50. The learning rate is initialized to 0.001 with no decay on each update. The dropout rate of 0.5 is used for fullyconnected layers to avoid the over-fitting risk. For comparison, the traditional CNN, i.e, corresponding to the MSCNN with one scale, is considered. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref> shows the overall accuracy curves of the training set and the testing set for both MSCNN and CNN methods during the whole training process over 50 epochs for one fold. It can be seen that the training accuracy and the testing accuracy for both methods reach the stable values after 20 epochs; no over-fitting is observed. This demonstrated that the training set used here is sufficiently large to train the model with the six-layer network structure. In addition, notice that MSCNN converges to the stable value faster than CNN, which means that training an optimal MSCNN model requires less time in practice. The testing classification results over ten folds with both MSCNN and CNN methods are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>  health condition. The x-axis and y-axis represent predicted labels and true labels, respectively. Compared with MSCNN and CNN, it is easily found that for each condition, more samples are misclassified when using CNN, leading to a poor diagnosis performance. This implies that fault features in different conditions are masked in noisy raw signals and therefore it is difficult to identify using the traditional CNN performed on only one scale.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Discussions on Effects of Scale and Depth</head><p>The proposed MSCNN model involves different number of scales and different depth (i.e., the number of pairs of convolutional layers and pooling layers). Both parameters will impact the diagnosis performance of the proposed MSCNN. Herein, we investigate the effects of scale and depth.</p><p>1) Effects of Scale: Vibration signals generally show great variations in multiple observation scales, therefore it is necessary to take multiscale information into consideration. In this study, multiscale coarse-grained signals are used in the MSCNN framework in order to extract fault features at different scales. To quantitatively evaluate the effects of the chosen scales in MSCNN on the classification performance, different scales ranging from two to four are considered. In these experiments, two-layer structure MSCNN (i.e., two convolutional layers and two pooling layers ) was adopted. The average results of F 1 score over ten folds for each condition are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>, where the errorbar represents the standard deviation showing the stability of classification performance. It is easily observed that, for each condition, the proposed MSCNN from two to four scales always outperforms the traditional CNN. In general, as more scales are incorporated, MSCNN can achieve better and more reliable performance. Specifically, a significant increase from CNN to MSCNN with two scales can be observed for each condition. Furthermore, compared to the traditional CNN, a smaller standard deviation for each condition can be noticed especially for MSCNN with three or four scales, which shows a more reliable performance. This result demonstrates that the proposed MSCNN can learn more discriminative and robust features from different scales of raw vibration signals than the traditional CNN that extracts representative features at only one scale, i.e. raw vibration signal itself. Therefore, the proposed MSCNN can produce an enhanced fault diagnosis performance.</p><p>To better understand the benefits of multiscale features incorporation in the proposed MSCNN, we use the t-SNE technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> to reduce the dimensions of the learned multiscale representations in two dimension for visualization. The reduced 2-D feature representations of the testing set with different scales are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8</ref>, where the different colors represent different health conditions described in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">I</ref>. From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8</ref>, we can observe that with the increase of scales from 1 (corresponding to the traditional CNN) to 4 for MSCNN, the features within the same health condition present better cluster performance while the features of different health conditions are much more separable, which in turn enables the classifier easier to classify different health conditions. This result shows a strong identifiability and high robustness for different health conditions of the WT gearbox under ten different speeds and loads. This further proves that incorporating multiscale features can greatly improve feature learning and therefore fault diagnosis ability.</p><p>In the present study, all experiments are conducted on a workstation (Intel Core (TM) 3.4 GHz processor with 64 GB of RAM) and an NVIDIA GeForce 1080Ti GPU on a Ubuntu system platform. All considered models are trained from scratch using the training set, and therefore much more training time is required. We evaluate the training time and the testing time for the traditional CNN and the proposed MSCNN with different scales. The results are given in Table II. In this table, the training time of one epoch averaged 50 epochs and the testing time of one testing sample are calculated, respectively. In terms of training time, the proposed MSCNN consumes much more time than CNN. As more scales are considered, the more time is needed. This can be easily explained that due to the incorporation of multiple scales, the MSCNN will introduce more parameters to be trained and therefore require more time. However, as mentioned in Section III-B, all models are trained offline, and then used for online fault diagnosis. Therefore, in fault diagnosis applications, the training time will not directly affect the performance of fault diagnosis system, while the testing time is the focus when the designed fault diagnosis system is put into use. During the testing phase, the maximum time spent by MSCNN with four scales for one test sample is only 0.2036 ms, which is just slightly larger than that of CNN or with fewer scales. Therefore, our MSCNN approach is also suitable for real-time monitoring and diagnosis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Effects of Depth:</head><p>The depth of the MSCNN can determine the abstraction level of extracted features. Low-level features obtained from the raw signal may greatly suffer from speed or load variations and background noises. The abstraction level of fault features can significantly impact the classification results. To test the effects of the depth on diagnosis performance, MSCNN with one to three layers were tested, and the results are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9</ref>. It can be first seen that, for both MSCNN and the traditional CNN, the classification performance increases with the depth. This is because MSCNN with more layers can learn and extract more abstract and robust features at higher levels that are helpful in classification. The MSCNN models with two and three layers have similar performance (about 98%) in terms of F 1 score, which is significantly better (with an improvement of 7%) than the MSCNN model with only one layer. We also calculated the training time and the testing time of the CNN and the MSCNN with different layers, and the results are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">III</ref>. It is obvious that the computation overhead increases with depth for both methods. In order to reduce the computation cost, however, we chose only two layers in the feature extraction. For practical applications, to deal with more challenging and complex diagnosis tasks, a deeper model may be considered to further improve performance, especially when a large amount of data are available.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Against Noise: MSCNC vs. CNN</head><p>In real-world applications, the WT gearbox often operates in complicated working environments and the measured vibrations signals are easily contaminated by strong background noises. Therefore, it is necessary to check the robustness of the proposed MSCNN against noise. For this reason, we inject additive Gaussian white noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> to the raw vibration signals to construct noisy signals with different signal-to-noise ratios (SNRs). The SNR is defined as follows: SNR dB = 10 log 10 (</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">P signal P noise )<label>(10)</label></formula><p>where P signal and P noise denote the power of the raw signal and the injected noise, respectively. In this study, we evaluate the proposed MSCNN approach using noisy signals with different SNRs ranging from -4 dB to 14 dB. The evaluation results for both MSCNN and CNN are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">10</ref>, where the average results of F 1 scores for all eight conditions are calculated as the evaluation metric. For MSCNN, four scales are considered. It is obvious that the proposed MSCNN significantly outperforms the traditional CNN, with over 90% testing performance in terms of F 1 score within all considered SNR levels. Specifically, we can find that MSCNN obtains above 95% testing performance even when SNR is 0 dB, where the power of the noise is equal to that of the raw signal, and even increases to 98% at a stable level when SNR is greater than 4 dB. Furthermore, the proposed MSCNN exhibits a more remarkable advantage over the traditional CNN at lower SNR levels from -4 dB to 2 dB. The largest difference reaches to 11.3% at the SNR level of -2 dB. To this end, the proposed MSCNN presents superior robustness against noise without any additional denoising preprocessing, which means that MSCNN can learn and extract more robust features than the traditional CNN under the noisy environment. The result also shows that the proposed MSCNN is more suitable in practical industrial environments where more complicated environment noises and measurement interferences exist. Our proposed MSCNN method will be further evaluated using the vibration data collected from real WT gearboxes in wind farms in our future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. Comparison with Existing Multiscale CNN Architecture</head><p>In a recent study in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, a similar multi-scale convolutional network (MCNN) was proposed to address the time series classification issue and has shown the state-of-the-art performance on a large number of benchmark datasets. Herein, MCNN is compared with our proposed MSCNN method. In general, MSCNN is different from MCNN in the three following aspects:  Four scales are considered and two pairs of convolutional layers and pooling layers are used in all three models. Specifically, MCNN has one convolutional layer followed by pooling layer in local convolution and full convolution, respectively. It can be found that MCNN is slightly better than MSCNN in terms of F 1 score. Compared with MSCNN and MSCNN-II, MSCNN performs better than MSCNN-II and suggested that the global convolution may not improve the performance of MSCNN. It can be concluded that the key difference between MSNN and MCNN lies in the multiscale operation. Then, we further validated if the performance difference in terms of F 1 score between our proposed MSCNN and MCNN is significant. A two-tailed t-test was conducted for validation under the significance level of 0.05 similar to the one in <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>. The t-test results demonstrated that given the significance level of 0.05, there is no significant difference (p = 0.0713 &gt; 0.05) between MSCNN and MCNN. Also, as further shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">IV</ref>, the computation overhead of MSCNN is lower than the MCNN, mainly due to the simpler structure and a smaller number of parameters to learn of MSCNN. It should be noted that the training time and the testing time should be important factors when developing a diagnosis device for online and real-time diagnosis. From Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">IV</ref>, it is obvious that the training time of MCNN is 2.5 times more than that of MSCNN. It means that MSCNN is more efficient than MCNN especially when much more training data are available and need to be processed in realworld applications. This allows a shorter development cycle of diagnosis systems and faster releases of updates, which hugely lowers the cost of the system development. For online testing, MSCNN also took less time, which means that the diagnosis system can be used efficiently and enable a faster diagnosis in practice, which is helpful to make a timely decision for the operators. Therefore, in practical applications, MSCNN is more computationally efficient at a competitive diagnosis performance. From the comprehensive consideration of F 1 score and training and testing time, it would be more effective to apply the MSCNN method, especially for realworld industrial applications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G. Comparison With Traditional Multiscale Approaches</head><p>Furthermore, in order to demonstrate the merits of our proposed MSCNN, three traditional feature extraction methods, including multiscale entropy (MSE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, wavelet package decomposition (WPD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, and empirical mode decomposition (EMD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, are compared. MSE is used for calculating the sample entropy over multiple coarse-grained signals from different time scales of a raw vibration signal. WPD and EMD can decompose a complex vibration signal into several different components containing different frequency bands information. These methods have been considered as multiscale feature extraction ones and widely used in vibration-based fault diagnosis for rotary machines <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Among three methods, MSE is the simplest multiscale approach only requiring the average operation in the time domain, while EMD and WPD require complex and time-consuming signal transformation or decomposition. For the MSE, entropy features over 20 scales are calculated for each sample. For the WPD, we use Daubechies 4 wavelet to decompose each sample into 4 levels, thus producing 16 nodes in different frequency bands. Then, energy values of 16 nodes are computed as features. For the EMD, we calculate the energy vector of first six intrinsic mode functions (IMFs) of each sample. All extracted features with different methods are fed to a support vector machine (SVM) classifier with a Radial basis kernel function to perform the fault diagnosis task. In the case of multiclass predictions for SVM, the one-versus-one strategy is adopted here. The kernel parameter and penalty factor of SVM are determined by a 5-fold cross-validation method.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">V</ref> gives the comparison results between the proposed MSCNN and traditional multiscale feature extraction methods in terms of F 1 score over ten folds, where the classification results for each health condition and the average performance (averaged on all eight conditions) are shown. The best performance is highlighted in bold. It is easily found that the proposed MSCNN method achieves the best overall performance of 98.53%. For each condition, MSCNN obtained the over 97% F 1 score, and more stable performance which corresponds to a smaller standard deviation. Unfortunately, three traditional feature extraction methods perform worse with below 85% F 1 score. This can be explained that these traditional methods only extract a small number of features at different time scales or different frequency bands, while a lot of information cannot be effectively captured and even will be lost in the feature extraction process. The results also indicate that all extracted energy features and entropy features between different classes may be similar and therefore cannot be distinguished. On the contrary, MSCNN can automatically learn useful fault features at multiple time scales from raw signals without depending on the hand-crafted features, 0278-0046 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. thus largely reducing the demand of prior knowledge and time-consuming signal processing algorithms. In summary, traditional multiscale feature approaches are on feature-level, while MSCNN is performed on signal-level that will keep all information from the input. Therefore, the proposed MSCNN method has the potential to provide a useful alternative as a general-purpose classification procedure for intelligent fault diagnosis due to its end-to-end feature learning ability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>This paper focuses on the multiscale feature learning of complex vibration signals and proposes a new MSCNN architecture for intelligent fault diagnosis of the WT gearbox under different operational conditions. The major contribution of the new architecture is the incorporation of multiscale feature learning by introducing a coarse-grained layer into the traditional CNN. The proposed MSCNN can automatically and effectively learn complementary and rich fault features at different time scales in a parallel way directly from raw vibration signals with multiple layers, which greatly enhances feature learning ability and fault diagnosis performance. Accordingly, an MSCNN-based end-to-end fault diagnosis system is also developed. Different from those traditional fault diagnosis methods greatly relying on the handcrafted features and a shallow classification model, the developed MSCNN-based system can perform automatic feature extraction and classification simultaneously without depending on complex signal processing algorithms and prior knowledge. Experimental results demonstrated that the proposed MSCNN significantly outperformed the traditional CNN in terms of feature learning, robustness against noise, and classification performance. Compared with the traditional multiscale feature extraction methods, our proposed MSCNN has presented an end-toend fault diagnosis capacity and achieved much better performance, which are crucial for WT gearboxes that are playing an important role in reliable operation and emergency response in large-scale wind farms. More importantly, it offers a new general-purpose framework for the field of fault diagnosis and can be easily extended to deal with different machines and industrial systems.</p><p>In our future work, we will verify the scalability of our proposed MSCNN on a real large-scale WT gearbox. In addition, in the case of imbalanced data distribution in the fault diagnosis field, we will further investigate the imbalanced learning based multiscale representation learning approach to mitigate the impact from skewed data distribution between normal and faulty data, so that the performance of learning algorithms can be further improved.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Manuscript received Month xx, 2xxx; revised Month xx, xxxx; accepted Month x, xxxx. This work was supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under grant 61673336 and the Natural Science Foundation of Hebei Province under grant F2018203413 and F2016203421.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Proposed MSCNN framework for fault diagnosis using 1D vibration signals. The ith convolutional layer is denoted as Ci layer, while the ith pooling layer is denoted as Pi layer. The FC layer means fully-connected layer. In this illustration, three scales (s = 1, 2, 3) are considered.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,-15.59,47.50,652.52,237.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>As shown in Fig. 2, for different scale factors, we can obtain multiple filtered signals, each of which corresponds to different smoothed representations of the original signals. In the case of fault diagnosis, it provides a more efficient way to characterize vibration signals over a range of scales, and results in multiple coarse-grained signals containing different and complementary fault pattern information. In the following stage, we will learn more useful and robust feature representations from these coarse-grained signals and the original signals with stacked convolutional layers and pooling layers. 2) Multiscale Feature Learning: The goal of this stage is to learn high-level effective fault features from multiple coarsegrained signals from different time scales in a parallel manner through multiple pairs of convolutional layers and pooling layers. Concretely, as shown in Fig. 1, for each coarse-grained signal {y (s) }, we use two pairs of convolutional layers (C1 and C2) and pooling layers (P1 and P2) are used to learn abstract and robust features. Specifically, the same filter size is used across all coarse-grained signals, and thus shorter signals would produce a larger local receptive field in the original signals. This way, each output feature map captures a different scale of the original signals.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Flowchart of the developed MSCNN-based fault diagnosis system for WT gearbox.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,14.63,52.51,354.11,128.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>2 ) 2 :Fig. 4 .</head><label>224</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Schematic of the WT gearbox test rig setup.TABLE I DESCRIPTION OF CONSIDERED GEARBOX HEALTH CONDITIONS.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Training performance curve in terms of overall accuracy.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,36.73,44.87,266.18,188.49" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TIE.2018.2844805, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON INDUSTRIAL ELECTRONICS Confusion matrix results with (a) MSCNN and (b) CNN.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Feature visualization via t-SNE reduced from the learned multiscale representations for the testing dataset with (a) the traditional CNN and the proposed MSCNN with (b) two scales, (c) three scales, and (d) four scales.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a)   and (b) using the confusion matrix, respectively. It gives the correctly classified samples and misclassified samples for each 0278-0046 (c) 2018 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TIE.2018.2844805, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON INDUSTRIAL ELECTRONICS</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Effects of depth on diagnosis performance using the proposed MSCNN and the traditional CNN.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Diagnosis performance on noisy signals with different SNRs using the proposed MSCNN and the traditional CNN.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TIE.2018.2844805, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON INDUSTRIAL ELECTRONICS</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>10.1109/TIE.2018.2844805, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</figDesc><table /><note><p>IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON INDUSTRIAL ELECTRONICS</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TIE.2018.2844805, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</figDesc><table><row><cell>0278-0046 (c) 2018 IEEE. IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON INDUSTRIAL ELECTRONICS</cell><cell>1) A new MSCNN architecture is proposed by introducing a multiscale coarse-grained layer into the traditional CNN. This MSCNN architecture can effectively extract the high-level features with a hierarchical learning structure using multiple pairs of convolutional and pooling layers. This also allows MSCNN to capture complementary and rich diagnostic information at different scales of raw vibration signals in parallel. The obtained multiscale feature representations have stronger discriminability and robustness over CNN and allow MSCNN to overcome the limitation of feature extraction in the traditional architecture that handles only a single time scale. 2) A novel end-to-end fault diagnosis system is developed based on the proposed MSCNN for the WT gearbox under different operational conditions. The system can automatically learn discriminative features directly from raw temporal vibration signals and classify different conditions simultaneously. Unlike traditional methods relying on manually defined or extracted features, the proposed design works well at a signal-level that keeps all information from the input. More importantly, it does not require any additional signal processing or expert knowledge, which has great potentials toward a general-purpose framework for intelligent fault diagnosis. 3) The proposed approach is evaluated through experi-ments on a WT gearbox test rig with a comprehensive performance evaluation. Compared with the traditional CNN and multiscale feature extraction methods, MSCNN achieves significantly better feature learning ability and diagnosis performance. Specifically, MSCNN exhibits superior robustness against noises of a large range than the traditional CNN, a promising result in real-world industrial applications. From the viewpoint of engineer-ing application, the proposed MSCNN provides a new solution to the challenging WT gearbox fault diagnosis problem. The rest of this paper is organized as follows. Section II briefly reviews the CNNs and their applications for fault diagnosis. Section III details our proposed MSCNN framework for WT gearbox fault diagnosis. Section IV demonstrates the experimental results on a WT gearbox test rig to evaluate the effectiveness of the proposed framework. Finally, Section V draws the conclusions.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE I DESCRIPTION</head><label>I</label><figDesc>OF CONSIDERED GEARBOX HEALTH CONDITIONS.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Label</cell><cell>Fault Description</cell><cell>Motor Speed (rpm)</cell><cell>Load (kW)</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Normal</cell><cell>200/300/400/500/600</cell><cell>3/1.5</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>Gear broken tooth</cell><cell>200/300/400/500/600</cell><cell>3/1.5</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>Gear chipped tooth</cell><cell>200/300/400/500/600</cell><cell>3/1.5</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>Gear pitted tooth</cell><cell>200/300/400/500/600</cell><cell>3/1.5</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>Bearing inner race defect</cell><cell>200/300/400/500/600</cell><cell>3/1.5</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>Bearing out race defect</cell><cell>200/300/400/500/600</cell><cell>3/1.5</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>Bearing ball defect</cell><cell>200/300/400/500/600</cell><cell>3/1.5</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>Imbalanced shaft</cell><cell>200/300/400/500/600</cell><cell>3/1.5</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>TABLE V COMPARISON</head><label>V</label><figDesc>RESULTS WITH DIFFERENT METHODS IN TERMS OF F 1 SCORE FOR EACH CONDITION (%). Similar to MCNN, we apply both local and global convolutions in our proposed MSCNN model and named it the MSNNN-II model. The comparison results with three different models of MCNN, MSCNN and MSCNN-II are given in Table IV in terms of F 1 score and computation time(including the average training time per epoch over all training samples and the average testing time per sample) averaged over 50 random trials. The 10-fold cross-validation is performed for each trial.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Methods</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell cols="2">Condition Label 5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>Average</cell></row><row><cell>MSE-SVM</cell><cell>75.13±4.75</cell><cell>87.41±3.24</cell><cell>81.65±2.95</cell><cell cols="2">90.34±1.90</cell><cell>85.36±1.72</cell><cell cols="3">89.32±2.54 73.30±3.42 80.53±1.89</cell><cell>82.88</cell></row><row><cell>WPD-SVM</cell><cell>80.40±4.31</cell><cell>86.92±2.84</cell><cell>72.50±5.40</cell><cell cols="2">96.93±2.99</cell><cell>78.95±3.21</cell><cell cols="2">87.18±4.71 93.78±3.47</cell><cell>77.80±3.80</cell><cell>84.31</cell></row><row><cell>EMD-SVM</cell><cell>71.01±1.04</cell><cell>70.42±2.32</cell><cell cols="3">62.70 ±3.04 72.09±1.97</cell><cell cols="3">71.30±1.57 83.26±1.82 82.39±1.14</cell><cell cols="2">68.51±2.03 72.71</cell></row><row><cell>Proposed MSCNN</cell><cell cols="3">97.34±0.96 98.20±0.72 96.76±1.46</cell><cell cols="4">98.94±0.85 99.05±0.69 99.59±0.26</cell><cell cols="3">98.84±0.68 99.51±0.38 98.53</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">implementation and takes less computation overhead</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">compared to the multiscale transformation in MCNN.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Her research interests include multi-modal information processing and fusion, brain-computer interface, rehabilitation robot biofeedback control, wearable equipment development, and condition monitoring and fault diagnosis of complex systems.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Future on power electronics for wind turbine systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Blaabjerg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal of Emerging and Selected Topics in Power Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-09">Sep. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey on wind turbine condition monitoring and fault diagnosis-part i: Components and subsystems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6536" to="6545" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-10">Oct. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monitoring wind turbine gearboxes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Qiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crabtree</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tavner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Wind Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="728" to="740" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-07">Jul. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey on wind turbine condition monitoring and fault diagnosis-part ii: Signals and signal processing methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6546" to="6557" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-10">Oct. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fault analysis and condition monitoring of the wind turbine gearbox</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Verma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kusiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Energy Conversion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="526" to="535" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">Jun. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sparse feature identification based on union of redundant dictionary for wind turbine gearbox fault diagnosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6594" to="6605" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-10">Oct. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wind turbine condition monitoring based on an improved spline-kernelled chirplet transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tavner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6565" to="6574" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-10">Oct. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integration of eemd and ica for wind turbine gearbox diagnosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Wind Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="757" to="773" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-05">May. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelets for fault diagnosis of rotary machines: a review with applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-03">Mar. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review on empirical mode decomposition in fault diagnosis of rotating machinery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mechanical Systems and Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-02">Feb. 2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="126" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fault diagnosis for a wind turbine transmission system based on manifold learning and shannon wavelet support vector machine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renewable Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-02">Feb. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation learning: A review and new perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bengio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Courville</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vincent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1798" to="1828" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-08">Aug. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lecun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bengio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">521</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7553</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="436" to="444" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-05">May. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep neural networks: A promising tool for fault characteristic mining and intelligent diagnosis of rotating machinery with massive data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Mechanical Systems and Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fault diagnosis of rotary machinery components using a stacked denoising autoencoder-based health state identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-L</forename><surname>Qin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-01">Jan. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Construction of hierarchical diagnosis network based on deep learning and its application in the fault pattern recognition of rolling element bearings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Mechanical Systems and Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An intelligent fault diagnosis method using unsupervised feature learning towards mechanical big data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3137" to="3147" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Realtime motor fault detection by 1-d convolutional neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ince</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kiranyaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Eren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Askar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gabbouj</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7067" to="7075" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-11">Nov. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Railway track circuit fault diagnosis using recurrent neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>De Bruin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Verbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Babuška</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-03">Mar. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bearing fault diagnosis using multi-scale entropy and adaptive neuro-fuzzy inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Expert Systems with Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6077" to="6085" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-08">Aug. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fault diagnosis method based on local mean decomposition and multi-scale entropy for roller bearings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mechanism and Machine Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-05">May. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rolling bearing fault detection and diagnosis based on composite multiscale fuzzy entropy and ensemble support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Mechanical Systems and Signal Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="746" to="759" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-02">Feb. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Receptive fields of single neurones in the cat&apos;s striate cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hubel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Wiesel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of physiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="574" to="591" />
			<date type="published" when="1959-10">Oct. 1959</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gradient-based learning applied to document recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lecun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bottou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bengio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Haffner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<meeting>IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-11">Nov. 1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2278" to="2324" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Goodfellow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bengio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Courville</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Deep</forename><surname>Learning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-11">Nov. 2016</date>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gearbox fault identification and classification with convolutional neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Sanchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Shock and Vibration</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-04">Apr. 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2015</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convolutional neural network based fault detection for rotating machinery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Janssens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Slavkovikj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Vervisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stockman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Loccufier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Verstockt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V D</forename><surname>Walle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Hoecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Sound and Vibration</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">377</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-09">Sep. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multi-scale convolution neural network for featureless fault diagnosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Symposium on</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-08">Aug. 2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="70" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Flexible Automation (ISFA</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time vibration-based structural damage detection using onedimensional convolutional neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Abdeljaber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Avci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kiranyaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gabbouj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Sound and Vibration</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">388</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-02">Feb. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Inman</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multi-scale convolutional neural networks for time series classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1603.06995</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-03">Mar. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiscale entropy analysis of complex physiologic time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Goldberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-K</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical review letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">68102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002-02">Feb. 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiscale entropy analysis of biological signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Goldberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review E</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21906</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005-02">Feb. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rectified linear units improve restricted boltzmann machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Nair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 27th international conference on machine learning (ICML-10)</title>
		<meeting>the 27th international conference on machine learning (ICML-10)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-06">Jun. 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="807" to="814" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adam: A method for stochastic optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kingma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1412.6980</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-12">Dec. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dropout: a simple way to prevent neural networks from overfitting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Srivastava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krizhevsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sutskever</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Salakhutdinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Machine Learning Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1929" to="1958" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-01">Jan. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine health monitoring using local feature-based gated recurrent unit networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1539" to="1548" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-02">Feb. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning from imbalanced data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1263" to="1284" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-09">Sep. 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing data using t-sne</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">V D</forename><surname>Maaten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Machine Learning Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2579" to="2605" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-11">Nov. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dislocated time series convolutional neural architecture: An intelligent fault diagnosis approach for electric machine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1310" to="1320" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-06">Jun. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A self-organizing learning array system for power quality classification based on wavelet transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Starzyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Power Delivery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="286" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-01">Jan. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
