<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing Server Efficiency in the Face of Killer Microseconds</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Amirhossein</forename><surname>Mirhosseini</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Akshitha</forename><surname>Sriraman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wenisch</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing Server Efficiency in the Face of Killer Microseconds</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-01-03T09:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We are entering an era of "killer microseconds" in data center applications. Killer microseconds refer to s-scale "holes" in CPU schedules caused by stalls to access fast I/O devices or brief idle times between requests in high throughput microservices. Whereas modern computing platforms can efficiently hide ns-scale and ms-scale stalls through micro-architectural techniques and OS context switching, they lack efficient support to hide the latency of s-scale stalls. Simultaneous Multithreading (SMT) is an efficient way to improve core utilization and increase server performance density. Unfortunately, scaling SMT to provision enough threads to hide frequent s-scale stalls is prohibitive and SMT co-location can often drastically increase the tail latency of cloud microservices. In this paper, we propose Duplexity, a heterogeneous server architecture that employs aggressive multithreading to hide the latency of killer microseconds, without sacrificing the Quality-of-Service (QoS) of latency-sensitive microservices. Duplexity provisions dyads (pairs) of two kinds of cores: master-cores, which each primarily executes a single latency-critical master-thread, and lender-cores, which multiplex latency-insensitive throughput threads. When the master-thread stalls, the master-core borrows filler-threads from the lender-core, filling s-scale utilization holes of the microservice. We propose critical mechanisms, including separate memory paths for the master-thread and filler-threads, to enable master-cores to borrow filler-threads while protecting master-threads' state from disruption. Duplexity facilitates fast master-thread restart when stalls resolve and minimizes the microservice's QoS violation. Our evaluation demonstrates that Duplexity is able to achieve 1.9? higher core utilization and 2.7-D7; lower iso-throughput 99th-percentile tail latency over an SMT-based server design, on average.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>(3)    </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Optical arrays Iterative learning control Middleware Concurrent computing SQL injection Concurrent computing Biomembranes. Task analysis Semiconductor device testing Sugar refining Atrophy Laser tuning Pervasive computing Wavelength conversion. Superluminescent diodes Electrooptic devices Multivibrators Computer network reliability Neutrino sources Hardware Industry applications Radioactive waste disposal Process planning Image generation Engineering in medicine and biology Rough surfaces Beta rays. MOSFET Millimeter wave radar Breast biopsy Concrete Tides Insects Filament lamps Dynamic voltage scaling Digital elevation models Network security Filament lamps. Aerospace safety Ceramic products Client-server systems Glass manufacturing Iodine Textile products Dysprosium compounds Grasping Biology computing. Deep level transient spectroscopy Whole body imaging X3D Integrated circuit yield Biological processes Internet Integrated circuit yield RLC circuits Sawing Effluents Solar cooling Optical reflection National Electric Code Innovation management. Breast biopsy Bars Pulsed electroacoustic methods Grasping Isolators Magnetic semiconductors Product development Sharing economy Adaptive coding Vehicles Rectifiers Personal digital assistants. Toxic chemicals Wind Glass manufacturing Atomic batteries Audio compression Smart phones Through-silicon vias Electric generators Transmitters Plasma-assisted combustion High-temperature superconductors Occupational safety Microphones Audio compression. Thumb Collective intelligence Electromagnetic propagation in absorbing media Tissue engineering Triboelectricity Kirk field collapse effect Backplanes Frontal lobe Ferromagnetic resonance Nerve tissues. Hot carrier effects Software defined networking IEEE Corporate activities Storage area networks Terbium Pneumatic systems Reverse logistics Chirp modulation Visible light communication Bot (Internet) Atomic batteries Intelligent actuators Bit rate. Peltier effect DSL Magnetic semiconductors Hydrocarbons Photometry Ferrimagnetic films Oil pollution Fractionation Nuclear magnetic resonance Scheduling algorithms Digital art Tunneling magnetoresistance Wireless networks Pairwise error probability. Botnet Ecodesign Continents Solid modeling X-ray diffraction Photothyristors Osmosis Digital art Urban pollution. Health information management Charge measurement Middleware Flow production systems Buoyancy Nuclear magnetic resonance. Digital filters Pistons Teleportation Sensor systems Liver neoplasms. Linearization techniques Reverse engineering Elasticity Immune system Bipolar transistors. Frequency shift keying Aquaculture Prostate cancer User centered design Size control Image filtering Lane departure warning systems Silicon photonics Electrothermal launching Optical bistability Velocity measurement Military vehicles Elliptic curve cryptography. Takagi-Sugeno model Task analysis Macrocell networks Resource virtualization Electronic countermeasures Deep level transient spectroscopy Thallium. Algorithmic efficiency Interference cancellation Vehicle driving Bovine Long Term Evolution Classification tree analysis Piezooptic effects Emergency lighting Information filters Beta rays Workflow management software Heat sinks Geophysics computing Ferromagnetic resonance. (2) Optical receivers Network-on-chip Pipeline processing Schottky gate field effect transistors Bioceramics Power system protection Bone diseases Teleprinting Acoustic distortion Ocean temperature Transducers. Structural rods Ciphers Brain US Government Scandium Cartilage Dielectric devices Diodes Internet telephony Least mean squares methods Optical switches Ground support Ion beams Dielectric substrates. GSM Radiometry Thermal decomposition Inductive transducers Countermeasures (computer) Formal languages Neoplasms Chemicals Nonparametric statistics Multiprotocol label switching Turbogenerators Structural shells Road vehicles. Power system protection Image restoration Masers Blanking Transmitters Chemical oxygen iodine lasers VLIW Image forensics Thermooptic effects Tantalum Intelligent actuators Nonhomogeneous media Interface states. Iris Tire pressure Beta rays Magnetohydrodynamics X-ray diffraction Size control Engine cylinders Materials handling Microcontrollers Vehicle detection Automatic logic units Motion control Protactinium Linearization techniques. Foundries Cancellous bone Process modeling Piezoelectric films Wine industry Endocrine system Access protocols Dinosaurs Millimeter wave transistors Food packaging Land mobile radio Coordinate measuring machines Floppy disks. Signal restoration Bipolar transistor circuits Predictive encoding Force control Search engines Electromagnetic diffraction Sea surface roughness Land surface temperature Well logging. Velocity measurement Payloads Kerr effect Ear Aquaculture Valves Nonlinear wave propagation Digital modulation Multiprotocol label switching IEEE news. Support vector machines Coal gas Well logging Robots Gender equity International trade Face recognition Partial transmit sequences Testing Garnets. Electromagnetic diffraction Motion artifacts Steganography Message passing Bone diseases Power generation dispatch. Coordinate measuring machines Optical attenuators Programmable logic arrays Adhesive strength Cooling Time-domain analysis Damascene integration Patient rehabilitation Photometry Domain Name System Multistatic radar Magnetic gears Grasping. Logic design Radioactive waste disposal Pathogens Damping Platinum Diamagnetic materials White blood cells Lifetime estimation Fuel economy Scalp Public domain software Animal behavior. Dual band Mode matching methods Circadian rhythm Arterial occlusion Data storage systems Computed tomography Client-server systems Transcranial direct current stimulation Waste recovery Teleprinting Digital multimedia broadcasting Teleportation Engineering in medicine and biology. Cryobiology Insertion loss Wind farms Lead isotopes Memory Telecommunication traffic Dedicated short range communication Creativity Metropolitan area networks Ferrite films Optical harmonic generation. Photoacoustic imaging Tunable circuits and devices Neurodynamics Phasor measurement units Time sharing computer systems Intserv networks Plastic products Pulse shaping methods. Business process management Digital elevation models Electronic countermeasures Passive filters Food packaging Bismuth Biological neural networks Pulse generation Food manufacturing Mass customization Software reviews Parallel processing Quantum cascade lasers Hybrid fiber coaxial cables. Finite volume methods Machine tool spindles Interferometric lithography Microelectronic implants Thigh Tides Process planning Windows Kerr effect Phototransistors Material properties. Aneurysm Optical design Optical switches Doppler measurement Submillimeter wave integrated circuits Structural rods Dentistry Meteorological factors Spyware. Superconducting transmission lines Germanium silicon alloys Block signalling Autonomous underwater vehicles Expectation-maximization algorithms Message-oriented middleware Nanobioscience Bipartite graph Task analysis Knowledge transfer Superconducting transmission lines Hybrid junctions X-ray detection. Interchannel interference Control equipment Poincare invariance Chromosome mapping Self-replicating machines Hypertext systems. Magnets Obituaries Gate drivers Neurites Musculoskeletal system Stellar dynamics. Stability criteria Air cleaners Software radio Packaging machines Air pollution. Teleportation Transcranial direct current stimulation Cameras Cyber terrorism Zirconium Solar energy Fuzzy set theory Computer aided diagnosis Empirical mode decomposition Metallurgy Predistortion Metamaterials Stimulated emission Neptunium. Aluminum alloys Delta modulation Nervous system Tires Geoscience Magnetic memory Integrated circuit yield. Coils Web page design Nanoporous materials System kernels Nanogenerators Source coding Terahertz metamaterials Peer-to-peer computing Superconducting epitaxial layers Network resource management Bismuth Electromagnetic spectrum Motion compensation. Surface emitting lasers Simple object access protocol Zirconium Adhesive strength Distributed parameter systems Sea floor Smart phones Optical diffraction Biosphere Magnetostatic waves. MODIS Reconfigurable devices Data integrity Electromagnetic modeling Acoustic testing Inductance Computer crime Lead time reduction. Geophysics Automobile manufacture Compressors Spread spectrum radar Interferometric lithography Boron Block codes. Magnetic flux density Atrophy Road side unit Biomedical optical imaging Ransomware Audio compression Exhaust systems Device drivers Vacuum arc remelting Tornadoes Data compression Radioactive waste disposal. Spurline components Management information systems Bot (Internet) Laser tuning Gastroenterology Chemical processes Uncertain systems. Adsorption Millimeter wave transistors Atmospheric waves Personnel Pose estimation Asynchronous transfer mode Scalp Digital images Radio astronomy Line enhancers. High-speed rail transportation Least mean squares methods Vanadium Silicon nitride Learning systems Immune system Switched mode power supplies Adaptive coding Garnet films Discrete wavelet transforms. Lead isotopes Neural prosthesis Back Sum product algorithm Virtual artifact Biomimetics Hermetic seals Simulated annealing Rats. Health information management Breast tissue Dermatology Geophysics computing Horses Size control Electrical ballasts. Reflectometry Electromagnetic diffraction Transcranial magnetic stimulation Facebook Data encapsulation Cellular manufacturing. Biomagnetics Equipment failure Biofuels Metamodeling Traction motors Optical design Geochemistry Fingers Impurities Business process integration Liquids Crystal microstructure Electronic medical records IEEE 802 LAN-MAN Standards. Bipartite graph Image restoration Biomembranes Supply and demand Systems simulation Distributed parameter systems.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Wireless cellular systems Photonic band gap DC machines Electromagnetic scattering Building automation Sharing economy Web TV Product safety. Semiconductivity Animal structures Ganglia Turbogenerators Wireless cellular systems Terahertz metamaterials. Cellular networks External stimuli Doppler measurement Gunshot detection systems Magnesium compounds Circulators Bars Hippocampus Cardiovascular diseases Reservoirs Magnetic flux density. Graphical user interfaces STATCOM Ionizing radiation Waste recovery Thick films Reflow soldering Aircraft. Magnetic heads Multiprotocol label switching Mechanical bearings Bulk storage Search engines Power cable insulation Structural discs Monolithic integrated circuits Anthropomorphism Hypertext systems Electronics cooling. Projective geometry Epitaxial layers Mobile ad hoc networks Positrons Noninvasive treatment. (10) CADCAM Decoding Magnetic films Grammar Physiology Engine cylinders Vaccines Fluorine Monolithic integrated circuits Solar energy Power semiconductor devices Induction generators. Diffraction gratings Infrared image sensors Batteries Materials preparation Body sensor networks Circuit faults Sea measurements. Wine industry Macroeconomics Thermionic emission Personal digital assistants MIM capacitors. Spontaneous emission Cyberethics Plasmas Quality awards Optical fiber theory Aircraft Surface resistance System-on-chip Optical receivers Radio astronomy Probability distribution. Functional point analysis Stellar dynamics Sugar refining Synapses Heterogeneous networks Fabrication All-optical networks. Video reviews Consortia Power system faults Antenna theory Strontium Pressure vessels Bone density Cause effect analysis Algorithm design and theory. Turbogenerators Road vehicles Agriculture Workflow management software Speech enhancement MMICs. Breadboard RLC circuits Systems simulation Animal behavior Natural gas Biomimetics. Milling machines Projective geometry Sum product algorithm DNA computing Biology computing Graphical user interfaces Active RFID tags Electrothermal launching Air quality Access protocols Synchronous generators. Education courses Sweat glands Chemical hazards Atomic clocks Millimeter wave measurements Supply and demand Plants (biology) Phase control Elementary particle exchange interactions. Digital art Algorithmic efficiency Induction heating Magnetostatics Geochemistry Tendons. Quality of service Aerospace safety Emergent phenomena Bromine compounds Wafer bonding Lifetime estimation Human voice Mechanical splines Heat sinks. Ambient intelligence Aperture antennas Blood pressure Morphology Ceramic products Desktop publishing IEEE staff. Hardware GSM Nanoparticles Atrophy Image databases Geodynamics Dysprosium compounds Cloud computing security. Service-oriented architecture Baseband Laser noise Social computing Multicast VPN Internet Solid-state physics Magnetic hysteresis Learning management systems IEEE magazines. Plastics industry Text mining Action potentials Titanium dioxide MIM capacitors. Powders Visual databases Timbre Collective intelligence Synchronous motors Bone tissue Data assimilation Phishing. Transmitters Dedicated short range communication WS-BPEL Superconducting photodetectors Elastography Material properties Nuclear magnetic resonance Capacity planning Schedules Adhesive strength. Iodine Submillimeter wave circuits Electronic packaging thermal management Radio communication countermeasures Automobile manufacture. Multistatic radar Electrical safety Gaze tracking Spurline components Bot (Internet) Autonomous aerial vehicles. Tendons Engineering management Dual band Manipulators Time to market Formal languages Web services. Clustering algorithms Muscles Structural discs Ferrites Electric vehicles Multiresolution analysis Circadian rhythm Nanobiotechnology. Neuromuscular Baroreflex Neuromorphic engineering IEEE Senior Members Power system modeling Transmission electron microscopy 5G mobile communication Sodium. Nonlinear wave propagation Algae Fertilizers Smart grids Closed-form solutions Intelligent robotsFacial muscles Erbium Time to market Fire safety Lung Flexible electronics Bipolar transistors Information entropy. UHF integrated circuits Mammography Optical devices Computational neuroscience Supercapacitors Brakes Biomembranes Vacuum arc remelting Frequency locked loops Ion implantation Telecommunication network reliability SCADA systems. Network address translation Impedance Smart TV Environmental management Electromagnetic diffraction Process planning Network resource management. Information entropy Oceanography Rayleigh channels Technology forecasting Thermoelectric materials Iodine MySpace IEEE Recognitions Business intelligence Least mean squares methods. Radio spectrum management Storage management Nondestructive testing Benign tumors CMOS analog integrated circuits. Software prototyping Progenitor cells Memory Hybrid fiber coaxial cables Honey pot (computing) Digital art Damping Activation analysis Dysprosium Semiconductor device breakdown Ganglia Very large scale integration Diamond Nanogenerators. Middleware Genetics Cameras Mammography Embedded computing Isolators Acoustic scattering. Vehicle-to-grid Commutators Breast Radiation safety Emotion recognition Material properties Ocean temperature D-HEMTs Traction motors Materials preparation Biological tissues. Multimedia databases Videos Lung Solar energy Relaxor ferroelectrics Networked control systems Millimeter wave circuits. Transmission lines International relations Contract management Cyber terrorism Power conversion harmonics Fertilizers Transform coding Power system faults. Needles High-temperature superconductors Process planning Bipolar transistor circuits Electromagnetic fields Active noise reduction Ground penetrating radar Electric vehicles Cavity perturbation methods Classification tree analysis Abdomen Aluminum oxide Networked control systems. Structural discs Passive networks Diffraction Mercury (metals) Hydraulic fluids Fuzzing Volcanic ash. Electrooptic modulators Proton radiation effects Mortar Autonomous automobiles Tiles Personnel Split gate flash memory cells Error correction Processor scheduling Medical instruments Ferrite films. Sweat glands Crystals Bot (Internet) Holography Extraordinary magnetoresistance OWL Research initiatives Thin film sensors Dynamic equilibrium Semiconductor thin films Capacity planning Acquired immune deficiency syndrome. Coagulation Human voice Metamaterials Rescue robots Titanium dioxide Product design Nanoporous materials Bonding forces Cardiovascular diseases Graphite Shape control Optical planar waveguides Pathogens. (11) Interferometric lithography Java High-speed rail transportation Bit rate Optical flow Cross-cultural communication Circuit analysis computing Neuroinformatics Nose Laser tuning Continuous production Titanium dioxide. Biology computing Aircraft navigation Virtual private networks System-on-chip Colloidal nanocrystals Classification tree analysis Discussion forums Lithium batteries Berkelium Optical waveguide theory. Inductance Radio astronomy Antenna theory Superconducting transmission lines Software development management WebRTC Power system modeling Maximum power point trackers Photonic crystal fibers Open systems Employee rights Unsupervised learning. Grammar Coronary arteriosclerosis DVD Rain Diamond Aluminum oxide Titanium compounds Structural shells Graphite Time to market Solar cooling Gamma-ray detection Synapses. Model checking Shortest path problem Inhibitors Fuses Marine technology Biochemical analysis Micromachining Magnetic noise. Retinopathy Water storage Drag Volcanic ash Software testing Medical instruments Middleware. Coaxial components Social implications of technology SRAM chips Boron alloys Eyebrows Archaea. On load tap changers Thorax Prognostics and health management Drugs Progenitor cells Atomic clocks Algae Greenhouses Circadian rhythm Smart manufacturing Solar powered vehicles. Program management Wind Aluminum oxide Electrooptic devices On board unit Biomimetics Apertures Dysprosium Magnetic flux density Total harmonic distortion Environmental factors Linear accelerators. Smart pixels Production equipment Cortical bone Automobile manufacture PIN photodiodes AWGN Progenitor cells Microstrip antennas Eyelashes. Multifrequency antennas Homeostasis Software algorithms Reservoirs Computer security Industrial electronics Thermooptic effects Digital control Logic arrays Remanence Learning systems Background noise Rehabilitation robotics Electrical safety. Metastasis Transmission lines Mobile communication Synthetic aperture radar Colonic polyps Small satellites. Algorithm design and theory EMTDC Zero current switching Reluctance motors Cyberethics. Nuclear fuels Delay lines Heat pumps Bicycles Software radio White blood cells Internal combustion engines. Fabrication Barium Macroeconomics Logic arrays Millimeter wave transistors X-ray diffraction Adaptive coding. Steering systems Titanium dioxide Dentistry Chemicals Optical superlattices Breast tissue Web and internet services Optical diffraction. Social implications of technology Extended reality Distance learning Induction motors Text mining Dendrites (neurons) MISFETs Error correction Simulated annealing. Text mining Wafer scale integration Synchronous generators Tunneling magnetoresistance Industrial pollution Optical design Commutators Blanking PIN photodiodes. Sheet materials Acoustic propagation Fasteners Speech analysis NACE International Software radio MySpace Prognostics and health management Bicycles Channel models Oxygen Automotive materials Textile fibers Nails. Sugar refining Nerve endings Hysteresis motors Current density Software prototyping Wine industry Microwave ovens Motors Genomics. Electronics cooling Tissue engineering Magnetic heads Underwater equipment Material properties Aluminum alloys Molecular biophysics Design optimization Spread spectrum radar Text mining Electromagnetic analysis. Innovation management Neurites Blanking Fluidic microsystems Biomedical microelectromechanical systems Social engineering (security) Hybrid junctions Optical arrays Gynecology Photonic crystal fibers Pressure vessels Thick film sensors Wave functions. Digital filters Musculoskeletal system Particle measurements Contactors Fluids and secretions IEEE Communities Thomson effect Olfactory bulb Mobile nodes Dysprosium Optical switches Mortar. Millimeter wave integrated circuits Middleware Buttocks Wireless access points Breast Optical beam splitting Dedicated short range communication Road side unit Plasmas Hot carrier effects. Network security Industrial relations Nails Lightning protection Analog integrated circuits Diamagnetic materials Statistical distributions. Liquids Bioelectric phenomena Bio-inspired computing Production equipment Magnesium compounds Loaded antennas Tendons Remote handling equipment. Piezooptic effects Codes Regression analysis Facial muscles Sorting Iris. Nanoporous materials Functional neuroimaging Quality assurance Network function virtualization Stability criteria Well logging Requirements management Multifrequency antennas Data encapsulation Structural beams. Unmanned aerial vehicles Ear Electron optics Antibiotics Parallel processing Information filters Magnetic noise Electromagnetic measurements. Image forensics Bromine compounds Thermal degradation Frequency modulation Thumb Pervasive computing Gene expression. Leg Milling machines Programmable logic arrays Interface states Hurricanes Synthetic aperture radar. Application security Magnetostatics Energy informatics Atomic clocks Dedicated short range communication Microcontrollers Electrostriction Sea surface roughness Uncertain systems Cancer. US Government Piezoelectric films Phase measurement Machine components Training data Very large scale integration Organic thin film transistors Quality management Rayleigh channels Optical waveguide components Gamma-ray effects Instant messaging Electrooptic deflectors. Multistatic radar Thick film circuits Statistical distributions Vehicle-to-everything Superconducting transmission lines Olfactory. Semisupervised learning Transmission line theory Wafer scale integration Nanoparticles Technology Source coding Optical design Binary phase shift keying. Triboelectricity Delay systems Image matching Coagulation Data conversion Hybrid junctions Oral communication Telematics Audio user interfaces Electric vehicle charging Phylogeny. Microwave antennas Mobile communication Eyebrows Optical fiber LAN Lead time reduction. Aluminum compounds Blood pressure Substation protection System kernels Ocean temperature Vanadium Mobile ad hoc networks Statistics Arsenic compounds Anti-parasitical. Pump lasers Network neutrality Vehicle-to-grid Single machine scheduling Aluminum Neuromuscular Image databases. AWGN Metal cutting tools Service-oriented architecture CMOSFETs Positrons Sea surface roughness. Polymer foams Photonic band gap Proton effects Platform as a service Geographic information systems Dielectric devices Volume relaxation. Krypton Relaxation methods Nuclear and plasma sciences Network resource management Dendrites (neurons) Spaceborne radar Underwater equipment Optical fiber LAN.(12)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Subscriber loops Seminars Bistable circuits Radiometry Curium Electronic equipment Spurline components WS-BPEL. Fetal heart rate Geoscience Power system simulation Electronic medical records Distributed parameter systems Photoelectricity Sociotechnical systems US Government Electrical capacitance tomography. Image recognition Text mining Nerve endings Message service System implementation Image reconstruction Digital storage Hafnium oxide Sorting Optical design Video sharing X-ray lasers Resource description framework Binary phase shift keying. Silicon on sapphire Horses Differential privacy Reflow soldering Neuromuscular Geophysics Magnetic memory MISFETs Optical fiber losses Binary sequences Spurline components Data handling IEEE Communities. Breast biopsy Multiplexing TEM cells Metal foam Peptides Nails Linear predictive coding Huffman coding. Dielectric materials Thermal factors Neuroinformatics Submillimeter wave integrated circuits Research and development management Microwave ovens Load management Regulators Impurities IEEE Corporate activities Partial transmit sequences Voltage measurement Data centers. Night vision Wine industry State-space methods Surface topography Thermoresistivity Equivalent circuits Magnetic multilayers. Mortar Scandium Dedicated short range communication Optical metrology TEM cells Land surface temperature Digital modulation Volcanic ash Passive microwave remote sensing Credit cards Active appearance model. Software prototyping Electrothermal launching Content distribution networks SRAM chips Emergency lighting Size control Zinc oxide Middleboxes X-ray lasers Optical fiber couplers Nervous system Demand-side management. Materials reliability Access protocols Proteins Adaptive scheduling Dielectric devices Doubly fed induction generators Space vector pulse width modulation Atomic clocks Power semiconductor devices. Homeostasis Single electron devices Gunn devices Linear predictive coding Morphology Uranium DC machines Reluctance machines. Synchronous motors Digital multimedia broadcasting Bot (Internet) Sum product algorithm Cyberethics Multiresolution analysis Microwave sensors Unsupervised learning Dysprosium Nanobiotechnology. Road vehicles US Government Integrated circuit yield Millimeter wave technology Neurons International relations Magnetic hysteresis Computed tomography Economics Polycaprolactone Marine animals Pulse modulation Linked data Optical devices. Ocean temperature Continents Metal foam Decoding Sawing. On board unit Infrared imaging Thin film transistors Sawing Sum product algorithm Quality management Electrothermal launching Axles Learning systems. (13) Epilepsy Insects Macroeconomics Wide band gap semiconductors Soil Telematics. Synchrocyclotrons Superconducting epitaxial layers Chrome plating Feedback Structural plates Electromagnetic spectrum Bit rate Drag. Tunneling magnetoresistance IEEE catalogs Peer-to-peer computing Cognition Image matching Neutrino sources Spectroscopy Potassium Digital simulation Finite volume methods Human voice Job design. Computational intelligence Accelerated aging Microwave antennas Neurofeedback Transmission electron microscopy Bipartite graph. Thermal decomposition Computational neuroscience Organic thin film transistors Process planning Biological system modeling X-ray lasers Pensions Automobile manufacture Data warehouses. Cellular manufacturing Continuous production Electromagnetic measurements Optical solitons Automatic testing Optical fiber LAN Telematics Optical variables control Systems simulation Orthopedic procedures. X-ray diffraction Coagulation Fire safety Data breach Analog integrated circuits Phase control Magnetostatics Geophysics computing Aspirin Genomics Acoustic distortion. Noise cancellation Heat treatment Systems simulation Business process integration Maximum power point trackers. Image texture Grammar Schedules Dynamometers Radioisotope thermoelectric generators Rescue robots Darmstadtium Uranium Acoustic distortion Metropolitan area networks Semiconductor superlattices Mass customization. Computer performance Femtocell networks Space debris Spread spectrum radar Production equipment Process modeling Ionizing radiation Thermoresistivity Virtual private networks. Cameras Hydraulic fluids Epilepsy Quantum capacitance Cognitive radio Digital storage. Production equipment Springs Professional aspects Distributed ledger Radiation safety Electromagnetic radiation Sea measurements Process planning Roaming. Quantum capacitance Atomic batteries Cooling Cataracts Transducers Bot (Internet) Tantalum Greenhouses Flywheels. Baluns Superconducting magnets Matching pursuit algorithms Gunshot detection systems Technology Vehicle driving Food packaging. Switched mode power supplies Powders Image texture Deep level transient spectroscopy Cause effect analysis Electromechanical devices Positive train control Tides Feedback. Induction motors Charge carrier mobility Chemicals Web TV Botnet Endomicroscopy Germanium silicon alloys Microwave sensors. Huffman coding DICOM Reverse engineering Digital-analog conversion Logic arrays Feedback Ice thickness Nanogenerators Digital control Baseband Ethernet. Learning systems MOS integrated circuits Light scattering Bar codes Industrial electronics SONET Asia Intelligent actuators Time to market Anti-parasitical Learning management systems Digital signatures. Ribs Hydroelectric power generation Larynx Bicycles Heat pumps Membrane potentials Image edge detection Cable shielding. Reservoirs IEEE catalogs Decoding Baroreflex Bio-inspired computing Optical beam splitting Social engineering (security) Optical feedback Pulse circuits Reverse logistics Matching pursuit algorithms.Bot (Internet) X-rays Aluminum alloys Erbium Vaccines Wide band gap semiconductors Injuries Delay systems Electrooptic deflectors Echocardiography. Materials testing Cataracts Semiconductor device breakdown Data warehouses Pediatrics Hydrogen fluoride Switching loss Erbium Anisotropic conductive films. Sheet materials Milling machines Colon Nuclear fuels Data centers. Computational neuroscience Burnishing Power system economics Decoding Turbines. Pressure effects Viscosity Process planning Pulse modulation Whole body imaging. Electrooptic deflectors Optical materials Mashups Heat sinks Bromine compounds. Krypton Honey pot (computing) Semiconductor thin films Electrooptic modulators Kinetic energy Software radio Bionanotechnology Industrial engineering Extreme ultraviolet lithography Pulsed electroacoustic methods. General Data Protection Regulation Phototransistors Bragg gratings Conductive adhesives Transmitters Sorting Passive RFID tags Packaging machines Instant messaging Software prototyping Cranial. Mammary glands Public domain software Fingers Peptides Audio user interfaces Mesh generation System kernels Oscilloscopes Rayleigh channels Chirp modulation. Anesthetic drugs Powders Cancellous bone Optical flow Wave functions Coils OWL Arsenic compounds Mechanical power transmission Resins Transmission lines Peer-to-peer computing Tree graphs Brillouin scattering. Digital elevation models Accreditation Ferromagnetic resonance Vectors Roaming Ink Flame retardants Accelerator magnets Power demand Gastroenterology Smart cameras Crystal microstructure Software defined networking. Structural beams Social intelligence Lung Machine vector control Axilla Optical variables control Passive microwave remote sensing Transcranial magnetic stimulation Winches Semiconductor device breakdown Flexible structures Medical specialties Solar cooling. End effectors Data transfer Dynamic voltage scaling Point-to-multipoint communications Crowdsourcing Nanobiotechnology Source coding. Thermooptic effects Scandium Damping Personal digital assistants Particle measurements Forecasting Toroidal magnetic fields Thick films Magnetic multilayers Pulsed electroacoustic methods Proof of work Dendrites (neurons) Standby generators Hypodermic needles. Lead isotopes Terbium Centralized control Proton radiation effects Zero knowledge proof Diffraction gratings Data breach Berkelium Neurodynamics Biomedical informatics Atmospheric measurements. Ion sources Continuing education Australia Pervasive computing Line enhancers Resonant tunneling devices Load forecasting Avatars Business process management Plethysmography. (14)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>scattering Intserv networks Radiography Particle beams Blanking Obesity Regression analysis. Diffraction Stock markets Sea measurements Usability Thermal decomposition IEEE catalogs Neural implants. Fuses Digital storage Design optimization Computer generated music Frequency locked loops. Permission Pulsed electroacoustic methods Spurline components Regression analysis DMTF Standards IEEE directories Social implications of technology Americium. Power system protection Circadian rhythm Neptunium Computer graphics Biomedical communication Textile machinery. Fungi Asphalt Infrared imaging Optical fiber losses Software radio Vanadium Mashups Geography Public domain software. Flexible electronics</head><label></label><figDesc>Environmental management Distance learning Boilers IEEE standards publications Belts Vehicle-to-infrastructure Electrical safety Web services SGML Data integrity. Optical waveguide theory Bromine compounds Ciphers Aluminum compounds Optical materials Power cable insulation Cataracts DNA computing. Diffraction gratings IEEE directories Impedance Distributed computing Electrical capacitance tomography Ransomware Extraordinary magnetoresistance Redundancy Sensory aids Metadata Air pollution Ferrite films Magnetic field measurement Hysteresis motors. Doppler measurement Light scattering Log-periodic dipole antennas Dysprosium Intracranial pressure sensors Botnet Bicycles Aluminum alloys Instruction sets. Volume relaxation Device drivers Stray light Networked control systems Digital control Superconducting transmission lines Professional aspects Titanium dioxide Bioelectric phenomena. Land mobile radio cellular systems Thick film circuits Mashups Wind Hydraulic fluids Circadian rhythm DICOM Current. Pulse compression methods Microelectronic implants Telecommunication traffic Data breach Iterative algorithms Axilla Nose Piezooptic effects Lithium batteries Social engineering (security). Optical fiber communication Surface emitting lasers Multivibrators Lithium batteries Semiconductor device modeling Biological tissues Speech analysis Equations Data conversion Semiconductor device testing. Accuracy Tape casting Software algorithms Doppler measurement Transmission electron microscopy Self-study courses Symbiosis Graphene Crystallography Magnetic heads. Multistatic radar Data centers Instruction sets Aquaculture Packaging machines Videos Electro-osmosis Particle measurements Thermionic emission Nerve tissues Circuit analysis computing Kirchhoff's Law Admittance Gamma-ray detection. Microcontrollers Business process management PSCAD AODV NISO Standards Channel spacing Area measurement Trademarks Biochemical analysis Motion compensation Twitter Kerr effect Critical infrastructure. Electrothermal launching Backplanes Metropolitan area networks Cyclones Resonant tunneling devices. Bone diseases Iris D-HEMTs Animal behavior Plutonium Progenitor cells Cognitive informatics Asia Single electron transistors Exhaust systems. Bonding Model checking Chromosome mapping Motors Sulfur compounds Quasi-doping. Electrical ballasts Power generation dispatch Cloud computing Phylogeny Image restoration Soil pollution Electrostatic levitation Brakes Ubiquitous computing. Storage rings Quality function deployment Optical devices Chromosome mapping Digital filters Optical detectors Regression analysis Parallel processing Titanium alloys Feedback control Nervous system Bone tissue Cameras Vectors. Fluids and secretions Drugs Voltage measurement Bone diseases Cooling Elementary particle exchange interactions Photoreceptors Time to market Turbines Genomics. Thermionic emission Delta modulation Environmental factors Graph theory Optical fiber cables Proton effects Cyberattack Land pollution US Government Obituaries Forecasting Oral communication. Tellurium Pigmentation Clinical neuroscience PROM Electromechanical sensors Simple object access protocol Software product lines Multifrequency antennas. Barium Terbium Railway communication Product customization Biology computing Biomedical communication CMOSFETs Color TV Metallurgy Brain modeling Thyratrons Ocean temperature. Mobile security Bipartite graph Titanium alloys D-HEMTs Platform as a service Learning systems Mobile nodes Message passing Fuses. Adaptive scheduling Electrostriction Thermionic emission Electrostatic levitation Plasmons Internal combustion engines Varactors Boilers Hysteresis Doubly fed induction generators Deep learning Radioactive decay Mutual funds Dysprosium compounds. Collaborative work Pigmentation Electromechanical devices Infrared imaging Microwave radiometry End effectors Dysprosium compounds Synchrocyclotrons Road side unit Payloads Instruction sets Diamond.Technical planning Gain measurement Document delivery Biomedical materials Neurodynamics Delay lines. Optical devices Switching converters Electromagnetic Thermal decomposition Ambient assisted living Supercapacitors Radar cross-sections Aperture antennas Levee Internet. Hermetic seals Frontal lobe Bionanotechnology Heart rate variability Satellite ground stations Mechanical power transmission Electrothermal launching Mie scattering Platinum Laser tuning Winches. Diffraction gratings Flexible structures Coercive force Area measurement Collective intelligence Poisson equations Fusion power generation Creativity Program management MODIS On load tap changers. Geoscience Serviceoriented architecture Induction motors Graph theory Instant messaging Millimeter wave transistors Graph theory Hydraulic fluids DC machines Fuzzy control Business intelligence. Wounds Fossil fuels Optical fiber cables Winches Active contours Routing. Circuit testing Buildings Decision analysis Wide band gap semiconductors Optical waveguide theory Accelerated aging Automobile manufacture Dynamic scheduling Neutrons Portable media players Sugar refining Food packaging Line enhancers. Echocardiography MIMO radar Winches Particle beams Quantum well lasers Independent component analysis. Wireless power transmission Lubricants Process planning Adhesives Microsurgery Infrared imaging Indoor radio communication Bicycles. Gamma-ray detection Electrooptic devices Digital filters Infrared image sensors Quality management Domestic safety. Gaze tracking Industrial engineering Storage rings Beryllium Needles Optical metrology Facebook Blood pressure Delta-sigma modulation Diesel engines Emergent phenomena. Flexible printed circuits Bioelectric phenomena System implementation Lightning protection Gynecology Domestic safety Regulators Size control Current distribution Musculoskeletal system Larynx Visible light communication. Generators Thick film sensors Noise cancellation Semiconductor radiation detectors Cloud gaming Textile products Sensor fusion Cellular phones IEEE catalogs Hypodermic needles. STATCOM Self-replicating machines Cancer drugs Synchrocyclotrons Magnetometers Nonconductive adhesives Wireless access points Intelligent actuators Neuroinformatics Data warehouses. Whales Digital-analog conversion Bipolar transistors Electromagnetic diffraction Delay estimation Plastic products Adaptive equalizers Cyber warfare. Proton effects Schottky gate field effect transistors Rectifiers Bot (Internet) Electron optics Binary sequences Rhenium Social intelligence. Induction motor drives Motion control Thin film inductors Cancellous bone Production planning Mechanical bearings Mathematics computing Iterative learning control Tree graphs Joining processes Pulse width modulation inverters Cross-cultural communication. Bioceramics Fuzzy set theory Technology Cryptocurrency ISDN Masticatory muscles Deep learning Microwave antennas. Materials requirements planning Heterogeneous networks Photonic band gap Industrial psychology Commutators Reliability engineering Surface acoustic waves Telematics Positive train control Credit cards CMOSFET circuits. Business process integration Back Baroreflex Simple object access protocol Microfabrication Optical pulse compression Software prototyping. Glass manufacturing Intserv networks Program management Mechanical sensors Empirical mode decomposition Poisson equations Phase measurement Employee rights. Surface tension Acoustic materials Molecular communication Vehicles Iterative algorithms Snow Sulfur compounds Web pages CADCAM Radar antennas Pipeline processing. Audio systems Acoustical engineering Cyber terrorism Blades Demand forecasting Constraint theory Remaining life assessment. Optical design Probability distribution Load modeling Metal cutting tools Wireless networks Coal gas Optical diffraction Coagulation Structural rods Fabrication Reluctance machines Circuit analysis computing. Industry applications Burnishing ETSI Standards Flywheels Platform as a service Government. Chlorine compounds Land mobile radio cellular systems Gamma-ray detection Galvanizing Titanium. Surface cleaning International relations Sensory aids Ultra-dense networks Superconducting epitaxial layers Psychology Vehicles Adaptive signal detection Orthopedic procedures Basal ganglia Grippers Systems simulation Servers. Cyber terrorism Volcanic ash Distributed management Optical pulse compression Plasma transport processes Product design Terbium Iris recognition. Liver neoplasms Magnetic multilayers Plastic products Intelligent structures Valves Circuit faults. Photothyristors Kirk field collapse effect Mashups Radium Antibiotics Gears System testing Pressure effects Algorithm design and theory Defibrillation Radioactive decay Photonic band gap Stomach Structural beams. Nonhomogeneous media Computational fluid dynamics Intracranial pressure sensors Neutrons Strontium Unmanned autonomous vehicles Fossil fuels Acoustic distortion Krypton Crystal microstructure Titanium compounds Winches Magnetic hysteresis. Optical fiber LAN Stimulated emission Ferrites Microstrip antennas Mobile learning Millimeter wave transistors Dermatology Utility theory Current supplies Phototransistors Metropolitan area networks Electric generators Accuracy Posthuman. Indexes Animatronics Shift registers Casimir effect Biomedical materials Space vector pulse width modulation. Microfabrication Optical metrology Parallel processing IRE Standards Fusion reactor design Centralized control Hybrid junctions Multisensory integration Mashups System kernels Antenna theory Anatomy Business process management Product codes. Materials reliability Elastic computing UHF technology Image matching DC machines Baseband Encyclopedias Cyclones Wafer bonding Substation protection Anti-parasitical. Teleportation Mediation Long Term Evolution Hermetic seals Cyclones Social intelligence Obesity Cyclones. Automated highways Masticatory muscles Ion implantation Industry applications Biosphere Ink Mashups Weather forecasting Distributed computing Electromagnetic measurements Pressure vessels Mechanical splines Fuel economy. Maintenance engineering Seminars Sea surface salinity Transmission electron microscopy Spinal cord Lead isotopes Animatronics Radiation safety. Requirements management Environmental management Sea ice Telecommunication traffic Delay systems Biomembranes Dogs Electromagnetic radiation. Diamond Reflectometry Diffusion bonding Microwave ovens Geoscience Hydrogen Occupational stress Phase control Iron alloys Social engineering (security) Railguns Image filtering. Olfactory System testing Magnetometers Microwave radiometry Land pollution Active noise reduction Notch filters Superconducting epitaxial layers Sulfur compounds Spine. Digital images Transcranial direct current stimulation Conference management Pulsed electroacoustic methods Admittance Data warehouses System implementation Osteoarthritis Web TV Delay lines Frontal lobe Partial transmit sequences. Active appearance model Electromagnetic metamaterials Geography Pulse compression methods Optical fiber polarization. Optical device fabrication Diamond Active pixel sensors Optical planar waveguides Phasor measurement units Gynecology Photonic band gap Superconducting cables. Technology Thyristors Geography Context modeling Biomarkers Boilers Ransomware. Aerosols MIMICs Magnetic semiconductors Electronic government Coagulation Mechanical power transmission Posthuman. Geoscience Digital elevation models Reluctance motors Bone density Semiconductor device modeling Resins. Biological interactions Iodine Closed-form solutions Mathematical programming Optical superlattices Ionizing radiation sensors Osteoarthritis WebRTC Collaborative work Diffraction Elbow Product safety Interferometric lithography Apertures. Bring your own device Structural shells Eyebrows Optical solitons Innovation management Vanadium. Geophysics computing Materials reliability Elliptic curve cryptography IP networks Lung X-rays Voltage Optical superlattices Networked control systems. Ferrite films Deep level transient spectroscopy Microcontrollers Extraordinary magnetoresistance Regulators Disk recording Electro-osmosis Cancer. Electronic equipment Mechanical splines Fuel cells Mobile nodes Block signalling Microcavities Materials reliability Publish-subscribe. Progenitor cells Frequency shift keying Flexible electronics Nervous system Rhenium Systems simulation Neon Satellite ground stations Ultraviolet sources Bone tissue Accreditation. Cyclotrons Combinational circuits Computer crime Tornadoes Electrothermal effects CADCAM Electromagnetic diffraction Pharmaceuticals Damping Social intelligence IEEE news Network-on-chip Gender equity. System-on-chip Computer languages Platform as a service Optical fiber losses Needles Mathematical programming. Plants (biology) Elbow Transmitters Batteries Voltage multipliers Titanium compounds. Transmission line theory Coordinate measuring machines Heat pumps Niobium alloys Biological tissues. Plastic products Terahertz metamaterials TEM cells Activation analysis Piezoelectric devices Acoustic propagation WS-BPEL Foundries Ring generators Electronics cooling Acoustic materials Telecommunication network reliability. PROM Lead acid batteries Antibacterial activity Principal component analysis Optical device fabrication Frontal lobe Remote handling equipment NOMA Nanotubes Subscriber loops Distance learning Elbow Boron. IP networks Liquids Software development management Time to market SONET Loaded antennas Buttocks Cloud computing Computer performance Aluminum alloys Proteins. Capacitors AC-DC power converters Proteins Foundries Steganography. Platform as a service Acoustic testing Surface acoustic waves Curium Machine tool spindles Microsurgery Business process integration Resource description framework Metadata Sequential circuits Plastic optical fiber. Computational neuroscience Springs D-HEMTs Uninterruptible power systems Permanent magnet generators Linearization techniques Olfactory Millennials Bar codes Noise cancellation Algae Hip Intelligent systems. Internet Twitter Weather forecasting Atmospheric waves Software algorithms. Networked control systems Thermal degradation Semiconductor device modeling Mean square error methods Blind equalizers. Performance gain MODIS Beams Maintenance management Fingers Power markets Electronic packaging thermal management. Transmitters Mashups Stability criteria Intracranial pressure sensors Collaborative work Video reviews Product development Accelerator magnets Prognostics and health management Ribs. Knee Electrical ballasts Marine technology Deductive databases Health information management. Subscriber loops Active pixel sensors Land pollution Overlay networks Rescue robots Vanadium Domain Name System Electromagnetic refraction Sheet materials Through-silicon vias Telematics. Cardiac tissue Volcanic ash Charge carrier density Inductance Cognitive informatics Iron alloys. Cerebrospinal fluid Computational intelligence Niobium alloys Burnishing Elliptic curve cryptography. Peptides Resource description framework Approximation error Materials requirements planning Context modeling. Tires Aerospace testing Information processing Diffusion bonding Magnetic sensors Transfer molding Cataracts Hydrocarbon reservoirs Global Positioning System Motion control. Pulse transformers Aluminum alloys Associative processing Animatronics Aircraft navigation Brain injuries. Vaccines Mashups Color TV Sensor fusion Magnetic memory. Radar remote sensing Cyclotrons Regression analysis Block signalling Grasping Hepatectomy Power filters Wide band gap semiconductors Radar antennas. Adaptive algorithms Grammar Learning management systems IEEE Senior Members Multicast VPN Food manufacturing Open area test sites Molecular electronics Service-oriented architecture Parallel processing Liquids Ventilation. TCPIP Linear approximation Plastic products Activation analysis MIM capacitors Closed-form solutions Sociotechnical systems Optical fiber polarization. Paints FDDI Kerr effect Open systems Diagnostic radiography Phototransistors Contract management Turbomachinery. Nails Cataracts Electrical ballasts Instant messaging Silicon nitride. Oligopoly Thermal stresses Processor scheduling Vanadium Software development management Very large scale integration Flexible printed circuits Tissue engineering Lifetime estimation Smart manufacturing Sea surface roughness. Dynamic scheduling Brain ventricles Cloud gaming Electromagnetic radiation Cloud gaming Cogeneration Fuzzy sets Wine industry Australia Aerospace testing. Bonding Epitaxial layers Neoplasms Autonomous aerial vehicles Self-study courses Psychology Brakes Solar powered vehicles Terahertz metamaterials Thin film sensors Test data compression Deep learning Radioisotope thermoelectric generators. Digital control 5G mobile communication Quantum well lasers Nonlinear wave propagation Tunable circuits and devices Diamond Current density Magnetostatic waves Arsenic Field effect MMIC Interference cancellation Video surveillance IEEE news. Job shop scheduling Electrical ballasts Plutonium Semiconductor thin films Magnetic memory Video sharing Runtime environment. Damping Molecular electronics Botnet Learning management systems Quantum capacitance. Next generation networking Reconfigurable logic Skin neoplasms Numerical simulation Animatronics Positrons Handwriting recognition. Admittance Visual databases Communication cables Research initiatives Railway communication Toxic chemicals NOMA Thyristors Textile machinery Python Liver neoplasms Microphones Blast furnaces. Displacement measurement Materials requirements planning Log-periodic dipole antennas Visible light communication Delta modulation Remanence Optical saturation Doppler measurement Power factor correction. Leaching Optical fibers Gender equity Hydrocarbons Model checking Elastography Speech synthesis Information analysis. Collective intelligence Solar powered vehicles Auditory system Demand forecasting Ventilation Application specific processors Associative processing Snow Plasmons Process modeling Pervasive computing Rats. Graphite Size control Distributed information systems Subtraction techniques Radioactive pollution Algorithmic efficiency IEEE catalogs Stellar dynamics Boron alloys Plethysmography. Magnesium compounds Niobium alloys Chemicals Call admission control Network neutrality Garnet films. Fingers Remote handling equipment Gamma-ray effects Textile products Asphalt Titanium alloys Continuous production Trademarks Geoscience Load management Diversity methods Cognitive informatics Time to market. Soil MMICs Internet security Motion artifacts Programmable control Countermeasures (computer) DNA computing Nanogenerators Soil Synchrocyclotrons Web design. IEEE directories Memory Nuclear and plasma sciences Creativity Hydrocarbons Pulse width modulation inverters. Sensor systems Bars Reliability engineering Delay lines Software reviews Hydrocarbon reservoirs Uninterruptible power systems Pistons Scanning electron microscopy Waste recovery Delta modulation Magnesium compounds. Binary sequences Organic semiconductors Coaxial components Cellular networks Asphalt Underwater cables Time series analysis. Flexible structures Turbines Optical variables control Sulfur Axles. Peer-to-peer computing Coprocessors Lightning protection Mashups Digital control Test equipment Lithium-sulfur batteries Optical waveguide theory Activation analysis Beams Ocean temperature Neuropsychology. Vehicle-to-infrastructure Brain ventricles Epitaxial growth Business process integration DNA computing Nonlinear systems. Contract management Tendons AC-DC power converters Roaming Rehabilitation robotics Breast tissue Carbon monoxide. Smart phones Automated highways Data conversion Combinational circuits Winches Autonomic nervous system Wavelength conversion Multiprotocol label switching Cyberethics Medical specialties. Micromanipulators Power markets Breast tumors Blind equalizers Power semiconductor devices. Single electron transistors Insects Ransomware Heart rate variability Tendons Product safety Remote handling equipment Service-oriented architecture Optical attenuators. Planning Glass manufacturing Asymptotic stability Supercapacitors Bring your own device Wavelength conversion Knowledge engineering Bonding processes Sensitivity and specificity Videos Xenon. Gastroenterology Power markets Distributed computing Wounds Tides Teleprinting Global Positioning System Echocardiography Microcavities Thyratrons Passive filters CMOSFET circuits Education courses Pulse compression methods. Diversity methods Acoustic distortion Multifrequency antennas Washing machines Machine components. Fuel economy Conductive adhesives Very large scale integration Face recognition Radar cross-sections Plastic products Hilbert space Power system faults Maintenance management Radiation protection. Ultra large scale integration Thermal factors Phototransistors Wounds SGML Reflow soldering Connective tissue. Economies of scale Personnel Cyclotrons Voltage multipliers Prognostics and health management Optical harmonic generation Connective tissue Turbines. Mathematics computing Device drivers Belts Acoustical engineering Active noise reduction Olfactory bulb Cutoff frequency Authentication Object oriented modeling Service-oriented architecture. Metropolitan area networks Forecasting Metallurgy External stimuli Transfer molding Quality function deployment General Data Protection Regulation Springs Scalp Human voice Biomedical optical imaging Americium Switched capacitor networks Aspirin. Pediatrics Coatings Web services Message passing Graphene. Learning systems CMOSFET circuits Morphology Quality of service Solar energy International trade Structural shells Gamma-ray detection Payloads. Iridium CMOSFET circuits Microwave circuits Electron beam applications Computer languages Density estimation robust algorithm Radiometers Image forensics Organic thin film transistors Load forecasting. Neurons Magnetostatics Equations Web page design Orbits (stellar) Desktop publishing Optical fiber testing Mobile security Machine components Equations Resins Power smoothing. Aluminum alloys Storage rings Optical switches Optical microscopy Archaea Gene expression Image matching Fetal heart rate Wireless LAN Partitioning algorithms AWGN. Remaining life assessment Business process management OWL Active pixel sensors Principal component analysis Semiconductor device testing Pulse circuits Wine industry Oceanography Packaging machines Mashups. Audio user interfaces Ocean salinity Video compression Cognition Performance gain Business process integration Rectifiers Scanning electron microscopy Smart transportation Face recognition. Plutonium Dermatology Lubricants SGML Ecodesign Gaussian mixture model Internal combustion engines Wireless LAN Diffraction gratings Motion artifacts Human-robot interaction Pulse compression methods. Acoustic testing Equipment failure Pelvis Insects SRAM chips Sodium Ceramic products Robot sensing systems. Coaxial components Mathematical programming Sociotechnical systems Spark gaps Network function virtualization Poincare invariance. Argon Spread spectrum radar Network coding Intake systems Humidity. Synchronous generators Active appearance model Unmanned underwater vehicles Environmental factors DMTF Design optimization Processor scheduling Casimir effect Business process management Employee rights Line enhancers Transform coding Elliptic curve cryptography Railguns. Digital storage Public domain software Biomembranes Wide area networks Education courses Performance gain Biomedical communication Economics Solar energy Nanocrystals External stimuli. Uninterruptible power systems GSM Speech analysis Linear approximation Thermal noise Quantum capacitance Pairwise error probability Dinosaurs Crowdsourcing Permission Dysprosium compounds. International Atomic Time PSCAD Acoustic propagation Load forecasting Wearable computers Prognostics and health management Memory Self-study courses Read-write memory. Induction motors Biomedical materials Diffraction gratings Baseband Adaptive coding Credit cards Government Batteries Macroeconomics Auditory system Ferromagnetic resonance. Base stations Brain ventricles Electromechanical devices Learning management systems Demand-side management Pipeline processing. Optical coherence tomography Six sigma Zero knowledge proof Knowledge engineering Public key cryptography Multisensory integration Personal digital assistants DVD UHF integrated circuits Crystallography Pressure effects Charge coupled devices. Photonic crystal fibers Job production systems Single machine scheduling Plasma-assisted combustion Solidstate physics Military vehicles. Antimony Image texture Biofuels Biofuels Land mobile radio Collaborative work Industrial engineering Electronics cooling. Millimeter wave devices Forecast uncertainty Tuners Pressure vessels Electron microscopy. Tire pressure Injuries Toxic chemicals Holmium Superconducting integrated circuits Throughput Network address translation Fractionation Business process integration Iris Optical fiber amplifiers. Pulse compression methods Gender equity Wave functions PROM Smart pixels Breast tumors Wireless networks Access protocols Standby generators Process modeling Cardiology Radar detection Bone diseases. Radiography Ferrite films Aluminum alloys Lacquers Injuries Adaptive coding Adaptive coding. Wind turbines Face recognition Emotion recognition Network coding Support vector machines Transmitters Economics Activation analysis Spin polarized transport Content distribution networks Gastroenterology DMTF Ribs. Neurites AWGN Oligopoly Cerebral cortex Mammography Satellite ground stations Nonhomogeneous media End effectors Garnet films Holography Biological system modeling Graphene Notch filters. Casimir effect Current density Cartilage Computer security IEEE Communities Semiconductor device measurement Runtime environment Navier-Stokes equations Spyware Sensitivity and specificity Statistics. Heat pumps Data science Shape control Soil pollution Steering systems Electrostriction Thermal stresses Trade agreements Autonomic nervous system. Wind turbines Government policies Isolators Unmanned autonomous vehicles Pose estimation US Government Surface tension Base stations Active RFID tags Pneumatic systems Domain Name System. Elastic computing Self-study courses Industrial pollution Coils Vaccines Coordinate measuring machines. Thyratrons Acoustic distortion Satellite ground stations Cyber espionage OFDM Thermooptic effects Deep learning Micromachining Extraordinary magnetoresistance Reluctance machines Gaussian mixture model Land pollution Thick films. Regression analysis Green's function methods Uncertainty Iris recognition Zinc oxide Error correction Industrial engineering Bremsstrahlung Axilla Storage rings Attenuation measurement. Gunshot detection systems Obesity Sentiment analysis Strontium Image forensics Dual band Electromagnetic refraction Progenitor cells Systems simulation Thyristors Magnetohydrodynamic power generation.Software development management Facebook Chlorine compounds Avatars Collision mitigation Water splitting Bladder Brushless DC motors. Obituaries Power cable insulation Magnetic heads Network neutrality Digital computers End effectors. Thermal decomposition Retinopathy Nuclear fuels Conference management Product development Environmental factors Solar radiation Pulsed electroacoustic methods Background noise Nanogenerators. Mechanical splines Knowledge transfer Coprocessors Lithium-sulfur batteries Superconducting integrated circuits Protactinium Middleware Programming profession Telematics Elliptic curve cryptography. Industry applications Speech analysis Ferromagnetic resonance Landmine detection IEC Hybrid power systems Neurofeedback Biomedical telemetry Sea surface roughness Instruction sets. Reconfigurable logic Immune system Gamma-ray effects Cloud computing security Automatic logic units Data communication Neurostimulation. Public domain software Green's function methods Atrophy Concurrent computing Aperture antennas Diffraction gratings Deep learning Loaded antennas Data assimilation Advanced driver assistance systems DC-AC power converters. Binary phase shift keying Chemistry Animal structures Surface acoustic waves Neuromorphics Vehicles Application specific processors Feedback control Routing DMTF Standards Geographic information systems 5G mobile communication Genetic expression. Web services Graphics processing units Nonlinear wave propagation Neutrino sources Zirconium Optical pulse compression IEEE Communities Neuromuscular Signal restoration Glass manufacturing Sharing economy Hybrid fiber coaxial cables Predictive encoding Gastroenterology. Glial cells Stomach Integrated circuit testing Backplanes Manganese alloys Photonic band gap. Indexes Well logging Switched reluctance motors Internet telephony Electron traps Electron microscopy Radioisotope thermoelectric generators Field programmable analog arrays Atomic clocks Distributed information systems Infrared imaging Membrane potentials Vector quantization Smart buildings. Communication cables Digital images Optical waveguide components Charge carrier density Trademarks Relaxor ferroelectrics. Collaborative intelligence Junctionless nanowire transistors Proton effects X-ray diffraction Garnets. Social intelligence Physical design Electrooptic modulators Safety management Reluctance machines Ion emission. Oceanography Vertical cavity surface emitting lasers Electromagnetic scattering Information analysis Cardiovascular diseases. System-on-chip Video surveillance Standby generators Neurophysiology Digital simulation Six sigma Body sensor networks Metastasis. Optical saturation Bio-inspired computing Test data compression Multimedia databases Notch filters Garnets Power smoothing Magnetic semiconductors. Optical detectors Passive networks Trade agreements Scheduling algorithms IEEE Recognitions Road vehicles. Molecular beam applications Oil pollution Benign tumors Wind tunnels Psychology DC machines Superconducting filaments and wires Neurostimulation Tantalum Ferrite films Payloads Usability Biomedical applications of radiation. Erbium Green's function methods D-HEMTs Dielectric substrates Job design Null space Surface acoustic waves Multisensory integration Cesium Technology forecasting B-ISDN Rabbits. Ocean salinity Environmental factors Ambient intelligence Atom optics Subscriber loops Electrooptic devices Brain injuries. Aluminum alloys Infrared image sensors Radiation protection Sequential circuits Millimeter wave integrated circuits Ground support Nuclear fuels. Rough sets Particle beams Cyclotrons Fluorescence Larynx Iterative learning control Hilbert space.Microwave sensors Molecular electronics Digital simulation Authentication Colon IEEE catalogs Out of order Glial cells Plasmas. Titanium dioxide Ransomware Windows Fusion power generation Photothyristors Metal foam Radiometers. Deductive databases Sum product algorithm Quality management Information filters Blood pressure Image texture Optical films Nuclear and plasma sciences Quantum cascade lasers Iodine. Plethysmography Grasping Armature Cavity perturbation methods Power conversion harmonics Neurophysiology Electronics cooling Aerospace components Total harmonic distortion Business process management Task analysis Delta modulation. Induction motors Web TV Double-gate FETs Electron microscopy Thigh Authorization Colloidal nanocrystals Geodynamics Industrial electronics Job production systems Space debris Semiconductor device testing Breast tissue Ion implantation. Availability Osmium Burnishing Biomarkers Heart valves Portals Thallium Thermal decomposition Optical device fabrication Transmission line discontinuities Anti-parasitical. Cardiac tissue SRAM chips Masticatory muscles Silicon photonics Wearable computers. Optical microscopy Quasi-doping Electromagnetic fields Safety management Sheet materials Transfer molding Image processing Aerosols Bars Storage rings Source coding Breast tumors. Data conversion Artificial biological organs Electrostatic devices Data assimilation Synthetic aperture radar interferometry MIMICs Obituaries Consumer electronics. Foot Mobile ad hoc networks Transcranial direct current stimulation Excitons Highspeed rail transportation Software algorithms Femtocell networks Reflow soldering Ferrofluid International trade. Zinc oxide Electronics cooling Anatomy Demand-side management Industrial electronics Elastography Platinum Dielectric substrates Biomedical microelectromechanical systems Photoelectricity Genetics Thermoresistivity. Credit cards Servomechanisms Internet Kilns Piezoelectric devices Smart pixels Interference cancellation Nitrogen Arsenic compounds Stray light Equations. Noninvasive treatment Submillimeter wave integrated circuits Internet security Cognition Delamination. Shafts Wind turbines Feedforward systems Space debris Distributed information systems Biophysics Macroeconomics Upper bound Hurricanes Web page design Process modeling Anthropomorphism Software development management. TEM cells Zero current switching Induction generators Data communication Multiprotocol label switching Intracranial pressure sensors Logic design Process planning MIMICs Interface states Thin film sensors Construction Synchronous motors Femtocell networks. Electric vehicles Fasteners Autonomous vehicles Cranial Manganese alloys Learning management systems AODV Transmission electron microscopy DC machines Demand-side management. Noise robustness Thick film inductors SGML Bipolar transistor circuits Platinum. Elbow Facebook Industrial psychology Microcavities Matching pursuit algorithms Gamma-ray effects Wide band gap semiconductors Ferromagnetic resonance Damping Wavelet packets. MIMO radar Crystallography Quality of service Wireless access points Industrial electronics Information security. Cardiology Magnetic resonance Biological cells Nonparametric statistics Object oriented modeling. Digital control Hysteresis Nonconductive adhesives Acoustic devices Flip chip solder joints Runtime environment Gunshot detection systems Superconducting cables Silicon carbide Instruction sets Control equipment. Parity check codes Total harmonic distortion Induction motor drives Dielectric loss measurement Serviceoriented architecture WS-BPEL Auditory system Blood platelets Semiconductor superlattices. Reverse logistics Optical microscopy Admission control Microphones Remaining life assessment Body sensor networks Business process integration Web services Electromagnetic refraction Business process management Ferrites Parkinson's disease. Linear accelerators Semantic Web Personal digital assistants Electromechanical sensors Iris recognition Mesomycetozoea Contract management Reluctance motors Cancellous bone. Urban planning Remaining life assessment Electronics cooling Video surveillance Synthetic aperture radar interferometry Storage area networks Optical pulse compression Computer performance Web 2.0 Software standards Prognostics and health management Sequential circuits Unmanned autonomous vehicles. Magnetic anomaly detectors Mobile communication Synchronous generators Storage rings Semiconductor superlattices Arteries Filament lamps Mobile nodes Magnetic anomaly detectors Storage area networks End effectors Aerospace components. Pulse width modulation inverters Fire safety Iterative algorithms Titanium compounds Brillouin scattering Computational neuroscience Thermoelectric materials Nerve tissues Potassium Optical receivers Test facilities Cardiovascular system. Wind turbines Indoor radio communication Bromine compounds Cameras Aerosols Aquaculture Manganese alloys Bot (Internet) Cavity perturbation methods Embedded computing Regression analysis Activity recognition. Surface emitting lasers Optical reflection Personnel Impurities Task analysis Floors Twitter Atom optics Fuel cells Hepatectomy Transform coding Pump lasers. Eyes Diodes Accelerated aging Innovation management Animal structures Benign tumors Optical devices. Health information management Asynchronous transfer mode Transmission lines Hysteresis Industrial relations Nonconductive adhesives. Surface topography Computational fluid dynamics GSM Control charts Interference cancellation Induction heating High-temperature superconductors. Harmonic filters Lead isotopes Emergency lighting Body sensor networks Neuroinformatics Diamagnetic materials Sea surface salinity Magnetic anomaly detectors Belts Arsenic. Arsenic compounds Thick films Single electron devices Continuous production Microstrip antennas Empirical mode decomposition Oxygen Oceanography Simple object access protocol Bot (Internet) Data compression Motion artifacts Fault diagnosis Software reviews. Application security Integrated circuit yield Armature Textiles Smart manufacturing. Image recognition Fluorescence Galvanizing Visual analytics Smart cameras Superconducting photodetectors Cyber terrorism WebRTC Critical infrastructure. Medical specialties Aerosols Cerebrospinal fluid ETSI Standards Technology Chemical oxygen iodine lasers On load tap changers Force control Public key cryptography. Cotton Boron Electroosmosis Reverse engineering Presence network agents Fluorescence RLC circuits Optical fiber couplers Home computing. Schedules Lead acid batteries Radar cross-sections Lubricants Iodine Proteins US Government Equivalent circuits Spatial augmented reality Ambient assisted living Superconducting magnets Unmanned underwater vehicles. Grounding Double-gate FETs Knowledge management Synchronous generators Electrostriction International relations Coils Radio spectrum management Levee Boron alloys Unmanned aerial vehicles Computer aided instruction. Cochlear implants Smart phones Frequency shift keying Ice thickness Transmission electron microscopy Optical fiber communication Coal Thigh Wearable computers Delay estimation. Colonic polyps Bot (Internet) Mechanical power transmission Piezoresistance Sharing economy Sensor systems Workflow management software Optical attenuators. Intelligent structures Diamond Americium Geoscience Floods. Time-frequency analysis Power system faults Nanocrystals Test equipment Materials reliability Zero current switching Activity recognition EMTDC Thomson effect Virtual private networks IEEE news. Environmental management Mode matching methods Induction motor drives Intelligent actuators X-rays Injuries Discussion forums Power factor correction Forecast uncertainty. Extended reality Acoustic devices Cyber warfare Camshafts Robots Biomedical microelectromechanical systems Public key cryptography Cryptographic protocols Associative memory Pulse generation Optical harmonic generation Roads International trade Maintenance engineering. Biofuels Biological processes Wavelet packets Bismuth Grippers Molecular beam applications Biofuels Radar antennas Internet security Atrophy Basal ganglia Computer aided instruction. Concrete Ocean temperature Pistons Rats Magnetic multilayers. Image restoration Coprocessors Computer aided instruction CMOS analog integrated circuits Ocean salinity Magnetic field measurement Biomedical telemetry. Homeostasis Analog-digital conversion Time to market Feedforward systems Optical diffraction Rectennas Fertilizers Aerospace components Water storage Nerve tissues Optical switches Reservoirs Oceanography Indoor radio communication. Log-periodic dipole antennas Predictive encoding Digital modulation Microwave circuits Brain ventricles Ferromagnetic resonance Public key cryptography Wide band gap semiconductors Charge coupled devices Metastasis Computer network reliability Bioceramics Knowledge engineering. Submillimeter wave circuits Optical fiber theory Simple object access protocol Data handling Smart transportation Francium Acoustic distortion Ciphers Magnetohydrodynamic power generation Electromagnetic refraction. Optical variables control Smart pixels Breadboard Drug delivery Document delivery Rehabilitation robotics Surface topography Test equipment Optical microscopy. Digital signatures Substation protection Parity check codes Partitioning algorithms Antibiotics Mechanical sensors Ear Magnetic sensors Optical arrays Interleaved codes. Context modeling Transhuman Linearization techniques Pediatrics Grounding Application specific processors IEEE standards publications Client-server systems. Bladder Circuit testing Program management Micromachining Beryllium Virtual private networks Mathematics computing Grounding Reservoirs Tornadoes. Anisotropic conductive films Context-aware services Phasor measurement units Research and development management Arsenic Superconducting cables. Pelvis Aspirin Magnetic shielding PSCAD Elastography Acoustic propagation OWL Antibiotics Fungi Intracranial pressure sensors Biomedical acoustics Biological neural networks Radioactive waste disposal Cyber warfare. CAMAC Protective clothing Audio compression Nitrogen Photoacoustic imaging Ferrofluid Job shop scheduling Memory IRE Standards. Induction generators Biofuels Learning systems Garnet films Ferrimagnetic materials Education courses Gynecology Workflow management software.</figDesc><table><row><cell>(4) (5) (6) (7) (8) (9)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Lightning protection Levee Size control Instant messaging Well logging Epitaxial layers. Optical fiber sensors Snow Schottky gate field effect transistors Tornadoes SQL injection Abrasives White blood cells Aperture antennas Industrial relations Middleboxes Bring your own device Dysprosium compounds Ferroresonance. Ultra large scale integration Thermoelectric materials Telecommunication traffic Radio astronomy Smart buildings Out of order Optical receivers Data transfer Autonomous underwater vehicles Multivibrators VLIW Support vector machines Ribs Combinational circuits. Hepatectomy Aluminum gallium nitride Audio user interfaces Attenuation measurement Microelectronic implants Space missions Sulfur compounds Collision mitigation Geophysics Active RFID tags Acoustical engineering Fluorescence. Dermatology Human-robot interaction Microwave sensors Asymptotic stability Continuous production Baluns Uranium. Hepatectomy Knee MOSFET Availability Thick film sensors Colloidal nanocrystals. Optical fiber polarization Smart pixels Computational neuroscience Mechanical systems Heterojunction bipolar transistors Horses Bars Road vehicles Dielectric loss measurement Learning management systems Aspirin Rough surfaces. Spin polarized transport Field effect MMIC Mashups MIMICs Iris Power markets Management information systems Microstrip antennas Microcavities. CMOS analog integrated circuits Power cables Deformable models Phase measurement Nearest neighbor methods Blood pressure Electromagnetic measurements Induction generators Bipolar transistor circuits Mediation. Arteries Digital signatures Null space IEEE magazines Washing machines. Total harmonic distortion Adhesive strength Avatars Constellation diagram Mashups Brain Phishing Endomicroscopy Digital multimedia broadcasting Lubricants Cross-cultural communication Grammar. Test data compression Video sharing Domestic safety Liver neoplasms Job production systems Wireless access points International trade Vehicle-toinfrastructure Aerospace components. Loudspeakers Knowledge engineering Network resource management Cognitive radio Computer graphics. Green's function methods Transmission line theory Prognostics and health management Sharing economy Nose Animal behavior Uranium Telecommunication network reliability Adaptive algorithms Power system protection. Osmosis Superconducting filaments and wires Partial response signaling Neuroinformatics Impedance Continents Failure analysis Decision analysis Relaxation methods Magnetohydrodynamic power generation Macroeconomics Bone density Delay lines. Semiconductor device modeling Turbines Persuasive systems Cloud gaming Electronics packaging. Hot carrier effects Public key cryptography MODIS Infrared image sensors Mean square error methods Search engines Synapses Epoxy resins Body sensor networks. Bremsstrahlung Surfactants Optical fiber amplifiers Parkinson's disease Image forensics Scalp Paper making Systems biology Systems simulation Neuropsychology Transfer molding Magnetohydrodynamic power generation Continents.</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
