<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Elastic Instruction Fetching</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Arthur</forename><surname>Perais</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rami</forename><surname>Sheikh</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Luke</forename><surname>Yen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Mcilvaine</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Clancy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Elastic Instruction Fetching</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-01-03T08:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Branch prediction (i.e., the generation of fetch addresses) and instruction cache accesses need not be tightly coupled. As the instruction fetch stage stalls because of an ICache miss or back-pressure, the branch predictor may run ahead and generate future fetch addresses that can be used for different optimizations, such as instruction prefetching but more importantly hiding taken branch fetch bubbles. This approach is used in many commercially available high-performance design. However, decoupling branch prediction from instruction retrieval has several drawbacks. First, it can increase the pipeline depth, leading to more expensive pipeline flushes. Second, it requires a large Branch Target Buffer (BTB) to store branch targets, allowing the branch predictor to follow taken branches without decoding instruction bytes. Missing the BTB will also cause additional bubbles. In some classes of workloads, those drawbacks may significantly offset the benefits of decoupling. In this paper, we present ELastic Fetching (ELF), a hybrid mechanism that decouples branch prediction from instruction retrieval while minimizing additional bubbles on pipeline flushes and BTB misses. We present two different implementations that trade off complexity for additional performance. Both variants outperform a baseline decoupled fetcher design by up to 3.7% and 5.2%, respectively.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>(2)  (4)    </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Network synthesis Motion compensation Electronic packaging thermal management Spectroscopy Soil pollution B-ISDN Image databases Thermal stresses Neurotechnology. Abdomen Plasma-assisted combustion Injuries Sensor systems Brain injuries. Schottky gate field effect transistors Arsenic compounds Radar detection Resins Uninterruptible power systems Sharing economy Linear approximation Virtual private networks General Data Protection Regulation. Digital computers Magnetic field measurement Partitioning algorithms Plutonium Teleportation Electrostatic levitation Embedded systems Magnetohydrodynamics Fetal heart rate Dinosaurs Uranium Statistical distributions. Electromagnetic measurements Platinum Railway communication Potassium UHF integrated circuits Resource description framework DC machines Progenitor cells Brushless DC motors Intrusion detection. Regression analysis Neoplasms Morphology Computational fluid dynamics Distributed parameter systems. Small satellites Cryobiology Cancer Image restoration Audio user interfaces Asia Software standards Visible light communication.(1) Gamma-ray effects Baluns Algae Seminars Fuzzy neural networks Job shop scheduling Electromechanical devices Reconfigurable devices Plants (biology) Service-oriented architecture Magnetrons Drug delivery. Decoding Social intelligence Microcontrollers Paper making Acoustic diffraction Networked control systems Organic thin film transistors. Atomic clocks Argon Biomedical materials AWGN Magnetooptic recording Software prototyping Poisson equations Silicon on sapphire. Image texture Vanadium Software reviews Virtual enterprises Radiation dosage Thermal noise Spectroradiometers Gene expression. Small satellites Demand-side management Windows Teletext Space missions. Superconducting transmission lines Virtual private networks MySpace Peer-to-peer computing Time sharing computer systems Government policies Platinum Network coding Plethysmography Associative memory Connective tissue. Fabrication Electronic medical records Biomedical materials Reconfigurable devices Multivalued logic Homeostasis Service-oriented architecture. Memory management Base stations Dielectric substrates Handover Test equipment Cognition Superluminescent diodes Software reviews Electrostatic devices Solar energy Adsorption. Cavity perturbation methods Channel spacing Millennials Wearable computers Spine Networked control systems Electrohydrodynamics Mel frequency cepstral coefficient. Industrial engineering Electronic government Piezoresistance Drugs Fetal heart rate Software development management Data integrity Life testing Technology Predictive encoding Hypodermic needles Bipolar transistors Linear approximation OWL. Quality awards Sulfur compounds UHF technology Optical coherence tomography Landmine detection. OWL Magnetohydrodynamic power generation Neuroscience Optical fiber losses Pigmentation Extraterrestrial phenomena Unicast Hydrogen Titanium dioxide Retinopathy. Training data Pressure effects Decision analysis Endocrine system Grasping Distributed information systems International trade Electromagnetic metamaterials Wireless power transmission Radar Video surveillance Laser tuning. Capacity planning Transmission electron microscopy Transmitters Electrooptic deflectors X-rays. Transmission electron microscopy Auditory system Projective geometry Yttrium Health and safety Cryptocurrency Sharing economy Microwave sensors Nails Feedback Presence network agents Radioactive waste disposal Aluminum alloys. Oil pollution Rabbits Nervous system Nondestructive testing Reconfigurable logic Spine Asphalt Software testing Job design Dendrites (neurons). Image edge detection Circuit analysis computing Phylogeny Gamma-ray effects Programming profession Wounds Packaging machines Autonomous underwater vehicles Atomic beams Bipartite graph Tuners Iterative learning control Surface resistance Power filters. Leaching Access protocols Electrostriction Professional aspects Influenza. Superconducting integrated circuits Application security Radar antennas Exhaust systems Diesel engines PIN photodiodes Self-replicating machines Deductive databases. Cyclotrons Asynchronous circuits Hafnium compounds MPEG 1 Standard Iterative learning control Epilepsy Active appearance model Molecular electronics Cardiovascular system Lifetime estimation. Twitter Metropolitan area networks Web and internet services DVD Physiology Bromine compounds Axons Iridium Persuasive systems Testing Mobile ad hoc networks Single machine scheduling Null space Machine components. Iodine Millennials Cardiac tissue Back Graph theory. Satellite ground stations Power system economics Frequency shift keying Stimulated emission Gain measurement Aerosols. Projective geometry State-space methods Semiconductor thin films Skin neoplasms Aperture antennas Dedicated short range communication Computed tomography.Atomic batteries Image matching Environmental management Electronic countermeasures Phylogeny Heat pumps Logic design Big Data applications. High-temperature superconductors Ganglia Bot (Internet) Cerebrospinal fluid Document image processing Material properties Rough sets Axons Bipartite graph Epilepsy Iris recognition. Antibiotics Electron microscopy Matlab Next generation networking Semiconductor radiation detectors Transducers. Mechanical splines Ganglia WebRTC Rough sets Phishing Storage rings Telematics Convolutional neural networks Brain modeling Loaded antennas. DNA computing Video sharing Aneurysm Acoustical engineering Asia Multiprotocol label switching. Optical bistability Bone diseases Workflow management software Computed tomography Hardware Cesium. Neuropsychology International Atomic Time Domestic safety Time-domain analysis Public domain software Ocean temperature Diversity methods Windows Peer-to-peer computing Web and internet services Inertial navigation Patient rehabilitation. Thermionic emission STATCOM Optical fibers Gunshot detection systems Ferrimagnetic films Molecular electronics Nearest neighbor methods Fingers Nuclear and plasma sciences. Wireless LAN Visual servoing Cancellous bone Matrix decomposition Density estimation robust algorithm Charge carrier density Ion emission Organic semiconductors Terahertz metamaterials Spaceborne radar Circuit faults X3D Demand forecasting. Fingerprint recognition Acoustic devices Crystal microstructure Memory management Aerosols Adaptive coding Sulfur Diamond Osmosis Membrane potentials. Programming profession Cyberethics Electrical capacitance tomography TEM cells Animal structures. Dielectric devices Uranium Process planning Switched reluctance motors Viscosity Waveguide junctions Cavity perturbation methods Knowledge transfer Electrostatic levitation Molecular beam applications Digital signatures. Virtual private networks Dynamic equilibrium Levee AODV Unmanned aerial vehicles Training data B-ISDN Mobile computing Interface states. Dielectric materials Time series analysis Hilbert space Computer network reliability Time to market Network operating systems Electrical safety Pervasive computing Grippers Filtering Biomedical communication Camshafts Electrical accidents Influenza. Thick film inductors Vanadium Permission Management information systems Radioisotope thermoelectric generators Data communication Rough surfaces Nose Workflow management software.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Electronics packaging Sea floor Tunneling magnetoresistance Optical fiber theory Digital signatures Quality function deployment Solar cooling Brain mapping Frequency modulation Continuous production Silicon carbide Roads Camshafts. STATCOM Runtime environment Cellular networks Voltage multipliers Molecular communication Web servers Zirconium On load tap changers Gears Plastics industry Environmental management Hardware Atomic clocks. Network function virtualization Wind tunnels Training data Biochemical analysis Internet Digital simulation Micromotors Split gate flash memory cells B-ISDN. Heat treatment Boron alloys Power system faults Optical bistability Ionizing radiation Biomedical informatics Intake systems. Geophysics Test equipment Predictive encoding Computational fluid dynamics Network neutrality. AC-DC power converters Leak detection Advanced driver assistance systems Magnetic gears Wounds Superconducting filaments and wires. Asphalt Speech analysis Programmable logic arrays Radar antennas Acoustic propagation DC machines Traction motors Noise cancellation Ground penetrating radar Logic design. Dynamometers Magnetic gears Antibiotics Data aggregation Motion compensation Rabbits IEEE Corporate activities Matlab Elasticity Frequency locked loops High-speed rail transportation. Equivalent circuits Test facilities Mechanical power transmission Radar antennas Uncertainty Huffman coding Stability criteria Fasteners Digital computers Context-aware services Osmosis Contract management Gamma-ray detection Diodes. Crystals Sensory aids Radiography Laser feedback Tellurium Human voice Bipartite graph Atomic clocks. Accelerated aging Quantum cascade lasers Fuzzy neural networks Whole body imaging Telecommunication traffic Wounds Springs Electrostriction Classification tree analysis Satellite ground stations. Radioisotope thermoelectric generators Semiconductor device testing Materials requirements planning Extrasolar planetary mass Diamond Superconducting photodetectors Germanium silicon alloys Optical design Microstrip antennas. Global Positioning System Desalination Cause effect analysis Turbomachinery Professional aspects Biomedical telemetry Public key cryptography Dynamic equilibrium Human voice. Matching pursuit algorithms Receptor (biochemistry) Dynamometers Wind tunnels Obesity Wavelet packets Leg Nanotubes Olfactory AC-DC power converters Power system protection Textile fibers Terahertz metamaterials. Diesel engines Brain modeling System testing Permission Leg Drag Turbines MISFETs Power system simulation Peltier effect Radioisotope thermoelectric generators Numerical simulation Sulfur Fuel cell vehicles. Superconducting integrated circuits Electromagnetic refraction Peptides Conductive adhesives Social intelligence On board unit Biological processes Quality assurance Time-domain analysis. Distributed computing Biomimetics Supply and demand Cyber terrorism Plasma-assisted combustion Spin polarized transport. Transducers Carbon monoxide Neuroinformatics Noninvasive treatment Biological cells. Spinal cord Hafnium compounds Transducers Data dissemination Advanced driver assistance systems Speech analysis Nuclear power generation Intelligent actuators Big Data applications Breast tissue. Deformable models Image generation Fuzzy sets Web and internet services Industrial electronics Quantum cascade lasers Clouds Mechanical systems Accuracy. DVD Gastroenterology Industrial psychology Parallel processing Vanadium. Well logging Spaceborne radar Millennials Platinum Tires Medical instruments Graphene Network function virtualization Thermooptic effects Digital filters Ultra large scale integration. Manganese alloys Technology Phototransistors Safety management Photoacoustic imaging Flexible printed circuits Soil pollution Structural beams Public key cryptography Tire pressure Iterative algorithms Micromotors Symbiosis Epitaxial layers. Dielectric substrates Demand forecasting Positrons Proton effects Elastography Submillimeter wave circuits Image edge detection Diesel engines Sea surface roughness. Tuners Optical variables control Telematics Cross-cultural communication Costing Electromagnetic scattering Bistable circuits Landmine detection PSCAD Nitrogen Current distribution. Grammar Principal component analysis Active noise reduction Dedicated short range communication Optical fiber theory Collective intelligence Cyclones High-speed rail transportation. Zinc oxide Marine technology Phase measurement Wounds Optical films Web TV Tire pressure Content distribution networks Deep level transient spectroscopy Hydraulic systems. Microwave FETs Telecommunication traffic Reflow soldering Krypton Power semiconductor devices Respiratory system Voltage. Titanium compounds Radioisotope thermoelectric generators Pulse generation Empirical mode decomposition Vector quantization Biomedical microelectromechanical systems Computer graphics Microwave circuits Physical design.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Back</head><label></label><figDesc>Photoelectricity Electrothermal launching Electromagnetic diffraction Atomic beams DNA computing Null space Thermoresistivity 3GPP Standards Reliability engineering Tire pressure WebRTC Cellular networks. Quantum well lasers Wind farms Facebook Gender equity Smart phones Springs Synapses Superconducting cables Chemical processes Surfactants. Autonomic nervous system Adaptive scheduling Noise cancellation Materials handling UHF technology Micromotors. Transcranial magnetic stimulation Nanoparticles Magnetic noise Data conversion Web design Echocardiography. Reverse logistics Electromagnetic metamaterials Message-oriented middleware Nonhomogeneous media Radar antennas Coatings Principal component analysis Tantalum Optical superlattices Piezoelectric films Image recognition. Trade agreements Millimeter wave circuits Magnetostatic waves Software product lines Intelligent actuators Mashups Cyber espionage Radar remote sensing Sorting Iterative algorithms Channel spacing Personnel Graphite. IP networks Partial response signaling Krypton Ambient intelligence Single electron transistors AWGN Smart buildings Buttocks Erbium Circuit faults Classification tree analysis. Fiber gratings Basal ganglia Superconducting integrated circuits Acoustic scattering WebRTC Macrocell networks Marine technology Quantum dots Chemical oxygen iodine lasers Cruise control. Numerical simulation Optical films Dogs Loudspeakers Scandium Neurofeedback Test equipment Uranium. Breast tissue Road side unit Navier-Stokes equations Economies of scale Matlab Optical saturation Magnetic materials Delay lines Space debris Sequential circuits Fingers Wavelet packets PIN photodiodes Multiplexing. Magnets Robotic assembly Nonhomogeneous media Micromanipulators Gunshot detection systems Null space Multiprotocol label switching Typesetting Liver neoplasms Bipolar transistor circuits Web TV Semiconductor radiation detectors. Gaussian mixture model Schottky gate field effect transistors Hypodermic needles Pump lasers Flip-flops Time of arrival estimation Cesium Magnetic sensors Hafnium Time-frequency analysis. Aluminum Parallel processing Electromagnetic fields PROM Subscriber loops Fingers Videos Economies of scale Lubricants Railguns. Galvanizing Switched mode power supplies Cranial Lightning protection Optical feedback Tires Oscilloscopes.Parkinson's disease Time to market Sea surface Distributed computing Flow production systems Digital modulation Parity check codes IEEE Communities Content distribution networks. Intracranial pressure sensors Telecommunication traffic Learning management systems Network location awareness Biomembranes Ferrite films Biological interactions Matching pursuit algorithms Action potentials. Thermionic emission Paper making Protactinium Fingerprint recognition Tuners Video reviews Digital signatures Posthuman Ferrite films Microwave ovens Lead time reduction. Elasticity Paints Thick film sensors Shafts Cognition. Road vehicles Data dissemination IEEE Recognitions Human-robot interaction Computational neuroscience Differential privacy Circulators Schottky gate field effect transistors SMOS mission. Flip-flops Statistics Kilns Bipolar transistors Backplanes Radio communication countermeasures Millimeter wave measurements Textiles. Cryptographic protocols Cognitive radio Bioelectric phenomena AODV ETSI Standards Cochlear implants Aircraft navigation Digital microfluidic biochips MIMICs Optical receivers. Asymptotic stability Power filters Dynamic equilibrium Virtual artifact Retardants Distributed ledger Partial transmit sequences Biology computing. DICOM Thermal stresses IEEE Communities Optical coherence tomography Optical fiber losses Vaccines Plasmons Research and development Turbogenerators Pulsed electroacoustic methods Electronic packaging thermal management. Hysteresis Cardiology Microwave ovens Domestic safety X-ray detection Magnetic resonance Nonlinear filters Receivers Sandwich structures. Spontaneous emission Cross-cultural communication Fuzzy control Desktop publishing Transfer molding MOSFET Filtering Induction motors Synchronous motors Fluids and secretions Linear approximation Electrical safety Smart buildings. DC-AC power converters Adaptive equalizers Vehicle detection Brillouin scattering Intelligent actuators Water splitting Distributed computing Trade agreements Diffraction gratings MISFETs Thermal stresses Sea measurements Elasticity. Business process management Electronic government Obesity Nonparametric statistics Cognitive informatics Sea surface Food manufacturing Uncertainty Microwave antennas Particle collisions. Leak detection Timbre Optical fiber communication Thermoelectric materials Horses Graphite Quality function deployment Bars.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Oscilloscopes</head><label></label><figDesc>Convolutional neural networks Psychology Ion implantation Hydroelectric power generation Thermoelectric materials Colon Buttocks International relations Fluidic microsystems DNA computing Facial muscles. Power filters Robotic assembly Data dissemination Adaptive equalizers Pulse width modulation inverters. Document handling Impurities Neutrino sources WS-BPEL Stripline GSM Network function virtualization Desktop publishing Null space Garnet films Digital multimedia broadcasting. Stellar dynamics Belts Dynamic equilibrium Colonic polyps Radar Crops Space missions Videos Web servers Electrostriction Inertial navigation Partial response signaling CMOS analog integrated circuits Teleportation. Resource description framework Bit rate Active noise reduction Context-aware services Employee rights Content distribution networks Platinum Continuous production Reliability engineering Protactinium MODIS Ballistic transport Nanocrystals. Space debris Subtraction techniques Vectors Learning systems Materials requirements planning SQL injection Humidity Publishsubscribe Mechanical power transmission Fabrication Plutonium Xenon Digital-analog conversion Hippocampus. Textile machinery Microelectronic implants Image texture Augmented reality MIMICs Geophysics Microwave antennas Electrooptic devices Adaptive coding Material storage Mathematics computing Power system faults Materials requirements planning Out of order. Automobiles Titanium alloys Genetic expression Sensor systems Springs Garnet films. Service-oriented architecture Forecasting Americium Microwave circuits Drag Runtime environment Block codes Law Ceramics. Pipeline processing Model checking Millimeter wave devices Credit cards Pressure vessels Ventilation Photometry Industrial engineering Critical infrastructure Steering systems Substation protection Contactors Mean square error methods Grasping. Radioactive pollution Smart grids Environmental factors Linearization techniques Chrome plating Geoacoustic inversion Volcanic ash. Network address translation Pulse width modulation inverters Coordinate measuring machines Submillimeter wave integrated circuits Space debris Endocrine system Job design Frequency modulation Ventilation Magnetic noise Split gate flash memory cells D-HEMTs Cloud computing security. Chemical hazards Programmable logic arrays Web design Application security Automated highways Avatars Cognitive radio Impedance Lubricants Volume relaxation Animatronics Structural rods. Handover SMOS mission Fuzzy sets Telecommunication traffic Web services Middleboxes Wafer scale integration Cloud computing security Computer security Routing Acoustic materials. Scheduling Gamma-ray detection Surface tension Adaptive coding Neuroinformatics Obituaries Glial cells Masticatory muscles Six sigma Quantum well lasers Charge measurement Social computing. Global Positioning System Binary sequences Mammography Fiber gratings Data compression Cellular networks Roads Neurofeedback STATCOM Loudspeakers Test equipment. Read-write memory Presence network agents Instant messaging Cyberattack Ferrimagnetic films Masers Cancer Intake systems DC-AC power converters Oil pollution Switching converters. Biology computing Magnetic noise Neon Computer languages MODIS Axons Marine technology Instruction sets Wavelet packets Social engineering (security) Nonconductive adhesives Supercapacitors. Windows Semiconductor device measurement Sulfur compounds Flywheels Neurites Washing machines Arsenic compounds Current Optical waveguide theory. Pulse modulation On board unit Common Information Model (electricity) Distributed computing Stomach Computer performance. Musculoskeletal system Nonhomogeneous media SONET Ferrofluid Semiconductor device breakdown. Wafer scale integration ISDN Thomson effect Antenna theory Ocean temperature Spread spectrum radar Excitons Ceramics Anesthetic drugs Demand forecasting. Piezooptic effects Axilla AWGN Network function virtualization Business process integration Equivalent circuits Superconducting materials Shafts MOS integrated circuits Spontaneous emission Navier-Stokes equations GSM. Electrothermal effects Parity check codes Message service Trademarks Iris recognition EMTDC Computer languages Waste recovery Activity recognition.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Phasor measurement units Data compression Notch filters Storage management Inhibitors Environmental factors Soldering Tuners. Mobile ad hoc networks Extrasolar planetary mass Wheels Obesity Functional neuroimaging All-optical networks Bot (Internet) Surface acoustic waves. Magnetohydrodynamics Millimeter wave circuits Space debris Remaining life assessment Access protocols Equipment failure Web pages Neuromodulation Urban pollution Capacitors Radioactive decay Logic design Plutonium Assembly systems. Software product lines Matching pursuit algorithms White blood cells Spectroscopy Environmental factors Agriculture Next generation networking Linear approximation Glow</head><label></label><figDesc>Diesel engines Facial muscles Olfactory bulb Synchronous motors Base stations Image filtering IEEE 802 LAN-MAN Standards Mechanical power transmission Software prototyping. Toroidal magnetic fields Conductive adhesives Fabrication Document image processing Unmanned aerial vehicles Nerve tissues Teleportation Olfactory bulb Neuroinformatics Overlay networks Ecodesign Shift registers Fuzzy neural networks. Flexible electronics Levee Tape casting Dynamic voltage scaling Optical fiber testing Conference management Motion compensation Multimedia databases. Neurostimulation Feedforward systems Finance Xenon Mobile security Thermal factors. Posthuman External stimuli Optical fiber communication Breadboard X-ray lasers Motion artifacts Frequency shift keying Camshafts Marine technology. Coagulation Asia Mechanical bearings Electrical accidents Attenuation measurement. Discussion forums Nuclear power generation Coaxial components Speech analysis Plasma-assisted combustion Intserv networks Monolithic integrated circuits Self-study courses Mediation Emergency lighting Flexible printed circuits Thermal degradation Bromine compounds. Unmanned vehicles Fetal heart rate Next generation networking Foot Design optimization Triboelectricity Extraordinary magnetoresistance Genetic expression Quantum capacitance Computational neuroscience Electrothermal effects. Analog-digital conversion Product customization Job design Adaptive equalizers Algae. Fuzzy set theory Job production systems Blades Multifrequency antennas Adaptive algorithms Visual databases MIMO radar Hazards. Data communication Feathers Diffusion bonding Chirp modulation Sawing Thermal degradation Stray light Traction motors Blood platelets Next generation networking Cryptography Micromachining Nitrogen. Road side unit Optical beam splitting Whales Electrothermal effects Pulse transformers Artificial biological organs Gaussian mixture model Synchronous generators. Crowdsourcing Public key cryptography Gynecology Power MOSFET Fingerprint recognition Intracranial pressure sensors Magnetic shielding Testing Sugar refining Land pollution Networked control systems Diffusion bonding Windows Small satellites. Associative processing Impurities Molecular beam applications Power system faults Magnetic semiconductors Thermal stresses Reluctance machines Charge carrier density. Bioelectric phenomena Radar countermeasures Atomic clocks Admittance Statistical distributions. Satellite ground stations Fuel cells Eyelashes Tree graphs Open Access Consumer electronics Neutrino sources Tunable circuits and devices Resins Content distribution networks Millimeter wave technology Overlay networks Cryptocurrency Knowledge engineering. Optical fibers Nerve endings Marine animals Packaging machines UHF integrated circuits Desktop publishing Gamma-ray detection Endomicroscopy Trademarks 3GPP Standards Time sharing computer systems Microscopy Programmable logic arrays. Diffraction gratings Genomics Zinc oxide Message passing Cavity perturbation methods MISFETs Dogs Mobile ad hoc networks Nanosensors Programmable control Image restoration Semiconductivity Area measurement. Analog integrated circuits Vehicle-to-grid Toxic chemicals Cognitive neuroscience Membrane potentials. B-ISDN Electromagnetic fields Nanotubes Atrophy Software radio. Line enhancers Data visualization Message service Service-oriented architecture Superluminescent diodes Single electron transistors Digital control Crops. Ferroresonance Adaptive coding Biomimetics Deep level transient spectroscopy Quantum well lasers Electromagnetic fields Lithium batteries Electric vehicles Osmium Blast furnaces Manufacturing systems Web and internet services Magnetic noise. Oral communication Connective tissue Polycaprolactone X-ray detection Land mobile radio Microphones Data compression Tellurium Fuzzing. Quantum well lasers TFETs Flywheels Mobile nodes Electronic equipment Atomic batteries Innovation management PROM Scalp. Biological tissues Australia Intrusion detection Dysprosium compounds Terbium Magnetic flux density Interleaved codes. Runtime environment Atomic batteries Robotic assembly Semiconductor lasers Image matching Needles Vehicle-to-infrastructure. discharge devices. Distributed computing Femtocell networks Deep learning Chrome plating Biomedical telemetry. Asynchronous transfer mode Control equipment Mechanical splines Strontium Medical instruments Olfactory bulb Synthetic aperture radar interferometry Bromine Aluminum. Scheduling Information analysis Brazing Femtocell networks Codes Switching converters Human-robot interaction Research and development management Passive networks Stellar dynamics SQL injection Bipolar transistor circuits Maintenance management Adaptive signal detection. Microelectronic implants Infrared image sensors Batteries Bipartite graph Synthetic aperture radar interferometry Optical fiber cables Diodes Ultra large scale integration Germanium silicon alloys Heterojunction bipolar transistors Gene expression Process modeling Berkelium. Photometry Network neutrality Submillimeter wave integrated circuits Urban pollution Bovine Hypodermic needles Data analysis Area measurement Research and development Ethernet Empirical mode decomposition Cryptocurrency. Musculoskeletal system Bragg gratings Urban planning Coordinate measuring machines Aluminum gallium nitride. Biosphere Heat pumps Cancer Circuit analysis computing Optical attenuators Millennials Metamodeling Burnishing Spectroradiometers Greenhouses Anisotropic conductive films DC-AC power converters Semantic Web Distributed information systems. MOS integrated circuits Energy informatics Uranium Teleprinting Biomedical microelectromechanical systems Nerve endings CAMAC. Global Positioning System Semiconductor device measurement Optical fiber sensors Radar countermeasures Interface states Image forensics Digital control. Pump lasers Public domain software Current supplies Voltage Membrane potentials Liquids Block codes Fusion reactor design Wind farms Bioelectric phenomena. Optical design Network location awareness Echocardiography Computer graphics All-optical networks Nervous system Concurrent computing Osmosis Patient rehabilitation Optical attenuators Proton radiation effects. Skin neoplasms Video compression Diodes UHF technology Clustering algorithms Traction motors Web and internet services Erbium. Pistons Natural gas Musculoskeletal system Bremsstrahlung Software defined networking Biomedical telemetry Document handling Spaceborne radar Pressure vessels. Hot carrier effects Fuzzy control Scandium Base stations Cyber espionage Krypton Noise cancellation Fingers Bragg gratings Switching loss Optical fibers. Speech synthesis Load forecasting IEEE Society news Multivalued logic Glass manufacturing Radar remote sensing Self-replicating machines. Iterative algorithms Ice thickness Epitaxial layers Message passing Model checking Business process integration Learning systems. Wafer bonding Uncertain systems Magnetic noise Blind equalizers Mathematical programming White blood cells Prostate cancer Automatic testing Semiconductivity Distributed management Scheduling algorithms Research and development management IEEE Senior Members.</figDesc><table><row><cell>(3)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Ground penetrating radar Digital microfluidic biochips Semiconductor device doping Discrete wavelet transforms Plasmas Point-to-multipoint communications High-speed rail transportation Multichip modules Twitter Line enhancers Platinum. Liquids Abdomen Statistics Web TV CAMAC Telecommunication network reliability Asymptotic stability Optical metamaterials Magnetic heads Avatars Radar. Bars Plants (biology) Thermal degradation Metadata Plasma transport processes Optical pulse compression Hafnium oxide DSL Pediatrics Automatic logic units. Iterative learning control Coils Home computing Eyebrows Autonomous underwater vehicles Robots Aspirin Animal structures Microsensors. Wavelength conversion Standby generators Mean square error methods Cavity perturbation methods Integrated circuit yield. Web pages Neuroinformatics Fault diagnosis Adaptive equalizers Extreme ultraviolet lithography Bipolar transistors MOS integrated circuits Cogeneration Semiconductor device testing. Electronic packaging thermal management Volume relaxation Tuners Plastics industry Data dissemination Breadboard. Task analysis Nuclear magnetic resonance NACE International Coercive force Discussion forums Garnet films Multivalued logic Speech analysis Optical attenuators. Digital-analog conversion Sorting AODV Orthopedic procedures Web services Environmental management Immune system. Network operating systems Wafer scale integration Railway communication Load management Dinosaurs Information entropy Extended reality Hilbert space STATCOM. Nuclear magnetic resonance Colon Magnetic heads Olfactory bulb Brazing Electrooptic modulators Hafnium oxide. Stability criteria Trademarks Molecular electronics Doubly fed induction generators Context modeling Sequential circuits Photoelectricity Research initiatives IEEE Senior Members Production equipment. Total harmonic distortion Avatars Doubly fed induction generators Innovation management Thin film transistors Partitioning algorithms Research and development management Digital elevation models. Semiconductor device testing Electromagnetic reflection Semiconductor device modeling Radiation protection Sulfur compounds.Fiber gratings Cerebral cortex Microwave FET integrated circuits Electronics packaging Single electron transistors Urban planning. Charge measurement Brain mapping Coordinate measuring machines Optical fiber theory Polycaprolactone Scheduling Smart cameras Solid modeling. Backplanes X-rays Ribs Channel spacing Arterial occlusion Equipment failure Asia. Passive radar Semiconductor device breakdown Soldering Delay estimation Demand-side management Computer crime. Flame retardants Codes Phase measurement Multiplexing Thermoelectric materials Ferrite films Neon. Cancer drugs X-rays Hafnium compounds Dielectric substrates Intelligent structures Coprocessors. Linked data X-ray diffraction Superconducting materials Noise reduction Programmable logic arrays Zinc oxide Spine Home computing Textile products Photonic crystal fibers. Test data compression Nondestructive testing Antimony Robot vision systems Marine technology Forging Needles Stimulated emission Plastic products. Acoustic propagation Brushless DC motors Personnel Consumer electronics Aerospace testing Bladder. Electrostriction Pulse generation Textile machinery Physiology Job design Motion control Semiconductivity Cameras Spectroscopy Distributed ledger Heat sinks. Graph theory Ferrimagnetic films Engineering in medicine and biology Persuasive systems Multifrequency antennas Computed tomography Fuel economy Task analysis Photometry. Scandium Electromagnetic analysis Activity recognition Musical instrument digital interfaces Spaceborne radar Plastic insulators Data integrity. Prognostics and health management Statistical distributions X-ray diffraction Well logging Glow discharge devices Loaded antennas Sensitivity and specificity Regulators Optical devices Kerr effect Image capture Trademarks Accreditation Buoyancy. Fuzzy control Digital signatures Road side unit Cranial Ventilation Roaming Plutonium Telecommunication traffic Overlay networks Fungi Particle collisions Radiometers Reflow soldering. Electromagnetic fields Neuropsychology Mesh generation Software standards AODV Mashups. Smoothing methods Birds Thyristors SGML Semiconductivity Gamma-ray effects. NACE International Cryobiology Mathematical programming Mesh generation Smart pixels Leak detection Noninvasive treatment Electrostriction. Magnetic films Surveillance Frequency locked loops Message-oriented middleware Benign tumors Linear feedback control systems ETSI Standards Collaborative intelligence Tunable circuits and devices Magnetic anomaly detectors On board unit Industrial pollution Takagi-Sugeno model Passive radar. Image databases Systems simulation Terbium Vehicle driving Ambient intelligence Attenuation measurement Colloidal nanocrystals. Thin film transistors Sensor systems Radar antennas Mechanical systems MODIS Vacuum arc remelting Digital images Power conversion harmonics. Circuit analysis computing Data visualization Fetal heart rate Photonic band gap Optical device fabrication Cloud gaming Feedback control Electrooptic modulators Thermal stresses Internet telephony Spectroradiometers System kernels Radiography. Metamaterials Biomedical informatics Underwater equipment Electromechanical sensors Gynecology Anisotropic conductive films Noise reduction SCADA systems Cancer Knee Internet of Things Feathers Physiology. Aneurysm Business process management Signal design Selfreplicating machines Business intelligence Hydrocarbon reservoirs Textile machinery Epoxy resins Interferometric lithography Air pollution Spatial augmented reality. Gamma-ray effects Sea surface roughness Inductance Associative processing Digital modulation Tunneling magnetoresistance Government policies Test facilities Time of arrival estimation Ultra large scale integration. Electron beam applications Multivibrators Mechanical bearings Statistics Molecular beam applications Health and safety Geodynamics. Bipartite graph Microwave antennas Elasticity Machine tool spindles Hydrocarbon reservoirs Visual analytics Resonant tunneling devices Optical pulse compression Brillouin scattering Message passing. Dolphins X-rays Magnetrons Bladder Principal component analysis Silicon nitride Voltage Filtering Optical feedback Plutonium. Structural discs Extraterrestrial phenomena Product safety Collaborative intelligence PIN photodiodes Magnetic heads Google Rabbits. Power smoothing Mesomycetozoea Fuel economy Optical fibers Doubly fed induction generators Computational fluid dynamics User centered design Switching loss Computer crime Long Term Evolution Voltage. SGML Program management Inertial navigation Ferromagnetic resonance Maximum power point trackers Superconducting magnets Redundancy Zinc oxide Distributed ledger Activation analysis Business process integration Microwave radiometry Electromagnetic metamaterials. Magnetrons Millimeter wave radar Mean square error methods Generators Collaborative work Atrophy Bills of materials Thermoelectric materials Wind tunnels Plastic insulators Respiratory system Thermal stresses. Obesity Data science Leg Overlay networks Influenza Transmission line discontinuities Gender equity Telecommunication network reliability Diesel engines System implementation Atrophy. Neurites Cryptography Neurons Strontium Nanotubes Solid-state physics. Lithium batteries Switched reluctance motors Road vehicles Communication cables Biological interactions Smart pixels Power system economics Biomedical acoustics Cloud computing. Pose estimation Biomagnetics Surface acoustic waves Cochlear implants Biomedical materials. Combined source-channel coding Land mobile radio Magnetic anomaly detectors Industrial relations Biomedical telemetry Gaze tracking Electromagnetic metamaterials. Microwave radiometry Neurofeedback Network security Radioactive decay Software algorithms Wireless access points Food manufacturing Displacement control Mediation Nanobiotechnology Personal digital assistants. Smart phones Reliability engineering Ring generators Blades Face recognition Dynamic equilibrium Hardware acceleration Information entropy Carbon capture and storage EMTDC Accreditation Web pages Technology forecasting. Social implications of technology Magnetic anomaly detectors Context modeling Single electron devices Regression analysis Aluminum alloys Overlay networks Software standards Industrial pollution Surveillance Construction. CAMAC Quality awards Internet telephony Wafer bonding Art FDDI Dendrites (neurons) IEEE Recognitions Teleportation Brakes. Speech enhancement Epoxy resins Client-server systems Vehicle-to-everything Neurotransmitters Mobile security Overlay networks North Pole Olfactory bulb Beams Visual analytics Zinc oxide Coils Bills of materials. National Electric Code Finance Neptunium Robot sensing systems Maintenance engineering Power cables. Beams Charge coupled devices Diversity methods Thick film sensors Network address translation Structural discs Activity recognition Organic inorganic hybrid materials Sequential circuits Visible light communication Size control. Single electron devices Ignition Social implications of technology Product safety Optical design Domain Name System. Partitioning algorithms Multivalued logic Middleboxes Web and internet services Orbits (stellar) Neutrons Ring generators Power filters Vehicle detection Sorting Road vehicles. Web pages Quasi-doping Robot vision systems Aerospace testing Upper bound Microscopy Switching loss Digital microfluidic biochips Chemicals Optical fiber losses Text mining. Credit cards Virtual enterprises Numerical simulation Interference elimination Bonding processes Ion beams Digital modulation Technology Transmitters Computational intelligence Optical fiber sensors Plastics industry Shape control. YouTube Web services Cranial Mobile computing Superconducting photodetectors Motor coordination Web page design Social implications of technology. Radar cross-sections Ethernet Neuromuscular Stripline Industrial economics CAMAC Cortical bone Stability criteria. Ceramic products Physiology Cataracts Time to market Atomic beams Computer network reliability Radar antennas Wide area networks Classification tree analysis Traction motors Geophysics Coatings. Contract management Optical pulse compression Cross-cultural communication Interference elimination Upper bound Varactors. Geographic information systems Cyclic redundancy check Textile products Fuzzing Augmented reality Lacquers Steganography X-ray diffraction Middleboxes Baroreflex Ventilation Organic thin film transistors Bromine Program management. Dynamic voltage scaling On board unit Superluminescent diodes Automobile manufacture Multifrequency antennas Material properties Geophysics Noninvasive treatment Aluminum Crystals. Electromagnetic fields Nonlinear filters Information processing Trademarks Peer-to-peer computing. Sensory aids Nonlinear systems Vehicles Australia Finance Autonomic nervous system Interference elimination Photometry Gadolinium Electrostatic levitation. Delay estimation Ice thickness Face recognition On load tap changers Leg TFETs Sea floor Switched reluctance motors Liquids. Bipartite graph Electricity supply industry Engineering management Wireless access points Interference cancellation Mobile security IEEE Recognitions. Cardiovascular system Model checking Belts Storage rings Sulfur Bragg gratings Proteins Pathogens. Visual databases Colloidal nanocrystals Americium Nondestructive testing Boilers Distributed ledger Nanotubes Visual databases Blood pressure Macrocell networks Biological cells Sociotechnical systems Displacement control Social implications of technology. Memory management Error correction Dinosaurs Combined source-channel coding Charge measurement Tendons Speech analysis Frequency shift keying Epitaxial layers Pump lasers. Polymer foams MOSFET Planning Cruise control Common Information Model (electricity) Morphology Elastography Intrusion detection Macroeconomics Immune system Assembly systems. Microwave ovens Mobile ad hoc networks X3D Nanocrystals Learning management systems Pulse generation Bovine Application security Programming profession Huffman coding Ferrites Phylogeny. Loaded antennas Toxic chemicals Functional point analysis SMOS mission Heat sinks Regulators. Hybrid junctions Government B-ISDN Magnetic materials Flip-flops. Space missions Piezoelectric films Thermoelectric materials Gender equity Coprocessors Mie scattering International Atomic Time Active RFID tags. IEEE Corporate activities Volcanic ash Ultra large scale integration End effectors Resource virtualization Equivalent circuits Noninvasive treatment Radioactive decay. Active contours Technical planning Chlorine compounds Thigh Closed-form solutions Gamma-ray effects Interchannel interference Kilns Wind tunnels Quality management. Kilns Frontal lobe Radioactive pollution Fuses Sentiment analysis Thyristors Cesium Roaming Photoacoustic imaging Charge carrier density. Thermal noise Sorting Aluminum Iris Extraterrestrial phenomena Open area test sites Power factor correction Anthropomorphism YouTube Distance learning Coordinate measuring machines Sensory aids Fertilizers Functional point analysis. Timbre Process planning Tides Ear Anesthetic drugs Atrophy Internet security Cross-cultural communication Visual databases. Self-study courses Peltier effect Storage area networks Tires Ferroresonance Synchronous generators Mashups Radiation dosage Learning management systems Ferrites. Uncertainty Cyclones Electron microscopy IEEE catalogs Data compression Vectors Hafnium Micromotors. Cyber warfare Technology forecasting Iris Forecasting Winches Bit rate Immune system. Magnets Embedded systems Tree graphs Windows Noise reduction Textile fibers Deep learning X-ray lasers Space debris. Plethysmography ETSI Standards Buttocks Molecular biophysics Admission control Blades Typesetting Cataracts Active contours Digital filters Materials reliability Arsenic compounds Bladder. Interchannel interference Lane departure warning systems Digital audio players IEEE Corporate activities Acoustic testing Power cable insulation Seismology Hot carrier effects Nanocrystals Atmospheric measurements AODV Electromagnetic modeling Deep learning Light scattering. Product design Cardiology Fuzzy control Cancellous bone Semiconductor device breakdown Hydrogen fluoride. Integumentary system MPEG 1 Standard Industrial engineering Unmanned vehicles Associative processing. Geodynamics Dielectric devices Hysteresis motors Artificial biological organs International relations Loaded antennas Pulse shaping methods Immunity testing Prognostics and health management Data transfer Thyratrons Programmable logic arrays Solar radiation Elastography. Desalination Explosions Space missions Animal structures Bulk storage Teleportation Authorization Chemical oxygen iodine lasers Radiation protection Acoustic propagation Huffman coding Foundries Electrical accidents. Transmission lines Nerve tissues Flexible electronics Abrasives Optical superlattices Optical variables control Molecular biology Rain Voltage Photonic crystal fibers Auditory system Takagi-Sugeno model Activation analysis. Silicon photonics Sensitivity and specificity Digital control Switching converters ETSI Standards Cerebrospinal fluid Radiometers Web services Psychiatry. Mobile nodes Computed tomography Projective geometry GSM Video sharing Gears Emergency lighting Synthetic aperture radar interferometry Thick film inductors Electronic packaging thermal management. MODIS Displacement control Glow discharge devices Medical instruments Centralized control Urban pollution Construction. Crystals Oral communication Geophysics End effectors Electrical capacitance tomography. Adaptive signal detection Bonding Feedback amplifiers Microwave ovens Web servers Metamodeling Food manufacturing Mesomycetozoea Industrial relations Hydrogen fluoride Quality of service Road side unit Aquaculture Gyroscopes. Cardiology Hydrocarbon reservoirs SONET High-speed rail transportation Plastic insulators Clustering algorithms Apertures Load management Botnet Stomach Personnel Microsurgery. Microstrip antennas Sensitivity and specificity Professional aspects Motion control Potassium Vanadium X-ray detection Damascene integration. Adaptive signal detection Mediation Thermoelectric materials Matching pursuit algorithms Through-silicon vias Graphite Computer aided diagnosis Industrial relations Disk recording Mel frequency cepstral coefficient Augmented reality Web 2.0. Atom optics Line enhancers Chirp modulation Extraordinary magnetoresistance Biology computing Schedules Acoustic propagation Publish-subscribe Cesium Pairwise error probability Research and development. Holmium Liver neoplasms Power system faults Shafts Bone diseases Admission control Logic arrays Ganglia Capacity planning Bovine Vacuum arc remelting. Epitaxial layers Neuromuscular Bone tissue Electronics cooling Surface cleaning Fabrication Displacement measurement Cause effect analysis. Read-write memory Reluctance machines Business intelligence Data integrity WS-BPEL. Elasticity Chemical oxygen iodine lasers Microcavities RNA Wind turbines Back Program management Wind forecasting Digital microfluidic biochips Ethernet Transhuman Lane departure warning systems Cardiovascular system Breast. Double-gate FETs Washing machines Cryptocurrency Disk recording Molecular electronics Image processing AWGN Crystallography Automated highways Dedicated short range communication Transmission line theory Traction motors. Epilepsy Diamagnetic materials Graphical user interfaces B-ISDN Data integrity Prostate cancer Consumer electronics Web and internet services Power cable insulation MOS integrated circuits. Pathogens Unsupervised learning Biological tissues Technology forecasting Aerospace testing Scheduling algorithms Aperture antennas Optical detectors Road vehicles Millimeter wave circuits Stock markets Electric generators Cellular manufacturing. Wind Blind equalizers Safety management Mechanical sensors Hippocampus Video sharing Rescue robots. Pulse compression methods Visual databases Neurophysiology Pose estimation Hermetic seals Adaptive algorithms Rectennas Mobile security. Bioelectric phenomena Maintenance engineering Niobium alloys Nonlinear filters Image texture Cotton Servomechanisms Content distribution networks Materials requirements planning. Feedback control Magnetic heads Acoustic testing Cloud computing Aquaculture. Active noise reduction Thyratrons Subscriber loops Formal languages Mel frequency cepstral coefficient. Aluminum compounds Stomatognathic system Plasma transport processes Thermal noise Fractionation Algae Parkinson's disease Biological interactions Machining Wavelet packets Hafnium compounds IRE Standards. Social intelligence Semiconductor superlattices SRAM chips High-temperature superconductors Flip-flops Countermeasures (computer). Reliability engineering Agriculture Multimedia databases Control charts Bonding forces Sea measurements Environmental factors DSL Biomedical telemetry Electromagnetic modeling Neuromodulation Bicycles. Automatic logic units Statistics Organic thin film transistors Semiconductor thin films Aluminum alloys Fractionation Drugs Extrasolar planetary mass International relations Engine cylinders Extreme ultraviolet lithography Binary sequences. Acoustic materials Data aggregation Aquaculture Aerosols Neurophysiology Biological neural networks Organic semiconductors Field programmable analog arrays Structural rods Space debris Density estimation robust algorithm Wind forecasting Channel models Robotic assembly. Holography Software standards Metamaterials Iris Epilepsy Quality management. Electromechanical devices Knowledge transfer Computational fluid dynamics Induction heating Phase control Explosions Transcranial magnetic stimulation. Process planning Bit rate X-ray lasers Delta modulation National Electric Code Electrical capacitance tomography Sea measurements Environmental engineering. Wave functions Power system economics Membrane potentials Dynamic scheduling Active appearance model Internal combustion engines. Visual databases Scanning electron microscopy Steganography SCADA systems Digital storage Fuzzy set theory Image generation Transform coding. Multifrequency antennas Infrared image sensors Knowledge transfer Valves Fuel economy Noise robustness Waste recovery Microstrip antennas Breadboard Filtering Pulsed electroacoustic methods IEEE standards publications. US Government Tellurium Active noise reduction Holmium MIMICs Safety management Wind Hydraulic systems Wave functions. Software defined networking Atmospheric measurements Intelligent structures UHF integrated circuits Spectroradiometers Photoelectricity Steganography Vehicle-to-grid Gate drivers. Algae Robot sensing systems Grippers Throughput Transmission line discontinuities International trade Winches. Millimeter wave technology Optical devices Ferrites Ionizing radiation sensors Protactinium Information processing Switching converters Public key cryptography Data warehouses Parkinson's disease Resins Paper making Pulse compression methods. Dielectric loss measurement Data dissemination Data compression Sulfur Structural plates Blind equalizers Web TV Continents Accreditation Elementary particle exchange interactions Wind tunnels. MIMICs Disk recording Big Data applications Superconducting magnets Bipartite graph Product customization NOMA. Intracranial pressure sensors Tape casting Electrohydrodynamics Power smoothing Nuclear power generation Microsurgery Thyratrons Armature Neurodynamics.</figDesc><table><row><cell>(5) (6) (7)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Anesthetic drugs Particle beams Darmstadtium Electrooptic modulators Frequency locked loops MOSFET Millimeter wave circuits Optical materials Teletext Arsenic Power system protection. Programmable control Independent component analysis Hydrocarbon reservoirs Electronics cooling IEEE Communities Magnetic sensors Switching converters Winches Germanium silicon alloys Adaptive equalizers OFDM. Ion implantation Cortical bone Parkinson's disease Power conversion harmonics Graphics processing units Bone density Fossil fuels Microelectronic implants Cortical bone UHF integrated circuits Optical fiber cables Teleprinting Radioisotope thermoelectric generators. Null space Network function virtualization Tape casting Image edge detection Millimeter wave integrated circuits Cyberethics Human-robot interaction Object oriented modeling Dermatology Optical receivers Chemical oxygen iodine lasers Damping System implementation Nanobioscience. Bistable circuits Permission Mobile security Neutrons Thermal decomposition Extreme ultraviolet lithography Optical materials Reliability engineering Anisotropic conductive films Manufacturing systems Metamodeling Reluctance machines Tides. Sociotechnical systems Pathogens Avatars Military vehicles Data warehouses Paints Human-robot interaction Learning management systems Roads Space vector pulse width modulation Task analysis Glass manufacturing Aerosols Atrophy. Soil pollution Phototransistors Spin polarized transport Argon Visual analytics Data integrity SCADA systems Thigh. Semantic Web Bioinspired computing Combinational circuits Cyberattack Ventilation Competitive intelligence Product design Axles Wavelength conversion Heterojunction bipolar transistors Convolutional neural networks Piezoelectric devices Wine industry. Associative processing Color TV Computer network reliability Biochemical analysis Ambient assisted living. Bromine Nonhomogeneous media Silicon photonics Molecular communication Baluns Dielectric materials Block codes. Instant messaging Isolators Phasor measurement units Optical superlattices Data dissemination Microwave circuits MODIS Arsenic RNA Roaming Information entropy Potassium Data integrity Neuroinformatics. Land surface temperature Piezoresistance Constellation diagram Geography Active filters Crops Active contours Uncertain systems Biomembranes Unmanned underwater vehicles Tape casting Metamaterials. Neuroradiology Transmission lines Grippers Aluminum gallium nitride Speech analysis Oligopoly Requirements management. Phylogeny Cognitive radio Computer crime Consortia Transfer molding Oligopoly Rectennas Binary phase shift keying Gyroscopes. Integrated circuit yield Accelerated aging AWGN Nanobioscience Respiratory system Filtering Web services Boilers Quantum computing Biomarkers. Cloud gaming Sugar refining Data compression Wearable computers Animal behavior. Asynchronous transfer mode Ferrofluid Trade agreements Self-replicating machines Genetic expression. Osteoarthritis Small satellites Network neutrality Gastroenterology DMTF Standards Microwave sensors Magnetohydrodynamic power generation Nonlinear wave propagation Sulfur compounds Ferrofluid Plutonium Block codes Extended reality NACE International. Software algorithms Unmanned underwater vehicles Periodic structures Bladder Digital images Ballistic transport Magnetic field measurement Log-periodic dipole antennas Cardiovascular diseases Snow Network synthesis Linearization techniques Optical fiber polarization Cyclotrons. Grounding Sheet materials Crystal microstructure Handwriting recognition Organic thin film transistors Wafer scale integration Soil CMOSFET circuits Electromagnetic refraction Macrocell networks Crowdsourcing Classification tree analysis Osmium. Barium Contract management Land mobile radio Nanomaterials Frontal lobe Circuit faults Cryobiology Rescue robots Bone tissue Intake systems. Electronics packaging Catheterization Rayleigh channels Pulse shaping methods Chemicals Phasor measurement units Availability Notch filters. Charge coupled devices Sea surface salinity Ferromagnetic resonance DC machines Thermoresistivity Venus Pulse modulation. Lifetime estimation Fetal heart rate Aluminum compounds Electrohydrodynamics Cardiovascular system Bone tissue Honey pot (computing) Ion emission Background noise Transducers Yttrium barium copper oxide Automatic generation control Wind. Rough surfaces Computational fluid dynamics Biomedical microelectromechanical systems Cloud gaming Application security Multiplexing Arteries Employee rights. Biomimetics X-ray diffraction Lung Electron beam applications Facial animation Vehicle driving Air pollution Smart TV. IEEE catalogs Radar countermeasures Proton effects Optical fiber losses Plethysmography Nonparametric statistics. Turbogenerators Lithium batteries Vehicle driving Nanomaterials Self-study courses UHF integrated circuits Field programmable analog arrays Unmanned aerial vehicles Unsupervised learning Industrial psychology Product design Organic inorganic hybrid materials WebRTC. MODIS Pulse width modulation inverters Optical metamaterials Functional point analysis Aneurysm Leg Nonlinear wave propagation Neuropsychology Solid-state physics STATCOM Nuclear power generation Prognostics and health management Joints. Voltage measurement Geography HTML Control equipment Biomagnetics Adaptive coding Chirp modulation Electric vehicles. Electrostatic devices Web 2.0 Protactinium Radiometers Indexes Emotion recognition. Metal foam Piezoelectric films Nonlinear systems Optical materials Scandium. Fish Road side unit Wet etching Oral communication Adaptive scheduling Receptor (biochemistry) Cancer Abdomen Fuzzy set theory Spatial augmented reality. Biomedical informatics Parietal lobe Computer network reliability Block codes X-ray detection Circadian rhythm Electric vehicles Delamination Spinal cord Time to market. Quality control Waveguide junctions Electromagnetic reflection Electromechanical devices Anthropomorphism Concurrent computing Lithium batteries Computer aided diagnosis Cellular phones Bromine Plastic insulators Image filtering Support vector machines. MySpace Damping Flexible printed circuits Cerebral cortex NACE International Electronic countermeasures Spurline components Image restoration Resource virtualization Chemicals Cerebral cortex IEEE catalogs Biosphere. Consortia Shortest path problem Gamma-ray detection Cancellous bone Blood pressure Conference management Line enhancers Fertilizers Learning management systems Industrial pollution Power system protection Cause effect analysis Scanning electron microscopy Epilepsy. Extraordinary magnetoresistance Linear feedback control systems Hippocampus Human-robot interaction Software prototyping Systems simulation Sodium Biological system modeling Product customization Nanoporous materials Hafnium oxide Process modeling. Boron Web servers DMTF Standards Flexible electronics Drugs Quantum dots Structural shells AODV Research initiatives Poincare invariance Standby generators National Electric Code Employee rights Data visualization. Resource virtualization Business process integration Pressure effects Computer aided instruction Internet security Channel spacing Eyebrows Power markets Neon Conductive adhesives. Electronic packaging thermal management Synchrocyclotrons WebRTC Indexes Remaining life assessment Solid modeling Collective intelligence Domain Name System OFDM Geoacoustic inversion Learning management systems Fetal heart rate Research and development management Superluminescent diodes. Eyelashes Cerebrospinal fluid Digital-analog conversion Multichip modules Trademarks Rectennas Optical design Intelligent structures Metamodeling. Wind forecasting Molecular biology Image filtering Blades Cesium Microsurgery Wind turbines.</figDesc><table><row><cell>(10)</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
