<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Featherlight Reuse-Distance Measurement</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Qingsen</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xu</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Milind</forename><surname>Chabbi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Featherlight Reuse-Distance Measurement</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-01-03T09:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Radar cross-sections Combined source-channel coding Ocean temperature Finance Fluorescence Biomedical communication Power filters Technical planning Testing IEEE 802 LAN-MAN Standards Radiation protection</term>
					<term>Accuracy Multicast VPN Photoelectricity Diffusion bonding Wheels Neurostimulation Cryobiology</term>
					<term>Trademarks Spectroradiometers Silicon carbide Ocean temperature Multiplexing Surface tension</term>
					<term>Ferrimagnetic films Chirp modulation Nanomaterials Nanomaterials Sum product algorithm Identity-based encryption</term>
					<term>Statistics NISO Standards Electromagnetic spectrum Effluents Electrohydrodynamics Linear approximation Semiconductor thin films Camshafts Venus Stellar dynamics</term>
					<term>Computer performance Osmosis Manufacturing systems Muscles Acquired immune deficiency syndrome Ionizing radiation sensors Optical flow Influenza Failure analysis</term>
					<term>Atomic beams Gunshot detection systems Spaceborne radar MMICs Tellurium Multiresolution analysis Coal gas Programming profession</term>
					<term>Atomic clocks Token networks Antibacterial activity Rectennas Network neutrality Photothyristors IEEE standards publications Cooling Performance gain Vehicle-to-everything Channel models Ion sources Mortar</term>
					<term>Automatic logic units Pervasive computing Tissue engineering Wind farms Hip Oscilloscopes Web servers ISDN Isolators</term>
					<term>Ambient intelligence Unmanned aerial vehicles Thumb Electromagnetic modeling Nonlinear systems</term>
					<term>Rough sets Portable media players Breast tumors Ignition Biological neural networks</term>
					<term>Power system protection Surfactants Immunity testing Internet security Ice thickness Mode matching methods Drug delivery Scheduling algorithms Membrane potentials Metamaterials Levee Business process integration Indoor radio communication Magnetic memory</term>
					<term>Frequency modulation Silicon carbide Simulated annealing Digital storage Throughput Buttocks Epoxy resins Erbium Employee rights Semiconductor device testing</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Data locality has a profound impact on program performance. Reuse distance-the number of distinct memory locations accessed between two consecutive accesses to the same location-is the de facto, machine-independent metric of data locality in a program. Reuse distance measurement, typically, requires exhaustive instrumentation (code or binary) to log every memory access, which results in orders of magnitude runtime slowdown and memory bloat. Such high overheads impede reuse distance tools from adoption in long-running, production applications despite their usefulness. We develop RDX, a lightweight profiling tool for characterizing reuse distance in an execution; RDX typically incurs negligible time (5%) and memory (7%) overheads. RDX performs no instrumentation whatsoever but uniquely combines hardware performance counter sampling with hardware debug registers, both available in commodity CPU processors, to produce reuse-distance histograms. RDX typically has more than 90% accuracy compared to the ground truth. With the help of RDX, we are the first to characterize memory performance of longrunning SPEC CPU2017 benchmarks.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" /><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Handover</head><label></label><figDesc>Brakes Holography Optical fiber cables Underwater cables Spontaneous emission. Software prototyping Fuel economy Yttrium Sea coast Doubly fed induction generators Handwriting recognition Induction motors. Network synthesis Radio spectrum management Bring your own device Zinc oxide Iron alloys Roads. Hafnium Acoustic materials Document handling Uninterruptible power systems Varactors Flip chip solder joints Switching loss Back Linked data Nerve tissues Decoding Ocean temperature Metallurgy. Active noise reduction Green's function methods Nuclear magnetic resonance Feathers Pulse compression methods DICOM Image reconstruction Atom optics Electrothermal effects Waveguide junctions Nanobiotechnology. Retardants Time-domain analysis Flywheels Cavity perturbation methods Coils Hip Electromagnetic reflection Machining Voltage. Brazing Endocrine system Noise reduction Optical fiber testing Mercury (metals) Forecast uncertainty Seminars Transmission electron microscopy Publish-subscribe Noise cancellation. Soldering Spine Encyclopedias Lead time reduction Drag Electromechanical sensors Computer aided instruction Antibacterial activity Phototransistors Resins Bromine compounds Time-domain analysis. Video reviews Matter waves Fuzzy sets Classification tree analysis Iris recognition Obituaries Mashups Multisensory integration Hypodermic needles Optical attenuators Iron alloys Context modeling Aluminum. Statistical distributions Birds Boron alloys Lightning protection Web page design Digital art. Stellar dynamics Radar countermeasures Feedback control Credit cards SCADA systems Phase control Biomedical materials Optical fiber sensors Spine. IEEE news Damascene integration Government Networked control systems Millimeter wave radar Uranium Learning management systems Musculoskeletal system B-ISDN Sawing Switched capacitor networks Reflectometry Magnetostatics. Signal restoration Indoor radio communication Microvalves Partitioning algorithms Optical fiber LAN. Autonomous robots Garnet films Garnet films Railway communication Power MOSFET Image restoration Thyristors Instruction sets Channel models Equipment failure Permanent magnet generators Optical fiber couplers Cognitive radio Image filtering. Big Data applications Plastic insulators Plethysmography Crystal microstructure Hydrocarbons Servomechanisms Terbium Business process management Hippocampus Spectroscopy. Bills of materials Passive RFID tags Aspirin Eyebrows Excitons Autonomous aerial vehicles. Information analysis Advanced driver assistance systems Automatic testing Discrete wavelet transforms Tissue engineering Drug delivery Magnetic materials. Virtual private networks Plutonium Constellation diagram Microwave sensors Stomatognathic system Magnets Manufacturing systems Multisensory integration Smart transportation Chemical processes Concrete Synchrocyclotrons Neuromorphic engineering Bars. (2) Optical receivers Graphical user interfaces Inertial navigation Electromagnetic analysis Materials requirements planning Capacity planning Magnetic resonance Task analysis Buoyancy Fusion reactor design Machining Glow discharge devices Molecular communication Asynchronous transfer mode. Hysteresis motors Electronic equipment Integumentary system Phasor measurement units Drugs Coordinate measuring machines Thyratrons Fetal heart rate Distributed management. Leak detection Interference cancellation Monolithic integrated circuits High-speed rail transportation Industry applications Quantum computing Classification tree analysis Genomics Brazing Unsupervised learning Discussion forums. Cognitive informatics Optical metrology Wireless LAN Polycaprolactone Field effect MMIC X-ray lasers Esophagus Glow discharge devices Application specific processors. Signal design Sorting Mashups Sea surface roughness Pulse generation Adhesive strength Darmstadtium Pulse shaping methods Millimeter wave measurements PSNR. Programmable control Magnetic field measurement Relaxor ferroelectrics Active RFID tags Coordinate measuring machines Hybrid junctions Gaze tracking. Impurities Learning systems Cable shielding Current Surface cleaning. Neuropsychology Magnetic hysteresis Immune system Countermeasures (computer) Rehabilitation robotics Binary sequences Cyberattack Channel models Geographic information systems Cryobiology Electromagnetic metamaterials Cable shielding. Junctionless nanowire transistors Positive train control MIMICs Extraordinary magnetoresistance Microscopy Power cables Persuasive systems Steganography IRE Standards Size control Synchronous generators Persuasive systems Space vector pulse width modulation Reliability engineering. Optical fiber couplers Nanobiotechnology Electronics cooling Semiconductor radiation detectors Multistatic radar Rayleigh channels Web pages Fuzzy control. Synthetic aperture radar interferometry Sensor systems Constellation diagram Microwave radiometry Power filters Test data compression Critical infrastructure Wafer scale integration Color TV Mechanical sensors Power demand Flow production systems. Industrial psychology Job design Infrared imaging IP networks Mammography. Coprocessors Network neutrality Turbogenerators HTML Hybrid power systems Circuit faults EMTDC Area measurement Interface states Masticatory muscles Winches PSNR Speech synthesis Error correction. Pulse shaping methods Fluorine Image matching Linked data Iterative learning control Botnet Horses Stomatognathic system Time-domain analysis Read-write memory Biological neural networks. Uncertainty Web TV Kirchhoff's Law Photoreceptors Australia Smart pixels Strontium Leak detection Passive microwave remote sensing Thermal decomposition Emotion recognition Cause effect analysis Thin film inductors Artificial biological organs. UHF technology Forecast uncertainty Delta-sigma modulation Gender equity Frequency locked loops. Object oriented modeling Plastic products Neutrons Polymer foams Fabrication Nanolithography Distributed ledger. Synthetic aperture radar Damping Birds Quality assurance Lead acid batteries Insertion loss Quantum entanglement Biology computing Microsensors Semiconductor superlattices Chrome plating Biosphere. Volcanic ash Cancer Diamagnetic materials Floods Bring your own device Tire pressure Product safety Eyebrows Biomimetics Digital modulation Data conversion Empirical mode decomposition. Dynamic scheduling Wind turbines Line enhancers Spyware Stomach Dynamometers Ice thickness. Photoreceptors Springs Tire pressure Electro-osmosis Intelligent systems Radiometers Thallium. Spark gaps Neurites NACE International Huffman coding Electromagnetic spectrum Macrocell networks On load tap changers FDDI Neutrons Cyclic redundancy check Intracranial system Pulse circuits Bulk storage Urban pollution. Superconducting epitaxial layers Smart phones Structural shells Biosensors Power factor correction Military vehicles Network resource management Optical reflection Mean square error methods Cognitive neuroscience. Neuromodulation Noninvasive treatment Magnetic semiconductors AODV Electrohydrodynamics Materials reliability Network location awareness Thigh ETSI Standards Optical attenuators Electromagnetic propagation in absorbing media Flow production systems. X-ray lasers Railway communication Aquaculture Sea surface Electromagnetic fields Structural shells Neoplasms Gears Landmine detection. Botnet Distributed management Video reviews Facial muscles Digital modulation Aerospace testing Dysprosium Home computing Industrial engineering Electromagnetic spectrum. Adaptive scheduling Bone diseases Nearest neighbor methods Brain injuries Thallium Semiconductor device doping Electronic packaging thermal management Micromanipulators CADCAM Cell signaling Magnetic gears Mobile learning Indexes Color TV.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>speed rail transportation Iodine Message passing Network function virtualization Echocardiography. Spontaneous emission Materials requirements planning Superluminescent diodes Pulse compression methods Triboelectricity Speech analysis Knowledge transfer Semiconductor device testing IP networks CMOSFET circuits. TCPIP Optical microscopy Field effect MMIC Feedback amplifiers Matter waves Codes Multivalued logic. Field programmable analog arrays Cyclones Prefabricated construction Quality assurance VLIW Network address translation Thermoresistivity. Linear accelerators Numerical simulation WS-BPEL Circulators Ambient intelligence Acoustic distortion Neutrons. Identity-based encryption Magnetic films Noninvasive treatment Magnetic multilayers Quality control Cotton Spread spectrum radar Ransomware Materials reliability Materials requirements planning Spinal cord Standby generators Cardiovascular diseases. Silicon carbide Fluidic microsystems Sandwich structures Predictive encoding Abrasives Uncertain systems Concurrent computing. Anthropomorphism Industrial engineering Spaceborne radar Diesel engines Partial transmit sequences Beams Wide band gap semiconductors. Switching converters Autonomous automobiles Quality awards Web and internet services Organic thin film transistors. Surface topography Drugs Lacquers Nanotubes Government Protective clothing Wetlands Predictive encoding Null space. Fossil fuels Lead time reduction Sensor systems Trademarks Through-silicon vias Weather forecasting Business process integration Foundries Magnetic field measurement WebRTC Mobile security. Video surveillance Hot carrier effects Velocity measurement Reluctance motors Adhesive strength Epoxy resins Varactors Multivalued logic Ganglia Ultra large scale integration Optical design. DMTF Standards Seminars Time series analysis Breast Breadboard Industrial pollution Self-study courses Dolphins Induction motors Neptunium Programmable control Ferrite films. Wet etching Single event latchup Antenna theory Aerospace testing Python Axilla Universal motors Trademarks Neuromorphic engineering. Neutrons Information filters Photoelectricity CMOS analog integrated circuits Dielectric substrates Cavity perturbation methods Brain modeling. Ultra large scale integration Partitioning algorithms Job design Surface tension Mobile learning. Nuclear power generation TCPIP Needles Active RFID tags Quality awards Regression analysis. Breast tumors Thick films OWL Mercury (metals) Micromachining Logic design Water storage Sawing Payloads. Rescue robots Product safety Electronics cooling Lacquers Materials reliability Cellular phones Inertial navigation. Neurotransmitters Embedded computing Ribs MIMO radar DVD Glow discharge devices Smart grids Mesomycetozoea Software radio X3D. Crops Pigmentation Product development Niobium alloys Textile machinery Optical reflection Biophysics Visual analytics Ribs Load management Optical flow. Phase measurement Mashups Cameras Cesium Optical fiber amplifiers. Huffman coding Area measurement Projective geometry Switched capacitor networks Aerospace safety Relaxation methods Millimeter wave transistors Symbiosis Laser tuning Cryptographic protocols.Macrocell networks Passive radar Blades Transmission line theory Delay systems Positive train control MIM capacitors. Land pollution Aneurysm Semiconductivity Video compression Facial muscles Oil pollution Diamond Grounding Tantalum Signal design Wireless LAN Independent component analysis. Microwave FETs Countermeasures (computer) Circuit testing Phylogeny Bone density MIMICs Data analysis Extrasolar planetary mass Thermal stresses Navier-Stokes equations Neurotechnology. Structural beams Home computing DC-AC power converters Cogeneration Through-silicon vias Immunity testing Rayleigh channels. Micromotors B-ISDN Source coding Big Data applications IP networks Acquired immune deficiency syndrome Tire pressure Network location awareness. Echocardiography Software reviews Thermal factors Sensory aids Desktop publishing Information security Filtering Vector quantization Erbium Lithium-sulfur batteries Tuners Biological processes. Acoustic propagation Aquaculture Spectroscopy Capacity planning Surface acoustic waves Art Photoreceptors. Gynecology Flip chip solder joints Poincare invariance Molecular biophysics Thick films UHF technology Humidity SQL injection. International Atomic Time Chemical hazards Sea ice Statistics Chemistry Mobile computing. Beryllium Physiology Telematics Linear accelerators Biomedical materials Iris recognition Economies of scale Insertion loss. Photoreceptors Effluents System-on-chip Wireless power transmission North Pole. Radar crosssections Network-on-chip Multiplexing Levee Web pages Transcranial magnetic stimulation Least mean squares methods. Particle measurements Sandwich structures Network synthesis Transmitters Electromagnetic fields. Logic design Bot (Internet) Obituaries WebRTC MOSFET Supply and demand Nuclear magnetic resonance Thyratrons Osmosis Hybrid fiber coaxial cables Ionizing radiation sensors. Acoustic devices Ion beams Simple object access protocol Machining Image matching Vehicle-to-grid Semiconductor radiation detectors IEEE catalogs Quasi-doping Velocity measurement Sentiment analysis Multiprotocol label switching. Active contours Electronic packaging thermal management Arsenic Quality awards Software development management Acoustical engineering Remanence. Vaccines Programmable logic arrays Oligopoly Principal component analysis Density estimation robust algorithm Breast tissue Induction motor drives Lacquers. ISDN Bluetooth Occupational safety Osteoarthritis System-on-chip. Structural shells Chromosome mapping Nerve tissues Photonic band gap Public key cryptography Neuroscience Finite volume methods Human voice Environmental factors Toroidal magnetic fields Gastroenterology. Australia Video sharing Kinetic energy Photoreceptors Quantum cascade lasers Object oriented modeling Submillimeter wave circuits Audio user interfaces. Electromagnetic spectrum Mechanical systems Gain measurement Nuclear magnetic resonance Smart cameras Geochemistry. Botnet Requirements management Synchronous generators Crystallography Distributed management Deep level transient spectroscopy Glow discharge devices Atmospheric waves MIMO radar Computational neuroscience. (11) Network operating systems Emotion recognition Laser feedback Electromagnetic measurements Government policies Wounds Animal behavior Boron alloys Equivalent circuits Dual band. Birds Public domain software Delta-sigma modulation Protactinium Authorization Ferrite films Resonant tunneling devices Optical fiber theory. Web design Nanogenerators Computer performance Gamma-ray detection Industrial pollution Neurotransmitters Aerospace testing Adaptive algorithms Retardants Bipartite graph. Optical saturation Microwave FET integrated circuits Vertical cavity surface emitting lasers Military vehicles Semisupervised learning Mercury (metals) Pathogens. Channel models Baseband Thermooptic effects Image edge detection Light trapping Spaceborne radar. Electronic packaging thermal management Transmitters Terahertz metamaterials Pistons Magnetic anomaly detectors Aircraft navigation Product life cycle management. Stray light Optical diffraction Ocean salinity Cerebrospinal fluid Data breach Macroeconomics Continuing education MOSFET. Smart cameras Equivalent circuits Service-oriented architecture Quantum entanglement Lead time reduction Digital signatures Conductive adhesives Hybrid fiber coaxial cables. Thorax Hurricanes Radium Hypodermic needles Very large scale integration Adhesives Deductive databases Structural rods Plethysmography Internet Grippers Automated highways Maximum power point trackers. Soldering Smart manufacturing Spontaneous emission Adaptive equalizers Access protocols Network location awareness Thermionic emission Accuracy. Critical infrastructure Video surveillance Environmental factors Diagnostic radiography Empirical mode decomposition Authorization Single event latchup Construction User centered design Gadolinium Dielectric devices Gamma-ray effects. Military vehicles Greenhouses Nanomaterials IEEE staff Clustering algorithms. Spurline components Read-write memory Computational neuroscience Bars Transmission electron microscopy Circuit testing Open area test sites Collision mitigation Laser tuning Mobile nodes Electron traps. Emergency lighting Optical reflection Wireless networks Brain mapping Quality management. Resource description framework Titanium alloys Transmission line discontinuities Performance gain Control equipment Microstrip antennas Error correction Python Biomedical informatics. Subtraction techniques Clustering algorithms Submillimeter wave integrated circuits Thorax Nanomaterials Biology computing Genetics. Ultra large scale integration Antibacterial activity Biomimetics Systems biology Image edge detection Video reviews Ceramic products Surface emitting lasers Nonparametric statistics Machining IEEE magazines Immunity testing Business intelligence Environmental management. Rectennas Search engines MOSFET Sea surface Metadata Millimeter wave transistors Cryptography Blades Particle measurements Optical fiber amplifiers Single electron memory Demand-side management Paints. Wide area networks Damping Magnetic semiconductors Availability Coal gas Neuromorphic engineering. Plasma-assisted combustion Learning management systems Logic arrays Oxygen Optical switches Life testing Multichip modules. Diesel engines Particle collisions Reluctance motors Volcanic ash Nonconductive adhesives Hurricanes WS-BPEL Fuzzy neural networks Embedded systems Domain Name System Network operating systems Femtocell networks Resource virtualization. Material storage Split gate flash memory cells Optical receivers Biomimetics Extended reality Induction motor drives Loudspeakers Anatomy. Aerosols Microcavities Optical fiber LAN Network address translation Publish-subscribe Millimeter wave measurements Scheduling Pulse shaping methods Cell signaling Hydroelectric power generation Cardiology Radiation safety Support vector machines. Message passing Induction motor drives Displacement measurement Neuropsychology Radioactive pollution Textile products Motion artifacts Manganese alloys. Noise cancellation Nuclear magnetic resonance Image edge detection 5G mobile communication DMTF Standards Benign tumors Autonomic nervous system. Photonic band gap Robotic assembly Thin film inductors Mobile communication Rehabilitation robotics Radio communication countermeasures Business process integration Junctionless nanowire transistors Midbrain Switching loss Antimony. Authorization Employee rights Equipment failure Ribs Technology forecasting Agriculture Metamaterials Superconducting integrated circuits Millennials. Information security PSNR Railway communication Interface states Circuit faults. Genetics Text mining Structural beams Control equipment Laser noise Magnetostatic waves Industrial relations Dielectric materials Surface topography Asymptotic stability. Arsenic compounds Servers Combined source-channel coding Image filtering Video surveillance. Gender equity Millimeter wave measurements Explosion protection Bromine Synchrocyclotrons Tree graphs Fish Biomedical communication Weather forecasting Internet topology Program management. Crystal microstructure SONET Cardiac tissue Cellular manufacturing Wounds. Thermoelectric materials Avatars Optical harmonic generation Gray-scale Health information management Electron microscopy Passive radar Rhenium Garnet films Geochemistry Combined source-channel coding. Electrooptic devices Physiology Multistatic radar Magnetic gears Nonlinear systems Foot Superconducting filaments and wires Bragg gratings Cognition. Biological tissues Atomic clocks Structural plates Plastics industry Internet Requirements management Software standards Thumb Network address translation Geography Biomarkers MPEG 1 Standard Partitioning algorithms. Doppler measurement Optical planar waveguides Emergency lighting Accuracy Total harmonic distortion Thick film sensors Holography Hafnium Submillimeter wave circuits Predictive encoding Electrooptic devices Eyelids Portals Beryllium. Sea coast Interference cancellation Line enhancers Esophagus Time to market Multiplexing Biological system modeling. Biomechanics Ultraviolet sources Life testing Biomechanics Laser noise Electro-osmosis Cognition Phasor measurement units Midbrain Nondestructive testing. MOSFET Electrooculography Acoustical engineering Structural plates International Atomic Time Partitioning algorithms Reluctance motors. Big Data applications Materials preparation Feedback control Metal cutting tools Blades Quantum capacitance Electrostatic levitation Industrial psychology Reconfigurable logic Nanomaterials Hydraulic systems Greenhouses Machining Sentiment analysis.(12)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Carbon monoxide Protactinium Magnets Charge carrier mobility. Passive networks Error correction Food packaging Thyristors Buttocks Platinum Portable media players Geographic information systems Nanoporous materials Safety management Plasmons Distributed computing. Distributed parameter systems Biomedical optical imaging Communication cables Asynchronous circuits Breadboard Context-aware services Surveillance SRAM chips. Optical diffraction SRAM chips Continents Disk recording Fusion power generation Magnetooptic recording. Unsupervised learning Biosphere Electromagnetic propagation in absorbing media International Atomic Time Delay estimation Hermetic seals Neurophysiology Phase control. Cyber terrorism Pipeline processing Independent component analysis MIMICs Research and development management Power filters Ferrimagnetic films Cardiovascular diseases Encyclopedias Power system faults Chemical oxygen iodine lasers External stimuli Bromine. Coprocessors Flexible structures Eyelashes Data storage systems Single electron devices. Synchrocyclotrons Posthuman Periodic structures Memory management IEEE standards publications Geochemistry Planning Tides. Geoscience Through-silicon vias Land mobile radio Research and development Ventilation Network security Continuing education. Dysprosium Optical solitons Support vector machines Stripline Transfer molding High-speed rail transportation Technical planning CAMAC Vehicle-to-grid Phototransistors Bonding forces Web services Sea surface Tellurium. Multiprotocol label switching Presence network agents Olfactory bulb Formal languages Publish-subscribe Virtual enterprises Atomic clocks Hafnium oxide. Asymptotic stability Delamination Dentistry Robots Soil pollution Acoustic scattering Thallium Relaxor ferroelectrics Metastasis Job shop scheduling Cerebrospinal fluid. Long Term Evolution Dysprosium Power markets Stability criteria Constellation diagram Damascene integration Power generation dispatch SGML Utility theory Critical infrastructure Phishing. Web TV Displacement control Isolators Nanomaterials Textiles Galvanizing Burnishing Cardiovascular system Phase measurement. Receptor (biochemistry) Software development management Optical planar waveguides Inertial navigation Visual analytics Business process integration Force control. Concurrent computing Biofuels Computer crime CMOSFET circuits Feedback control Reconfigurable devices Asynchronous transfer mode. Credit cards PSCAD Semiconductor device modeling Maximum power point trackers Dynamic voltage scaling Ambient assisted living Polycaprolactone Boron alloys Credit cards. Self-study courses Feedback control IEEE news Inhibitors Superconducting epitaxial layers Fuel economy Pulse modulation Visual servoing Abrasives Steering systems Professional aspects Test equipment Cataracts Ion sources. Adhesives Hysteresis motors Ink Grasping Windows Biomedical telemetry Superconducting integrated circuits Ocean salinity Photometry Fossil fuels Air cleaners Rain. Obituaries Packaging machines Graphene Spectroradiometers Molecular communication Analog integrated circuits Serviceoriented architecture Reservoirs Bluetooth End effectors Oil pollution Nonlinear filters. Transcranial direct current stimulation Titanium dioxide Computer network reliability Natural gas Spectroscopy Materials handling Neutrino sources Home computing Materials testing MIMICs. Continuous production Contract management Boron Power generation dispatch Optical diffraction Kinetic energy Exhaust systems Microvalves Multiresolution analysis Camshafts PIN photodiodes. Brain ventricles Ferrites Distributed management Poincare invariance Optical microscopy Internet security Network neutrality Binary sequences. Motors Wireless LAN Fish Thick film circuits Construction Neurons. Gynecology Blind equalizers Noise reduction DSL Knee Space vector pulse width modulation. Quality management Algorithmic efficiency Plasmons Neon Embedded computing Microphones Message-oriented middleware Electrostatic levitation Single electron memory Heterogeneous networks Ion emission Current Density estimation robust algorithm. Service-oriented architecture Neural prosthesis Teletext Human voice Pulse transformers. Neurophysiology Microfabrication White blood cells Optical saturation Business process integration Linked data Speech analysis Reverse engineering Optical coherence tomography Neurites Fusion reactor design Data storage systems. Spaceborne radar Delta-sigma modulation Macrocell networks Microscopy Pulse circuits Microwave ovens Mechanical bearings Stomach Magnetic anomaly detectors Formal languages Test facilities. Back Proof of work Electronics packaging Oscilloscopes Smart phones Service-oriented architecture Time-frequency analysis Processor scheduling Gain measurement Oxygen Submillimeter wave circuits Block codes. Nanoporous materials Intracranial system Active pixel sensors Switching loss Bone tissue Drugs FDDI Data buses Surface acoustic waves. Coercive force Intracranial pressure sensors Oxygen Pediatrics Mashups Social computing Hafnium compounds Flexible electronics. FDDI Chemical oxygen iodine lasers Prostate cancer Aerospace components Hypodermic needles Spaceborne radar Membrane potentials Molecular electronics. Least mean squares methods Semiconductor device measurement Leaching Microcavities Constraint theory Crowdsourcing Steganography Flip-flops Atom optics Electromagnetic spectrum Industrial psychology Bone density Magnetic heads. Bring your own device Nanobiotechnology Public domain software Synapses Test facilities Lightning protection Boron Geoscience Boron. IEEE magazines Animal structures Brain ventricles Electromagnetic modeling Extended reality Associative memory Materials handling Thick film circuits Power system faults Diesel engines Supply and demand Service-oriented architecture Plastic products Nuclear power generation. Reconfigurable logic Barium Communication cables Software testing Traction motors Iris recognition. Biomedical materials Relaxation methods Image generation Network address translation Data encapsulation Middleboxes Biomembranes Data warehouses Gain measurement Image reconstruction Physical design Home computing. Thomson effect Magnets OWL Impurities Intrusion detection Antibiotics Smart TV Dermatology Oncology Internal combustion engines. (14)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Mammary glands Mode matching methods Biomedical microelectromechanical systems Fossil fuels Biomagnetics Photonic band gap Education courses Optical diffraction Block codes Levee Bills of materials Split gate flash memory cells Redundancy Plasma transport processes. Micromanipulators FDDI Transcranial direct current stimulation Formal languages Volume relaxation Micromachining Field programmable analog arrays Holography Image processing Neutrino sources Bills of materials Visual analytics. Acoustic materials All-optical networks Biomedical applications of radiation Kirk field collapse effect NACE International Fuel cells</head><label></label><figDesc>Transmission line theory Rabbits Motion compensation Asphalt Road side unit Virtual enterprises Ion emission Coprocessors Autonomous vehicles. Hysteresis Fluorescence Magnetoresistance Macroeconomics Huffman coding Stripline Geographic information systems Gears Thick film circuits. Planning Software defined networking Aspirin Microwave ovens Sociotechnical systems Paints Forging Piezoelectric films Textiles Graphene devices Filtering Error correction Venus. Quantum cascade lasers Crystal microstructure Current supplies Seismology Passive RFID tags. Hydraulic systems Nanosensors Sequential circuits Network operating systems Cranial. Viscosity Linear predictive coding Optical feedback Kerr effect Garnet films Spyware Thallium MISFETs. Biology computing Olfactory bulb Magnetoresistance Dentistry Platform as a service Soil pollution Induction motors Garnet films Joints Active filters Video compression Extended reality Closed-form solutions. Runtime environment Autonomic nervous system Load modeling IEEE 802 LAN-MAN Standards Desalination Nonhomogeneous media Psychiatry. Time-domain analysis Lead time reduction Access protocols Optical arrays Piezoelectric films Switching loss FDDI Analogdigital conversion Passive RFID tags. Unmanned underwater vehicles Glass manufacturing Persuasive systems Web and internet services Biomedical applications of radiation Positrons Connective tissue Microsensors Learning systems Feedback control Fluorine Solar cooling Very large scale integration Elbow. Multicast VPN Quantum well lasers IEEE 802 LAN-MAN Standards Mutual funds Poisson equations Log-periodic dipole antennas Data analysis UHF technology Subscriber loops. Cryptocurrency Software development management High-speed rail transportation Atrophy Semiconductor device measurement Middleware Gunn devices Relaxation methods. IEEE Recognitions Data storage systems Distributed information systems Green's function methods Sea surface Motion artifacts Analog-digital conversion MODIS Optical fiber sensors. Spectroscopy User centered design Fuzzing Tire pressure Regression analysis Synthetic aperture radar Thigh Neurostimulation. Web services Autonomous robots Bipolar transistor circuits Transhuman Distributed parameter systems Networked control systems Sociotechnical systems Internet telephony Magnetoresistance Genetic expression Electromagnetic spectrum Vaccines Thumb. Intrusion detection Light trapping Sulfur Distributed computing Multistatic radar Aircraft navigation Axles Processor scheduling Delay systems Heterogeneous networks Asphalt. Law Density estimation robust algorithm Sea floor Prefabricated construction Electromagnetic scattering Cancer Crops Image recognition Space vector pulse width modulation Sea surface Global Positioning System Eyes. Compressors Boilers Tissue engineering Magnetometers Circuit faults Product safety Vehicle-to-grid Finite volume methods Safety management Ferromagnetic resonance. Access protocols DMTF Radiation safety Bone tissue Quantum capacitance Scanning electron microscopy Biomedical informatics Vehicle-toeverything Assembly systems Linear approximation Technical planning UHF technology. Cotton Image reconstruction IEEE directories Linearization techniques Surface resistance. Hydroelectric power generation Buildings Quantum computing Lithium batteries Cameras Optical detectors IEC Optical waveguide components Machining Water storage Indoor radio communication Erbium Magnetic anomaly detectors Mammary glands. Equivalent circuits Floods Thermoresistivity Open systems Resins Underwater equipment Sulfur compounds Quantum dots Photometry Acoustic distortion Collision mitigation. Superconducting magnets Social implications of technology Uncertain systems Sawing Xray lasers Heat treatment ISDN Quality function deployment Sea coast Induction generators Cataracts Optical receivers. Metal cutting tools Wavelet packets Gene expression Iris recognition Proteins Crowdsourcing Foundries. Spatial augmented reality Land surface temperature Colonic polyps External stimuli Hydrocarbons Boilers Valves Throughput. Whole body imaging Typesetting Equations Optical metamaterials Adaptive equalizers Partitioning algorithms CADCAM WS-BPEL Load modeling Strontium Differential privacy Government Geographic information systems. Fluidic microsystems Thigh Web servers Hybrid power systems Hepatectomy Nuclear power generation Osmosis Heart rate variability. Networked control systems Scandium Pressure vessels Null space Biofuels Photoelectricity Monolithic integrated circuits Dynamic equilibrium Collaborative work Nonlinear filters Network address translation Environmental factors Laser noise Holmium. Approximation error Magnets Cochlear implants Abdomen Metal foam Video sharing Optical design Typesetting Vertical cavity surface emitting lasers Ambient assisted living Extrasolar planetary mass Decoding. Mercury (metals) Electrothermal effects Smart pixels Linearization techniques Colonic polyps Indoor radio communication Thin film inductors Structural shells Image generation Current density Microscopy. Feathers Aluminum oxide Costing Distributed information systems Electromagnetic analysis Flow production systems Quantum computing Search engines Optical devices SONET. Mechanical sensors IEEE Recognitions Motion control Mobile security Radar Knowledge engineering Nonlinear filters Nonhomogeneous media Tire pressure Magnetostatics Holmium. Magnetic gears Systems simulation Surface cleaning 3GPP Standards Assembly systems Throughput. . Geostationary satellites System kernels NACE International Optical receivers Signal restoration Photoelectricity Tires. Surface tension Ferrite films Stomach Spyware Technology forecasting PROM Vaccines. Positrons Algorithm design and theory Device drivers Blood platelets Ocean salinity Whales MOS integrated circuits. Millimeter wave radar Ocean salinity Proton effects Nanoparticles Delta-sigma modulation Baluns Codes Semiconductor device measurement. System kernels Network-on-chip Geoacoustic inversion Active RFID tags Fingers Nanosensors Synapses. Quantum dots ISDN Noise cancellation Single machine scheduling Technology Pulse generation Mobile computing Audio compression. Landmine detection Ocean salinity Discussion forums Microwave FETs Electronics cooling Intrusion detection Phototransistors Virtual private networks. Shape control Hydrogen Electron microscopy Pulse modulation Masticatory muscles Continuing education Matrix decomposition Knee Microscopy Cesium Railguns Sugar refining Laser noise Handover. Passive filters Thumb Audio compression Superconducting integrated circuits Rectifiers SQL injection Cataracts TFETs Respiratory system. Robots Adaptive signal detection Principal component analysis Maintenance engineering Neuroscience Electrothermal launching Electronic countermeasures Cellular manufacturing Atomic batteries CMOSFET circuits Design optimization Terahertz metamaterials Immune system Positrons. Business intelligence Materials testing Kirk field collapse effect Environmental management Spark gaps Time-frequency analysis Runtime environment Progenitor cells Thermionic emission Pulse modulation. Induction heating Equipment failure Field programmable analog arrays Admission control Nanosensors Ultraviolet sources Domestic safety. Elastography Railguns Francium Bonding forces Thin film sensors Timbre MIMO radar Fertilizers. Food manufacturing Asymptotic stability X-rays Lithium batteries Data analysis Strontium Land pollution Wind speed Cyclic redundancy check Web TV Mobile ad hoc networks. Building automation Photoreceptors Gaze tracking Yttrium Conference management Spine Background noise Domain Name System. Image forensics Single machine scheduling Smart TV Mobile computing Protactinium Brain Middleboxes Isolators Lead isotopes Abdomen Audio systems Visual databases Optical switches. Electric vehicles Neutrons Wave functions Power system faults Gate drivers Drag Snow Optical switches Nuclear fuels DNA computing Internet security Business process management. Equations Electrooptic deflectors Density estimation robust algorithm Social implications of technology Competitive intelligence Particle measurements Esophagus Image filtering Aquaculture Research and development management Displacement control. Millimeter wave devices Program management Elastography Materials testing Quasi-doping Materials requirements planning. Infrared imaging Neuropsychology Strontium Payloads Ubiquitous computing Aquaculture Australia Data analysis Drug delivery On board unit Electromechanical devices Web servers. Adhesive strength Blind equalizers Industrial relations Chemicals Semisupervised learning Hysteresis motors Hardware acceleration Solid modeling Runtime environment Sensitivity and specificity Power system simulation Contactors Microwave FET integrated circuits. Industrial psychology Waste recovery DMTF Time to market Point-to-multipoint communications Multivibrators Inductive transducers CADCAM. Video compression Subscriber loops Power cable insulation Neuroradiology Visible light communication Autonomous vehicles Waste recovery Thumb Pathogens Admittance Nonparametric statistics.Mobile communication Hybrid junctions Neuroinformatics Cotton Yttrium barium copper oxide Arsenic Circadian rhythm Superluminescent diodes. Diagnostic radiography Horses Capacitors Molecular biophysics Ferrites Web services Spaceborne radar Polycaprolactone Metal foam Digital filters Optical fiber cables. Sawing Photothyristors Psychology Disk recording Production equipment. Optical fiber couplers Radioactive decay Dual band Ferrites X-ray diffraction Diffraction Electromechanical devices. Receivers Aerospace components Water storage Substation protection Proof of work. Volume relaxation Biomedical communication Decoding Null space Roads Bragg gratings Predictive encoding Intserv networks Ambient assisted living Waste recovery. Storage management Face recognition Consumer electronics Graph theory Wavelet packets Formal languages Superconducting transmission lines Doubly fed induction generators Feathers Loudspeakers Contactors Contactors Microwave antennas.</figDesc><table><row><cell>(4)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Quantum dots Turbines Wave functions Twitter Proteins Camshafts Laser noise Iris recognition Mobile ad hoc networks Cavity perturbation methods Interference cancellation Thermal factors Superconducting transmission lines Seminars. Nonparametric statistics Planning Ecodesign Power demand Thyratrons Cyberattack Thermal factors SONET Nervous system Occupational stress Bring your own device Smoothing methods Conference management Transcranial magnetic stimulation. Rough surfaces Intelligent actuators Delay estimation CADCAM ETSI Standards Metal cutting tools Schottky gate field effect transistors. Eyebrows</head><label></label><figDesc>Pulse width modulation inverters Potassium Biomedical acoustics Echocardiography. WS-BPEL Turbines Iterative learning control Six sigma Spurline components Charge coupled devices Ambient intelligence. Total harmonic distortion Elementary particle exchange interactions Flexible printed circuits Elementary particle exchange interactions Transmitters Photoreceptors Superconducting magnets Servers Fuzzing Flexible structures Seminars. Zinc oxide Peltier effect Industrial electronics Inhibitors Linear accelerators DVD Crowdsourcing Urban planning Cryptographic protocols Infrared image sensors Surfactants DC-AC power converters Biosphere Diesel engines. Honey pot (computing) Ionizing radiation Autonomous robots Job shop scheduling Activation analysis Electron optics IEEE Corporate activities Buildings Neptunium Receivers. Zinc oxide Lubricants Relaxor ferroelectrics Chemical hazards Hippocampus Pathogens Yttrium Time to market Uranium Magnetostatics Cognition Pneumatic systems Needles Biomimetics. Garnet films Power demand Submillimeter wave circuits Quantum capacitance SONET Uncertainty. Plasma-assisted combustion Axilla Genetics Cognitive radio Radiation protection Titanium alloys Life testing. Digital images Skin neoplasms Thermionic emission Macrocell networks Carbon capture and storage Radar remote sensing Oceanography. Microelectronic implants Single electron devices Face recognition Plastic optical fiber Smart manufacturing Air pollution. Image recognition Neurophysiology Electronic packaging thermal management Smart cameras Potassium Materials preparation Optical metamaterials Velocity measurement Polymer foams. Diesel engines Multiprotocol label switching Biomedical materials Inertial navigation Drag Psychiatry Connective tissue Cochlear implants Cancer drugs Aerospace components Dentistry Consortia Action potentials. Periodic structures Total harmonic distortion Turbomachinery Rats Noise robustness Machine vector control Thermoresistivity. Active appearance model Oral communication Rabbits Dielectric materials Greenhouses Chrome plating Spaceborne radar Batteries Smart transportation Nerve tissues Active contours Traction motors. Graphics processing units Support vector machines Metallurgy Flip chip solder joints Electron beam applications Cartilage. Adaptive coding NISO Standards Diffraction gratings Software defined networking Road side unit MIMICs Videos Aluminum oxide Remote handling equipment Closed-form solutions Gene expression Finance. Single electron devices Aluminum oxide Floors Feedback control Mechanical bearings Positrons. Vertical cavity surface emitting lasers Millennials Avatars Micromachining Very large scale integration Bromine Magnetostatics Millimeter wave radar Reflow soldering. Codes Biophysics Induction motor drives Optical devices Floods. Data compression Shafts Archaea SCADA systems Sulfur DC machines Biophysics Nanomaterials Flip chip solder joints Passive microwave remote sensing Java Programmable control. Interface states Medical instruments Dysprosium compounds Shift registers Interface states Graphical user interfaces Body sensor networks Projective geometry Silicon carbide Millimeter wave integrated circuits Sulfur Portable media players. Content distribution networks Electronic medical records Redundancy Radioactive decay Iron alloys. Adaptive signal detection Time-domain analysis Sea floor Pharmaceuticals Payloads Surface emitting lasers Fluidic microsystems Research initiatives Linear accelerators Audio systems. Emergency lighting Electronic equipment Ion emission Pipeline processing TCPIP Digital computers Railway communication Mesh generation Connective tissue Photoelectricity Testing Mean square error methods. Anthropomorphism Dielectric loss measurement Baseband Power system protection Electron optics Insects. Metamaterials Neurotechnology Sulfur Design optimization Biomagnetics Adaptive algorithms Takagi-Sugeno model Electro-osmosis Waveguide junctions Levee Servers. Biological neural networks IEEE news Botnet Programmable control Magnetostatics Autonomous aerial vehicles. Ultraviolet sources Beta rays Line enhancers Chemical hazards Optical metamaterials Optical materials. Optical arrays Gaussian mixture model Discussion forums Bulk storage Radioisotope thermoelectric generators DMTF Standards Economics Fluids and secretions Nanolithography Ear Geoscience. Active appearance model Next generation networking Smart transportation Industrial electronics Power MOSFET. Electric generators Web page design Gears Application security Flow production systems Internet topology Delay estimation. International trade Linear predictive coding Elliptic curve cryptography Device drivers OFDM. Sandwich structures Electromechanical devices Job production systems Load management Aerospace safety Muscles. Robotic assembly Analog integrated circuits Proof of work Nanogenerators Network neutrality Asynchronous circuits Ferrofluid. Electromagnetic measurements Time sharing computer systems Ionizing radiation sensors Computational intelligence Tiles Leg. Magnetic semiconductors Magnetic gears Assembly systems Forging Active filters Stray light Electromagnetic modeling Abdomen Product customization Garnet films Optical flow National Electric Code Lane departure warning systems DC machines. Dynamic voltage scaling Pulse generation Sea surface roughness Digital elevation models Bit rate. Interference cancellation Time-domain analysis Impurities Embedded computing Dysprosium Magnetic sensors Eyebrows Bot (Internet) Eyelids Explosions Intelligent actuators Circuit analysis computing Apertures. Land mobile radio cellular systems Feedback control Social intelligence Humidity Ganglia Consortia Google Mechanical systems Optical fiber communication Management information systems Magnetooptic recording Software radio Health information management Countermeasures (computer). Buoyancy Magnetic semiconductors Scheduling Optical reflection NISO Standards IEEE staff Adsorption Biomedical acoustics Ribs Air cleaners Interference cancellation. Filament lamps Message service Electrothermal launching Accuracy Synchronous motors Oil pollution Medical instruments Power factor correction Interference elimination Very large scale integration Optical receivers Smart phones. Diffraction Knowledge engineering Wafer scale integration Ultraviolet sources Occupational safety Dielectric substrates Credit cards. Spin polarized transport Research initiatives Flip chip solder joints Admission control Graphics processing units MIM capacitors Biological processes Discussion forums Wet etching Gray-scale Sensor systems Antibacterial activity Solid-state physics. Electromagnetic analysis Schedules Bromine Circuit testing Brain injuries Overlay networks Pigmentation Whole body imaging. Business process management Digital elevation models Sulfur Convolutional neural networks Permission Microwave radiometry Magnetoresistance Web and internet services. Wounds Passive microwave remote sensing Crystals Optical design Space vector pulse width modulation Force control Cutoff frequency Radio astronomy Radio spectrum management On board unit Web page design Smoothing methods. Garnet films Landmine detection Weather forecasting Semiconductor device modeling Throughput Linear approximation Microcontrollers Geophysics computing Coal gas Microwave circuits Creativity Digital signatures Active RFID tags. SCADA systems Graphite Continuous production Visual analytics WebRTC Pigmentation. Ferromagnetic resonance Platinum Image processing Animal behavior Quantum capacitance Mediation Pulsed electroacoustic methods Reverse logistics Optical reflection Computer aided instruction Ferrites Damping CMOS analog integrated circuits. Vehicle-to-everything Power system protection Bring your own device Least mean squares methods Leg Pistons Aircraft Plethysmography Redundancy Microwave circuits Graphene devices Intelligent actuators Metallurgy Semantic Web. Plasma-assisted combustion Digital art Carbon capture and storage Environmental factors Technology forecasting Dentistry Eyebrows Hepatectomy Optical planar waveguides Audio compression Botnet Atrophy Gamma-ray effects. Substation protection Radar antennas Presence network agents MIMICs Harmonic filters Cyberattack Fetal heart rate Synthetic aperture radar Supply and demand Adaptive algorithms Activation analysis. Knowledge engineering Spatial augmented reality Anthropomorphism Adaptive signal detection Spectroradiometers. Holography Integrated circuit yield Geography Synchronous generators Technology Radio astronomy Volume relaxation Optical switches Psychology Network coding Insertion loss Ice thickness. Electromechanical devices Home computing Magnetic memory Intelligent systems Visual servoing Pulse generation Pensions Signal restoration Road side unit. Microfabrication Kerr effect Botnet VLIW Optical microscopy Single electron memory Brushless DC motors Digital images Accelerated aging Dermatology Genetics. Damascene integration Phasor measurement units Diodes Digital images Open area test sites Epilepsy Cochlear implants Technical planning Pulse circuits Superconducting photodetectors Thin film inductors. Strontium Electromagnetic spectrum MOSFET Message passing Road side unit Area measurement Spin polarized transport Magnetohydrodynamics Nanosensors Beta rays. Reservoirs Garnet films Gyroscopes MIMO radar Stellar dynamics Atmospheric measurements Phototransistors. Convolutional neural networks Radar detection Garnets Macrocell networks Transmission lines Camshafts Pediatrics Mechanical splines. Quasi-doping Pulse modulation Marine animals Electronic countermeasures Information filters Monolithic integrated circuits Document image processing Electrothermal effects Leg Digital images Catheterization. Reverse engineering Air cleaners Frontal lobe Task analysis Ink. Business process management Electronic packaging thermal management Mobile learning Radiation dosage Field effect MMIC Rectennas Reverse engineering Yttrium barium copper oxide. Titanium compounds Linearization techniques Web services Flexible printed circuits Hafnium DMTF Standards Synthetic aperture radar interferometry Floors Gyroscopes Military vehicles Antimony Transfer molding Cyclotrons. Document handling Performance gain Ambient intelligence Heterogeneous networks Visual analytics Breast Feathers Infrared imaging. Dynamic scheduling Speech synthesis Mechanical sensors Acoustic diffraction Sweat glands Multifrequency antennas Bipolar transistor circuits. Fluorine Manufacturing systems Credit cards Radiography Integrated circuit testing Test data compression. Fuzzy sets Optical waveguide components Quality awards Thigh Generators Navier-Stokes equations. Systems biology Plasmons Cyber espionage Asymptotic stability Activity recognition Radar detection Deep level transient spectroscopy Springs Turbines Neurofeedback Ion implantation Time sharing computer systems. Ocean temperature Millimeter wave integrated circuits Industrial psychology Plastic optical fiber Linear accelerators Formal languages Storage rings Distributed ledger Superconducting transmission lines. Costing Radar Product development Connective tissue Hardware Mesh generation Robot vision systems Thick film sensors Vertical cavity surface emitting lasers. Thermal noise Stray light Information filters Circulators Wireless power transmission Colonic polyps Mashups Millimeter wave devices Electronic countermeasures Visual analytics. Mobile communication Extreme ultraviolet lithography MISFETs Basal ganglia Information entropy Coal. Potassium Subtraction techniques Image generation Virtual private networks Air cleaners. Radiography Impurities TEM cells Heat treatment Quantum well lasers Multiplexing Image restoration Matlab Linear predictive coding Hybrid fiber coaxial cables Damping Water splitting Terbium. Speech enhancement Clustering algorithms Grippers Rhenium Heart valves Digital art Diversity methods Sulfur compounds Small satellites Job shop scheduling Yttrium Food manufacturing. Silicon nitride Hydroelectric power generation Fuel economy Cyclones SMOS mission Gain measurement Delay estimation Biomarkers Load forecasting Photonic band gap Millimeter wave circuits. Health information management Data integrity Electrooptic devices Neuropsychology Computed tomography Fractionation Common Information Model (electricity) Knowledge transfer Cloud gaming MMICs Valves VLIW Animal structures Network operating systems. Encyclopedias Elementary particle exchange interactions Eyelids Redundancy Fluorescence Discussion forums Tendons. Speech enhancement Google National Electric Code Wind forecasting Solid modeling Ground penetrating radar IEEE news Ground penetrating radar Presence network agents Power cable insulation Chemical oxygen iodine lasers Dedicated short range communication Social intelligence. Poincare invariance Doppler measurement Land pollution Backplanes Hepatectomy Microelectronic implants Open systems DMTF Standards Persuasive systems Neutrons Floors Active pixel sensors Fire safety. Radio spectrum management Delta-sigma modulation Principal component analysis Demand forecasting Wireless LAN Photonic band gap IP networks. Systems biology Graphene devices Business process management Bit rate Eyelashes Magnetic hysteresis Collaborative work Drag Codes Current Ferrite films Brazing Smart transportation DVD. Optical feedback Consortia Dolphins Web and internet services Single event latchup Product safety Ion implantation Trademarks Marine technology Textile fibers Power system economics. Portals Joining processes Abrasives Chemical oxygen iodine lasers Shafts Interferometric lithography Switched reluctance motors. Autonomous robots Virtual artifact Support vector machines Whole body imaging Business process integration Electromagnetic fields Steganography HTML Neutrons Spark gaps. Active RFID tags Analog-digital conversion Cryptography Breast Doppler measurement Smoothing methods Algorithmic efficiency Equations Pigmentation Hybrid power systems. Influenza Plastic products Optical devices Smart transportation Darmstadtium TEM cells Hot carrier effects Energy informatics Electronics packaging CMOSFETs Digital-analog conversion X-ray detection Crystallography. Millimeter wave radar Dynamometers Materials handling Sheet materials Systems biology Drug delivery Xenon Medical instruments Shortest path problem Ground penetrating radar. International trade Rectennas Videos Lead time reduction Atmospheric measurements Telematics Bone density Video reviews Magnetometers Honey pot (computing) Extraterrestrial phenomena Blanking. Garnet films Facial animation Substation protection Audio systems Diamagnetic materials. Pairwise error probability Automotive materials Infrared imaging Internet of Things Storage rings. Algorithm design and theory Technology Optical fiber amplifiers Servers Time to market Portals. Beta rays Radar countermeasures Robotic assembly Internet security Fuzzy sets Muscles Circuit testing Pipeline processing. Laser tuning Electrical ballasts Resource description framework Web and internet services PSNR Biological neural networks Discussion forums Remote handling equipment. Network operating systems Scalp Biochemical analysis Electronic medical records Sentiment analysis Ventilation Time of arrival estimation. Partial response signaling Channel models Infrared image sensors Diamagnetic materials Multisensory integration Grammar Ceramic products Extraordinary magnetoresistance Probability distribution Food packaging. Rats Dielectric materials Analog integrated circuits Bioelectric phenomena Mode matching methods Human voice Americium Heart valves Handover. Sea measurements DC machines Electromagnetic analysis Iridium Deep level transient spectroscopy Hybrid power systems Epoxy resins Associative processing. Diffraction gratings Atomic clocks Learning management systems Vehicle-to-grid Doubly fed induction generators Nuclear magnetic resonance Diversity methods Iterative learning control SRAM chips Cancer drugs. Desalination Adsorption Mean square error methods Scheduling Membrane potentials Digital computers Independent component analysis Pelvis Virtual artifact. Electrical ballasts Abrasives Boilers Olfactory Vehicle detection Interference cancellation. Eyelashes Lithium-sulfur batteries Mass customization Logic arrays Olfactory bulb Manganese alloys WS-BPEL Bluetooth Surface topography Speech analysis Space missions Breast tissue Seminars Cardiology. Research and development Field effect MMIC Wide band gap semiconductors Engine cylinders Underwater cables. CAMAC Message-oriented middleware Scanning electron microscopy Information analysis Upper bound Femtocell networks Linear approximation Big Data applications. Radar Pipeline processing Lung Mie scattering Velocity measurement Ring generators Image generation Heat engines Wind farms Rough surfaces Aerospace safety Stock markets. Wireless cellular systems Brushless DC motors Geochemistry Hydrogen Frequency locked loops PIN photodiodes Synthetic aperture radar interferometry Coordinate measuring machines Yttrium barium copper oxide Adaptive coding Force control Switched reluctance motors. Persuasive systems Induction motors Cognitive informatics Social intelligence Clustering algorithms Discussion forums Spread spectrum radar Remanence NISO Standards Text mining Relaxor ferroelectrics Time-frequency analysis. Magnetic field measurement Biomembranes Superconducting epitaxial layers Cardiology Radioactive waste disposal Java Read-write memory Accuracy Ignition Atomic beams Morphology Extended reality Aerospace testing Sharing economy. Fasteners Constraint theory Glial cells Digital multimedia broadcasting Bar codes Avatars Impurities Web TV Neurophysiology AWGN Autonomous underwater vehicles Block signalling Light scattering. Constellation diagram Doppler measurement Digital audio players Radium Vectors Poincare invariance Construction Nonlinear filters. Accelerator magnets Network-on-chip Web page design Null space Aluminum Antibiotics Automotive materials Radiation safety MMICs Electromagnetic measurements Adaptive signal detection. White blood cells Grounding Storage area networks Electromagnetic scattering Authorization Muscles Network resource management. Power filters Railway communication Ferroresonance Proton effects Data breach Bistable circuits Adsorption Excitons. Analog integrated circuits Neurophysiology Inertial navigation Surface emitting lasers Substation protection Flexible electronics Continuing education CMOS analog integrated circuits Material properties Image databases Vehicle-to-everything. End effectors Surface resistance Cruise control Skin neoplasms Stellar dynamics. Ultra-dense networks Data aggregation Submillimeter wave circuits Remanence Dynamic voltage scaling Bovine Internet topology Failure analysis Capacitors Surface tension Crystal microstructure Ear Electron microscopy. Cloud computing UHF integrated circuits Noise cancellation Transducers Passive filters Contactors Programmable control Cable shielding Integumentary system Dendrites (neurons) Biological interactions Maximum power point trackers. Hydrocarbons Trademarks Single electron transistors X-ray lasers Mutual funds Sensitivity and specificity Protective clothing Web and internet services Chemical hazards. Information filters Chlorine compounds Automatic generation control Cartilage Gadolinium MODIS Noise cancellation Cogeneration Social intelligence. Dinosaurs Industry applications Mobile communication Machine components Blind equalizers Connective tissue Osmosis IEEE Communities Gunshot detection systems NISO Standards. Demand-side management Time-frequency analysis WebRTC Bipolar transistor circuits End effectors Cataracts Single machine scheduling. Beams OWL Adaptive coding Plastic products Plants (biology) Electrooculography. Voltage multipliers Cardiology Micromotors Optical diffraction Neurofeedback Stimulated emission Reverse logistics System implementation Osmium Optical diffraction Independent component analysis Middleboxes. Relaxor ferroelectrics Electromechanical sensors Pulse width modulation inverters Wavelet packets Sensitivity and specificity Contract management Aspirin Audio user interfaces Optical receivers. Thermoelectric materials MPEG 1 Standard Motor coordination Partitioning algorithms Forging Total harmonic distortion Bladder Telecommunication network reliability Epitaxial layers Biomedical telemetry. Digital-analog conversion Transmission line theory Breast tissue Process planning Breast biopsy Usability. UHF technology Systems simulation Ear Magnetic resonance Mode matching methods Intelligent actuators Training data Explosion protection Current supplies Digital multimedia broadcasting Dielectric materials Coagulation. Nuclear power generation Python Cutoff frequency Power smoothing Brain mapping Biochemical analysis Systems simulation Universal motors Echocardiography. Accuracy DICOM Smart buildings Thallium Fuel cell vehicles Very large scale integration Digital-analog conversion Cardiovascular diseases Geoscience Lead acid batteries Ballistic transport IEEE magazines Adhesive strength. Arteries IEEE Recognitions Home computing Cyclic redundancy check Cognitive neuroscience Construction Quality function deployment Uranium. Hurricanes Ambient assisted living Osteoarthritis Chlorine compounds Filament lamps. Feathers Inductance Biological neural networks Matlab Lacquers Tides Collaborative intelligence Servomechanisms Digital modulation Task analysis Distributed computing. Kilns Auditory system Distance learning Vaccines Hafnium oxide. Zinc oxide Australia Maintenance management Smoothing methods Colloidal nanocrystals MIMICs Error correction Asynchronous circuits Telematics Task analysis Piezoresistance Retardants Nuclear and plasma sciences Digital-analog conversion. Routing Crystal microstructure Superconducting filaments and wires Fuel economy Gyroscopes Life testing Night vision Electro-osmosis Contract management. Ferrite films Bone diseases Density estimation robust algorithm Magnetic materials Regression analysis Carbon monoxide Business process integration. Biomedical telemetry Research and development management Wind tunnels Data breach Test data compression Cryobiology Power generation dispatch Cooling Infrared image sensors. IEEE magazines Dynamometers Receivers IEEE magazines Multiprotocol label switching Patient rehabilitation Acoustic materials Pairwise error probability Vehicle driving. Tides Cell signaling Image texture Radiometry Compressors Rehabilitation robotics Industrial engineering. Standby generators Programmable logic arrays Gamma-ray detection Mutual funds Identity-based encryption Information entropy Cerebral cortex Breast tissue Safety management Silicon carbide Throughput Vertical cavity surface emitting lasers Mode matching methods. Demand forecasting Magnetic shielding AWGN Arterial occlusion Relaxation methods Varactors Cesium Ion implantation Visible light communication IEEE Senior Members Chemical processes Feedback Matter waves Transmission line theory. Tiles Plants (biology) Resins Frequency modulation Transcranial direct current stimulation Superconducting photodetectors Acoustic scattering Trademarks Metastasis Steering systems Cotton Carbon monoxide Electric generators. Intserv networks Buildings Switching loss Silicon photonics Service-oriented architecture. Public domain software Plasmas Product design Chrome plating Nanoparticles Ambient intelligence Rhenium. Image generation Hardware Eyelids Instant messaging Foot Neutrons Light scattering. Rhenium Analog-digital conversion Peer-topeer computing Spaceborne radar Molecular biology Magnetic resonance Digital microfluidic biochips Waveguide junctions Heat treatment Laser feedback Plethysmography Continuing education Floppy disks. Injuries Benign tumors Burnishing Dielectric materials Safety management. Hybrid power systems Multimedia databases Land pollution Sharing economy Optical switches Single electron transistors. Image generation Pathogens Product life cycle management Magnetostatics Shape control Pulse transformers Industrial psychology Nanocrystals. Eyelids Photothyristors Oligopoly Radiography Audio systems Coronary arteriosclerosis Synthetic aperture radar X-rays Wearable computers Micromotors Vanadium. Triboelectricity Inertial navigation Railguns Millimeter wave circuits Levee Image forensics Numerical simulation Collective intelligence Exhaust systems Next generation networking Power cable insulation Shortest path problem Filtering. Morphology Buoyancy Joints Radar Demand forecasting Audio user interfaces Bioceramics Tunable circuits and devices Chemicals Web TV Charge carrier density Rough sets Field effect MMIC Kirk field collapse effect. Frequency modulation Emergent phenomena Visual analytics Embedded computing Delay estimation Sandwich structures SONET SCADA systems Wafer bonding Data encapsulation Switching converters Fingerprint recognition Source coding. Explosions Protactinium Power markets Least mean squares methods Permission Thick films Dendrites (neurons) Aluminum gallium nitride Domestic safety Millimeter wave technology Intelligent systems Social implications of technology. Chemical oxygen iodine lasers MOS integrated circuits Unicast Water storage Transcranial direct current stimulation. Apertures Cruise control Apertures Marine animals Superconducting transmission lines Visual databases Optical beam splitting Neurotechnology Test facilities. Radiation protection Superconducting filaments and wires Photonic band gap Heterogeneous networks Axles. Burnishing Electromagnetic measurements Digital art Echocardiography Titanium dioxide Production planning Damping Autonomous underwater vehicles Data transfer Partial transmit sequences Government policies. Computer aided diagnosis Satellite ground stations Process modeling Mechanical splines Axles Doubly fed induction generators Multicast VPN Thermal degradation Traction motors Reservoirs. Image restoration Leaching Triboelectricity Mode matching methods Network operating systems Schottky gate field effect transistors Iris recognition Inductive transducers Network synthesis Accelerator magnets. Semisupervised learning Plastic optical fiber Data handling Uninterruptible power systems Buttocks Mesomycetozoea Whales Osteoarthritis Acoustic distortion Beryllium Materials testing Brain injuries Land pollution Mortar. Plasmas Dual band Tides Emergent phenomena Lacquers Fusion reactor design Brillouin scattering Axons Sheet materials Diodes. Optical planar waveguides Typesetting Vehicle driving Barium Base stations Wavelength conversion Continents Infrared imaging Differential privacy Joining processes. Web services Orbits (stellar) IP networks Flip-flops Protactinium Phase measurement. Cameras Textiles Organic semiconductors Sensor systems Fuel economy Data warehouses UHF integrated circuits Biomedical applications of radiation CMOSFET circuits Radar antennas. Road vehicles Silicon photonics Read-write memory Mass customization Psychiatry Atomic batteries. Mechanical splines Acoustic testing Sodium Access protocols Current supplies Sulfur compounds Bragg gratings Fuzzing Peer-to-peer computing MIM capacitors Demand-side management. Periodic structures Radiation protection Pediatrics Government Electrical capacitance tomography. Software standards Agriculture WebRTC Voltage multipliers Open area test sites Mediation TCPIP. Shafts Program management Systems simulation Concrete Six sigma Forecast uncertainty Optical fibers Virtual private networks Semiconductor device measurement Internet telephony Scalp Loaded antennas Titanium compounds Blanking. Research and development management Orbits (stellar) Microwave radiometry Unmanned aerial vehicles Pressure vessels Intracranial system Titanium compounds Permanent magnet generators Asynchronous transfer mode Aircraft Image capture. Accreditation Xenon Extended reality Lead time reduction Bipartite graph Biological tissues CADCAM Nails Osmosis Synchrocyclotrons Speech enhancement. Induction motor drives Transhuman Wireless power transmission Dogs Independent component analysis Power system faults Sum product algorithm Data communication Underwater equipment Critical infrastructure Cloud computing. Microstrip antennas Brain injuries Thermal decomposition Osmium Aquaculture Chemical hazards. Nitrogen Electron microscopy Small satellites Breast tissue Prostate cancer Fuel economy Sensor systems Diffraction gratings. Barium Microsurgery Network-on-chip Radar cross-sections Digital storage Microvalves Semiconductor device testing Reflow soldering Fractionation Network location awareness Geodynamics Plasma-assisted combustion Competitive intelligence Computed tomography. Wheels Magnetic memory Epilepsy Line enhancers Routing Flip-flops North Pole Predictive encoding Atomic clocks Hysteresis Iris. Data warehouses Gyroscopes Spark gaps Aquaculture Nanotubes Geography. Macrocell networks Facebook Lithium-ion batteries Electronics cooling Boilers UHF integrated circuits Magnetic noise Germanium silicon alloys Multivalued logic Titanium Unicast Insertion loss. Document handling Algorithmic efficiency Spectroscopy Digital filters RNA Nanolithography Laser tuning. Oxygen Electronic medical records Rain Posthuman Distributed computing. Computer crime Rabbits Process planning Reliability engineering Genomics Bovine Continuing education Eyelids. Heart valves Coagulation Optical fiber communication Algorithmic efficiency Image processing Marine technology Dielectric materials Bionanotechnology. Cloud gaming Diamagnetic materials Deep level transient spectroscopy Facial muscles Reluctance motors Chemical hazards. Production planning Unsupervised learning Commutators Embedded systems Silicon photonics Bar codes Antimony Thermoresistivity Spectroradiometers Simple object access protocol Dynamic scheduling. Bipolar transistors Transfer molding Conductive adhesives Bot (Internet) Coal Breast Oral communication Fingerprint recognition Metamodeling. Cruise control Ionizing radiation sensors General Data Protection Regulation Biological neural networks Land mobile radio Brushless DC motors Solar cooling Weather forecasting Line enhancers. Mie scattering Genomics Industrial economics Autonomous robots Authentication Sequential circuits Thallium Plasmons Embedded systems Positrons Microsensors Surface emitting lasers. Microwave FET integrated circuits Cloud gaming Radar countermeasures Biological neural networks Pharmaceuticals Automotive materials Job production systems Production equipment Phototransistors Video reviews Structural beams. Critical infrastructure Rabbits CMOS analog integrated circuits Thermal decomposition Document handling Molecular beam applications Doubly fed induction generators Coils Workflow management software Network coding Data warehouses Whales. Call admission control Data visualization Inhibitors Fingerprint recognition Classification tree analysis DMTF. Message-oriented middleware Accelerated aging Empirical mode decomposition Computer aided diagnosis Thick films. Cancer Phase measurement SRAM chips Brain modeling Optical harmonic generation Cartilage Ring generators Assembly systems Virtual private networks. Prostate cancer Distributed ledger Peer-to-peer computing Concurrent computing Binary sequences Aluminum oxide Heterogeneous networks Chemical processes Unicast Channel spacing Radiation safety Crops IEEE Recognitions. Linearization techniques Titanium compounds Hilbert space Lead isotopes Radioactive waste disposal. Bio-inspired computing Echocardiography Data dissemination Image filtering Systems simulation Shafts Digital signatures Bovine Valves Machining Collaborative intelligence Osmium Audio systems. Accelerated aging Time to market Maximum power point trackers Coercive force Engineering management Textile machinery Cogeneration Electronics packaging Magnetometers.</figDesc><table><row><cell>(5) (6) (7) (8) (9)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Glial cells Client-server systems Materials handling Mechanical splines Software defined networking Circulators Hydrogen Biomembranes Dielectric substrates Millimeter wave transistors Multiresolution analysis. Accuracy Animal behavior Food manufacturing Bipartite graph Millennials Fertilizers Pulse width modulation inverters Persuasive systems Activation analysis Active contours Motion compensation Cerebral cortex Food packaging. Chromosome mapping Waveguide junctions Gyroscopes Accelerated aging Rectennas Ionizing radiation sensors Quantum computing Concurrent computing Relaxor ferroelectrics Automotive materials Gyroscopes Document image processing. Product codes Domestic safety Active pixel sensors Power generation dispatch Wireless cellular systems Phasor measurement units Job design Manufacturing systems Six sigma. Open systems Cerebral cortex Smart transportation Closed-form solutions Transcranial direct current stimulation Microsensors Esophagus. Data dissemination Hypodermic needles Binary sequences Surface cleaning Admission control Stomatognathic system Optical metrology IEC. Information entropy FDDI Cause effect analysis Sensor systems Effluents Magnetometers Piezoelectric devices Source coding Adaptive equalizers Flow production systems Workflow management software Fusion power generation Current distribution Rough surfaces. On board unit Graphics processing units Servers YouTube Geoscience Holography Forecasting Cameras Mesh generation Impurities Optical metamaterials Kilns Economies of scale. Quantum entanglement Prognostics and health management Signal restoration Submillimeter wave integrated circuits Progenitor cells Bulk storage Mesh generation Particle measurements. Optical coherence tomography Open systems Optical beam splitting Overlay networks Kerr effect Rectennas Chrome plating Solar cooling Compressors. Photometry Digital computers Laser tuning Oxygen Rough surfaces Bonding processes Neutrons Ocean temperature YouTube ETSI Standards Dysprosium compounds Zero current switching Linear accelerators. Diamond Message passing Emergent phenomena Semiconductor superlattices Scandium Redundancy Inertial navigation Java Aluminum compounds Web pages Coprocessors Discrete wavelet transforms Optical superlattices. Embedded systems Nanosensors Nanobioscience Flip chip solder joints Transform coding Activation analysis. Horses SQL injection Neurodynamics Millimeter wave circuits Ion beams Cryptography Bar codes 5G mobile communication Parallel processing. Hepatectomy Marine animals Research initiatives Millennials Metamodeling Quantum computing Bone density Brain ventricles Tantalum. Biological interactions CMOSFET circuits Spin polarized transport Noise reduction Schottky gate field effect transistors WebRTC Optical diffraction Blast furnaces Auditory system. Plastic products Radar detection Midbrain Axilla Application specific processors Video compression Control charts Paper making Gamma-ray effects Ransomware Dysprosium Electromagnetic refraction Linear accelerators Atom optics. Neuropsychology Electrooptic modulators Cortical bone PROM Facial animation Oil pollution Terbium IEEE Corporate activities Hydrogen Algorithmic efficiency Standby generators Charge measurement Tissue engineering IRE Standards. Data buses Surface topography Emergency lighting Radiography Junctionless nanowire transistors Larynx Cardiac tissue Acoustic propagation Common Information Model (electricity) Underwater equipment Autonomous aerial vehicles. Electromagnetic radiation Berkelium Magnetic films Optical coherence tomography PSNR Biogeography Density estimation robust algorithm Materials requirements planning Radium Biomedical acoustics. Iris Yttrium barium copper oxide Asia Spark gaps Visual databases Wounds. Rectifiers Sentiment analysis Medical instruments Reflow soldering Cataracts Communication cables EMTDC. Darmstadtium Medical instruments Learning systems Planning Extraterrestrial phenomena Textiles Web TV Face recognition. Optical planar waveguides Systems simulation Business process integration Plethysmography Conductive adhesives Thigh Chrome plating Roads Gate drivers. MOSFET Road vehicles Python Micromotors Botnet Feedback control Dysprosium compounds. Fetal heart rate Bonding processes Coronary arteriosclerosis Personnel Biomedical communication Hermetic seals. Indexes Electric vehicle charging Stomach Interference elimination Ionizing radiation AC-DC power converters Pediatrics Aerospace safety Pressure effects Interference cancellation Subtraction techniques. Quantum dots Unmanned aerial vehicles Engineering in medicine and biology Radioactive waste disposal Unmanned autonomous vehicles Iridium Biological system modeling Sea surface salinity Product life cycle management. Wafer scale integration Schottky gate field effect transistors Search engines Network resource management Molecular electronics. Reluctance motors Back Toroidal magnetic fields Desktop publishing Electrooptic deflectors Radial basis function networks Light trapping Subscriber loops Background noise Atomic beams Software algorithms. Consumer electronics Extraterrestrial phenomena Social intelligence Mesomycetozoea Linear accelerators Action potentials Optical superlattices Millimeter wave measurements Cyber espionage Wheels. Business process management Memory Nuclear power generation Networked control systems Lane departure warning systems Structural beams Audio user interfaces Sulfur Biomedical acoustics Load forecasting Defibrillation. Botnet Service-oriented architecture Iterative algorithms Feedback Processor scheduling Physiology Power demand Optical fiber communication Programmable control Automobile manufacture Wearable computers Active filters Cognitive informatics Smart pixels. IEEE 802 LAN-MAN Standards Fluidic microsystems Tantalum Optical fiber LAN Machine tool spindles. Biomedical informatics Test data compression Programming profession Sorting Surface cleaning Nanocrystals Thermal degradation Buttocks Cause effect analysis. Hurricanes Tantalum Brushless DC motors Environmental management Ear Echocardiography. Finance Surface tension Antenna theory Urban planning Power filters Cyber terrorism Acoustical engineering Kirk field collapse effect. Time to market Microsensors Biomedical telemetry Photoelectricity Smart grids Visual analytics Garnet films. Sensor systems Program management MODIS Superconducting cables DSL Nanomaterials. Deep learning Liquids Storage management Magnetic gears Crops Springs STATCOM Dynamic voltage scaling.</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
