<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">New results on exact controllability of a class of fractional neutral integro-differential systems with state-dependent delay in Banach spaces</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ravichandran</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Valliammal</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Juan</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nieto</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">PG &amp; Research Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Kongunadu Arts and Science College</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Coimbatore -641 029</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Tamil Nadu</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sri Eshwar College of Engineering</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Coimbatore -641 202</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Tamil Nadu</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Instituto de Matemáticas</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Facultade de Matemáticas</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidade de Santiago de Compostela</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>15782</postCode>
									<settlement>Santiago de Compostela</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">New results on exact controllability of a class of fractional neutral integro-differential systems with state-dependent delay in Banach spaces</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">47BD97AADFAD57FA8BEC48803E595EEB</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jfranklin.2018.12.001</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received date: 17 October 2017 Revised date: 29 September 2018 Accepted date: 6 December 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T12:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>controllability</term>
					<term>continuous dependence</term>
					<term>fractional calculus</term>
					<term>fixed point theorems</term>
					<term>resolvent operator</term>
					<term>state-dependent delay. 2010 Mathematics Subject Classification: 47D06</term>
					<term>47H10</term>
					<term>34K05</term>
					<term>34K30</term>
					<term>35R10</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This article deals with the use of Krasnoselskii's fixed point theorem and Leray-Schauder alternative theorem combined with resolvent operator and some analytical methods to investigate the exact controllability and continuous dependence of a class of neutral fractional integro-differential systems with state-dependent delay in Banach spaces. An application to exemplify the concept is provided at the end.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The Fractional calculus is a generalization of classical calculus concerned with integrals and derivatives of non-integer order. It has become a powerful tool in modeling several complex phenomena in numerous seemingly diverse and widespread fields of science and engineering such as electromagnetics, viscoelasticity, fluid mechanics, electrochemistry, biological population models, optics and signals processing. Fractional differential equations (FDEs) are recognized as an indispensable tool to compile the dynamical behavior of real-life phenomena in a precise manner and can be described very successfully by models using mathematical tools from the fractional calculus. Case in point, the nonlinear oscillation of earthquake can be effectively displayed with the fractional derivative. This includes fluid flow, rheology, dynamical processes in self-similar and porous structures, dielectric polarization, electrode-electrolyte polarization,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T electromagnetic wave, electrical networks, traffic model with fractional derivative, control theory of dynamical systems and so on. Many problems in engineering systems can be resolved by incorporating fractional calculus.</p><p>Controllability plays a significant role in the evolution of modern mathematical control theory. This is a qualitative property of dynamical control systems and is of appropriate significance in control theory. Many fundamental problems of control theory such as pole-assignment, stabilizability and optimal control may be solved under the presumption that the system is controllable. Controllability is generally referred that, it is possible to steer dynamical control system from an arbitrary initial state to an arbitrary final state using the set of admissible controls. It has many significant applications not only in control theory and systems theory, but also in such fields as industrial and chemical process control, reactor control, control of electric bulk power systems, aerospace engineering and recently in quantum systems theory. To have an effective illustration one can refer to <ref type="bibr">[1, 5, 7, 9, 20, 21, 23, 25, 30-33, 35, 36, 39, 49, 50]</ref>.</p><p>Controllability is also strongly related to the theory of realization and so-called minimal realization and canonical forms for linear time-invariant control systems such as the Kalman canonical form, the Jordan canonical form and the Luenberger canonical form. It should be mentioned that, for many dynamical systems there exists a formal duality between the concepts of controllability and observability. Moreover, it is strongly connected with the minimum energy control problem for many classes of linear finite dimensional, infinite dimensional dynamical systems, and delayed systems both deterministic and stochastic.</p><p>The study of delay differential equations(DDEs) was originally motivated by problems in feedback control theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> and have become popular in biological models, such as those involving population dynamics, epidemology and physiology. It may be a special kind of functional ordinary differential equations and their evolution includes the past values of the state variable. The dynamical structure exhibited by DDEs is richer than that of ordinary differential equations. It is worth mentioning that many practical delay systems can be modeled as differential systems of neutral type, the differential expression of which depends on both present state and past state. Some concrete instances in engineering involve lossless circuits and transmission lines, population dynamics, heat exchanges, and so on. Recently, several number of research theories have dealt with fractional-order problems with state-dependent delay(SDD) and infinite delay <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> and the sources therein.</p><p>The most inviting aspects in terms of existence and controllability, as well as the qualitative and quantitative of FDEs can be referred in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref>. Santos et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">15]</ref> discussed the existence of solutions for a fractional integro-differential equation with an unbounded delay in Banach spaces. Vijayakumar et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> analyzed the approximate controllability for a class of fractional neutral integro-differential inclusions with SDD using Dhage fixed point theorem which plays an important role. In addition, Kailasavalli et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> acknowledged the existence and controllability of fractional neutral integro-differential systems with SDD with Banach contraction and resolvent operator technique as the main reference. Dabas et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[10]</ref> studied the existence, uniqueness and continuous dependence of mild solution for an impulsive neutral fractional order differential equation with infinite delay.</p><p>Recently, Heping Ma and Biu Liu <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> interpreted the exact controllability and continuous dependence of fractional neutral integro-differential equations with state-dependent delay in Banach spaces. Also Yan <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> discussed the approximate controllability of neutral integrodifferential delay systems with inclusion type in Hilbert space by using the fixed point theorem of discontinuous multi-valued operators supported by Dhage fixed point technique with the α-resolvent operator. Additionally, Yan and Jia <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> explained the approximate controllability of partial fractional neutral stochastic functional integro-differential inclusions with state-</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T dependent delay.</formula><p>A factual report, at this position, is to admit the controllability and continuous dependence of mild solutions for fractional neutral integro-differential systems with SDD in B h space adages have not yet been completely examined. The above verdict is in fact driven us to explore the exact controllability of the structure (1.1) -(1.2) in Banach spaces. As a contrast to the current, we include the integral term in the non-linear terms G and F which act an appropriate notion of mild solution of the system (1.1) -(1.2). Instead of Dhage's fixed point theorem pointed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>, by employing Krasnoselskii's fixed point theorem and Leray-Schauder alternative theorem combined with the resolvent operator, contraction principle respectively, we have presented the exact controllability for the fractional-order control system with statedependent delay. Besides, there is a focus on the continuous dependence of the mild solution as well while many results of approximate controllability problems.</p><p>This manuscript emphasizes the exact controllability and continuous dependence of a class of neutral fractional integro-differential systems with state-dependent delay of the model</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">C D α t x(t) + g t, x ρ(t,xt) = Ax(t) + Bu(t) + t 0 H(t -s)x(s)ds + G t, x ρ(t,xt) , t 0 k 1 (t, s, x ρ(s,xs) ds + F t, x ρ(t,xt) , t 0 k 2 (t, s, x ρ(s,xs) ds , t ∈ I = [0, T ],<label>(1.1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">x(t) = φ(t) ∈ B h , x (0) = 0, t ∈ (-∞, 0],<label>(1.2)</label></formula><p>where α ∈ (1, 2) and the unknown x(•) takes the values in a Banach space with norm • , C D α t f (t) represents Caupto derivative and defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">D α t f (t) := t 0 g (n-α) d n</formula><p>ds n f (s)ds, where n is the smallest integer greater than or equal to α and g β (t) := t (β-1) Γ(β) , t &gt; 0, β &gt; 0. A is the infinitesimal generator of semigroup (T (t)) t≥0 . B is a bounded linear operator on a Banach space, u(•) ∈ L 2 [I, U ], a Banach space of admissible control functions and B h is a phase space endowed with a seminorm . B h . For almost any continuous function x characterized on (-∞, T ] and for almost any t ≥ 0, we designate by x t the part of B h characterized by x t (θ) = x(t + θ) for θ ≤ 0. Now x t (•) speaks to the historical drop of the state from every θ ∈ (-∞, 0], likely the current time t. Further G, F :</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">I × B h × X → X, k i : D × B h → X, i = 1, 2; D = (t, s) ∈ I × I : 0 ≤ s ≤ t ≤ T , ρ : I × B h → (-∞, T ] are apposite functions.</formula><p>This manuscript is structured as follows. Section 2, we have listed some basic definitions and introductory facts that would be employed in this work to attain our primary results. In section 3, the controllability issues of the system are analyzed using Krasnoselskii's fixed point theorem and some additional techniques. The continuous dependence with regard to initial values and control is addressed in section 4. As the final part, in section 5, the applications are offered to intensify the abstract techniques.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Preliminaries</head><p>In this part, we provide some definitions, lemmas and preparatory facts from functional analysis, solution operator and fractional calculus theory which are employed in the course of this work. Throughout this paper, A and H for t ≥ 0, are closed linear operators defined on D(A), which is dense in X. Let 0 ∈ ρ(A), the resolvent set of A and define fraction power A ξ , 0 &lt; ξ &lt; 1, as a closed linear operator on D(A ξ ). We can define the inverse fraction power</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T A -ξ for any ξ &gt; 0 by A -ξ := 1 Γ(ξ) ∞ 0 t ξ-1 T (t)dt.</formula><p>In addition to that A -ξ is a bounded linear operator for 0 &lt; ξ &lt; 1, then there exists C ξ &gt; 0 such that A -ξ ≤ C ξ . Also we define X ξ = D(A ξ ), (0 &lt; ξ &lt; 1) is a Banach space with norm corresponding to the fraction power is defined by x ξ = A ξ x , for x ∈ X ξ . It is known that, for 0 &lt; η &lt; ξ &lt; 1, x ξ → x η and the embedding is compact only R(λ, A) := (λI -A) -1 , the resolvent operator of A, is compact. L X ξ , X η will represent the space of bounded linear operators x ξ → x η with • ξ,η and X 0 = X. Further C([0, T ], X ξ ), the Banach space of continuous functions from [0, T ] into X ξ with the corresponding norm</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">x C = sup θ∈[0,T ] A ξ x(θ) , x ∈ C([0, T ], X ξ ). If B is a linear space from (-∞, 0] into X with a seminorm • B , satisfies the following axioms: If x : (-∞, σ + a) → X, a &gt; 0 is continuous on [σ, σ + a)</formula><p>and x σ ∈ B, then for every t ∈ [σ, σ + a) the accompanying conditions hold:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">P1 x t is in B; P2 x(t) X ≤ H x t B ; P3 x t B ≤ D 1 (t -σ) sup{ x(s) X : σ ≤ s ≤ t} + D 2 (t -σ) x σ B , where H &gt; 0 is a constant and D 1 (•) : [0, +∞) → [0, +∞) is continuous, D 2 (•) : [0, +∞) → [0, +∞) is locally bounded, and D 1 , D 2 are independent of x(•).</formula><p>For the function x(•), x t is a B-valued continuous function on [σ, σ + a]. The space B is complete. We represent B h as the set of all the elements in B which takes values in X ξ , is illustrated that, for all θ ≤ 0, B h = {φ ∈ B, φ(θ) ∈ X ξ }. Therefore B h is a subspace of B endowed with the seminorm • B h , which is inducted by • B . Moreover B h should satisfy the above said properties that hold for B. More precisely, for any φ ∈ B h , the seminorm • B is defined by A ξ φ(θ) instead of φ(θ) . Remark 2.1. Considering the phase space B = C r × L p (g : X), r ≥ 0, 1 ≤ p &lt; ∞ consist of all classes of functions φ ∈ (∞, 0] → X such that φ is continuous on [-r, 0], Lebesgue measurable and g φ(•) p is Lebesgue integrable on (-∞, r), where g : (-∞, r) → R is a positive Lebesgue integrable function. The seminorm in B is defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">φ B = sup { φ(θ) : -r ≤ θ ≤ 0} + -r -∞ g(θ) φ(θ) p dθ 1 p .</formula><p>Similarly, the seminorm in B h is declared as</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">φ B h = sup A ξ φ(θ) : -r ≤ θ ≤ 0 + -r -∞ g(θ) A ξ φ(θ) p dθ 1 p .</formula><p>The term φ t , t ≤ 0, φ ∈ B h indicates that φ t (θ) = φ(t + θ). To be able to attain our results, we assume that the fractional integro-differential problem,</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">D α t x(t) = Ax(t) + t 0 H(t -s)x(s)ds, t ∈ [0, T ],</formula><p>(2.1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">x(t) = x ∈ X, x (0) = 0,<label>(2.2)</label></formula><p>has associated α-resolvent operator of bounded linear operators (R α (t)) t≥0 on X.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T Definition 2.2. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>) A one parameter family of bounded linear operators (R α (t)) t≥0 on X is called a α-resolvent operator of (2.1) -(2.2) if the following conditions are verified. (a) The function R α (•) : [0, ∞) → X is strongly continuous and R α (0)x = x, for all x ∈ X and α ∈ (1, 2).</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">(b) For x ∈ D(A), R α (•)x ∈ C([0, ∞), [D(A)]) C 1 ([0, ∞), X)</formula><p>, and for every t ≥ 0, we receive</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">C D α t R α (t)x = AR α (t)x + t 0 H(t -s)R α (s)xds,<label>(2.3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">C D α t R α (t)x = R α (t)Ax + t 0 R α (t -s)H(s)xds,<label>(2.4)</label></formula><p>The existence of a α-resolvent operator for problem (2.1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">-(2.</formula><p>2) is analyzed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[14]</ref>. The followings are the conditions, that requires to investigate our system. A1 The operator A : D(A) ⊆ X → X is a closed linear operator with D(A) dense in X.</p><p>For some ψ 0 ∈ (0, π 2 ), for each ψ &lt; ψ 0 and α ∈ (1, 2), there exist a positive constant In the sequel, for r &gt; 0 and θ ∈ ( π 2 , υ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">K 0 = K 0 (ψ) such that for each λ ∈ ρ(A) λ ∈ 0,αυ = {λ ∈ C : λ = 0, |arg(λ)| &lt; αυ} , where υ = ψ + π 2 and R(λ, A) ≤ K 0 |λ| , for all λ ∈ 0,αυ . A2 For all t ≥ 0, H(t) : D(H(t)) ⊆ X → X is a closed linear operator, D(A) ⊆ D(H(t)) and H(•)x is strongly measurable on (0, ∞) for each x ∈ D(A). There exists b(•) ∈ L 1 loc (R + ) (the notation L 1 loc (R + )</formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">r,θ = {λ ∈ C : λ = 0, |arg(λ)| &gt; r, |arg(λ)| &lt; θ} , for Γ r,θ , Γ i r,θ , i = 1, 2, 3 are the paths Γ 1 r,θ = {te iθ : t ≥ r}, Γ 2 r,θ = {re iξ : -θ ≤ ξ ≤ θ}, Γ 3 r,θ = {te -iθ : t ≥ r} and Γ r,θ = ∪ 3 i=1 Γ i r,θ oriented clockwise. Furthermore, ρ α (G α ) are the sets ρ α (G α ) = {λ ∈ C : G α (λ) := λ α-1 (λ α I -A -B(λ)) -1 ∈ L (X)}.</formula><p>The operator family (R α (t)) t≥0 can be defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">R α (t) =    1 2πi Γr,θ e λt G α (λ)dλ, t &gt; 0, I, t = 0.</formula><p>(2.5)</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T Theorem 2.3.</formula><p>(see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>). Assuming the conditions A1 -A3 are fulfilled. Then there exists a unique α-resolvent operator for problem (2.1) -(2.2).</p><p>Theorem 2.4. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>). The function R α : [0, ∞) → L (X) is strongly continuous and R α : (0, ∞) → L (X) is uniformly continuous, then S α (t) : (0, ∞) → L (X) is uniformly continuous.</p><p>Definition 2.5. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>) Let α ∈ (1, 2), the family (S α (t)) t≥0 can be identified as</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">S α (t)x = t 0 g α-1 (t -s)R α (s)xds,</formula><p>for each t ≥ 0.</p><p>Lemma 2.6. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>). It is assumed that the conditions A1 -A3 are satisfied. Let α ∈ (1, 2) and ξ ∈ (0, 1) such that αξ ∈ (0, 1, ) then there exists a positive number C such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">(-A) ξ R α (t) ≤ C e rt t -αξ ,<label>(2.6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">(-A) ξ S α (t) ≤ C e rt t α(1-ξ)-1 ,<label>(2.7)</label></formula><p>for all t &gt; 0.</p><p>Lemma 2.7. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>). If the function R α (•) is exponentially bounded in X, then S α (•) is exponentially bounded in X.</p><p>Lemma 2.8. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>).</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">If the function R α (•) is exponentially bounded in D(A), then S α (•) is exponentially bounded in D(A).</formula><p>Remark 2.9. If H(λ)(-A -ξ )y = (-A -ξ ) H(λ)y, for y ∈ D(A). We can see that for ξ ∈ (0, 1) and x ∈ [D(-A ξ )] such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">(-A) ξ R α (t)x = R α (t)(-A) ξ x, (-A) ξ S α (t)x = S α (t)(-A) ξ x.</formula><p>It is assumed that the conditions A1 -A3 are fulfilled. Further, an indepth analysis is required for the system (1.1) -(1.2). For this fact, it is necessary to discuss the subsequent non-homogeneous model,</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">C D α t x(t) = Ax(t) + t 0 H(t -s)x(s)ds + F (t), t ∈ [0, T ],<label>(2.8)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">x(0) = x 0 ∈ X, x (0) = 0,<label>(2.9)</label></formula><p>where α ∈ (1, 2) and F ∈ L 1 (J[0, T ], X) are provided. Let us revoke the subsequent concept of classical solution and mild solution.</p><p>Definition 2.10. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>). A function</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">x : [0, T ] → X, T &gt; 0, is called a classical solution of (2.8) -(2.9) on [0, T ] if x ∈ C([0, T ], [D(A)]) C([0, T ], X), g n-α * x ∈ C 1 ([0, T ], X), n = 1, 2,</formula><p>then the condition (2.9) holds and the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">(2.8) is verified on [0, T ]. Theorem 2.11. (see [2]). Let z ∈ D(A). It is assumed that F ∈ C([0, T ], X) and x(•) is called a classical solution of (2.8) -(2.9) on [0, T ]. Then x(t) = R α (t)z + t 0 S α (t -s)F (s)ds, t ∈ [0, T ]. (2.10) A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T It is quite indispensable that R α (•)z is a solution of problem (2.1) -(2.2) on (0, ∞), for z ∈ D(A).</formula><p>Definition 2.12. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>). Let</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">F ∈ L 1 ([0, T ], X). A function x ∈ C([0, T ], X) is called a mild solution of (2.8) -(2.9) if x(t) = R α (t)z + t 0 S α (t -s)F (s)ds, t ∈ [0, T ].</formula><p>Lemma 2.13. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16]</ref>). Let α</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">∈ (1, 2). If R(λ α , (-A)) := (λ α -A) -1 is compact for some λ α ∈ ρ(A), then R α (t)</formula><p>and S α (t) are compact, for all t &gt; 0.</p><p>Definition 2.14. Let x T (x 0 , u) be the state value of the system (1.1) -(1.2) at terminal time T corresponding to the control u and the initial value</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">x 0 = φ ∈ B h , present the set R(T, x 0 ) = x T (x 0 , u) : u(•) ∈ L 2 (I, U )</formula><p>, which is known as the reachable set of the system (1.1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">-(1.2) at terminal time T. The system (1.1) -(1.2) is said to be exactly controllable on the interval I if R(T, x 0 ) = X ξ .</formula><p>It is assumed that the fractional differential control model</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">C D α t x(t) = Ax(t) + (Cu)(t), t ∈ [0, T ],</formula><p>(2.11)</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">x(0) = φ ∈ B h , x (0) = 0. (2.12)</formula><p>It is practical at this point to introduce the controllability operator associated with (2.11)-(2.12) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">Γ T 0 = t 0 S α (t -s)CC * S * α (t -s)ds,</formula><p>where C * and S * α (t) denote the adjoint of C and S α (t). It is simplified that, the operator Γ T 0 is a bounded operator.</p><p>Lemma 2.15. (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>) The linear fractional control system (2.11) -(2.12) is exactly controllable if and only if there exist some d &gt; 0 such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">Γ T 0 x, x ≥ d x 2 , for all x ∈ X, and (Γ T 0 ) -1 ≤ 1 d .</formula><p>Remark 2.16. We assume the existence of positive constants</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">M , M B , M 1 , M 2 , and M 3 , such that R α (t) ≤ M , S α (t) ≤ M , B ≤ M B , (-A) -η ≤ M 1 , (-A) -(ξ+η) ≤ M 2 and (-A) η-1 ≤ M 3 for all t ∈ [0, T ].</formula><p>In the rest of this manuscript, M * T and K * T are constants and given by M * T = sup</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">s∈[0,T ] M (s), K * T = sup s∈[0,T ] K (s).</formula><p>Now, we end this section by introducing the following fixed point techniques which will be utilized in section 3.</p><p>Theorem 2.17. (Krasnoselskii's theorem) (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>). Let X be a Banach space and E be a bounded closed and convex subset of</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">X. Assume F 1 , F 2 be maps of E into X such that F 1 x+F 2 y ∈ E, for every x, y ∈ E. If F 1 is a contraction and F 2 is completely continuous, then the equation F 1 x + F 2 y = x has a solution on E.</formula><p>Theorem 2.18. (Leray-Schauder alternative theorem) (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[17]</ref>). Let X be a Banach space, the operator ς : X → X is completely continuous. Then the map ς has a fixed point on</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">T , if the set {x|x ∈ X, x = γςx, 0 &lt; γ &lt; 1} is bounded, where T = {x|x ∈ X, x ≤ R}, where R = sup { x |x = γςx, 0 &lt; γ &lt; 1}.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T 3 Fractional control systems</head><p>In this segment, we formulate and prove conditions for exact controllability for the system (1.1) -(1.2). We have illustrated that under certain assumptions, the exact controllability of (1.1) -(1.2) is implied by the exact controllability of the corresponding linear systems. Initially, we present the mild solution of the system (1.1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">-(1.2). Definition 3.1. A function x ∈ [-∞, T ] → X is called a mild solution of the system (1.1)-(1.2) on [0, T ] if x 0 = φ, x ρ(s,xs) ∈ B h , for every s ∈ [0, T ], the restriction of x(•) to [0, T ] is continuous for each 0 ≤ t ≤ T, the function AS α (t -s)g(s, x ρ(s,xs) ), s ∈ [0, T ] is integrable and the following integral equation x(t) = R α (t) φ(0) + g(0, φ(0)) -g t, x ρ(t,xt) - t 0 AS α (t -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) ds - t 0 s 0 H(s -τ )S α (t -s)g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)Bu(s)ds,<label>(3.1)</label></formula><p>is satisfied for t ∈ [0, T ]. To prove our results, we always assume that ρ :</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">I × B h → (-∞, T ] is continuous. Moreover, we introduce the set R(ρ) = {ρ(s, φ) : (s, φ) ∈ [0, T ] × B h } into B h .</formula><p>To guarantee the existence of mild solution, we impose the subsequent restrictions on the system (1.1) -(1.2).</p><p>(H0) The function t → φ t is continuous and bounded function</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">J φ : R(ρ) → (0, ∞) to ensure that for each t ∈ R(ρ), φ t B h ≤ J φ (t) φ B h .</formula><p>(H1) There exists a constant η ∈ (0, 1) with</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">ξ + η ≤ 1 such that H(t) ∈ L (X ξ+η , X) for each t ∈ [0, T ]. Suppose there exists a positive number M h such that H(t) ξ+η,0 ≤ M h , t ∈ [0, T ].</formula><p>In addition to that, L (X ξ , X η ) will represents the space of bounded linear operator X ξ → X η with norm • ξ,η and X 0 = X.</p><p>(H2) The function g : [0, T ]×B h → X ξ+η satisfies the Lipschitz condition, there exists a constant</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">L g , L * g &gt; 0 such that for all (t j , φ j ) ∈ [0, T ] × B h , j = 1, 2; (-A) η g(t 1 , φ 1 ) -(-A) η g(t 2 , φ 2 ) ξ ≤ L g (|t 1 -t 2 | + φ 1 -φ 2 ) B h , (-A) η g(t, φ) ξ ≤ L * g (1 + φ ) B h , where L * g = max t∈I (-A) η g(t, 0) X . A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T (H3)</formula><p>The function g : I × B h → X ξ+η satisfies the following conditions. (i) g is completely continuous and there exists positive constants d 1 and</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">d 2 such that g(t, φ) ξ+η ≤ d 1 φ B h + d 2 , for every (t, φ) ∈ I × B h ; (ii) For every bounded set b such that b ⊂ S(b) = y : (-∞, T ] → X, y 0 = 0; y| [0,T ] ∈ C(I; X)</formula><p>endowed with the uniform convergence topology and x = y + z; x t = y t + z t , t ∈ I, where z : (-∞, T ] → X defined by z 0 = φ on (-∞, 0] and z(t) = R α (t)φ(0) on [0, T ]. Moreover the set of functions t → g t, y ρ(t,yt+zt) + z ρ(t,yt+zt) ; y ∈ b is equicontinuous on I.</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">(H4) (i) The function G : I × B h × X → X is continuous and we can find a positive constants L G , L G &gt; 0 and L * G &gt; 0 in ways that G(t 1 , Ψ 1 , x) -G(t 2 , Ψ 2 , y) X ≤ L G |t 1 -t 2 | + Ψ 1 -Ψ 2 B h + L G x -y X , x, y ∈ X,</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">L * G = max t∈I G(t, 0, 0) X .</formula><p>(ii) The function F : I × B h × X → X is continuous and we can find a positive constants L F , L F &gt; 0 and L * F &gt; 0 in ways that</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">F(t 1 , Ψ 1 , x) -F(t 2 , Ψ 2 , y) X ≤ L F |t 1 -t 2 | + Ψ 1 -Ψ 2 B h + L F x -y X , x, y ∈ X,</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">L * F = max t∈I F(t, 0, 0) X .</formula><p>(H5) The function k i : D × B h → X is continuous and there exists constants</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">L k i &gt; 0, L * k i &gt; 0 such that for all (t, s) ∈ D, (φ, Ψ) ∈ B 2</formula><p>h , i = 1, 2; we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">k i (t 1 , s, φ) -k i (t 2 , s, Ψ) X ≤ L k i |t 1 -t 2 | + φ -Ψ B h ,<label>and</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">L * k i = max t∈I k i (t, s, 0) X , i = 1, 2.</formula><p>(H6) There are functions P G , P F ∈ C(I, [0, ∞)) and non-decreasing functions Ω G ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">Ω F from [0, ∞) into [0, ∞) such that G(t, φ, Ψ) X ≤ P G (t)Ω G ( φ + Ψ ) B h , F(t, φ, Ψ) X ≤ P F (t)Ω F ( φ + Ψ ) B h , for any t, φ, Ψ ∈ I × B h × B h .</formula><p>(H7) There is a function m ∈ C(I, [0, ∞)) and for a continuous non-decreasing function</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">Ω k i : [0, ∞) → (0, ∞), i = 1, 2; to ensure that k i (s, t, u) ≤ m(s)Ω k i ( u ) B h , for every s, t, u ∈ I × I × B h . (H8) R(λ α 0 , (-A)) := (λ α 0 -A) -1 is compact, for some λ α 0 ∈ ρ(A), α ∈ (1, 2)</formula><p>, that is R α (t) and S α (t) are compact, for all t &gt; 0.</p><p>(H9) There are functions</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">F 1 (•), F 2 (•) and δ(•) in L 1 (I, R + ), such that (-A)S α (t) ξ+η,ξ ≤ F 1 (t), t ∈ [0, T ], H(s)S α (t) ξ+η,ξ ≤ δ(s)F 2 (t), 0 ≤ s ≤ t ≤ T. A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T Lemma 3.2. Let x : (-∞, T ] → X be continuous on [0, T ] and let x 0 = φ. If the hypothesis (H0) is satisfied, then x s B h ≤ (M * T + J φ ) φ B h + K * T sup { x(θ) : θ ∈ [0, max {0, s}]} , s ∈ R(ρ) ∩ I,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">J φ = sup t∈R(ρ) J φ (t). Proof. If s ∈ I, we obtain x s B h ≤ (M * T + J φ ) φ B h + K * T sup { x(θ) : θ ∈ [0, s]} , otherwise s ∈ (-∞, 0], then x s B h ≤ φ s B h ≤ J φ (s) φ B h ≤ J φ φ B h .</formula><p>Therefore, the assertion follows from the above inequalities.</p><p>Remark 3.3. For any x(•) ∈ C([0, T ]; X), the feedback control function can be chosen as</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">u(t, x) = B * S * α (T -t) Γ T 0 -1 x T -R α (T )(φ(0) + g(0, φ(0))) + g T, x ρ(T,x T ) + T 0 AS α (T -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) ds + T 0 s 0 H(s -τ )S α (T -s)g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) dτ ds - T 0 S α (T -s)G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds - T 0 S α (T -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds ,<label>(3.2)</label></formula><p>where x T ∈ X. Since the feedback control function u depends on the state x, therefore in the subsequent description, we change u(t) to u(t, x).</p><p>Theorem 3.4. Let the corresponding hypotheses be hold, then the control system (1.1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">-(1.</formula><p>2) is exactly controllable on I provided that</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">K * T C 1 + T M 2 B M 1 d &lt; 1,<label>(3.3)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">C = M 1 L * g + C αη T αη L * g + M h M 2 L * g C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T L G + T L k 1 L G + L F + T L k 2 L F , C αη = 1 αη Ce rT , C αξ = 1 α(1 -ξ) Ce rT .</formula><p>Proof. Consider the space E = {x ∈ C([0, T ]; X) : x(0) = φ(0)} endowed with the uniform convergence topology. Using the hypotheses, for any arbitrary function x(•) ∈ C([0, T ], X), the feedback control function is illustrated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">u(t, x) = B * S * α (T -t) Γ T 0 -1 x T -R α (T )(φ(0) + g(0, φ(0))) + g T, x ρ(T,x T ) + T 0 AS α (T -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) ds + T 0 s 0 H(s -τ )S α (T -s)g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) dτ ds - T 0 S α (T -s)G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds - T 0 S α (T -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds , x T ∈ X. A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T Consider B l (0, E) = {x ∈ E : x C ≤ l}, where l is a positive constant. Let l * := (M * T + J φ ) φ B h + K * T l. For any x ∈ B l (0, E), by Lemma (3.1), x s B h ≤ (M * T + J φ ) φ B h + K * T sup { x(θ) : θ ∈ [0, s]} ≤ l * . It ensures that Bu(t, x) C ≤ 1 d L * b ,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">L * b =M 2 B M x T X + M (H φ B h + M 1 L * g (1 + φ B h )) + L * g (1 + l * ) M 1 + C αη T αη + M h M 2 C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T [l * (L G + T L k 1 L G ) + L G T L * k 1 + L * G + l * (L F + T L k 2 L F ) + L F T L * k 2 + L * F ] .</formula><p>For applying Lemma (2.1), for x ∈ B l (0, E), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">Bu(t, x) X = BB * S * α (T -t) Γ T 0 -1 x T -R α (T )(φ(0) + g(0, φ)) + g T, x ρ(T,x T ) + T 0 AS α (T -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) ds + T 0 s 0 H(s -τ )S α (T -s)g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) dτ ds - T 0 S α (T -s)G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds - T 0 S α (T -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds ≤ M 2 B M 1 d x T X + M H φ B h + M 1 L * g (1 + φ B h ) + M 1 L * g (1 + x T B h ) + T 0 Ce (T -s) (T -s) αη-1 L g (1 + x s B h )ds + M h M 2 T 0 Ce (T -s) (T -s) α(1-ξ)-1 s 0 L * g (1 + x τ B h )dτ ds + M T 0 G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ -G(s, 0, 0) X + G(s, 0, 0) X ds + M T 0 F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ -F(s, 0, 0) X + F(s, 0, 0) X ds ≤ M 2 B M 1 d x T X + M H φ B h + M 1 L * g (1 + φ B h ) + L * g (1 + l * ) M 1 + C αη T αη + M h M 2 C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T 0 L G x ρ(s,xs) + L G s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) ) -k 1 (s, τ, 0) + k 1 (s, τ, 0) dτ + L * G ds + M T 0 L F x ρ(s,xs) + L F s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) ) -k 2 (s, τ, 0) + k 2 (s, τ, 0) dτ + L * F ds ≤ M 2 B M 1 d x T X + M H φ B h + M 1 L * g (1 + φ B h ) + L * g (1 + l * ) × M 1 + C αη T αη + M h M 2 C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T [l * (L G + T L k 1 L G ) + L G T L * k 1 + L * G + l * (L F + T L k 2 L F ) + L F T L * k 2 + L * F ] ≤ 1 d L * b , A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T where L * b = M 2 B M x T X + M (H φ B h + M 1 L * g (1 + φ B h )) + L * g (1 + l * ) M 1 + C αη T αη + M h M 2 C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T [l * (L G + T L k 1 L G ) + L G T L * k 1 + L * G + l * (L F + T L k 2 L F ) + L F T L * k 2 + L * F ] , C αη = 1 αη Ce rT ; C αξ = 1 α(1 -ξ) Ce rT .</formula><p>Next, we define the operator Υ on B l (0, E) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">(Υx)(t) = R α (t) φ(0) + g(0, φ(0)) -g t, x ρ(t,xt) - t 0 AS α (t -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) ds - t 0 s 0 H(s -τ )S α (t -s)g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)Bu(s, x)ds.</formula><p>We confirm that, (-A)S α (ts)g s, x ρ(s,xs) is integrable. It is considered</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">(-A)S α (t -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) X = (-A) 1-η S α (t -s)(-A) η g s, x ρ(s,xs) ≤ Ce r(t-s) (t -s) αη-1 L * g (1 + l * ), t 0 (-A)S α (t -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) X ds ≤ t 0 Ce r(t-s) (t -s) αη-1 L * g (1 + l * )ds ≤ C αη T αη L * g (1 + l * ).</formula><p>It follows that (-A)S α (ts)g s, x ρ(s,xs) is integrable. This concludes that Υ is well defined on B l (0, E).</p><p>In order to achieve our outcomes, we will apply Krasnoselskii's theorem. For our convenience, we divide the proof into several steps:</p><p>Step I. Υ(B l (0, E)) ⊂ B l (0, E). Now, if this is not the case, then for each l &gt; 0, there exists x l ∈ B l (0, E) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">t l ∈ [0, T ] such that l &lt; (Υx l )(t l ) C .</formula><p>Initially, for 0 &lt; s &lt; t l , we observe that,</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">lim l→∞ = l * l = K * T , x l ρ(s,x l s ) B h ≤ l * . A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>Then by the corresponding hypotheses, one can get</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">l &lt; (Υx l )(t l ) C ≤ sup 0 ≤ t l ≤T R α (t l ) φ(0) + g(0, φ(0)) X + g t l , x l ρ(t l ,x l t l ) X + t l 0 AS α (t l -s)g s, x l ρ(s,x l s ) ds X + t l 0 s 0 H(s -τ )S α (t l -s)g τ, x l ρ(τ,x l τ ) dτ ds X + t l 0 S α (t l -s)G s, x l ρ(s,x l s ) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x l ρ(τ,x l τ ) )dτ ds X + t l 0 S α (t l -s)F s, x l ρ(s,x l s ) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x l ρ(τ,x l τ ) )dτ ds X + t l 0 S α (t l -s)Bu(s, x l )ds X ≤ M (H φ B h + M 1 L * g (1 + φ B h )) + L * g (1 + l * ) M 1 + C αη T αη + M h M 2 C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T [l * (L G + T L k 1 L G ) + L G T L * k 1 + L * G + l * (L F + T L k 2 L F ) + L F T L * k 2 + L * F ] + M T 1 d L * b .</formula><p>Dividing both sides by l and applying the lower limit as l → ∞, we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">1 &lt; K * T C 1 + T M 2 B M 1 d ,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">C = M 1 L * g + C αη T αη L * g + M h M 2 L * g C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T L G + T L k 1 L G + L F + T L k 2 L F ,</formula><p>which produces contradiction to (3.3). Hence, there exist l &gt; 0 such that Υ(B l (0, E)) ⊂ B l (0, E). Now decompose Υ as Υ = Υ 1 + Υ 2 as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">(Υ 1 x)(t) = R α (t)g(0, φ(0)) -g t, x ρ(t,xt) - t 0 AS α (t -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) ds - t 0 s 0 H(s -τ )S α (t -s)g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds, (Υ 2 x)(t) = R α (t)φ(0) + t 0 S α (t -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)Bu(s, x)ds.</formula><p>Step II. Υ 1 is a contraction map.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>For any x, y ∈ B l (0, E) arbitrary, then for each t ∈ [0, T ], we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">Υ 1 x(t) -Υ 1 y(t) X ≤ g t, x ρ(t,xt) -g t, y ρ(t,yt) X + t 0</formula><p>AS α (ts) g s, x ρ(s,xs)g s, y ρ(s,ys) ds</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">X + t 0 H(s -τ ) s 0 S α (t -s) g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) -g τ, y ρ(τ,yτ ) dτ ds X + t 0 S α (t -s) G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ -G s, y ρ(s,ys) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, y ρ(τ,yτ ) )dτ ds X ≤ K * T M 1 L g + C αη T αη L g + M h M 2 L g C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T L G + T L k 1 L G x -y C ≤ K * T C1 x -y C , where C1 = M 1 L g + C αη T αη L g + M h M 2 L g C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T L G + T L k 1 L G .</formula><p>The above indicates that Υ 1 is a contraction mapping.</p><p>Step III. Υ 2 is a completely continuous operator. (i) Υ 2 is continuous on B l (0, E).</p><p>For arbitrary {x n } ∞ n=1 ⊂ B l (0, E) and x n → x in B l (0, E), as n → ∞. By the reference of phase axioms, we infer that x n s → x s uniformly for s ∈ [0, T ], as n → ∞, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">x n ρ(s,x n s ) -x ρ(s,xs) B h ≤ x n ρ(s,x n s ) -x ρ(s,x n s ) B h + x ρ(s,x n s ) -x ρ(s,xs) B h ≤ K * T x n -x C + x ρ(s,x n s ) -x ρ(s,xs) B h .</formula><p>Since ρ is continuous on [0, T ] × B h , we have ρ(s, x n s ) → ρ(s, x s ) as n → ∞. Therefore x n ρ(s,x n s ) → x ρ(s,xs) uniformly in B h . From the hypotheses (H4) -(H5), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">F s, x n ρ(s,x n s ) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x n ρ(τ,x n τ ) )dτ -F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ≤ L F x n ρ(s,x n s ) -x ρ(s,xs) + T L F L k 2 x n ρ(τ,x n τ ) -x ρ(τ,xτ ) , as n → ∞, F s, x n ρ(s,x n s ) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x n ρ(τ,x n τ ) )dτ → F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ . Now consider, u(s, x n ) -u(s, x) X ≤ M B M 1 d K * T C1 x n -x C + M T 0 G s, x n ρ(s,x n s ) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x n ρ(τ,x n τ ) )dτ -G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds X + M T 0 F s, x n ρ(s,x n s ) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x n ρ(τ,x n τ ) )dτ -F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds X .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>It is to be concluded that as n → ∞ , u(s, x n ) → u(s, x) by applying Lebesgue dominated convergence theorem. In addition to that Bu(s, x n ) -Bu(s, x) X ≤ 2 d L * b , and</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">Υ 2 x n (t) -Υ 2 x(t) X ≤ M t 0 F s, x n ρ(s,x n s ) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x n ρ(τ,x n τ ) )dτ -F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ X ds + M t 0 Bu(s, x n ) -Bu(s, x) X ds.</formula><p>Again with the same evident, for each s ∈ [0, T ], we get (Υ</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">2 x n )(t) -(Υ 2 x)(t) → 0, as n → ∞.</formula><p>This shows that Υ 2 is a continuous operator.</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">(ii) Υ 2 (B l (0, E)) = {Υ 2 x : x ∈ B l (0, E)} is equicontinuous in C([0, T ], X).</formula><p>We presume that x 1 , x 2 ∈ B l (0, E), t 1 , t 2 ∈ T and &gt; 0 such that 0 &lt; &lt; t 1 &lt; t 2 ≤ T. Since S α (t) and R α (t) are uniformly continuous on [ , T ], and there exists a δ &gt; 0 such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">R α (t 1 ) -R α (t 2 ) &lt; whenever 0 &lt; |t 1 -t 2 | &lt; δ, then Υ 2 x(t 1 ) -Υ 2 x(t 2 ) X ≤ R α (t 1 ) -R α (t 2 ) φ(0) B h + t 1 - 0 S α (t 1 -s) -S α (t 2 -s) F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ X ds + t 1 t 1 - S α (t 1 -s) -S α (t 2 -s) F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ X ds + t 2 t 1 S α (t 2 -s) F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ X ds + t 1 - 0 S α (t 1 -s) -S α (t 2 -s) Bu(s, x) X ds + t 1 t 1 - S α (t 1 -s) -S α (t 2 -s) Bu(s, x) X ds + t 2 t 1 S α (t 2 -s)Bu(s, x) X ds ≤ H φ B h + t 1 - 0 L F l * + L F T (L k 2 l * + L * k 2 ) + L * F ds + 2M t 1 t 1 - L F l * + L F T (L k 2 l * + L * k 2 ) + L * F ds + M t 2 t 1 L F l * + L F T (L k 2 l * + L * k 2 ) + L * F ds + d t 1 - 0 L * b ds + 2M d t 1 t 1 - L * b ds + t 2 t 1 L * b ds ≤ H φ B h + t 1 - 0 F * k ds + 2M t 1 t 1 - F * k ds + M t 2 t 1 F * k ds + d t 1 - 0 L * b ds + 2M d t 1 t 1 - L * b ds + M d t 2 t 1 L * b ds,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">F * k := L F l * + L F T (L k 2 l * + L * k 2 ) + L * F . It indicates that Υ 2 x(t 1 ) -Υ 2 x(t 2 ) C → 0 as (t 1 -t 2 ) → 0. Thus Υ 2 maps B l (0, E) into an equicontinuous family of functions on [0, T ]. (iii) (Υ 2 B l (0, E))(t) = {Υ 2 x(t) : x ∈ B l (0, E)} is relatively compact in X for each t ∈ [0, T ].</formula><p>Obviously, (Υ 2 x)(0) is relatively compact since (Υ 2 x)(0) = φ(0).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>Now let t ∈ [0, T ] be fixed and it is just enough to prove that, for x ∈ B l (0, E) </p><formula xml:id="formula_82">Q(t) := t 0 S α (T -s)F s, x ρ(s,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">∈ conv S α (T -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ + S α (T -s)Bu(s, x), t, s ∈ [0, T ], x ∈ B l (0, E) ,</formula><p>where conv(•) represents the convex hull. By assumption (H8), for x ∈ B l (0, E), we can get</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">S α (T -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ + S α (T -s)Bu(s, x), t, s ∈ [0, T ],</formula><p>is relatively compact in X. Finally, along these steps with Ascoli's theorem, we conclude that the operator Υ 2 is completely continuous. Considering Krasnoselskii's theorem, we conclude that there exists a fixed point x(t) for Υ on C([0, T ], X). Hence the system (1.1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">-(1.</formula><p>2) is exactly controllable on I.</p><p>The following uniqueness theorem for system (1.1)-(1.2) is based on the Banach contraction principle.</p><p>Theorem 3.5. It is assumed that the hypotheses (H0), (H1), (H2), (H4) and (H5) are satisfied and the system (2.11) -(2.12) is exactly controllable, furthermore, ρ(t, ϕ) ≤ t for every (t, ϕ) ∈ I × B h , then the control system (1.1) -(1.2) is exactly controllable on I, and it is provided that</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">M + M 2 M 2 B T 1 d x T ξ + M &lt; l,<label>(3.4</label></formula><p>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">µ 1 + M 2 M 2 B T 1 d &lt; 1,<label>(3.5)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">M = M (H φ B h + M 1 L * g (1 + φ B h )) + L * g (1 + l * ) M 1 + C αη T αη + M h M 2 C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T l * (L G + T L k 1 L G ) + L G T L * k 1 + L * G + l * (L F + T L k 2 L F ) + L F T L * k 2 + L * F , µ = K * T M 1 L g + C αη T αη L g + M h M 2 L g C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T L G + T L k 1 L G + L F + T L k 2 L F .</formula><p>Proof. We will transform the system (1.1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">-(1.2) into a fixed point problem. Consider B l (0, E) = {x ∈ E : x C ≤ l} . Then B l (0, E) is bounded and closed convex subset in C([0, T ], X).</formula><p>Let us define the operator Υ : B l (0, E) → B l (0, E) as the following: 2) is exactly controllable. In order to prove the exact controllability of the system (1.1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">(Υx)(t) = R α (t) φ(0) + g(0, φ(0)) -g t, x ρ(t,xt) - t 0 AS α (t -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) ds - t 0 H(s -τ )</formula><formula xml:id="formula_91">-(1.</formula><p>2), it is sufficient to prove that Υ has a fixed point.</p><p>For this, we can employ the contraction mapping principle. In the following, we will divide the proof into two steps.</p><p>Step I. We show that Υ maps B l (0, E) into itself. By utilizing the hypotheses, for x ∈ B l (0, E), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">(Υx)(t) ≤ R α (t) φ(0) + g(0, φ(0)) + M 1 g t, x ρ(t,xt) ξ+η + t 0 (-A) 1-η S α (t -s) g s, x ρ(s,xs) ξ+η ds + t 0 s 0 M 2 H(s -τ ) ξ+η,0 (-A) ξ S α (t -s) g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) ξ+η dτ ds + t 0 M G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ξ ds + t 0 M F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ξ ds + t 0 M BB * S * α (T -t) Γ T 0 -1 x T -R α (T )(φ(0) + g(0, φ(0))) + g T, x ρ(T,x T ) + T 0 AS α (T -r)g r, x ρ(r,xr) dr + T 0 H(r -τ ) r 0 S α (T -r)g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) dτ dr - T 0 S α (T -r)G r, x ρ(r,xr) , r 0 k 1 (r, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ dr - T 0 S α (T -r)F r, x ρ(r,xr) , r 0 k 2 (r, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ dr ξ ds ≤ M + M 2 M 2 B T 1 d x T ξ + M ≤ l,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_93">M = M (H φ B h + M 1 L * g (1 + φ B h )) + L * g (1 + l * ) M 1 + C αη T αη + M h M 2 C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T l * (L G + T L k 1 L G ) + L G T L * k 1 + L * G + l * (L F + T L k 2 L F ) + L F T L * k 2 + L * F .</formula><p>Therefore, the above terms declare that Υ maps B l (0, E) into itself.</p><p>Step II. We prove that Υ is a contraction mapping on B l (0, E). For that, any x, y ∈ B l (0, E),</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T we have (Υx)(t) -(Υy)(t) ξ ≤ g t, x ρ(t,xt) -g t, y ρ(t,yt) ξ + t 0</formula><p>AS α (ts) g s, x ρ(s,xs)g s, y ρ(s,ys) ξ ds</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">+ t 0 H(s -τ ) s 0 S α (t -s) g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) -g τ, y ρ(τ,yτ ) dτ ds ξ + t 0 S α (t -s) G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ -G s, y ρ(s,ys) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, y ρ(τ,yτ ) )dτ ξ ds + t 0 S α (t -s) F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ -F s, y ρ(s,ys) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, y ρ(τ,yτ ) )dτ ξ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)B u(s, x) -u(s, y) ds ξ ≤ K * T M 1 L g + C αη T αη L g + M h M 2 L g C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T L G + T L k 1 L G + L F + T L k 2 L F + M 2 M 2 B T 1 d M 1 L g + C αη T αη L g + M h M 2 L g C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T L G + T L k 1 L G + L F + T L k 2 L F x -y C ≤ µ 1 + M 2 M 2 B T 1 d x -y C ,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">µ = K * T M 1 L g + C αη T αη L g + M h M 2 L g C αξ T α(1-ξ)+1 + M T L G + T L k 1 L G + L F + T L k 2 L F . Therefore, (Υx)(t) -(Υy)(t) ξ ≤ µ 1 + M 2 M 2 B T 1 d x -y C . (3.7)</formula><p>From (3.6), (3.7) and induction on n, it follows that</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">(Υ n x)(t) -(Υ n y)(t) ξ ≤ µ n! 1 + M 2 M 2 B T 1 d n x -y C .</formula><p>For n, large enough, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">µ n! 1 + M 2 M 2 B T 1 d n &lt; 1.</formula><p>Hence Υ is a contraction. By the contraction mapping theorem, we deduce that Υ has a unique fixed point x(t) on C([0, T ], X) as well it is the mild solution of the model. Thus the system (1.1)-(1.2) is exactly controllable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p>A N U S C R I P T Theorem 3.6. It is assumed that the hypotheses (H0), (H3), (H6) and (H9) are satisfied, then the system (1.1) -(1.2) is exactly controllable, provided that ρ(t, ϕ) ≤ t for every (t, ϕ) ∈ I × B h there exist constants Λ and Ω such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">Λ &lt; 1,<label>(3.8)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_100">T 0 M K * T 1 -Λ P(s)ds &lt; ∞ π 1-Λ 1 Ω(s) ds.<label>(3.9)</label></formula><p>Proof. We define the operator Υ :</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">S(b) → S(b) by (Υy)(t) =                          0, t ∈ (-∞, 0], R α (t)g(0, φ(0)) -g(t, x ρ(t,xt) ) - t 0 AS α (t -s)g s, x ρ(s,xs) ds - t 0 H(s -τ ) s 0 S α (t -s)g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)Bu(s, x)ds, t ∈ [0, T ],</formula><p>for b and S(b), refer hypothesis (H3)(ii).</p><p>In order to apply Leray-Schauder alternative theorem, we establish some estimates for the solution of the integral equation y = λΥy, λ ∈ (0, 1). Let y λ be a solution of y = λΥy, λ ∈ (0, 1).</p><formula xml:id="formula_102">If a λ (t) = x λ ρ(t,xt) B h ≤ (M * T + J φ ) φ B h + K * T M H φ B h + K * T sup 0≤θ≤t y λ (θ) ξ ,</formula><p>we obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">y λ (t) ξ ≤ M g(0, φ(0)) ξ + M 1 g t, x λ ρ(t,x λ t ) ξ+η M 1 t 0 F 1 (t -s) g s, x λ ρ(s,x λ s ) ξ+η ds + M 1 t 0 s 0 δ(t -s)F 2 (t -s) g τ, x λ ρ(τ,x λ τ ) ξ+η</formula><p>dτ ds</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">+ M t 0 P G (s)Ω G x λ ρ(s,x λ s ) B h + m(s)Ω k 1 x λ ρ(τ,x λ τ ) B h ds + M t 0 P F (s)Ω F x λ ρ(s,x λ s ) B h + m(s)Ω k 2 x λ ρ(τ,x λ τ ) B h ds + t 0 M 2 M 2 B T 1 d x T X + M H φ B h + M M 1 g(0, φ(0)) ξ+η + M 1 g T, x λ ρ(T,x λ T ) ξ+η + M 1 T 0 F 1 (T -r) g r, x λ ρ(r,x λ r ) ξ+η dr + M 1 T 0 r 0 δ(r -τ )F 2 (T -τ ) g τ, x λ ρ(τ,x λ τ ) ξ+η dτ dr + M T 0 P G (r)Ω G x λ ρ(r,x λ r ) B h + m(r)Ω k 1 x λ ρ(r,x λ r ) B h dr A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T + M T 0 P F (r)Ω F x λ ρ(r,x λ r ) B h + m(r)Ω k 2 x λ ρ(r,x λ r ) B h dr ds ≤ M M 1 (d 1 φ B h + d 2 ) + t 0 M P G (s)Ω G a λ (s) + m(s)Ω k 1 (a λ (s)) ds + t 0 M P F (s)Ω F a λ (s) + m(s)Ω k 2 (a λ (s)) ds + M 1 d 1 a λ (t) 1 + t 0 F 1 (s)ds + t 0 t-s 0 δ(τ )F 2 (s)dτ ds + M 1 d 2 1 + t 0 F 1 (s)ds + t 0 t-s 0 δ(τ )F 2 (s)dτ ds + t 0 M 2 M 2 B T 1 d x T X + M H φ B h + M M 1 (d 1 φ B h + d 2 ) + M 1 d 1 a λ (T ) + M 1 d 2 1 + T 0 F 1 (r)dr + T 0 T -r 0 δ(τ )F 2 (r)dτ dr + M 1 d 1 a λ (T ) T 0 F 1 (r)dr + T 0 T -r 0 δ(τ )F 2 (r)dτ dr + M t 0 P G (r)Ω G a λ (r) + m(r)Ω k 1 (a λ (r)) dr + M t 0 P F (r)Ω F a λ (r) + m(r)Ω k 2 (a λ (r)) dr ds. Now (1 -Λ)a λ (t) ≤ M K * T t 0 P G (s)Ω G a λ (s) + m(s)Ω k 1 (a λ (s)) ds + t 0 P F (s)Ω F a λ (s) + m(s)Ω k 2 (a λ (r)) ds + π,<label>(3.10)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">Λ = K * T M 1 d 1 1 + T 0 F 1 (s)ds + T 0 T 0 δ(τ )F 2 (s)dτ ds + M 2 M 2 B M 1 d 1 T d T 0 F 1 (r)dr + T 0 T 0 δ(τ )F 2 (r)dτ dr ,<label>and</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_106">π = (M * T + J φ ) φ B h + K * T M H φ B h + K * T M M 1 d 1 φ B h + d 2 + M 1 d 2 1 + T 0 F 1 (s)ds + T 0 T 0 δ(τ )F 2 (s)dτ ds + T 0 M 2 M 2 B 1 d x T X + M H φ B h + M M 1 (d 1 φ B h + d 2 ) + M 1 d 1 a λ (T ) + M 1 d 2 1 + T 0 F 1 (r)dr + T 0 T -r 0 δ(τ )F 2 (r)dτ dr A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T + M T 0 P G (r)Ω G a λ (r) + m(r)Ω k 1 (a λ (r)) dr + T 0 P F (r)Ω F a λ (r) + m(r)Ω k 2 (a λ (r)) dr ds .</formula><p>From (3.8) and (3.10), we estimate that,</p><formula xml:id="formula_107">a λ (t) ≤ π 1 -Λ + M K * T 1 -Λ t 0 P G (s)Ω G a λ (s) + m(r)Ω k 1 (a λ (s)) ds + t 0 P F (s)Ω F a λ (s) + m(s)Ω k 2 (a λ (s)) ds , t ∈ [0, T ],<label>(3.11)</label></formula><p>representing by δ λ (t) the right hand side of (3.11), we can get</p><formula xml:id="formula_108">δ λ (t) ≤ M K * T 1 -Λ P G (t)Ω G a λ (t) + m(t)Ω k 1 (a λ (t)) + P F (t)Ω F a λ (t) + m(t)Ω k 2 (a λ (t)) ≤ M K * T 1 -Λ P(t)Ω(t),<label>(3.12)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_109">Ω(t) = max Ω G a λ (t) + m(t)Ω k 1 (a λ (t)) , P F (t)Ω F a λ (t) + m(t)Ω k 2 (a λ (t)</formula><p>) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_110">P(t) = max {P G (t), P F (t)} , δ λ (0) = π 1 -Λ .</formula><p>Integrating both sides of (3.12) from 0 to t and from (3.9), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_111">δ λ (t) δ λ (0) ds Ω(s) ≤ T 0 M K * T 1 -Λ P(s)ds &lt; ∞ π 1-Λ ds Ω(s)</formula><p>.</p><p>The above inequalities ensure that the set of functions {δ λ (t) : 0 &lt; λ &lt; 1} is bounded uniformly on [0, T ] and, as consequence, that y λ : λ ∈ (0, 1) is bounded in S(b). In order to prove Υ is completely continuous, for t ∈ I, we introduce For any &gt; 0, 0 &lt; &lt; t 1 &lt; t 2 &lt; T, choose δ &gt; 0 is chosen that |t 1t 2 | &lt; δ, strong continuity of R α (t), (-A)S α (t) and completely continuous of g, (R α (t 1 ) -R α (t 2 ))g(0, φ(0) X+η ≤ , ((-A)S α (t 1 ) -(-A)S α (t 2 ))g s, y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) X ≤ , g t 1 , y ρ(t 1 ,yt 1 +zt 1 ) + z ρ(t </p><formula xml:id="formula_112">Υ 1 y(t) = R α (t)g(0, φ(0)) -g t, y ρ(t,yt+zt) + z ρ(t,yt+zt) - t 0 AS α (t -s)g s, y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) ds, Υ 2 y(t) = t 0 H(s -τ ) s 0 S α (t -s)g τ, y ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) + z ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) dτ ds, Υ 3 y(t) = t 0 S α (t -s)G s, y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) , s 0 k 1 s, τ, y ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) + z ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)F s, y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) , s 0 k 2 s, τ, y ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) + z ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) dτ ds + t 0 S α (t -s)Bu(s, y + z)ds.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_113">≤ 2M 1 + T + M 1 (d 1 W * + d 2 ) t 2 t 1 F 1 (t 2 -s)ds.</formula><p>Therefore, the right hand side of the above inequality tends to zero and it does not dependent on the specific choice of y, when t 1 → t 2 . This shows that Υ 1 B W (0, S(b)) is right equicontinuous on [0, T ]. Similarly, we can prove that, it is right equicontinuous at zero and left equicontinuous on [0, T ]. Hence, we conclude that Υ 1 B W (0, S(b)) is equicontinuous on [0, T ]. (ii) Υ 1 is a compact operator. It is enough to prove that Q(t) is relatively compact in X, where Q(t) = t 0 (-A)S α (ts)g s, y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) ds : y ∈ B W (0, S(b)) .</p><p>From the assumptions, the set g(s, φ) : s ∈ [0, T ], φ B h ≤ W * is relatively compact in X and (-A)S α (ts) is strongly continuous which leads to the relatively compact to the set</p><formula xml:id="formula_114">(-A)S α (t -s)g(0, φ) : s, θ ∈ [0, T ], φ B h ≤ W * .</formula><p>In addition to that, for y ∈ B W (0, S(b)) and the mean value theorem for Bochner integral, for s, ∈ [0, T ], φ B h ≤ W * , we can get t 0 (-A)S α (ts)g s, y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) ds ∈ t conv (-A)S α (ts)g(0, φ) , where conv(•) denotes the convex hull. Now taking all these properties into consideration, we conclude that the set {Υ 1 y(t) : y ∈ B W (0, S(b))} is relatively compact in X, for every t ∈ [0, T ].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p>The assertion is now consequence of Ascoli theorem. Next Υ 2 is a completely continuous operator. (i) We show that the set {Υ 2 y : y C ≤ W} is equicontinuous.</p><p>To consider, for each &gt; 0, 0 &lt; &lt; t 1 &lt; t 2 &lt; T, choose δ &gt; 0, |t 1t 2 | &lt; δ such that S α (t 1 ) -S α (t 2 ) ≤ , and</p><formula xml:id="formula_115">g t 1 , y ρ(t 1 ,yt 1 +zt 1 ) + z ρ(t 1 ,yt 1 +zt 1 ) -g t 2 , y ρ(t 2 ,yt 2 +zt 2 ) + z ρ(t 2 ,yt 2 +zt 2 ) ≤ . Now Υ 2 y(t 1 ) -Υ 2 y(t 2 ) X ≤ t 1 - 0 s 0 H(s -τ ) S α (t 1 -s) -S α (t 2 -s) g τ, y ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) + z ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) X dτ ds + t 1 t 1 - s 0 H(s -τ ) S α (t 1 -s) -S α (t 2 -s) g τ, y ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) + z ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) X dτ ds + t 2 t 1 s 0 H(s -τ )S α (t 2 -s)g τ, y ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) + z ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) X dτ ds ≤ M 1 T (d 1 W * + d 2 ) T 0 H(s) ds + M 1 (d 1 W * + d 2 ) t 1 t 1 - T 0 (F 2 (t 1 -s) + F 2 (t 2 -s))δ(τ )dτ ds + M 1 (d 1 W * + d 2 ) t 2 t 1 T 0 F 2 (t -s)dτ ds,</formula><p>which shows that Υ 2 B W (0, S(b)) is right equicontinuous on (0, T ). Similarly, we can prove that it is right equicontinuous at zero and left equicontinuous on (0, T ]. Therefore Υ 2 B W (0, S(b)) is equicontinuous on (0, T ]. (ii) Υ 2 is a compact operator.</p><p>For each t ∈ [0, T ], we show that {Υ 2 y(t) : y ∈ B W (0, S(b))} is relatively compact in X. The case t = 0 leads to trivial. For a fixed t ∈ I and for each &gt; 0, choose the points 0 = t 0 &lt; t 1 &lt; t 2 &lt; ...... &lt; t n = tsuch that S α (s) -S α ( s) ≤ for every s, s ∈ [t i , t i+1 ] and for i = 1, 2, .....n. By mean value theorem for the Bochner integral, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_116">Υ 2 y(t) = n i=1 t i t i-1 s 0 H(s -τ ) S α (t -s) -S α (t -t i ) g τ, y ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) + z ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) dτ ds + n i=1 t i t i-1 s 0 H(s -τ )S α (t -t i )g τ, y ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) + z ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) dτ ds + t tn s 0 H(s -τ )S α (t -s)g τ, y ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) + z ρ(τ,yτ +zτ ) dτ ds ∈ M 1 (d 1 W * + d 2 ) T T 0 H(τ ) dτ + t t- T 0 F 2 (s)δ(s)dτ ds + n i=1 (t i -t i-1 )conv s conv( H(θ) : x : x ∈ V 1 W * (t -t i ), θ ∈ [0, s] ) : s ∈ [0, T ] A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T ⊂ M 1 (d 1 W * + d 2 ) T T 0 H(τ ) dτ + t t- T 0 F 2 (s)δ(s)dτ ds + n i=1 (t i -t i-1 )conv s H(θ) : x : x ∈ V 1 W * (t -t i ), 0 &lt; θ, s &lt; t = d + S ,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_117">d =M 1 (d 1 W * + d 2 ) T T 0 H(τ ) dτ + t t- T 0 F 2 (s)δ(s)dτ ds , S = n i=1 (t i -t i-1 )conv s H(θ) : x : x ∈ V 1 W * (t -t i ), 0 &lt; θ, s &lt; t .</formula><p>This indicates that {Υ 2 y(t) : y ∈ B W (0, S(b))} is relatively compact in X, since S is a compact set and diam(d ) → 0 as → 0. This completes the proof that Υ 2 is completely continuous. Similarly, we can prove Υ 3 is also completely continuous in the prescribed way as we have done for Υ 2 . The proof can be omitted. We conclude that Υ has a fixed point y ∈ B W (0, S(b)). Hence x = y + z is a mild solution of (1.1) -(1.2) on [0, T ]. Therefore the system (1.1) -(1.2) is controllable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Continuous dependence</head><p>Below, we discuss the continuous dependence of mild solution for (1.1) -(1.2). Theorem 4.1. Suppose φ j (0) ∈ B h , u j ∈ L 2 (I, U ), j = 1, 2 and the hypotheses (H0), (H1), (H2) and (H4) are satisfied and the system (2.11) -(2.12) is exactly controllable. Moreover for every (t, ϕ) ∈ I × B h such that ρ(t, ϕ) ≤ t,</p><formula xml:id="formula_118">x j (t) =                                φ j (t), t ∈ (-∞, 0], R α (t)(φ j (0) + g(0, φ j (0))) -g t, x j ρ(t,x j t ) - t 0 AS α (t -s)g s, x j ρ(s,x j s ) ds - t 0 H(s -τ ) s 0 S α (t -s)g τ, x j ρ(τ,x j τ )</formula><p>dτ ds</p><formula xml:id="formula_119">+ t 0 S α (t -s)G s, x j ρ(s,x j s ) , s 0 k 1 (s, τ, x j ρ(τ,x j τ )</formula><p>)dτ ds</p><formula xml:id="formula_120">+ t 0 S α (t -s)F s, x j ρ(s,x j s ) , s 0 k 2 (s, τ, x j ρ(τ,x j τ )</formula><p>)dτ ds</p><formula xml:id="formula_121">+ t 0 Sα(t -s)Bu j (s, x j )ds, t ∈ [0, T ].</formula><p>Then there exists a constant N * &gt; 0 such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_122">x 1 (t) -x 2 (t) X ≤ N * φ 1 (0) -φ 2 (0) X + φ 1 -φ 2 B h + u 1 -u 2 L 2 (I,U ) , t ∈ I x 1 (t) -x 2 (t) B h = φ 1 (t) -φ 2 (t) B h , t ∈ (-∞, 0). A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T Proof. Consider x 1 (t) -x 2 (t) X ≤ M φ 1 (0) -φ 2 (0) X + M M 1 L g φ 1 -φ 2 B h + L g Ce rT t 0 (t -s) αη-1 x 1 s -x 2 s B h ds + M h M 3 M 1 L g Ce rT t 0 s 0 (t -s) αη-1 x 1 τ -x 2 τ B h dτ ds + M 3 Ce rT t 0 (t -s) αη-1 (L G + L F ) x 1 ρ(s,x 1 s ) -x 2 ρ(s,x 2 s ) + (L G T L k 1 + L F T L k 2 ) x 1 ρ(τ,x 1 τ ) -x 2 ρ(τ,x 2 τ ) B h ds + M t 0 Bu 1 (s, x 1 ) -Bu 2 (s, x 2 ) X ds ≤ M φ 1 (0) -φ 2 (0) X + M M 1 L g φ 1 -φ 2 B h + L g Ce rT (1 + M h M 3 M 1 T ) t 0 (t -s) αη-1 x 1 s -x 2 s B h ds + M 3 Ce rT t 0 (t -s) αη-1 (L G + L F ) x 1 ρ(s,x 1 s ) -x 2 ρ(s,x 2 s ) + (L G T L k 1 + L F T L k 2 ) x 1 ρ(τ,x 1 τ ) -x 2 ρ(τ,x 2 τ ) B h ds + M M B T 1 2 u 1 -u 2 L 2 (I,U ) .<label>(4.1)</label></formula><p>Since ρ(t, φ) ≤ t for every (t, φ) ∈ I × B h , we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_123">x 1 ρ(s,x 1 s ) -x 2 ρ(s,x 2 s ) B h ≤ K * T sup x 1 (θ) -x 2 (θ) X : 0 ≤ θ ≤ s + M * T φ 1 -φ 2 B h := ∆(s) (4.2) x 1 s -x 2 s ≤ ∆(s).<label>(4.3)</label></formula><p>Therefore from (4.1) -(4.3), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_124">∆(t) = K * T M φ 1 (0) -φ 2 (0) B h + M M 1 L G + K * T φ 1 -φ 2 B h + M M B T 1/2 u 1 -u 2 L 2 (I,U ) + K * T Ce rT (×) L g + L g M h M 3 M 1 T + M 3 (L G + L F + L G T L k 1 + L F T L k 2 ) (×) t 0 (t -s) αη-1 ∆(s)ds.</formula><p>With reference to Gronwall inequality <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>, there exists a constant N &gt; 0 and for all t ∈ I such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_125">∆(t) = N K * T M φ 1 (0) -φ 2 (0) B h + M M 1 L G + K * T φ 1 -φ 2 B h + M M B T 1 2 u 1 -u 2 L 2 (I,U ) . A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p>The above inequality and (4.1) infer that</p><formula xml:id="formula_126">x 1 (t) -x 2 (t) X ≤ N 1 φ 1 (0) -φ 2 (0) X + N 2 φ 1 -φ 2 B h + N 3 u 1 -u 2 L 2 (I,U )</formula><p>, where</p><formula xml:id="formula_127">N 1 = M 1 + Ce rT T αη αη N K * T L g + L g M h M 3 M 1 T + M 3 (L G + L F + L G T L k 1 + L F T L k 2 ) , N 2 = M M 1 L g + Ce rT T αη αη N K * T L g + L g M h M 3 M 1 T + M 3 (L G + L F + L G T L k 1 + L F T L k 2 ) (M M 1 L g + M * T ), N 3 = M M B T 1 2 1 + Ce rT T αη αη N K * T L g + L g M h M 3 M 1 T + M 3 (L G + L F + L G T L k 1 + L F T L k 2 ) ,</formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_128">N * = max {N 1 , N 2 , N 3 }. Finally, we have x 1 (t) -x 2 (t) X ≤ N * φ 1 (0) -φ 2 (0) X + φ 1 -φ 2 B h + u 1 -u 2 L 2 (I,U ) , t ∈ I, x 1 (t) -x 2 (t) B h = φ 1 (t) -φ 2 (t) B h , t ∈ (-∞, 0].</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Application I</head><p>To exemplify our theoretical results, we consider the following model</p><formula xml:id="formula_129">D α t x(t, ξ) + t -∞ e 2(s-t) a 2 x s -ρ 1 (s)ρ 2 ( x(s) ), ξ ds = ∂ 2 ∂ξ 2 x(t, ξ) + t 0 (t -s) δ e -γ(t-s) ∂ 2 ∂ξ 2 x(s, ξ)ds + µ(t, ξ) + t -∞ e 2(s-t) 4 x s -ρ 1 (s)ρ 2 ( x(s) ), ξ ds + t 0 G(s -t) s -∞ e 2(η-s) b 2 x η -ρ 1 (η)ρ 2 ( x(η) ), ξ dηds + t -∞ e 2(s-t) c 2 x s -ρ 1 (s)ρ 2 ( x(s) ), ξ ds + t 0 H(s -t) s -∞ e 2(η-s) d 2 x η -ρ 1 (η)ρ 2 ( x(η) ), ξ dηds,<label>(5.1)</label></formula><p>x(t, 0) = 0 = x(t, π), t ∈ [0, T ], (5.2)</p><formula xml:id="formula_130">x(t, ξ) = φ(0, ξ), t ≤ 0, 0 ≤ ξ ≤ π,<label>(5.3)</label></formula><p>where D α t is Caputo's fractional derivative of order α ∈ (1, 2), δ, γ and a 2 , b 2 , c 2 , d 2 are positive numbers. In addition to that, the space X = L 2 [0, π] is considered having the norm |•| L 2 and the operator (-A), defined by (-A)z = z with domain D(-A ) = {z ∈ X : z, z are absolutely</p><formula xml:id="formula_131">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T continuous, z ∈ X, z(0) = z(π) = 0}. Then (-A)z = ∞ n=1 n 2 z, z n z n , z ∈ D(-A), in which z n (s) = 2</formula><p>π sin(ns), n = 1, 2, .... is the normalized eigenvectors of (-A). It generates a strongly continuous semigroup T (t) t≥0 in X is characterized by T (t)z = ∞ n=1 e -n 2 t z, z n z n , for all z ∈ X, t &gt; 0, which is analytic, compact and self adjoint. The operator (-A) 1/2 is given by (-A) 1/2 z = ∞ n=1 n z, z n z n , z ∈ D(-A) 1/2 on the space (D(-A) 1/2 ) = z(•) ∈ X :</p><formula xml:id="formula_132">∞ n=1</formula><p>n z, z n z n ∈ X and (-A) -1/2 = 1.</p><p>Therefore, we conclude (-A) that it is sectorial type and the corresponding property (A1) hold. We also consider the operator g(t) : D(A) ⊆ X → X, t ≥ 0 such that g(t) = t δ e -γt (-A)x for x ∈ D(A). It shows that the conditions (A2) and (A3) in section 2 are satisfied with D = C ∞ 0 ([0, π]) and it is the space of infinitely differentiable functions that vanishes at ξ = 0 and ξ = π. Therefore our system (5.1) -(5.3) has associated α resolvent operator (R α (t)) t≥0 on X. We take ξ = η = 1 2 and the phase space B h = C P , where C P is defined as follows. Let P be a continuous function on (-∞, 0] with P (0) = 1, lim Digital filter design has significant attention amongst researchers over the last few decades. A digital filter is a system that performs mathematical operations on a sampled, digitized signal to reduce or enhance certain features of the processed signal. The class of digital filters may broadly be categorized into finite duration impulse response (FIR) and infinite duration impulse response (IIR) filter. FIR filters exhibit significant advantages like boundedinput-bounded-output stability, phase-linearity, and low-coefficient sensitivity which have made them perfectly suitable in many industrial applications.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref>, methodology for an upgraded framework of a FIR digital filter from software level to the hardware level on the basis of the FIR filter structure is detailed. Also in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, the coupling between a non-uniform sampling scheme and an asynchronous designs are discussed in order to implement a digital filter. Inspired by the above, we have considered the filter model for our system which is shown in the Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>. R α (t), the input signal is added with the values of η at time t = 0 and its previous samples g(t). Now the input signal g(t) and its previous samples are given to a phase shifter network to change the phase of the signal. Fourier transform of g(t) is calculated for finding g(s). Also the inputs S α (ts) and A are applied to the mixer network to obtain the product of A, S α (ts) and g(s), the resultant value is given to the integrator block which integrates the signal over the time interval 0 to t. The resultant value is added with the response H(Sτ ), inputs S α (ts) and g(t) are given to a mixer block and the solution is integrated with respect to t over the interval (0, s). Further the output is integrated over 0 to t.</p><p>Additionally, the inputs S α (ts) and G are mixed and it is multiplied with the output of integrator over (0, t). The same process is then applied with the input F . Also the same input S α (ts) is again multiplied with B and u(s), the resultant is integrated over the interval (0, t). Finally all the outputs from integrator are moved to summer network. The output x(t) thus </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusions</head><p>This manuscript illustrates that the exact controllability and continuous dependence of fractional neutral integro-differential system with state-dependent delay in a Banach space by using the fractional calculus, resolvent operator, Krasnoselskii's fixed point theorem Leray-Schauder alternative theorem. Our theorem guarantees the effectiveness of exact controllability which is the results of the system concerned.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>2 →</head><label>2</label><figDesc>stands for the set of all locally integrable functions from R + to R + ) such that b (Laplace of b(•)) exists for Re(λ) &gt; 0 and H(t)x ≤ b(t) x 1 for all t &gt; 0 and x ∈ D(A). Moreover, the operator valued function H : 0, π L ([D(A), X]) has an analytic extension (still denoted by H) to 0,υ such that, for all x ∈ D(A), H(λ)x ≤ H(λ) x 1 and H(λ) = O 1 |λ| as |λ| → ∞. A3 There exists a subspace D ∈ D(A) and a positive constant c such that (A)(D) ⊆ (D(A)) ⊆ D(A) and A H(λ)x ≤ c x for every x ∈ D and all λ ∈ 0,υ .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>s 0 S 0 S 0 k 1 0 S 0 k 2 0 S</head><label>00010020</label><figDesc>α (ts)g τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) dτ dsA C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T + t α (ts)G s, x ρ(s,xs) , s (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds + t α (ts)F s, x ρ(s,xs) , s (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds + t α (ts)Bu(s, x)ds.(3.6) By Theorem 3.4; the control (3.2) transfers the system (3.1) from the initial state to the final state x T provided that the operator Υ has a fixed point on C([0, T ], X). Therefore if the operator Υ has a fixed point then the system (1.1) -(1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>ConstructW</head><label></label><figDesc>= sup { y X = λΥ y : 0 &lt; λ &lt; 1} , B W (0, S(b)) = {y ∈ S(b) : y C ≤ W} . Since ρ s, y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) ≤ S, for every S ∈ [0, T ], y ∈ B W (0, S(b)), y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) B h ≤ (M * T + J φ + K * T H) φ B h + K * T W := W * .A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P TIt is clearly seen that Υ is bounded and continuous on B W (0, S(b)). Now to ensure Υ 1 is completely continuous.(i) Υ 1 B W (0, S(b)) is equicontinuous.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>.c 2 d 2</head><label>22</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Filter System</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>S C R I P Tobtained is hence bounded and controllable.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>xs) ,</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>s</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>t</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell cols="3">k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds +</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>S α (T -s)Bu(s, x)ds</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">is relatively compact in X. With reference to Bochner integral theorem, we can get</cell></row><row><cell>t</cell><cell></cell><cell>s</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>t</cell></row><row><cell>0</cell><cell>S α (T -s)F s, x ρ(s,xs) ,</cell><cell>0</cell><cell cols="2">k 2 (s, τ, x ρ(τ,xτ ) )dτ ds +</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>S α (T -s)Bu(s, x)ds</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1 ,yt 1 +zt 1 )g t 2 , y ρ(t 2 ,yt 2 +zt 2 ) + z ρ(t 2 ,yt 2 +zt 2 ) X+η ≤ for y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) , y ρ(t 1 ,yt 1 +zt 1 ) + z ρ(t 1 ,yt 1 +zt 1 ) , y ρ(t 2 ,yt 2 +zt 2 ) + z ρ(t 2 ,yt 2 +zt 2 ) ∈ B W * (0, B h ).From the above said restrictions, for y ∈ B W (0, S(b)) and |t 1 -t 2 | &lt; δ such that Υ 1 y(t 1 ) -Υ 1 y(t 2 ) X ≤ M 1 (R α (t 1 ) -R α (t 2 ))g(0, φ(0)) X+η + M 2 g t 1 , y ρ(t 1 ,yt 1 +zt 1 ) + z ρ(t 1 ,yt 1 +zt 1 )g t 2 , y ρ(t 2 ,yt 2 +zt 2 ) + z ρ(t 2 ,yt 2 +zt 2 ) X+η</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>t 1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>+</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>((-A)S α (t 1 -s) -(-A)S α (t 2 -s))g s, y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) X ds</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>t 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>+</cell><cell></cell><cell>(-A)S</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>t 1</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>α (t 2s)g s, y ρ(s,ys+zs) + z ρ(s,ys+zs) X ds</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Acknowledgment</head><p>The authors are highly grateful to Editor/Associate Editor of the journal for their comments. Also the authors are thankful to the referees for their valuable suggestions. The first author wishes to thank the President Dr. M. Aruchami; Secretary and Director Dr. C. A. Vasuki, for their constant encouragement and support for this research work. The research of J.J. Nieto has been partially supported by the AEI of Spain under Grant MTM2016-75140-P and co-financed by European Community fund FEDER, and XUNTA de Galicia under grants GRC2015-004 and R2016/022.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meehan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>O'regan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fixed Point Theory and Applications</title>
		<title level="s">Cambridge Tracts in Mathematics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analytic resolvent operator and existence results for fractional integro-differential equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cuevas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Abstract Differential Equations and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controllability of fractional integro-differential equations with state-dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Aissani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Benchohra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Integral Equations and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="167" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence of solutions for a fractional neutral integro-differential equation with unbounded delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electronic Journal of Differential Equations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controllability problem of fractional neutral systems: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Babiarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Niezabitowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematical Problems in Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An event-driven FIR filter : design and implementation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Beyrouthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fesquet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">proc. 22nd IEEE International Symposium on Rapid System Prototyping</title>
		<meeting>22nd IEEE International Symposium on Rapid System Prototyping</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="65" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated technology fractional order proportional-integral-derivative design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Caponetto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dongola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Maione</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pisano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Vibration and Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1066" to="1075" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Memory-based controller design for neutral time-delay systems with input saturations: A novel delay-dependent polytopic approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Alsaadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Franklin Institute. Engineering and Applied Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">354</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5245" to="5265" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence and uniqueness of mild solution for an impulsive neutral fractional integro-differential equation with infinite delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dabas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chauhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematical and Computer Modelling</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="754" to="763" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional differential equations of fractional order with state-dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Darwish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ntouyas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dynamic Systems and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relaxation in controlled systems described by fractional integro-differential equations with nonlocal control conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Debbouche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nieto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electronic Journal of Differential Equations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controllability and optimality of linear time-invariant neutral control systems with different fractional orders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Nieto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mathematica Scientia. Series B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1003" to="1013" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence results for fractional neutral integro-differential equations with state-dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mallika Arjunan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cuevas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Mathematics with Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1275" to="1283" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence of mild solutions for nonlocal Cauchy problem for fractional neutral integro-differential equation with unbounded delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vijayakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Murugesu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications in Mathematical Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence results for a fractional equation with state-dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cuevas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>De Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Difference Equations, 2011</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Granas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dugundji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fixed Point Theory</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mild solutions for class of neutral fractional functional differential equations with not instantaneous impulses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gautam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dabas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Mathematics and Computation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">259</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="489" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence of mild solutions for impulsive fractional stochastic differential inclusions with state-dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Guendouzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Benzatout</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chinese Journal of Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hilfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Applications of Fractional Calculus in Physics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Singapore</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>World Scientific</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimum energy control of fractional positive continuous-time linear systems using Caputo-Fabrizio definition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kaczorek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of the Polish Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence and controllability of fractional neutral integro-differential systems with state-dependent delay in Banach spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kailasavalli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suganya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mallika Arjunan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Korean Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kilbas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Srivastava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Trujillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Theory and Applications of Fractional Differential Equations, North-Holland Mathematics Studies</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier Science</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">204</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Delay Differential Equations With Applications in Population Dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lakshmikantham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Leela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vasundhara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Devi</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Theory of Fractional Dynamic Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge Scientific Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controllability of nonlocal fractional differential systems of order α ∈ (1, 2] in Banach spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reports on Mathematical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exact controllability and continuous dependence of fractional neutral integro-differential equations with state dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mathematica Scientia. Series B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On controllability of linear stochastic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Mahmudov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Denker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="144" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate controllability results for fractional semilinear integro-differential inclusions in Hilbert Spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Mahmudov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Murugesu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ravichandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vijayakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Results in Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An Introduction to the Fractional Calculus and Differential Equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pazy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Semigroups of Linear Operators and Applications to Partial Differential Equations</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fractional Differential Equations. An Introduction to Fractional Derivatives, Fractional Differential Equations, to Methods of Their Solution and Some of Their Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Podlubny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>San Diego</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New results on nondensely characterized integro-differential equations with fractional order</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ravichandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jothimani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Baskonus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Valliammal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The European Physical Journal Plus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate controllability of fractional differential equations with state-dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sakthivel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Results in Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="963" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Smart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Fixed Point Theorem</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fractional order oscillators based on operational transresistance amplifiers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Said</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Radwan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Madian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Soliman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Electronics and Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="988" to="1003" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">About the existence results of fractional neutral integro-differential inclusions with state-dependent delay in frechet spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suganya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Baleanu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Selvarasu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mallika Arjunan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Function Spaces</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Existence of a class of fractional neutral integro-differential systems with state-dependent delay in Banach spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suganya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kalamani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mallika Arjunan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Mathematics with Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time-delay and fractional derivatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tenreiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Machado</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Difference Equations, 2011</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the controllability of fractional neutral integro-differential delay equations with nonlocal conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Valliammal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ravichandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ju</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mathematical Methods in the Applied Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5044" to="5055" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Results on fractional neutral integro-differential systems with state-dependent delay in Banach spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Valliammal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ravichandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nonlinear Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate controllability for a class of fractional neutral integro-differential inclusions with state-dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vijayakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ravichandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Murugesu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nonlinear Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controllability results for a class of fractional semilinear integro-differential inclusions via resolvent operators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vijayakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ravichandran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Murugesu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Trujillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Mathematics and Computation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">247</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="152" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate controllability of partial neutral functional differential systems of fractional order with state-dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1051" to="1062" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate controllability of fractional neutral integro-differential inclusions with state-dependent delay in Hilbert spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Control and Information</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="462" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate controllability of partial fractional neutral stochastic functional integro-differential inclusions with state-dependent delay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Collectanea Mathematica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A generalized Gronwall inequality and its applications to a fractional differential equation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">328</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1075" to="1081" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design and implementation of an efficient FIR digital filter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zahoor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Naseem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cogent Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1323373</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controllability of fractional-order Chua&apos;s circuit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chinese Physics B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">30203</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Basic Theory of Fractional Differential Equations</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>World Scientific</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Singapore</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
