<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Completion Time Minimization for Multi-UAV Enabled Data Collection</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Cheng</forename><surname>Zhan</surname></persName>
							<email>zhanc@swu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer and Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South-west University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>400715</postCode>
									<settlement>Chongqing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Yong</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
							<email>yong_zeng@seu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer and Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South-west University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>400715</postCode>
									<settlement>Chongqing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Information Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Mobile Communications Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zhan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Information Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Mobile Communications Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southeast University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Completion Time Minimization for Multi-UAV Enabled Data Collection</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B5CBC101826E30B1D8BBA6D3ED6258BA</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TWC.2019.2930190</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T11:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Multi-UAV enabled WSNs</term>
					<term>data collection</term>
					<term>mission completion time</term>
					<term>trajectory optimization</term>
					<term>wake-up scheduling and association</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Energy consumption is one important issue for data collection in wireless sensor networks (WSNs). This paper studies data collection from a set of sensor nodes (SNs) in WSNs enabled by multiple unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs). We aim to minimize the maximum mission completion time among all UAVs by jointly optimizing the UAV trajectory, as well as the wake-up scheduling and association for SNs, while ensuring that each SN can successfully upload the targeting amount of data with a given energy budget. The formulated problem is a non-convex problem which is difficult to be solved directly. To tackle this problem, we first propose a simple scheme that each UAV only collects data while hovering, termed as hovering mode (Hmode). For this mode, in order to find the optimized hovering locations for each SN and the serving order among all locations, we propose an efficient algorithm by leveraging the min-max multiple Travelling Salesman Problem (min-max m-TSP) and convex optimization techniques. Next, we propose the more general scheme that enables continuous data collection even while flying, termed as flying mode (Fmode). By leveraging bisection method and time discretization technique, the original problem is transformed into a discretized equivalent with a finite number of optimization variables, based on which a Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) solution is obtained by applying the successive convex approximation (SCA) technique. Simulation results show that the proposed multi-UAV enabled data collection with joint trajectory and communication design achieves significant performance gains over the benchmark schemes.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Recently, unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs), which are also known as drones, have found fast growing applications such as for aerial inspection, photography, package delivery, and aerial communication platforms <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Different from conventional manned vehicles, UAVs are able to be configured with software programs to complete mission autonomously or semi-autonomously, which are appealing for dangerous and/or emergent missions without personnel involved. Furthermore, multiple UAVs can be employed to work cooperatively in order to complete complex tasks, which is one of the appealing advantages for UAV enabled applications in large areas <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p><p>One of the key UAV applications is energy-efficient data collection over wireless sensor networks (WSNs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Energy consumption is one important design aspect for WSNs since battery replacement or recharging for sensor nodes (SNs) is typically inconvenient, costly, and sometimes impossible. Idle listening is one important cause of energy waste for many sensor network applications. To address this issue, sleep/wakeup scheme has been introduced <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, which is able to adjust the ratio between sleeping and awake time of each SN to minimize idle listening. Conventionally, different SNs may wake up to send their sensed data to a fusion center with different transmit power since the distance between each SN to the fusion center may differ significantly. As a result, the energy consumption rate of each SN may be quite different, which leads to limited lifetime of the WSNs. For multi-hop WSNs, similar unbalanced energy issues also exist <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, since SNs near the fusion center are usually required to wake up more frequently not only for transmitting their own data, but also help relaying others'. By employing UAV as mobile data collector, each SN can directly send its sensed data to the UAV. Furthermore, the higher probability of having line-of-sight (LoS) ground-to-air communication link may result in higher data rate compared with ground-to-ground link, and each SN is required to wake up only when the UAV flies sufficiently close to it to enjoy better channel quality. Thus, UAV-enabled data collection is a promising technology to reduce the energy consumption of SNs, especially for SNs in large geographic area <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>However, UAV-enabled data collection also faces new challenges. In particular, UAVs usually have limited endurance due to the practical physical constraints (e.g., 30 minutes for the typical rotary-wing UAV <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>), and need to be recalled for battery swap or recharging. As such, it is important to minimize the completion time needed for each data collection mission. Furthermore, SNs may generate data periodically <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, which renders it important to minimize the mission completion time for the ongoing data collection task such that the subsequent missions can start early. There exists a fundamental tradeoff between the mission completion time and the energy consumption of each SN. Intuitively, if each SN only wakes up and transmits the sensed data when the UAV flies closer to it so as to enjoy better channel quality, then the required energy consumption of each SN decreases. However, this will incur higher mission completion time, since longer flying distance is required for the UAV to fly closer to each SN. It is a non-trivial problem to achieve the optimal balance between minimizing the energy consumption of SNs and minimizing the mission completion time. Moreover, multiple UAVs can be employed to work cooperatively to further reduce the overall mission completion time via joint design of UAV 1536-1276 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p><p>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TWC.2019.2930190, IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications 2 trajectory, wake-up scheduling and association for SNs, which is the main focus of this work. To our best knowledge, this problem has not been studied in prior work. Compared to the conventional terrestrial communication systems, trajectory design is one important issue for UAVenabled wireless communications, which typically needs to be jointly considered with communication resource allocations. For example, the joint optimization of UAV trajectory and transmit power in a UAV-enabled mobile relaying system to maximize the system throughput was investigated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The energy-efficient UAV communication with UAV trajectory design was studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, in order to achieve a balance between the communication rate and the UAV's propulsion power consumption. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, the authors studied the optimal deployment and movement of multiple UAVs to guarantee the best time-averaged performance through a Lagrangian approach. Multi-UAV enabled wireless networks with UAV trajectory design was investigated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> such that the minimum average rate among all ground users is maximized.</p><p>Furthermore, there has been a growing research interest in UAV-enabled data collection and dissemination in WSNs. By taking into account the mobility of the UAV, a priority-based data access scheme was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> to collect data from a large areas efficiently. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, efficient data collection from Internet of Things (IoT) devices was investigated with the design of deployment and mobility of multiple UAVs, aiming at minimizing the transmit power of IoT devices. The design of power-efficient communication for data dissemination in UAVaided WSN was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> to minimize the total power consumption of the UAV. The distributed estimation in a UAVenabled WSN via trajectory design was investigated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, such that the mean square error for the unknown parameter estimation is minimized.</p><p>On the other hand, the limited UAV endurance is one critical issue for UAV-enabled communications. The UAV energy minimization problem with rotary-wing UAV was studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> subject to the targeting rate constraints of ground users by using a rigorously derived energy consumption model. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, the authors investigated the effective use of UAV base stations, in order to achieve a balance between the number of information bits transmitted to ground users and the UAVs' hovering duration. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, the authors aimed to minimize the mission completion time of UAV, while ensuring that each ground terminal can recover its requested files successfully with a desired decoding probability. The data collection from a set of energy constrained SNs with a single UAV on a straight line was studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> such that the UAV's total flying time is minimized with the data upload requirement of each SN, without considering the general two-dimensional (2D) scenario.</p><p>Different from the above work, this paper considers a general multi-UAV enabled WSN, where multiple UAVs are dispatched to collect data from a set of ground SNs in a given 2D area. We focus on the issue to minimize the UAV mission completion time, which is important for UAV systems since the UAV endurance is limited in practice. Specifically, we aim to minimize the maximum mission completion time among all UAVs by jointly optimizing the UAV trajectory, as well as the wake-up scheduling and association for SNs, while ensuring that each SN can successfully upload a targeting amount of data with a given energy budget. The main contributions of this paper are summarized as follows:</p><p>• We consider a general multi-UAV enabled WSN, where multiple UAVs are dispatched to collect data from a set of ground SNs in a given 2D area. We assume that each SN is energy-constrained and it employs the sleep/wakeup scheme to prolong the lifetime of the WSN. Under this setup, an optimization problem is formulated to minimize the maximum mission completion time among all UAVs, and then the feasibility of the formulated problem is analyzed. The formulated problem is a nonconvex problem which involves an infinite number of optimization variables, thus it is difficult to be directly solved in general. • To tackle the formulated problem, we first propose a simple scheme that each UAV only collects data while hovering, termed as hovering mode (Hmode). In this mode, the problem is reduced to finding the optimal hovering locations and time duration at each hovering location, as well as flying speed and the serving order among these locations. We show that the optimal trajectory solution is achieved when each UAV flies with its maximum speed by following a path consisting of connected line segments only, based on which we propose an efficient algorithm by leveraging the min-max multiple Traveling Salesman Problem (min-max m-TSP) and convex optimization techniques.</p><p>• Next, we propose a more general scheme that enables continuous data collection even while flying, termed as flying mode (Fmode). By leveraging bisection method and time discretization technique, the original problem is transformed into a discretized equivalent which consists of a finite number of variables, based on which a Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) solution is obtained by applying the successive convex approximation (SCA) technique. To speed up the convergence and achieve high performance of the proposed algorithm, we also propose a systematic and low-complexity initialization scheme for the UAV trajectory by utilizing the min-max m-TSP method applied in two cases. • Moreover, extensive simulation results are provided to illustrate the tradeoff between the energy budget of the SNs and the mission completion time of the UAVs, which validate the performance of the proposed scheme. It is shown that the proposed scheme with joint optimization outperforms other benchmark schemes in terms of the mission completion time, which is appealing when considering the limited UAV endurance in practice.</p><p>The rest of this paper is organized as follows. In Section II, we introduce the system model and present the problem formulation to minimize the maximum mission completion time among all UAVs. In Section III, we present the proposed algorithm based on min-max m-TSP and convex optimization techniques for the simple Hmode. Section IV proposes the general algorithm for Fmode by using the bisection method and SCA technique. In Section V, we present simulation results to evaluate the performance of the proposed designs. Finally, Section VI concludes this paper.</p><p>Notations: In this paper, scalars are denoted by italic letters, vectors and matrices are denoted by bold-face lower-and upper-case letters, respectively. In addition, the space of Mdimensional real-valued vector is denoted by R M ×1 . a and a T represent the Euclidean norm and the transpose of vector a, respectively. For a time-dependent function x(t), ẋ(t) denotes the derivative with respect to time t. The logarithm with base 2 is denoted as log 2 (•), and |K| denotes the cardinality of set K.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. SYSTEM MODEL AND PROBLEM FORMULATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. System Model</head><p>We consider a WSN where M ≥ 1 UAVs are dispatched to collect data from K &gt; M SNs on the ground. The sets of UAV and SN are denoted as M = {u m , 1 ≤ m ≤ M } and K = {s k , 1 ≤ k ≤ K}, respectively. The horizontal coordinate of the SN s k is denoted as w k ∈ R 2×1 . The number of information bits that needs to be collected from SN s k is denoted as S k , and the total energy budget of s k is denoted as E k . It is assumed that all UAVs fly at a fixed altitude H above ground, where H may correspond to the minimum altitude required for building or terrain avoidance. We assume that all UAVs need to start the mission at a predetermined location, whose horizontal coordinate is denoted as q I ∈ R 2×1 , and they need to return to the same location after the mission completes. Note that in practice, q I may correspond to the depot where UAVs can replenish energy and/or offload the collected data.</p><p>Let T m denote mission completion time required for UAV u m to complete the data collection, which is one of the design variables. Assume that the UAVs operate at orthogonal frequency channels for data collection. During time horizon T m , the UAV u m collects data from its associated SNs via time-division multiple access (TDMA), where each SN only wakes up when it is scheduled for data transmission to save energy. Denote by q m (t) ∈ R 2×1 with 0 ≤ t ≤ T m the UAV trajectory of u m projected on the ground. As such, v m (t) qm (t) is the instantaneous UAV velocity vector, and v m (t) ≤ V max , ∀m and 0 ≤ t ≤ T m , where V max is the maximum UAV speed.</p><p>The distance between the SN s k and UAV u m at any time</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">instant t is given by d m,k (t) = H 2 + q m (t) -w k 2 .</formula><p>It is assumed that the wireless channels between SNs and UAVs are dominated by LoS links. Therefore, the channel power gain between SN s k and UAV u m at each time instant t can be modeled based on the free-space path loss model, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">h m,k (t) = β 0 d 2 m,k (t) = β 0 H 2 + q m (t) -w k 2 , (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">)</formula><p>where β 0 is the channel power gain at 1 meter. Denote P k as the transmit power for each SN s k when it is scheduled for communication, which is assumed to be fixed and could correspond to the peak power constraint of the SN. As such, if scheduled, the achievable rate between SN s k and UAV u m measured in bits per second (bps) at time instant t can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">R m,k (t) = B log 2 1 + P k h m,k (t) σ 2 = B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + q m (t) -w k 2 , (<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">)</formula><p>where B is the channel bandwidth allocated for each UAV measured in hertz (Hz) , σ 2 denotes the noise power at the UAV, and γ k P k β0 σ 2 is defined as the received signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) at 1 m.</p><p>Define a binary variable</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">x m,k (t) ∈ {0, 1}, ∀u m ∈ M, s k ∈ K, t ∈ [0, T m ],</formula><p>where x m,k (t) = 1 indicates that SN s k is waked up for data transmission to UAV u m at time instant t and x m,k (t) = 0 otherwise. As such, x m,k (t) specifies not only the SN wake up scheduling across different time instants, but also the SN-UAV association. Since TDMA protocol is applied for each UAV to collect data from its associated SNs, at each time instant, each UAV collects data from at most one SN. Furthermore, we assume that each SN is served by at most one UAV at each time instant. Let T max max{T m , ∀m}, we have the following constraints,</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">K k=1 x m,k (t) ≤ 1, ∀u m ∈ M, t ∈ [0, T m ],<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">M m=1 x m,k (t) ≤ 1, ∀s k ∈ K, t ∈ [0, T max ],<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where we define x m,k (t) 0 when T m &lt; t ≤ T max , such that (4) is valid for t ∈ [0, T max ].</p><p>To guarantee the data collection requirement and energy budget constraint for each SN s k , we must have</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">M m=1 Tm 0 x m,k (t)R m,k (t)dt ≥ S k , ∀k,<label>(5)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">M m=1 Tm 0 x m,k (t)(P k + P c )dt ≤ E k , ∀k,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where P c denotes the constant circuit power for the waked up SN. Note that we have ignored the power consumption when the SN is in sleep mode since it is typically much smaller than P k + P c . The key notations used in this paper are summarized in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Problem Formulation</head><p>We aim to minimize the maximum mission completion time among all UAVs via jointly optimizing the UAV trajectory {q m (t)}, wake-up scheduling and association {x m,k (t)}, as well as the UAV mission completion time {T m }, while satisfying the data collection requirement and energy budget for each of the K SNs. The problem can be formulated as The altitude of the UAV (m) K</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">(P1) : m i n {qm(t)},{x m,k (t)},{Tm} max m T m s.t. x m,k (t) ∈ {0, 1}, ∀m, k, ∀t ∈ [0, T m ],<label>(7)</label></formula><p>The number of SNs M</p><p>The number of UAVs s k</p><p>The k-th SN um</p><p>The m-th UAV P k</p><p>The transmit power of the s k (Watt)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pc</head><p>The circuit power for the waked up SN (Watt)</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">E k</formula><p>The energy budget of the s k (Joule) S k</p><p>The size of data that need to be collected from s k (bit) Tm Mission completion time required for the UAV um (s) w k</p><p>The (2D) coordinates of s k q I</p><p>The initial and final (2D) coordinates of the UAV qm(t)</p><p>UAV location for um at time t vm(t)</p><p>UAV velocity for um at time t x m,k (t)</p><p>The wake-up scheduling and association indicator at time t R m,k (t)</p><p>The achievable rate between s k and um at time t (bps)</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">K k=1 x m,k (t) ≤ 1, ∀m, ∀t ∈ [0, T m ],<label>(8)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">M m=1 x m,k (t) ≤ 1, ∀k, ∀t ∈ [0, T max ],<label>(9)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">M m=1 Tm 0 x m,k (t)B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + q m (t) -w k 2 dt ≥ S k , ∀k,<label>(10)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">M m=1 Tm 0 x m,k (t)(P k + P c )dt ≤ E k , ∀k,<label>(11)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_16">qm (t) ≤ V max , ∀m, ∀t ∈ [0, T m ],<label>(12)</label></formula><p>q m (0) = q I , q m (T m ) = q I , ∀m.</p><p>(</p><p>Intuitively, if E k decreases, then the wake-up time for each SN decreases correspondingly due to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>. As a result, the left-hand sides (LHSs) of constraints in (10) also decrease. Therefore, if E k is too small, and the constraints in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> may not be satisfied and thus (P1) may be infeasible. As a result, we should first check the feasibility of problem (P1), similar as that in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>Proposition 1: (P1) is feasible if and only if</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">BE k P k +Pc log 2 1 + γ k H 2 ≥ S k , ∀k. Proof: Please refer to Appendix A.</formula><p>Note that (P1) requires optimizing the UAV trajectory {q m (t)}, as well as wake-up scheduling and association {x m,k (t)}, which are continuous function and binary function with respect to time t, respectively. As a result, problem (P1) consists of an infinite number of optimization variables. In addition, the non-convex constraints in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> include complicated functions involving a integral with the upper limit given by the variables {T m }. Therefore, the mixed-integer non-convex problem (P1) is difficult to be optimally solved efficiently.</p><p>In the following, we first propose the simple Hmode, where each UAV sequentially flies to a set of hovering locations and collects data from its associated SN when hovering at each location. Based on Hmode, we propose an efficient algorithm by leveraging the min-max m-TSP and convex optimization techniques in Section III. Next we propose a more general scheme called Fmode, and a KKT solution is obtained by applying efficient bisection and SCA technique in Section IV.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. FLY-HOVER-COLLECT SCHEME</head><p>Hmode is a very intuitive scheme which is also easy to implement. In this mode, all SNs are partitioned into M non-overlapping groups, i.e., </p><formula xml:id="formula_19">G m ⊆ K, 1 ≤ m ≤ M , m G m = K, G m1 G m2 = ∅, 1 ≤ m 1 = m 2 ≤ M ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">G m = {s k |x m,k = 1, ∀k}, 1 ≤ m ≤ M . Let Γ m = (π m,1 , . . . , π m,|Gm| ) be a permutation of SN labels in G m , then Γ m represents a serving order of tour (s πm,1 , s πm,2 , . . . , s π m,|Gm| ). For example, if G 1 = {s 1 , s 3 , s 5 } and Γ 1 = (3, 1, 5</formula><p>), then the UAV u 1 serves the SNs in G 1 by following the serving order of tour (s 3 , s 1 , s 5 ). Denote q π m,l ∈ R 2×1 as the hovering location for UAV u m to collect data from its associated SN s π m,l , 1 ≤ l ≤ |G m |. For notational convenience, define q πm,0 = q I and q π m,|Gm|+1 = q I . Proposition 2: The optimal solution to problem (P1) for the special Hmode can be achieved when each UAV u m flies along the line segment connecting q π m,l and q π m,l+1 with the maximum speed V max , 0 ≤ l ≤ |G m |.</p><p>Proof: Please refer to Appendix B. Let T f m and T h m be the total flying time and total hovering time for UAV u m , respectively, then mission completion time T m consists of both T f m and T h m , i.e., T m = T f m + T h m , ∀m. From Proposition 2, each UAV will fly to its hovering locations with maximum speed V max , then we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">T f m = |Gm|+1 l=1 q π m,l -q π m,l-1 V max . (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">)</formula><p>Denote τ h π m,l as the hovering time for UAV u m at location q π m,l , during which u m collects data from SN s π m,l ∈ G m . Then we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">T h m = |Gm| l=1 τ h π m,l , ∀m. (<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">)</formula><p>As a result of Proposition 2, problem (P1) for the special Hmode reduces to finding the optimal SN-UAV association {x m,k }, the serving order {Γ m }, as well as hovering locations {q π m,l } and hovering time allocations for the K SNs {τ h π m,l }. The problem can be re-written as follows: <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> where</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">(P2) : m i n {x m,k },{Gm},{Γm},{qπ m,l },{τ h π m,l } max m (T f m + T h m ) s.t. M m=1 xm,k = 1, ∀k,<label>(16)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">G m = {s k |x m,k = 1, s k ∈ K}, ∀m, (17) xm,k ∈ {0, 1}, ∀m, k, (18) τ h π m,l (P π m,l + P c ) ≤ E π m,l , ∀s π m,l ∈ G m , ∀m, (19) τ h π m,l B log 2 1 + γ π m,l H 2 + q π m,l -w π m,l 2 ≥ S π m,l , ∀s π m,l ∈ G m , ∀m,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">π m,l is the SN label in G m , 1 ≤ l ≤ |G m |.</formula><p>It can be verified that at the optimal solution to problem (P2), the equality holds in the constraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> , then problem (P2) can be reformulated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">(P3) : m i n {x m,k },{Gm},{Γm},{qπ m,l },μ μ s.t. (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">) -(18), (P π m,l + P c )S π m,l B log 2 1 + γπ m,l H 2 + qπ m,l -wπ m,l 2 ≤ E π m,l , ∀s π m,l ∈ G m , ∀m, (<label>21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_30">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_31">T f m + |Gm| l=1 S π m,l B log 2 1 + γπ m,l H 2 + qπ m,l -wπ m,l 2 ≤ μ, ∀m.(22)</formula><p>Theorem 1: Problem (P3) is NP-hard.</p><p>Proof: Consider the special case of (P3) that q π m,l is given in advance, e.g., q π m,l = w π m,l , ∀s π m,l ∈ G m , ∀m, which means that the UAV hovering location for each SN is just the top of the SN. In this case, the constraints in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> are always satisfied due to Proposition 1, and the total hovering time for each UAV is fixed. Therefore, problem (P3) reduces to minimize the maximum flying time among all UAVs due to <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>, i.e., (P4) : min</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">{x m,k },{Gm},{Γm} max m |Gm|+1 l=1 w π m,l -w π m,l-1 V max s.t. M m=1 xm,k = 1, ∀k, (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_34">G m = {s k |x m,k = 1, s k ∈ K}, ∀m, (24) xm,k ∈ {0, 1}, ∀m, k. (<label>25</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">)</formula><p>Noth that problem (P4) is equivalent to the min-max m-TSP <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, which is NP-hard. Given a set of K cities and M salesmen, as well as a distance matrix specifying the distances between any two cities, the min-max m-TSP is to determine the route for each salesman such that each city is visited exactly once by only one salesman, and a cost of the most expensive route among all salesmen are minimized. Therefore, we have created an equivalent instance of (P3) as the min-max m-TSP which is NP-hard. As a result, (P3) is also NP-hard.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Proposed Solution</head><p>Inspired by the proof of Theorem 1, an efficient approximate solution to (P3) is proposed, by applying the existing techniques for solving min-max m-TSP and convex optimization. Specifically, we decompose the problem (P3) into two subproblems. In the first subproblem, with given locations of all SNs, we obtain the SN-UAV association {x m,k } and serving order {Γ m } of each UAV by solving (P4) to minimize the maximum traveling distance among all UAVs, such that each SN is visited by exactly one UAV. In the second subproblem, with given association and serving order of each UAV obtained from the first subproblem, we determine the hovering locations {q π m,l } for each UAV to minimize the maximum mission completion time among all UAVs.</p><p>For the first subproblem, although problem (P4) (min-max m-TSP) is NP-hard, there exists various algorithms which can efficiently find high-quality approximate solutions (e.g., neural network or genetic algorithm) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. In the second subproblem, given association {x m,k } and serving order {Γ m }, problem (P3) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">(P5) : m i n {qπ m,l },μ μ s.t. (<label>21</label></formula><p>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>.</p><p>In the following, we first introduce the slack variables {z π m,l } and problem (P6),</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">(P6) : m i n {qπ m,l },{zπ m,l },μ μ s.t. (P π m,l + P c )S π m,l z π m,l ≤ E π m,l , ∀s π m,l ∈ G m , ∀m,(26) |Gm|+1 l=1 q π m,l -q π m,l-1 V max + |Gm| l=1 S π m,l z π m,l ≤ μ, ∀m,(27) B log 2 1 + γ π m,l H 2 + q π m,l -w π m,l 2 ≥ z π m,l , ∀s π m,l ∈ G m , ∀m. (<label>28</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_38">)</formula><p>Theorem 2: Solving problem (P5) is equivalent to solving problem (P6).</p><p>Proof: It can be shown that at the optimal solution to problem (P6), the equality of constraints in (28) holds. Otherwise, the slack variable z π m,l can always be increased with other variables fixed, then the objective value of (P6) keeps unchanged and all other constraints are still satisfied. Therefore, there always exists an optimal solution to (P6) such that all constraints in (28) are met with equality. Therefore, problem (P5) is equivalent to problem (P6), which concludes the proof.</p><p>It can be shown that problem (P6) is still non-convex due to the non-convex constraints in (28). To tackle this issue, the  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_37">28</ref>) is non-convex with respect to q π m,l , it is convex with respect to q π m,l -w π m,l 2 , i.e., by treating the norm square as a single term. On the other hand, any differentiable convex function is globally lower-bounded by its first-order Taylor expansion at the given local point <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. As a result, with given local point q r π m,l in the r-th iteration, we obtain the following lower bound for the LHS in (28) by applying the first-order Taylor expansion on logarithm function as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">R π m,l B log 2 1 + γ π m,l H 2 + q π m,l -w π m,l 2 ≥ Rπ m,l A r π m,l -I r π m,l ( q π m,l -w π m,l 2 -q r π m,l -w π m,l 2 ),<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">I r π m,l = Bγπ m,l log 2 e H 2 + q r π m,l -wπ m,l 2 H 2 + q r π m,l -wπ m,l 2 +γπ m,l , and A r π m,l = B log 2 1 + γπ m,l H 2 + q r π m,l -wπ m,l 2</formula><p>. The proof of the lower bound in (29) follows similar arguments as that for [ <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, Lemma 2], [ <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, Theorem 2], where we omit the details for brevity. From the proof, we can also obtain that at the local point q π m,l = q r π m,l , ∀m, l, the equality of (29) holds and furthermore, both R π m,l and Rπ m,l have identical gradient, i.e., ∇R π m,l = ∇ Rπ m,l , ∀m, l.</p><p>With any given local points {q r π m,l } and the lower bound expression in (29), problem (P6) is approximated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">(P7) : m i n {qπ m,l },{zπ m,l },μ μ s.t. (<label>26</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">), (<label>27</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_43">), Rπ m,l ≥ z π m,l , ∀s π m,l ∈ G m , ∀m. (<label>30</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">)</formula><p>It can be shown that problem (P7) is a convex optimization problem, and then standard convex optimization tools such as CVX <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> can be utilized to solve it efficiently. The original non-convex problem (P5) can be solved by iteratively optimizing (P7) with local points {q r π m,l } updated in each iteration, and the details is summarized in Algorithm 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Algorithm 1 Successive optimization algorithm for (P5)</head><p>1: Initialize {q 0 π m,l }, and let r = 0; 2: repeat 3:</p><p>Solve the convex problem (P7) for the given local points {q r π m,l }, and denote the optimal solution as {q * π m,l };</p><p>4:</p><p>Update the local points q r+1 π m,l = q * π m,l , ∀s π m,l ∈ G m , ∀m;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5:</head><p>Update r = r + 1; 6: until The objective value μ converges within a prescribed accuracy.</p><p>For simplicity, the initial hovering locations {q 0 π m,l } for each UAV u m can be set as q 0 π m,l = w π m,l , which is just the top of the associated SN s π m,l . Since monotonic convergence is guaranteed in the SCA algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, and the lower bound expression in (29) has both identical value and identical gradient as original function at given local point, Algorithm 1 is guaranteed to converge to at least a locally optimal solution that satisfies the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) conditions of problem (P5) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. Furthermore, note that Algorithm 1 requires alternatively solving the standard convex optimization problems (P7) with the polynomial complexity, and the number of optimization variables only depends on K. As a result, the time complexity of the proposed Algorithm 1 is roughly given by O(LK for each hovering</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">location q π m,l , 1 ≤ l ≤ |G m |, 1 ≤ m ≤ M ; 5:</formula><p>Based on the obtained serving order {Γ m } and hovering locations {q π m,l }, as well as hovering time {τ h π m,l }, construct UAV trajectory for each group G m with line segments and maximum flying speed V max .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. THE GENERAL SOLUTION TO (P1)</head><p>The Hmode gives an efficient solution to (P1), which is strictly sub-optimal since it assumes that the UAV does not collect data while flying. In this section, a more general scheme to (P1) is proposed, by relaxing the above assumption to enable the possibility of continuous data collection even while flying, termed as Fmode. Under this mode, we jointly optimize the UAV trajectory, wake-up scheduling and association, as well as mission completion time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Problem Reformulation</head><p>Recall that problem (P1) consists of an infinite number of closely coupled optimization variables, among which T m is used as the upper bound of the integration interval, thus making it difficult to be directly solved. For any given time duration T , (P8) aims to maximize the minimum ratio η between the number of information bits that can be collected from each SN and the target number of information bits that should be collected. The optimal value of (P8) is denoted as η * (T ), which is a function of duration T . Proposition 3: The optimal value η * (T ) of problem (P8) is a non-decreasing function of T .</p><p>Proof: With any given period T and T such that T &gt; T , we should prove that η * (T ) ≥ η * (T ). Given time horizon T , the optimal solution to (P8) is denoted as {q </p><formula xml:id="formula_46">(t ) = q * m (T * m ), xm,k (t ) = 0 when t &gt; T * m .</formula><p>In other words, the feasible solution with T can be constructed by following the same behavior as the optimal solution with T when t ≤ T and each UAV just hovers over q I without collecting data when T &lt; t ≤ T . In this case, the objective value η(T ) = η * (T ). Note that η(T ) is the objective value for a feasible solution {{q m (t)}, {x m,k (t)}, { Tm }} to (P8), which is obviously no larger than the objective value for the optimal solution η * (T ). Thus, η * (T ) ≥ η(T ) = η * (T ), which concludes the proof.</p><p>It can be verified that for any given T , the target number of information bits S k that should be collected from all SNs are achievable if and only if η * (T ) ≥ 1. Thus, problem (P1) is equivalent to</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">(P9) : min T T s.t. η * (T ) ≥ 1.<label>(33)</label></formula><p>From Proposition 3, problem (P9) can be efficiently solved by applying the bisection search over time duration T until the equality in (33) holds. As a result, the main difficulty of solving (P1) lies on finding an efficient algorithm to (P8) with any given duration T . Similar to the proof of Theorem 2, it can be verified that at the optimal solution to problem (P8), the equality of constraints in (31) holds. Otherwise, the variable T m can always be increased with other variables fixed, then all other constraints are still satisfied, and the objective value of (P8) keeps unchanged. Therefore, there always exists an optimal solution to (P8) such that all constraints in (31) are satisfied with equality. As a result, problem (P8) can be written as follows:</p><p>(P10) : max</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">{qm(t)},{x m,k (t)},η η s.t. x m,k (t) ∈ {0, 1}, ∀m, k, ∀t ∈ [0, T ], (<label>34</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">) K k=1 x m,k (t) ≤ 1, ∀m, ∀t ∈ [0, T ], (<label>35</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_50">) M m=1 x m,k (t) ≤ 1, ∀k, ∀t ∈ [0, T ],<label>(36)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_51">M m=1 T 0 x m,k (t)B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + qm(t)-w k 2 dt S k ≥ η, ∀k, (<label>37</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">) M m=1 T 0 x m,k (t)(P k + P c )dt ≤ E k , ∀k, (<label>38</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_53">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">qm (t) ≤ V max , ∀m, ∀t ∈ [0, T ],<label>(39)</label></formula><p>q m (0) = q I , q m (T ) = q I , ∀m.</p><p>(40)</p><p>Note that although T is fixed, problem (P10) still involves an infinite number of coupled optimization variables, which is difficult to be solved directly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Proposed Solution</head><p>In this subsection, an efficient solution to problem (P10) is proposed by using time discretization and SCA techniques.</p><p>To obtain a more tractable form of (P10), we apply a time discretization approximation technique as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Specifically, the time horizon [0, T ] is discretized into N time slots, i.e., T = Nδ t , where δ t denotes the elemental slot length. Typically, δ t is set to be small enough such that within each time slot, the distance between the SNs and the UAV can be considered as approximately unchanged. As a result, the UAV trajectory q m (t) can be approximated by the sequence</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">{q m [n], 1 ≤ n ≤ N }, where q m [n]</formula><p>q m (nδ t ) represents the UAV's location at time slot n. Therefore, the UAV speed constraints in (39) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">q m [n + 1] -q m [n] ≤ V max δ t , 1 ≤ n ≤ N -1.<label>(41)</label></formula><p>The distance between the UAV u m and SN s k at time slot n can be approximated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">d m,k [n] = H 2 + q m [n] -w k 2 .</formula><p>As such, the achievable rate between SN s k and UAV u m in (2) at time slot n can be represented as</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">R m,k [n] = B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + q m [n] -w k 2 . (<label>42</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">)</formula><p>Let α m,k [n] denote the wake-up time allocation fraction for s k to communicate with UAV u m at time slot n, 0 ≤ α m,k [n] ≤ 1. Then constraints in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_49">35</ref>) and (36) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">K k=1 α m,k [n] ≤ 1, ∀m, n and M m=1 α m,k [n] ≤ 1, ∀k, n,</formula><p>respectively. The number of information bits that can be collected from SN s k for the given time horizon T in (37) can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">δ t M m=1 N n=1 α m,k [n]R m,k [n]</formula><p>. Furthermore, the total energy consumption of SN s k in (38) can be written as  </p><formula xml:id="formula_62">δ t M m=1 N n=1 α m,k [n](P k + P c ). Therefore, problem (P10) is reformulated as (P11) : max {qm[n]},{α m,k [n]},η η s.t. 0 ≤ α m,k [n] ≤ 1, ∀m, k, 1 ≤ n ≤ N, (<label>43</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_63">) K k=1 α m,k [n] ≤ 1, ∀m, 1 ≤ n ≤ N, (<label>44</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_64">α m,k [n] ≤ 1, ∀k, 1 ≤ n ≤ N, (<label>45</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_66">δ t M m=1 N n=1 α m,k [n]B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + qm[n]-w k 2 S k ≥ η, ∀k, (<label>46</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_67">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_68">δ t M m=1 N n=1 α m,k [n](P k + P c ) ≤ E k , ∀k, (<label>47</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_69">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_70">q m [n + 1] -q m [n] ≤ V max δ t , 1 ≤ n ≤ N -1, (48) q m [1] = q I , q m [N ] = q I , ∀m. (<label>49</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_71">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_72">δ t M m=1 N n=1 α m,k [n]y m,k [n] S k ≥ η, ∀k, (<label>50</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_73">) B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + q m [n] -w k 2 ≥ y m,k [n], ∀m, k, n. (51)</formula><p>Similar as the proof of Theorem 2, it can be shown that at the optimal solution to problem (P12), the equality of constraints in (51) holds. Otherwise, the slack variable y m,k <ref type="bibr">[n]</ref> can always be increased with other variables fixed, then the objective value of (P12) keeps unchanged and all other constraints are still satisfied. Therefore, there always exists an optimal solution to (P12) such that all constraints in (51) are met with equality. Therefore, solving problem (P11) is equivalent to solving problem (P12).</p><p>With such a reformulation, problem (P12) is still non-convex due to the the non-convex constraints (50) and (51). To tackle such issues, similar SCA technique can be applied where the original function is lower bounded by a concave function at a given local point in each iteration. To be specific, by applying the first-order Taylor expansion to</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">(α m,k [n] + y m,k [n]) 2 at the given point α r m,k [n] and y r m,k [n]</formula><p>in the r-th iteration, the following inequality holds,</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">(α m,k [n] + y m,k [n]) 2 ≥ -(α r m,k [n] + y r m,k [n]) 2 +2(α r m,k [n] + y r m,k [n])(α m,k [n] + y m,k [n]), ∀m, k, n.(52)</formula><p>Due to (52), we can obtain the lower bound of</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">α m,k [n]y m,k [n]</formula><p>as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">α m,k [n]y m,k [n] = (α m,k [n] + y m,k [n]) 2 -(α m,k [n] 2 + y m,k [n] 2 ) 2 ≥ (α r m,k [n] + y r m,k [n])(α m,k [n] + y m,k [n]) (53) - (α m,k [n] 2 + y m,k [n] 2 ) 2 - (α r m,k [n] + y r m,k [n]) 2 2 λ r m,k [n].</formula><p>In constraint (51), with given local point q r m [n] in the r-th iteration, the lower bound for LHS of constraints in (51) can be obtained by applying the first-order Taylor expansion on logarithm function similar as in (29), i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + q m [n] -w k 2 ≥ Rm,k [n] (54) A r m,k [n] -I r m,k [n]( q m [n] -w k 2 -q r m [n] -w k 2 ),</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_79">I r m,k [n] = Bγ k log 2 e (H 2 + q r m [n] -w k 2 )(H 2 + q r m [n] -w k 2 + γ k ) , A r m,k [n] = B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + q r m [n] -w k 2 . (<label>55</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_80">)</formula><p>With any given local points α r m,k [n], y r m,k [n], q r m [n] and the lower bound expressions in ( <ref type="formula">53</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">54</ref>), problem (P12) is approximated as follows: <ref type="formula" target="#formula_68">47</ref>) -(49),</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">(P13) : m a x {qm[n]},{α m,k [n]},{y m,k [n]},η η s.t. (43) -(45), (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_82">δ t M m=1 N n=1 λ r m,k [n] S k ≥ η, ∀k, (<label>56</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_84">Rm,k [n] ≥ y m,k [n], ∀m, k, n. (<label>57</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_85">)</formula><p>It can be shown that problem (P13) is convex, and then it can be solved efficiently with the standard convex optimization tools such as CVX. The original non-convex problem (P12) can be solved iteratively by optimizing (P13) with the local points α r m,k [n], y r m,k [n], and q r m [n] updated in each iteration, and the details is summarized in Algorithm 3. </p><formula xml:id="formula_86">* m,k [n], y * m,k [n], q * m [n]; 4: Update the local points α r+1 m,k [n] = α * m,k [n], y r+1 m,k [n] = y * m,k [n], q r+1 m [n] = q * m [n]; 5:</formula><p>Update r = r + 1; 6: until The objective value η converges within a prescribed accuracy.</p><p>Similar as Algorithm 1, Algorithm 3 is guaranteed to converge to a KKT solution, which satisfies the KKT conditions of problem (P11). Furthermore, the number of optimization variables depends on M , N and K. As a result, the computation complexity of the Algorithm 3 is roughly given by O(LM 3 K 3 N 3 ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, where L is number of iterations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Initialization scheme and overall algorithm</head><p>Note that for locally optimal algorithm with SCA technique, the system performance and the converged solution depend on the initialization scheme in general. Inspired by the solution in Section III, the min-max m-TSP solution with maximum flying speed can be used as a simple and efficient initial trajectory for {q 0 m [n]}. In this case, we assume that the total flying time and associated SNs for u m is T mI and G mI , respectively. Note that the given time period T may be different from T mI for min-max m-TSP solution. In the following, we propose a two-cases min-max m-TSP initial trajectory for each UAV u m similar as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, i.e.,</p><p>• Case 1: T ≥ T mI . In this case, each UAV u m is capable of flying to the top of all its associated SNs with time T mI and the remaining time T -T mI can be equally divided among the associated SNs in G mI for u m to hover above the SNs. Specifically, the hovering time</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">{τ h π m,l } at location w π m,l is T -TmI |GmI | , 1 ≤ l ≤ |G mI |. • Case 2: T &lt; T mI .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In this case, the given time horizon</head><p>T is insufficient for each UAV u m to fly over all SNs in G mI . Similar as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, a disk-shaped region with radius r is determined for each SN, and the initial trajectory for u m is designed such that it can reach the disk region of each SN with given time horizon T . Given r, the minimum flying time of u m can be determined by solving the following convex problem, i.e., (P14) : min</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">{qπ m,l } |GmI |+1 l=1 q π m,l -q π m,l-1 V max . s.t. q π m,l -w π m,l-1 ≤ r, 1 ≤ l ≤ |G mI |.</formula><p>It is not difficult to see that the objective value of (P14) is non-increasing with respect to r. As a result, the waypoints {q π m,l } of UAV u m can be obtained by solving (P14) with fixed r, and then applying efficient bisection search to find the optimal radius r for given time horizon T . Given {q 0 m [n]}, {α 0 m [n]} can be obtained by solving the following linear programming (LP) problem, i.e., (P15) : max</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">{α m,k [n]},η η s.t. (43) -(47).</formula><p>Note that solving problem (P11) is equivalent to solving problem (P12), then we set</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">y 0 m,k [n] = B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + q 0 m [n]-w k 2</formula><p>, ∀m, k, n. Recall that problem (P9) can be efficiently solved by applying the bisection search over time duration T , then the overall bisection algorithm for (P1) is summarized in Algorithm 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. SIMULATION RESULTS</head><p>In this section, simulation results are provided to illustrate the tradeoff between the energy budget of the SNs and the mission completion time of the UAVs, which validate the performance of the proposed scheme. We consider a UAV enabled WSN with K = 20 SNs, and the SNs are uniformly and randomly located in a square area, whose side length is equal to 2 km. The results obtained in the following are based on one realization of SNs' locations as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref>, and we set q I = [0, 0] T . All SNs are assumed to have equal transmit power, i.e., P k = 0.1 W, ∀k. Furthermore, we assume that all SNs have identical data upload requirements and energy budgets, i.e., S k = S, E k = Ē, ∀k. Unless otherwise stated, the parameter values are given in Table <ref type="table">II</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Algorithm 4 Overall bisection algorithm for (P1)</head><p>1: Let T 1 = 0, T 2 be sufficiently large, and let tolerance &gt; 0.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_91">y 0 m,k [n] = B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 + q 0 m [n]-w k 2</formula><p>, ∀m, k, n.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7:</head><p>Solve non-convex problem (P11) with Algorithm 3 to obtain the objective value η and solution</p><formula xml:id="formula_92">{α m,k [n]}, {q m [n]}. 8: if η ≥ 1 then 9: Let T 2 = T , and update {α * m,k [n]} = {α m,k [n]}, {q * m [n]} = {q m [n]}, T * = T . 10:<label>else 11:</label></formula><p>Let T 1 = T .</p><p>12: </p><formula xml:id="formula_93">end if 13: until (T 2 -T 1 ) ≤ . Output: {α * m,k [n]}, {q * m [n]}, T * m = T * , ∀m.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Single-UAV Case Study</head><p>We first consider the special case with one single UAV, i.e., M = 1. The optimized trajectories over the two modes under different energy budget Ē are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">1</ref> with S = 30 Mbits. As expected, the trajectory of Hmode contains line segments only and the UAV only collects data when it hovers at the optimized location, while the trajectory of Fmode contains smooth curves since the UAV may always collect data during its flight. It is also observed that for smaller Ē, the UAV hovering locations get closer to the corresponding SNs. The reason is that as Ē decreases, the total wake-up time for each SN decreases, and the UAV should fly sufficiently close to the SN to complete the data collection task with better channel quality. However, such a trajectory is expected to incur larger distance for the UAV and thus more flying time is generally needed.</p><p>The wake-up scheduling for all SNs is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. It is observed that each SN remains in sleep state for most of the time and it is only waked up when the UAV is hovering at the optimized location for Hmode or moving sufficiently close to it for Fmode, which is expected since allocating time resources to better channels in general leads to higher transmission efficiency. Furthermore, it is also observed that as Ē increases, the mission completion time decreases for the two modes. Specifically, the hovering time increases while the flying time decreases for Hmode. The reason is that as Ē increases, each SN is able to afford more energy to complete the task even for long SN-UAV distance case, and thus the UAV does not have to fly close to each SN. This thus leads to lower flying time, while longer hovering time is needed since the channel quality is not that good. However, the decrease of the flying time more than compensates the increase of the hovering time, which results in the decrease for the total mission completion time. This is also verified by the tradeoff plot in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>, which gives the total UAV flying time versus the total hovering time for Hmode with different energy budget at the SN.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> depicts the total mission completion time versus the SN energy budget for the proposed design. It is observed that as Ē increases, the mission completion time decreases, which is in accordance with the results in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. It is also observed that as Ē gets sufficiently large, the mission completion time reaches its floor value where no further reduction is possible. The reason is that when Ē is large enough, then energy constraints in problem (P1) is in fact inactive at the optimal solution and hence can be removed, and the optimized solution only depends on the efficient allocation   for the data collection requirements among all SNs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Multi-UAV Case Study</head><p>Next, we study the performance of the multi-UAV network. For the proposed successive optimization Algorithm 1 and Algorithm 3, we show the convergence behaviour for the four-UAV system (M = 4) in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref> with S = 30 Mbits, Ē = 1 Joule and T = 30 s. It is observed that the cost value of (P5) μ with Algorithm 1 decreases quickly and the objective value of (P11) η with Algorithm 3 increases quickly with the number of iterations, and the two algorithms converge within 15 iterations with prescribed accuracy = 10 -4 .</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>, the optimized UAV trajectories for the four-UAV system (M = 4) are shown with S = 30 Mbits. From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>, it can be observed that each UAV collects data from different groups of SNs, as expected. Similar as in the single UAV scenario, for relatively small SN energy budget Ē, each UAV should fly close to its associated SN, in order to achieve a sufficiently good communication channel. Therefore, the minmax mission completion time increases.</p><p>The wake-up scheduling for all SNs with M = 4 UAVs is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. Similar to the single UAV scenario, it is observed that the min-max mission completion time among all UAVs decreases with the increasing of Ē, as expected. It is also observed that at each time instant, there may exist four SNs waked up simultaneously, which is expected due to the orthogonal frequency bands used by the four UAVs. It can also be observed that the min-max mission completion time reduces by almost 60% compared to the single UAV scenario, due to the usage of multiple UAVs and concurrent data collection.</p><p>Lastly, to show the effectiveness of our proposed schemes, we compare them with three benchmarks, namely Minimum hovering time benchmark, Minimum flying time benchmark and Cluster-distance based benchmark. In the minimum hovering time benchmark, each UAV flies to the top of its associated SNs with the maximum speed by solving the min-max m-TSP, and hovers there for a sufficient duration to complete the data collection. In the minimum flying time benchmark, each UAV flies to some hovering locations for its associated SNs with the maximum speed by minimizing the total flying time, and hovers there for data collection, which can be obtained by total flying time as the objective function of (P2), where Algorithm 2 can be similarly applied. In the cluster-distance based benchmark, the K-means clustering strategy is adopted as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> to group the SNs into M non-overlap clusters based on their proximity, each cluster corresponds to a UAV. The visiting order of SNs in each cluster is based on their distance with the initial UAV location, i.e., w k -q I . Each UAV flies to some hovering locations for its associated SNs with the maximum speed and hovers there for data collection to minimize the maximum mission completion time, where Algorithm 2 can be similarly applied. It is observed from Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref> that our proposed schemes perform better than other benchmarks, thanks to the joint design of UAV trajectory and wake-up scheduling and association. Note that although the minimum flying time benchmark may achieve the lowest flying time, its total mission completion time is larger than our proposed two schemes that jointly consider the flying and hovering time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we investigate UAV-enabled data collection in WSNs, where the maximum mission completion time among all UAVs is minimized by jointly optimizing the UAV trajectory, wake-up scheduling and association for SNs, while ensuring that each SN can successfully upload the targeting amount  of data with a given energy budget. An efficient solution is proposed for the simple Hmode to find the optimized hovering locations and durations, as well as the serving order among these locations, by leveraging the min-max m-TSP and convex optimization techniques. Furthermore, a general solution is proposed with Fmode, where the UAV may also collect data while flying, by applying efficient bisection method and the SCA technique. Numerical results show that the proposed multi-UAV enabled data collection with optimized joint design achieves significant performance gains over the benchmark schemes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A PROOF OF PROPOSITION 1</head><p>From (2), we have R m,k (t) ≤ B log 2 1 + γ k H 2 , ∀m, k, t, and the equality holds when the UAV u m hovers on top of SN s k for data collection, i.e., q m (t) = w k . If constraints in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> are satisfied, then we have  ≥ S k , ∀k, and the equality holds when each SN s k transmits data with energy consumption E k when its associated UAV hovers on top of it for data collection.</p><p>If BE k P k +Pc log 2 1 + γ k H 2 ≥ S k , ∀k, we can always construct a feasible solution that satisfy all constraints of (P1), i.e., T m , ∀m are large enough to make sure that each SN s k transmits data with energy consumption E k when its associated UAV hovers on top of it for data collection. On the contrary, if there exists a SN s k ∈ K such that BE k P k +Pc log 2 1 + γ k H 2 &lt; S k , then the constraints in both <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> are not able to be satisfied simultaneously due to (58) and (59). Therefore, (P1) is feasible if and only if BE k P k +Pc log 2 1 + γ k H 2 ≥ S k , ∀k, which completes the proof.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX B PROOF OF PROPOSITION 2</head><p>We prove Proposition 2 by contradiction. Suppose on the contrary that the optimal solution to (P1) for Hmode contains curved trajectories among q π m,l and q π m,l+1 , 0 ≤ l ≤ |G m |. Then, we can always replace any curved path the waypoints q π m,l and q π m,l+1 with a line segment, along which the UAV flies with the maximum speed V max , to obtain an alternative trajectory with smaller flying time. Such a replacement will not influence the data collection performance since UAV only collects data when it hovers over the corresponding hovering location. With such a replacement, the flying time decreases and then the corresponding mission completion time decreases, which results in a smaller cost value. Therefore, each UAV u m should fly along the line segment connecting q π m,l and q π m,l+1 with the maximum speed V max , 0 ≤ l ≤ |G m |, which completes the proof. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where G m represents the SN group associated to UAV u m with the cardinality denoted by |G m |. UAV u m will collect data from G m by sequentially flying to the |G m | optimized hovering locations, each for one SN, and collects data from each associated SN only when it is hovering at the corresponding location. A. Problem Reformulation Define xm,k ∈ {0, 1} as the SN-UAV association variable, where xm,k = 1 if SN s k is associated to UAV u m ; otherwise xm,k = 0. Thus we have M m=1 xm,k = 1, ∀k, and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Algorithm 3 repeat 3 :</head><label>33</label><figDesc>Successive optimization algorithm for (P11) 1: Initialize {α 0 m,k [n]}, {y 0 m,k [n]}, {q 0 m [n]}, and let r = 0; 2: Solve the convex problem (P13) for the given local points α r m,k [n], y r m,k [n], q r m [n], and denote the optimal solution as α</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>T , initialize {q 0 m [n]} with two-cases min-max m-TSP solution proposed in Section IV-C. Given {q 0 m [n]}, initialize {α 0 m [n]} by solving LP problem (P15).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Optimized UAV trajectory with different SN energy budget Ē. The triangle denotes the initial and final UAV locations, and the circles denote the optimized hovering locations for data collection.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>(b) Ē = 1 Fig. 2 .Fig. 3 .</head><label>123</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Optimized wake-up scheduling with different SN energy budget Ē. The vertical lines denote the mission completion time for different modes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>3 Fig. 5 .</head><label>35</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.Convergence behaviour of the proposed successive optimization algorithms.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig.6. Optimized UAV trajectories for the four-UAV system with different SN energy budget Ē. The triangle denotes the initial and final UAV locations, and the circles denote the optimized hovering locations for data collection.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 7 .Fig. 8 .</head><label>78</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Optimized wake-up scheduling for the four-UAV system with different SN energy budget Ē. The vertical lines denote the mission completion time for different UAVs and modes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Cheng</head><label></label><figDesc>Zhan received the B.Eng. and Ph.D. degrees in Computer Science from the School of Computer Science, University of Science and Technology of China, Anhui, China, in 2006 and 2011 respectively. He is currently an associate professor with the School of Computer and Information Science, Southwest University, China. His research interests include unmanned aerial vehicle communications, multimedia communications, wireless sensor networks, and network coding. He served as a TPC Member for the IEEE ICC, WCNC, IWCMC, and UIC. Yong Zeng (S'12-M'14) is with the National Mobile Communications Research Laboratory, School of Information Science and Engineering, Southeast University, China. He received the Bachelor of Engineering (First-Class Honours) and Ph.D. degrees from Nanyang Technological University, Singapore, in 2009 and 2014, respectively. From 2013 to 2018, he was a Research Fellow and Senior Research Fellow at the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, National University of Singapore. From 2018 to 2019, he was a Lecturer at the School of Electrical and Information Engineering, the University of Sydney, Australia. Dr. Zeng is the recipient of the Australia Research Council (ARC) Discovery Early Career Researcher Award (DECRA), the 2018 IEEE Communications Society Asia-Pacific Outstanding Young Researcher Award, 2017 IEEE Communications Society Heinrich Hertz Prize Paper Award, 2017 IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications Best Reviewer, 2015 and 2017 IEEE Wireless Communications Letters Exemplary Reviewer. He served as a Leading Guest Editor of IEEE Wireless Communications on "Integrating UAVs into 5G and Beyond" and China Communications on "Network-Connected UAV Communications". He was the workshop co-chair for ICC 2018, ICC2019 workshop on UAV communications, the tutorial speaker for Globecom 2018 and ICC 2019 tutorials on UAV communications.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. Otherwise, τ h π m,l can be decreased with other variables fixed, then the total hovering time T h m decreases and all other constraints are still satisfied, which results in the decrease of the objective value. Define μ max</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">(T f m + T h m ) as the maximum mission completion time among all UAVs and substitute τ h m π m,l with Sπ m,l</cell></row><row><cell>B log 2 1+</cell><cell>γπ m,l H 2 + qπ m,l -wπ m,l</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TWC.2019.2930190, IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications 6 SCA technique can be applied, where the original function is approximated by a more tractable function at a given local point in each iteration. Note that although the LHS in (</figDesc><table /><note><p>1536-1276 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>3 )<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, where L is number of iterations. By combining the solution of the first subproblem, the overall algorithm for problem (P2) is summarized in Algorithm 2. : Initialize the hovering locationsq 0 π m,l = w π m,l , 1 ≤ l ≤ |G m | for group G m , 1 ≤ m ≤ M ; 3:Obtain the optimized hovering locations {q π m,l } for each UAV with Algorithm 1;</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">Algorithm 2 Overall algorithm for problem (P2)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4: Obtain</cell><cell>hovering Sπ m,l</cell><cell>time</cell><cell>τ h π m,l</cell><cell>=</cell></row><row><cell>B log 2 1+</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>1: Solve (P4) with min-max m-TSP method to obtain SN-UAV association {x m,k }, and serving order {Γ m }, 1 ≤ m ≤ M ; 2γπ m,l H 2 + qπ m,l -wπ m,l 2</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TWC.2019.2930190, IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>M m=1</cell><cell>Tm 0</cell><cell>x m,k (t)B log 2 1 +</cell><cell>γ k H 2 + qm(t)-w k</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>dt</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>S k</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">≥ η, ∀k.</cell><cell>(32)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>To tackle such</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">difficulty, the following optimization problem is introduced</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">first with any given time duration T :</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(P8) :</cell><cell>m a x</cell></row></table><note><p>{qm(t)},{x m,k (t)},{Tm},η η s.t. (7) -(9), (11) -(13), T m ≤ T, ∀m, (31) 1536-1276 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>As the time horizon increases to T such that the time interval becomes t ∈ [0, T ], a feasible solution to (P8) with period T , i.e., {{q m (t)}, {x m,k (t)}, { Tm }} can be constructed by letting Tm = T , qm (t ) = q *</figDesc><table><row><cell>*  m (t)}, {x  *  m,k (t)}, m }, t ∈ [0, T ]. m (t ), and {T  *  xm,k (t ) = x</cell></row></table><note><p>* m,k (t ) when t ≤ T * m , and qm</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TWC.2019.2930190, IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications</figDesc><table><row><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>M</cell></row><row><cell>m=1</cell></row></table><note><p><p>)</p>1536-1276 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Note that problem (P11) is still non-convex due to the nonconvex constraints in (46) with coupled variables {q m [n]} and {α m,k [n]}, which is difficult to be directly solved in general. To tackle such issue, we first introduce the slack variables {y m,k [n]}, and then we have</figDesc><table><row><cell>(P12) :</cell><cell>m a x</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>{qm[n]},{α m,k [n]},{y m,k [n]},η η s.t. (43) -(45), (</p>47</p>) -(49),</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>12 s 2 s 3 s 6 s 17 s 7 s 11 s 4 s 8 s 19 s 14 s 13 s 15 s 16 s 20 s 1 s 5 s 9 s 18 12 s 2 s 3 s 6 s 17 s 7 s 11 s 4 s 8 s 19 s 14 s 13 s 15 s 16 s 20 s 1 s 5 s 9 s 18</figDesc><table><row><cell>Fmode</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hmode</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Timeline (s) 100 s 10 s (a) Ē = 0.4 Joule 0 50 150</cell><cell>200</cell></row><row><cell>Fmode</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hmode</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>s 10 s</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>0</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>200</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Timeline (s)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TWC.2019.2930190, IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>250</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Hmode</cell></row><row><cell>Mission completion time (seconds)</cell><cell>50 100 150 200</cell><cell>Fmode</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SN energy budget Ē (Joule) 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 0</cell><cell>1.1 1.2</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Fig. 4. Mission completion time versus SN energy budget Ē with the two</cell></row><row><cell>modes.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>1536-1276 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TWC.2019.2930190, IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications Obviously, (59) is feasible only if BE k P k +Pc log 2 1 + γ k</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">≤ B log 2 1 +</cell><cell cols="2">γ k H 2</cell><cell>M m=1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>T</cell><cell>x m,k (t)dt</cell></row><row><cell>≤</cell><cell cols="2">BE k P k + P c</cell><cell cols="4">log 2 1 +</cell><cell>γ k H 2 .</cell><cell>(58)</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">On the other hand, if constraints in (10) are satisfied at the</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">same time, then we have</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>M</cell><cell cols="3">Tm</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">S k ≤</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">x m,k (t)R m,k (t)dt</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>m=1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>≤</cell><cell cols="3">BE k P k + P c</cell><cell cols="2">log 2 1 +</cell><cell>γ k H 2 , ∀k.</cell><cell>(59)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>H 2</cell></row></table><note><p>1536-1276 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under Grant 61702426 and Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities under Grant XDJK2019C084.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Survey of important issues in UAV communication networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vaszkun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Surveys Tuts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1123" to="1152" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<pubPlace>2nd Quart</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wireless communications with unmanned aerial vehicles: opportunities and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Accessing from the sky: a tutorial on UAV communications for 5G and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>arxiv.org/abs/1903.05289</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted to Proceedings of the IEEE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple moving targets surveillance based on a cooperative network for multi-UAV</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Guizani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-04">Apr. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flight time minimization of UAV for data collection over wireless sensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Select. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1942" to="1954" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-09">Sep. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An optimal wake-up scheduling algorithm for minimizing energy consumption while limiting maximum delay in a mesh sensor network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kapchits</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Trans. Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="570" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-04">Apr. 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating the energy sink-hole problem in connected k-covered wireless sensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ammari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2729" to="2742" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-11">Nov. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy-efficient data collection in UAV enabled wireless sensor network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Wireless Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-06">Jun. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overcoming endurance issue: UAV-enabled communications with proactive caching</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Select. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1231" to="1244" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-06">Jun. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scheduling method for solving successive contentions of heterogeneous periodic flows based on mathematical formulation in Multi-Hop WSNs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tanigawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tode</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Sensors J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9021" to="9033" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-11-01">1 Nov, 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Throughput maximization for UAVenabled mobile relaying systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4983" to="4996" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-12">Dec. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy-efficient UAV communication with trajectory optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3747" to="3760" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-06">Jun. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deployment and trajectory optimization of UAVs: A quantization theory approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Koyuncu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shabanighazikelayeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Seferoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8531" to="8546" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-12">Dec. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Joint trajectory and communication design for Multi-UAV enabled wireless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2109" to="2121" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-03">Mar. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Priority-based data gathering framework in UAV-assisted wireless sensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Say</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Inata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shimamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Sensors J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5785" to="5794" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-07">Jul. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mobile unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) for energy-efficient internet of things communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mozaffari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Saad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Debbah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7574" to="7589" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-11">Nov. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Powerefficient communication in UAV-aided wireless sensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Commun. Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1264" to="1267" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-06">Jun. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trajectory design for distributed estimation in UAV enabled wireless sensor network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Techn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10155" to="10159" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-10">Oct. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy minimization for wireless communication with rotary-wing UAV</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2329" to="2345" />
			<date type="published" when="2019-04">Apr. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wireless communication using unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs): Optimal transport theory for hover time optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mozaffari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Saad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Debbah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8052" to="8066" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-12">Dec. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trajectory design for completion time minimization in UAV-enabled multicasting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2233" to="2246" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-04">Apr. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CVX: MATLAB software for disciplined convex programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://cvxr.com/cvx" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The multiple traveling salesman problem: an overview of formulations and solution procedures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bektas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Omega</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Competition-based neural network for the multiple traveling salesmen problem with minmax objective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Somhom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Modares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Enkawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers and Operations Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="407" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Globally optimal energy-efficient power control and receiver design in wireless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zappone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bjornson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sanguinetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jorswieck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2844" to="2859" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-06">Jun. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Convex Optimization: Cambridge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Vandenberghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>U.K.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UAV-enabled radio access network: multi-mode communication and trajectory design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Signal Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5269" to="5284" />
			<date type="published" when="2018-10">Oct. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
