<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Managing Multigranular Unbalanced Hesitant Fuzzy Linguistic Information in Multiattribute Large-Scale Group Decision Making: A Linguistic Distribution-Based Approach</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Zhen</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<email>zhen.zhang@dlut.edu.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wenyu</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Luis</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
							<email>luis.martinez@ujaen.es</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yuan</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Eco-nomics and Management</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Dalian University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>116024</postCode>
									<settlement>Dalian</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Jáen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>23071</postCode>
									<settlement>Jáen</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Managing Multigranular Unbalanced Hesitant Fuzzy Linguistic Information in Multiattribute Large-Scale Group Decision Making: A Linguistic Distribution-Based Approach</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6051EEA2D7FE54FB41F540EF0D1DB687</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TFUZZ.2019.2949758</idno>
					<note type="submission">This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TFUZZ.2019.2949758, IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems received XX-XX-XXXX; revised XX-XX-XXXX; accepted XX-XX-XXXX. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TFUZZ.2019.2949758, IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.3" ident="GROBID" when="2023-07-28T16:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>group decision making (GDM)</term>
					<term>large-scale GDM</term>
					<term>hesitant fuzzy linguistic term set</term>
					<term>unbalanced linguistic term set</term>
					<term>linguistic distribution assessment</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>With the increase of technological and societal demands, more and more decision makers are involved in the process of group decision making which is called large-scale group decision making (LGDM). For an LGDM problem with linguistic information, it is common that different decision makers tend to provide linguistic assessments defined on multigranular linguistic term sets due to the difference in knowledge and culture background and that hesitant fuzzy linguistic term sets (HFLTSs) are used by decision makers to model the hesitancy of their assessments. This paper proposes first an algorithm to represent a linguistic distribution assessment (LDA) using a hesitant linguistic distribution (HLD). Two other algorithms are then proposed to transform an unbalanced HFLTS into a balanced LDA and to transform a balanced LDA into an unbalanced LDA, respectively. An approach is then proposed to deal with multiattribute LGDM problems with multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information based on these algorithms. In the proposed approach, all unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information is transformed into LDAs defined on a balanced linguistic term set and then an LDA-based clustering algorithm is devised to cluster decision makers. Based on the clustering result, decision makers' linguistic distribution decision matrices are further fused to obtain collective assessments of alternatives. In order to provide linguistic results easy to understand for decision makers, all LDAs of alternatives are represented by HLDs defined on each decision maker's initial linguistic term set. Finally, an example for the selection of subway lines is used to demonstrate the proposed approach.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>G Roup decision making (GDM) is a process during which a group of decision makers express their assessments over alternatives to obtain a final solution of a decision making problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. The resolution of a typical GDM problem usually involves two processes, i.e., the consensus process and the selection process <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. The consensus process aims to help decision makers achieve a satisfactory level of agreement about their assessments over alternatives, while the selection process is achieved by fusing different decision makers' opinions to obtain a collective assessment of alternatives and hence a ranking of alternatives. In the literature, different proposals have been devoted to the studies of consensus process and selection process in GDM <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>For classical GDM problems, it is usually assumed that only a small group of decision makers is involved in the decision making process. With the increase of technological development and societal demands, such as social networks, egroup shopping and e-democracy, more and more individuals can take part in the decision making process <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, which makes GDM activities become more and more complex due to the large group of decision makers and the individual differences among decision makers in knowledge and culture background. Such GDM problems are usually called largescale GDM (LGDM) problems. Currently, LGDM faces four main trends, including <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> clustering methods in LGDM <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, (2) consensus reaching processes in LGDM <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, (3) selection models and methods in LGDM <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref> LGDM support systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>.</p><p>These studies have significantly advanced the studies of LGDM, among which LGDM with linguistic information has attracted attention from scholars because in linguistic LGDM problems, decision makers usually provide their assessments using linguistic expressions instead of exact numerical numbers due to the fuzziness and impreciseness of their knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> that is close to real world situations. To achieve the goal of linguistic LGDM, the techniques of computing with words (CW) are usually used to fuse linguistic information <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, including the membership degree-based model <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> , ordinal scale model <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, the 2-tuple linguistic model <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, the type-2 fuzzy set-based model <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> and the numerical scale model <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, to name a few; in which the linguistic 2-tuple model stand out because of its characteristics and computational model <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. Based on these CW techniques, different models and approaches have been developed to deal with linguistic LGDM problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</p><p>Although previous models and approaches are effective for linguistic LGDM problems, there are still some challenges that need to be tackled.</p><p>(1) Most of current linguistic LGDM problems usually assume that decision makers will provide their linguistic assessments using a simple linguistic term. For some complex linguistic LGDM problems with high uncertainty, it is possible that decision makers may need more elaborated expressions when providing their assessments <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. In this case, hesitant fuzzy linguistic term sets (HFLTSs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, which allow decision makers to express linguistic assessments using some consecutive linguistic terms, may be a good choice for modelling such situations <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. However, in the literature, LGDM problems with HFLTSs have not been extensively studied so far.</p><p>(2) Linguistic LGDM problems usually involve a large group of decision makers with different knowledge and backgrounds, which implies that multigranular linguistic information can be used by decision makers. For instance, in practical decision making problems, a decision maker may provide HFLTSs based on a linguistic term set S<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> = {s 1 0 : poor, s 1  1 : slightly poor, s 1 2 : fair, s 1 3 : slightly good, s 1 4 : good} and another decision maker may provide HFLTSs using a linguistic term set S 2 = {s 2 0 : very poor, s 2 1 : poor, s 2 2 : slightly poor, s 2  3 : fair, s 2 4 : slightly good, s 2 5 : good, s 2 6 : very good}. In this case, fuzzy granular approaches may be a good choice to manage multigranular linguistic information, such as the linguistic hierarchy model <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, the type-2 fuzzy set based models <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, and ordinal models based on discrete fuzzy numbers <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. Moreover, in most situations, decision makers tend to use a linguistic term set which is uniformly and symmetrically distributed. However, in some situations, decision makers need to use linguistic term sets that are not uniformly and symmetrically distributed, i.e., the unbalanced linguistic term set <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>. For instance, in the grading system, the number of linguistic terms on the right of the midterm is larger than that on the left. Although some studies have been conducted to deal with GDM problems with unbalanced HFLTSs <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, there are fewer studies that focus on LGDM with multigranular unbalanced HFLTSs.</p><p>(3) In the resolution process of a linguistic LGDM problem, linguistic distribution assessments (LDAs) have been proved as an effective tool to keep the maximum information of decision makers in the initial stages of the decision making process <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. However, the aggregation of LDAs is also an LDA in which the symbolic proportions of linguistic terms are dispersedly distributed which makes hard to provide interpretable linguistic results to decision makers.</p><p>Motivated by these three challenges, the aim of this paper is to develop some novel models and algorithms to manage multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information in LGDM. This research first develops an algorithm to represent an LDA using a hesitant linguistic distribution (HLD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, which can provide interpretable results regarding an LDA. To fuse multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information, it is developed two algorithms to transform an unbalanced HFLTS into a balanced LDA and to transform a balanced LDA into an unbalanced LDA, respectively based on the 2-tuple linguistic model <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. Subsequently, an approach is proposed to deal with multiattribute LGDM problems with multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information. In the proposed approach, all multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information is transformed into LDAs defined on a balanced linguistic term set and then an LDAbased clustering algorithm is devised to cluster decision makers, based on which the collective assessments of each cluster are calculated. A proportion and normalized accuracy index induced ordered weighted averaging (PA-IOWA) operator is further proposed to fuse each cluster's linguistic distribution decision matrix. The collective assessments of alternatives are obtained by aggregating all attribute values for each alternative. Based on the dominance degree-based ranking method, all alternatives are ranked. Finally, the collective assessments are represented by HLDs defined on each decision maker's initial linguistic term set to provide interpretable results.</p><p>This paper contributes the area of CW and GDM from the following aspects. First, we discuss the relationship between an LDA and an HLD, and the relationships among multigranular unbalanced linguistic information and balanced LDAs, and develop some algorithms to achieve the transformation among different formats of linguistic information 1 , which lays a good foundation to manage multigranular linguistic information in practical GDM problems. Second, an approach to LGDM with multigranular unbalanced HFLTSs is developed based on the proposed CW methodology, which can both preserve the maximum information of decision makers and provide interpretable linguistic results by using the HLDs for practical LGDM problems.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. Section II revises some preliminaries related to the topic of this paper. In Section III, an algorithm is proposed to represent an LDA using an HLD. Followed by this, it is proposed two algorithms to achieve the transformation between unbalanced linguistic information and a balanced LDA in Section IV. Subsequently, an approach to multiattribute LGDM with multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information is developed in Section V and a numerical example is presented to demonstrate the proposed approach in Section VI. Eventually, some conclusions are drawn in Section VII.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PRELIMINARIES</head><p>In this section, some preliminaries are revised. In subsection II-A, the 2-tuple linguistic representation model is introduced. In subsection II-B, some basic knowledge about unbalanced linguistic term set and numerical scale model is provided. Finally, some related work about HFLTSs, LDAs and HLDs is introduced in subsection II-C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. 2-tuple linguistic model</head><p>Let S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g } denote a linguistic term set with odd cardinality, the element s i of which represents the i-th linguistic term in S, and g+1 is the cardinality of the linguistic term set S. Moreover, for the linguistic term set S, we assume that the midterm representing an assessment of "approximately 0.5", with the rest of the terms being placed uniformly and symmetrically around it. The linguistic term set should satisfy the following characteristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>: <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> The set is ordered:s i &gt; s j , if i &gt; j; (2) There is a negation operator: Neg(s i ) = s j , such that j = g -i.</p><p>Herrera and Martínez <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> proposed the 2-tuple linguistic representation model based on the concept of symbolic translation, which is defined as follows.</p><p>Definition 1. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> Let S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g } be a linguistic term set, β ∈ [0, g] be a value representing the result of a symbolic aggregation operation and S = S × [-0.5, 0.5), then the 2-tuple that expresses the equivalent information to β is obtained by</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">∆ : [0, g] → S ∆(β) = (s k , α),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>with k = round(β), α = β -k, where round(•) is the usual round operation, s k has the closest index label to β, and α is the value of symbolic translation.</p><p>Definition 2. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> Let S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g } be a linguistic term set and (s k , α) be a linguistic 2-tuple, there exists a function ∆ -1 , which can transform a linguistic 2-tuple into its equivalent numerical value β ∈ [0, g]. The transformation function is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">∆ -1 : S → [0, g] ∆ -1 (s k , α) = k + α = β. (<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">)</formula><p>Based on the above definitions, a linguistic term can be considered as a linguistic 2-tuple by adding the value 0 to it as symbolic translation, i.e. s k ∈ S ⇒ (s k , 0).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Unbalanced linguistic information and numerical scale model</head><p>For actual decision making problems, decision makers may provide linguistic terms from linguistic term sets which are not uniformly and symmetrically distributed, i.e., unbalanced linguistic term set. The modelling of unbalanced linguistic information was initially proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> and extended by linguistic hierarchies in <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. Usually, an unbalanced linguistic term set S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g } with an odd granularity g+1 has a minimum label, a maximum label and a central label, and the remaining labels are non-uniformly and non-symmetrically distributed around the central one on both left and right lateral sets, where</p><p>• S L is called the left lateral set, which contains all the labels less than the central label. • S C is called the central set, which just contains the central label.</p><p>• S R is called the right lateral set, which contains all the labels greater than the central label. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, it is developed a linguistic computational model to represent the labels of an unbalanced linguistic term set through the levels of a linguistic hierarchy and to compute with words based on the 2-tuple linguistic representation model. Subsequently, different extensions of unbalanced linguistic term sets are proposed, such as the numerical scale model proposed by Dong et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>, it was also proved the equivalence between the linguistic hierarchy based computational model and the numerical scale model for dealing with unbalanced linguistic information. To make this paper selfcontained, some basic knowledge of numerical scale model is revised as follows. Definition 3. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> Let S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g } be a linguistic term set and R be the set of real numbers. The function: N S : S → R is defined as a numerical scale of S, and N S(s i ) is called the numerical scale of s i . Definition 4. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> Let S, S and N S be defined as before. For each (s i , α) ∈ S, the numerical scale N S is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">N S((s i , α)) = N S(s i ) + α(N S(s i+1 ) -N S(s i )) α ≥ 0 N S(s i ) + α(N S(s i ) -N S(s i+1 )) α &lt; 0.<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Definition 5. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> Let N S be an ordered numerical scale, i.e., N S(</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">s i ) &lt; N S(s i+1 ). ∀y ∈ [N S(s 0 ), N S(s g )], if N S(s i ) ≤ y ≤ N S(s i+1 ), then N S -1 (y) =        si, y -N S(si) N S(si+1) -N S(si) , y &lt; N S * (si) si+1, y -N S(si+1) N S(si+1) -N S(si) , y ≥ N S * (si),<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">N S * (s i ) = N S(s i ) + N S(s i+1 ) 2 , i = 0, 1, . . . , g -1.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. HFLTS, LDA and HLD</head><p>When providing linguistic assessments over alternatives, decision makers sometimes may have some hesitancy. To model such situations, Rodríguez et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> proposed the concept of HFLTS. Definition 6. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> Let S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g } be a linguistic term set. An HFLTS H S on S is an ordered finite subset of consecutive linguistic terms in S.</p><p>Remark 1. Later on, Rodríguez et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> proposed the use of HFLTS and context-free grammars to build in a formal way Comparative Linguistic Expressions (CLEs) like at most, at least, between, etc. Such expressions are more flexible than a single linguistic label and closer to the expressions provided by human beings in real world decision problems. These CLEs provide an important improvement regarding flexibility to decision makers when eliciting preferences, together a formalization for generating expressions closer human beings' expressions <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</p><p>Remark 2. Clearly, if S is a balanced linguistic term set, H S is called a balanced HFLTS; if S is an unbalanced linguistic term set, H S is called an unbalanced HFLTS.</p><p>For a balanced linguistic term set, Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> defined the LDA and its expectations. Definition 7. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> Let S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g } denote a balanced linguistic term set and β t be the symbolic proportion of s t , where s t ∈ S, β t ≥ 0, t = 0, 1, . . . , g and g t=0 β t = 1, then an assessment m = {⟨s t , β t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g} is called a balanced LDA of S, and the expectation of m is defined as a linguistic 2-tuple E(m), where E(m) = ∆ g t=0 tβ t .</p><p>Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> defined the inaccuracy degree of a balanced LDA based on the concept of information entropy. Based on this work, it is defined the normalized inaccuracy degree of a balanced LDA. Definition 8. Let m = {⟨s t , β t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g} be a balanced LDA of a linguistic term set S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g }, where s t ∈ S, β t ≥ 0, t = 0, 1, . . . , g and g t=0 β t = 1. The normalized inaccuracy degree of m is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">T (m) = - 1 log 2 (g + 1) g t=0 β t log 2 β t .</formula><p>Subsequently, for an unbalanced linguistic term set, Dong et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> defined the LDA with interval symbolic proportions. Based on Refs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>, an unbalanced LDA is defined based on the numerical scale model as follows.</p><p>Definition 9. Let S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g } be an unbalanced linguistic term set, then m = {⟨s t , β t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g} is called an unbalanced LDA of S, where s t ∈ S, β t ≥ 0 is the symbolic proportion of s t , t = 0, 1, . . . , g and</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">g t=0 β t = 1. The expectation of m is defined by E(m) = N S -1 ( g t=0 β t N S(s t )).</formula><p>Given a collection of LDAs, the weighted averaging operator is defined as: Definition 10. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> Let {m 1 , m 2 , . . . , m n } be a collection of LDAs of S, where m i = {⟨s t , β i t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g}, i = 1, 2, . . . , n, and w = (w 1 , w 2 , . . . , w n ) T be an associated weighting vector that satisfies w i ≥ 0 and n i=1 w i = 1, then the weighted averaging operator of {m 1 , m 2 , . . . , m n } is defined as DAWA w (m 1 , m 2 , . . . , m n ) = {⟨s t , β t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g}, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> where β t = n i=1 w i β i t , t = 0, 1, . . . , g. Recently, by combing the concept of HFLTSs and LDAs, Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> proposed the concept of a complete HLD and an incomplete HLD. In this paper, only the concept of a normalized complete HLD is provided.</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Definition 11. [45] Let S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g } be a linguistic term set, then M = {⟨H S i , β H S i ⟩|H S i ∈ H S } is called a normalized complete HLD of S, where H S is the set of all LDA defined on S , β H S i ≥ 0 is the symbolic proportion of H S i , ∀H S i ∈ H S and H S i ∈H S β H S i = 1.</formula><p>For simplicity, a normalized complete HLD is called an HLD in this paper.</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Remark 3. If S is a balanced linguistic term set, M = {⟨H S i , β H S i ⟩|H S i ∈ H S } is called a balanced HLD; if S is an unbalanced linguistic term set, M = {⟨H S i , β H S i ⟩|H S i ∈ H S } is called an unbalanced HLD.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. REPRESENTING AN LDA BY USING AN HLD</head><p>Here it is discussed the representation of an LDA by using an HLD to provide results easy to understand.</p><p>Given a collection of LDAs, if an aggregation operator is applied, the aggregation result is also an LDA. For such an aggregation result, one question is how to provide more intuitively interpretable results for decision makers. Let us consider the following LDA m = {⟨s 0 , 0.24⟩, ⟨s 1 , 0.35⟩, ⟨s 3 , 0.15⟩, ⟨s 4 , 0.26⟩} defined on S = {s 0 , s 1 , s 2 , s 3 , s 4 }, which is obtained by some aggregation operators of LDAs. As all linguistic terms in S except s 2 have non-zero symbolic proportions, i.e., the symbolic proportions are dispersedly assigned to each linguistic term, it is difficult to have an interpretable intuitively linguistic result. One possible solution is to represent the LDA using an HFLTS which supports the linguistic distribution assessment most with an accurate constraint, see the maximum support degree model (MSDM) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>. In what follows, the MSDM is introduced in brief.</p><p>Let m = {⟨s t , α t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g} be an LDA defined on a linguistic term set S = {s 0 , s 1 , . . . , s g }, then the HFLTS H that most supports m with an accurate constraint #(H) ≤ N is obtained by solving the following model:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">max H D(H, m) = st∈H α t s.t. #(H) ≤ N H ∈ H S , (<label>6</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">)</formula><p>where N is the maximum number of simple linguistic terms that can be used to represent m using H (also called accuracy degree of an HFLTS in <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>), H is an HFLTS defined on S such that #(H) ≤ N and D(H, m) is the degree to which H supports m.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>, the model ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">6</ref>) was transformed into a mixed 0-1 linear programming model. By solving the model, the HFLTS H is obtained. In what follows, an alternative method is developed to derive an HFLTS H that most supports an LDA m.</p><p>Given an N for S, the set of possible HFLTSs that can be used to represent m can be defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">H S N = {H ∈ H S |#(H) ≤ N, ∀s t ∈ H, α t &gt; 0}.<label>(7)</label></formula><p>Remark 4. In Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, the condition ∀s t ∈ H, α t &gt; 0 ensures that all simple linguistic terms in a possible HFLTS that is used to represent m should have a positive support degree to m. Therefore, the conditions in Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">7</ref>) are stricter than that in Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>.</p><p>One can find that the number of elements in H S N are not very large. Hence, to find H, it would be enumerated all possible HFLTSs and then calculate the support degree D(H, m) for each possible HFLTS. By selecting the HFLTS with the maximum D(H, m) value, H can be determined by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">H = arg max H∈H S N st∈H α t . (<label>8</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">)</formula><p>In the above example, if the maximum number of simple terms that are used for an HFLTS is set as N = 3, by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">8</ref>), the HFLTS that supports m most can be obtained as H = {s 0 , s 1 } and the support degree is 0.59. However, by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">6</ref>), the HFLTS that supports m most can be obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">H = {s 0 , s 1 } or H = {s 0 , s 1 , s 2 }. Obviously, H = {s 0 , s 1 , s 2 }</formula><p>should not be considered as the optimal HFLTS since the symbolic proportion of s 2 is 0. Therefore, Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">8</ref>) refines the results obtained by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">6</ref>).</p><p>Even though either Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">6</ref>) or Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">8</ref>) can yield an HFLTS {s 0 , s 1 } to represent the LDA {⟨s 0 , 0.24⟩, ⟨s 1 , 0.35⟩, ⟨s 3 , 0.15⟩, ⟨s 4 , 0.26⟩} with an accurate constraint N = 3, one can find that the degree to which {s 0 , s 1 } supports the LDA is not quite large because the symbolic proportions in an LDA are dispersedly assigned to all linguistic terms in a linguistic term set which makes that the symbolic proportions cannot be concentrated on some successive linguistic terms, especially for an LDA obtained by the aggregation of some LDAs. In this case, some information is lost. To address this issue, it is developed a new algorithm to represent an LDA comprehensively by using an HLD, which can make full use of the linguistic information in an LDA and avoid the loss of information.</p><p>Keeping in mind that nonzero symbolic proportions should be concentrated on some consecutive linguistic terms, the proposed algorithm tries to discover a collection of HFLTSs with large support degrees to the LDA and output an HLD <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> to provide interpretable results. The basic idea is as follows. First, one can obtain an HFLTS H by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">8</ref>). If the support degree is less than 1, all HFLTSs which contain simple linguistic terms in H are removed from H S N , and then Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">8</ref>) is employed to discover another HFLTS from H S N . Afterwards, the collective support degree is further calculated. The process is repeated until the collective support degree is equal to 1. This process has been developed in Algorithm 1 included in Appendix A of the supplementary materials.</p><p>Remark 5. For the HLD obtained by Algorithm 1, symbolic proportions are assigned to a few disjointed HFLTSs, which guarantees that the result is intuitive and does not result in information loss. Now we consider the above LDA m = {⟨s 0 , 0.24⟩, ⟨s 1 , 0.35⟩, ⟨s 3 , 0.15⟩, ⟨s 4 , 0.26⟩}.</p><p>Let the maximum number of simple terms for an HFLTS be 3, then the set of all possible HFLTSs can be generated as  <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">8</ref>), we have that H = {s 3 , s 4 } has the largest support degree 0.41 (i.e., 0.15+0.26) to m. The collective support degree is 0.59+0.41=1. As a result, the algorithm terminates and an HLD {⟨{s 0 , s 1 }, 0.59⟩, ⟨{s 3 , s 4 }, 0.41⟩} is output to provide interpretable results for m. The meaning of the HLD {⟨{s 0 , s 1 }, 0.59⟩, ⟨{s 3 , s 4 }, 0.41⟩} can be interpreted as follows: for the LDA {⟨s 0 , 0.24⟩, ⟨s 1 , 0.35⟩, ⟨s 3 , 0.15⟩, ⟨s 4 , 0.26⟩}, there are two possible CLEs based on HFLTSs that support it most, i.e., "at most s 1 " and "at least s 3 ", the support degree of "at most s 1 " is 0.59, and the support degree of "at least s 3 " is 0.41.</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">H S N = {{s 0 },</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. TRANSFORMATION BETWEEN UNBALANCED LINGUISTIC INFORMATION AND A BALANCED LDA</head><p>To fuse multigranular unbalanced linguistic information, Dong et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> introduced a function to transform multigranular unbalanced linguistic information into linguistic 2-tuples defined on a balanced linguistic term set.</p><p>For convenience of description, let S B = {s B 0 , s B 1 , . . . , s B g } be a balanced linguistic term set and</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">S (k) = {s k 0 , s k 1 , . . . , s k g(k)</formula><p>} be an unbalanced linguistic term set with a cardinality of g(k)+1. Here, let N S (k) be the numerical scale of</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">S (k) , N S (k) = N S (k) (s k 0 ) and N S (k) = N S (k) (s k g(k)</formula><p>). The following two propositions can transform a linguistic term of an unbalanced linguistic term set into a linguistic 2-tuple defined on S B . Proposition 1. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> Let N S (k) be defined as before and let s k h ∈ S (k) , then the corresponding numerical scale with the normal support [0, g], associated with N S (k) is given by k) , then the corresponding linguistic 2-tuple s B associated with s k h is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">N S (B) (s k h ) = g(N S (k) (s k h ) -N S (k) ) N S (k) -N S (k) . (<label>9</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">) Proposition 2. [39] Let s k h ∈ S (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">s B = ∆(N S (B) (s k h )) = ∆ g(N S (k) (s k h ) -N S (k) ) N S (k) -N S (k) . (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">)</formula><p>According to Proposition 2, an unbalanced linguistic term can be transformed into a linguistic 2-tuple defined on a balanced linguistic term set. Based on Definition 1 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, the following proposition is deduced straightaway. k) , then the corresponding LDA defined on s B associated with s k h is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">Proposition 3. Let s k h ∈ S (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">m h = {⟨s B l h , 1 -β B h ⟩, ⟨s B l h +1 , β B h ⟩}, (<label>11</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">l h = trunc g(N S (k) (s k h ) -N S (k) N S (k) -N S (k) and β B h = N S (B) (s k h ) -l h , h = 0, 1, . .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>. , g(k).</head><p>To fuse multigranular unbalanced HFLTSs, it is necessary to transform them into linguistic expressions defined on the same linguistic term set. In this paper, we try to transform an unbalanced HFLTS into a balanced LDA.</p><p>Let H S (k) = {s k i , s k i+1 , . . . , s k j } be an HFLTS defined on S (k) . By Proposition 3, each s k h ∈ H S (k) can be transformed into an LDA defined on S B , i.e., m h . Considering the importance of each m h , i.e., 1/(j -i+1), these LDAs can be further aggregated into a new LDA by using the DAWA operator. The following definition is given formally. Definition 12. Let H S (k) = {s k i , s k i+1 , . . . , s k j } be an HFLTS defined on S (k) , then it can be transformed into an LDA defined on a balanced linguistic term set S B as</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">m = DAWA w (m i , m i+1 , . . . , m j ),<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">m h = {⟨s B l h , 1 -β B h ⟩, ⟨s B l h +1 , β B</formula><p>h ⟩} is calculated by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">11</ref>), h = i, i + 1, . . . , j and w = (1/(j -i + 1), 1/(j -i + 1), . . . , 1/(j -i + 1)) T . Algorithm 2 is devised to carry out the transformation from an unbalanced HFLTS into a balanced LDA, which is included in Appendix A of the supplementary materials.</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">Example 1. Let H S (k) = {s k 1 , s k 2 , s k 3 } be an HFLTS defined on S (k) = {s k 0 , s k 1 , . . . , s k 4 }</formula><p>and the numerical scales of each linguistic term set be N S (k) </p><formula xml:id="formula_30">(s k 0 ) = 0, N S (k) (s k 1 ) = 0.2, N S (k) (s k 2 ) = 0.5, N S (k) (s k 3 ) = 0.7, N S (k) (s k 4 ) = 1. Now we consider how to transform {s k 1 , s k 2 , s k 3 } into an LDA of a balanced linguistic term set S = {s B 0 , s B 1 , . . . , s B 6 }.</formula><p>The procedure is as follows:</p><p>Step 1: let α t = 0, t = 0, 1, . . . , 6.</p><p>Step 2: let h = 1, then we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">p h = p 1 = 6 × (0.2 - 0)/(1 -0) = 1.2. It follows that l 1 = 1, β B 1 = 1.2 -1 = 0.2. Therefore, we have that α 1 = 0+(1-0.2)/(4-2+1) = 4/15, α 1+1 = α 2 = 0 + 0.2/(4 -2 + 1) = 1/15.</formula><p>Step 3: let h = 2, then we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">p h = p 2 = 6 × (0.5 - 0)/(1 -0) = 3. It follows that l 2 = 3, β B 2 = 3 -3 = 0. Therefore, we have that α 3 = 0 + (1 -0)/(4 -2 + 1) = 1/3, α 3+1 = α 4 = 0 + 0/(4 -2 + 1) = 0.</formula><p>Step 4: let h = 3, then we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">p h = p 3 = 6 × (0.7 - 0)/(1 -0) = 4.2. It follows that l 3 = 4, β B 3 = 4.2 -4 = 0.2. Therefore, we have that α 4 = 0+(1-0.2)/(4-2+1) = 4/15, α 4+1 = α 5 = 0 + 0.2/(4 -2 + 1) = 1/15.</formula><p>Step 5:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">An LDA m = {⟨s B 1 , 4/15⟩, ⟨s B 2 , 1/15⟩, ⟨s B 3 , 1/3⟩, ⟨s B</formula><p>4 , 4/15⟩, ⟨s B 5 , 1/15⟩} can be obtained.</p><p>Once unbalanced HFLTSs are transformed into LDAs defined on a balanced linguistic term set S B , these LDAs can be aggregated by an aggregation operator and the aggregation result is also a balanced LDA. In order to provide interpretable results to decision makers who use an unbalanced linguistic term set, it is also necessary to transform a balanced LDA into an unbalanced LDA. The basic idea is as follows. First, we transform each linguistic term defined on a balanced linguistic term set into an unbalanced LDA and then aggregate these unbalanced LDAs to obtain a new unbalanced LDA. From this perspective, the first problem that needs to be solved is how to transform a balanced linguistic term into an unbalanced LDA. Proposition 4. Let N S (k) be defined as before and s B h ∈ S (B) , then the corresponding numerical scale of s B h associated with N S (k) , denoted by N S (k) (s), is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">N S (k) (s) = ∆ -1 (s B h )(N S (k) -N S (k) ) g + N S (k) , (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">)</formula><p>and N S (k) (s) ∈ [N S (k) , N S (k) ].</p><p>Proof. As s B h ∈ S (B) , by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">∆ -1 (s B h ) = g(N S (k) (s) -N S (k) ) N S (k) -N S (k)</formula><p>.</p><p>Hence</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">∆ -1 (s B h )(N S (k) -N S (k) ) = g(N S (k) (s) -N S (k)</formula><p>), which yields <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>.</p><p>Clearly, N S (k) (s) is a monotonic increasing function of ∆ -1 (s B h ), which belongs to [0, g]. As the function ∆ -1 (s B h ) is monotonic increasing with s B , N S (k) (s B ) is also a monotonic increasing function on s B , i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">N S (k) (s) ≥ N S (k) (s 0 ) = 0(N S (k) -N S (k) ) g + N S (k) = N S (k) , N S (k) (s) ≤ N S (k) (s g ) = g(N S (k) -N S (k) ) g + N S (k) = N S (k) .</formula><p>This completes the proof of Proposition 4.</p><p>By applying the inverse function of numerical scale, the linguistic representation of s B h based on S (k) can be derived as follows.</p><p>Proposition 5. Let s B h ∈ S (B) , then the corresponding linguistic representation of s B h based on S (k) is a linguistic 2-tuple s, where</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">s =    s k i h , α , N S (k) (s) &lt; N S (k) * (s k i h ) s k i h +1 , α -1 , N S (k) (s) ≥ N S (k) * (s k i h ) , (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_41">)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">N S (k) * (s k i h ) = N S (k) (s k i h ) + N S (k) (s k i h +1 ) 2 , N S (k) (s k i h ) ≤ N S (k) (s) ≤ N S (k) (s k i h +1</formula><p>) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">α = ∆ -1 (s B h )(N S (k) -N S (k) ) + g(N S (k) -N S(s k i h )) g(N S(s k i h +1 ) -N S(s k i h )) . (<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_44">)</formula><p>Proof. The proof can be easily derived by applying the inverse function of N S (k) , i.e. N S -1(k) on N S (k) (s).</p><p>Proposition 5 demonstrates that s derived by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_40">14</ref>) is a linguistic 2-tuple which denotes the linguistic information between s k i h and</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">s k i h +1 such that N S (k) (s k i h ) ≤ N S (k) (s) ≤ N S (k) (s k i h +1</formula><p>). Obviously, the linguistic information between s k i h and s k i h +1 can also be denoted by an LDA m = {⟨s k i h , 1 -</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">β k i h ⟩, ⟨s k i h +1 , β k i h } such that N S (k) (s) = N S (k) (E(m)), i.e., ∆ -1 (s B h )(N S (k) -N S (k) ) g + N S (k) = (1 -β k i h ) × N S (k) (s k i h ) + β k i h × N S (k) (s k i h +1 ).<label>(16)</label></formula><p>Solving Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_46">16</ref>) yields that</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">β k i h = ∆ -1 (s B h )(N S (k) -N S (k) ) + g(N S (k) -N S(s k i h )) g(N S(s k i h +1 ) -N S(s k i h )) , (<label>17</label></formula><p>) which is the same as the value of α in Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>.</p><p>Based on the above analysis, the following definition is given.</p><p>Definition 13. Let S (B) = {s B 0 , s B 1 , . . . , s B g } be a balanced linguistic term set, then the equivalent LDA of each s B h defined on an unbalanced linguistic term set</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">S (k) = {s k 0 , s k 1 , . . . , s k g(k) } is denoted by m (k) h = {⟨s k i h , 1 -β k i h ⟩, ⟨s k i h +1 , β k i h ⟩} such that N S (k) (s k i h ) ≤ ∆ -1 (s B h )(N S (k) -N S (k) ) g + N S (k) ≤ N S (k) (s k i h +1</formula><p>) and β k i h is calculated by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_47">17</ref>). Once a linguistic term in a balanced linguistic term set is transformed into an unbalanced LDA, it is easy to transform an balanced LDA into an unbalanced one by aggregating all the transformed unbalanced LDAs. Definition 14. Let m B = {⟨s B h , β B h ⟩|h = 0, 1, . . . , g} be a balanced LDA, then it can be transformed into an LDA defined on an unbalanced linguistic term set</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">S (k) = {s k 0 , s k 1 , . . . , s k g(k) } as m (k) = DAWA w (m (k) 0 , m (k) 1 , . . . , m (k) g ),<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where m In what follows, we try to transform m into an LDA of S (k) using Algorithm 3.</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">(k) h = {⟨s k i h , 1 -β k i h ⟩, ⟨s k i h +1 , β k i h ⟩}</formula><p>Step 1: let α t = 0, t = 0, 1, . . . , 6.</p><p>Step 2: Obviously, Step 4: Let h = 5, then temp = 5×(1-0)/6+0 = 5/6. As N S (k) </p><formula xml:id="formula_51">β B h ̸ = 0 when h = 3, 4, 5. Let h = 3, then temp = 3 × (1 -0)/6 + 0 = 1/2. As N S (k) (s k 2 ) = 0.5 ≤ temp &lt; 0.7 = N S (k) (s k 3 ), we have i h = 2 and β k i h = 3 × (1 -0) + 6(0 -0.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">(s k 3 ) = 0.7 ≤ temp ≤ 1 = N S (k) (s k 4 ), we have i h = 3 and β k i h = 5 × (1 -0) + 6(0 -0.7) 6 × (1 -0.7) = 4/9. Therefore, α 3 = 1/3 + (1 -4/9) × 0.3 = 1/6, α 4 = 0 + 4/9 × 0.3 = 2/15.</formula><p>Step 5: Based on the above results, we can obtain an LDA m = {⟨s k 2 , 11/30⟩, ⟨s k 3 , 1/2⟩, ⟨s B 4 , 2/15⟩}.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. MULTIATTRIBUTE LGDM BASED ON MULTIGRANULAR UNBALANCED HESITANT FUZZY LINGUISTIC INFORMATION</head><p>In order to deal with multiattribute LGDM defined in multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic contexts, a new approach is proposed. The main novelties of the proposed approach are three-fold:</p><p>• This is the first study that can manage multigranular unbalanced HFLTSs in LGDM problems, which makes decision makers provide their linguistic assessments over alternatives more flexibly. • The LDA is used as the aggregation tool to deal with the GDM problem, which can keep the maximum information elicited by decision makers and avoid the loss of information.</p><p>• The collective assessments of alternatives are represented by HLDs defined on decision makers' initial linguistic term sets to provide interpretable results. The multiattribute LGDM problem based on multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information is formulated as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Formulation of the multiattribute LGDM problem</head><p>For convenience, let I = {1, 2, . . . , n}, J = {1, 2, . . . , m} and K = {1, 2, . . . , q}.</p><p>Let A = {A 1 , A 2 , . . . , A n } be a set of alternatives, where A i is the i-th alternative, i ∈ I. In order to select the optimal alternative, a large group of decision makers d 1 , d 2 , . . . , d q provide their assessments over each alternative with respect to some attributes U = {U 1 , U 2 , . . . , U m }, where U j is the j-th attribute, j ∈ J. The weight vector of attributes is denoted by w = (w 1 , w 2 , . . . , w m ) T , where w j is the weight of U j and m j=1 w j = 1, w j ≥ 0, j ∈ J. Due to the uncertainty of decision environment and decision makers' imprecise knowledge, the assessments provided by each decision maker are HFLTSs. Moreover, it is assumed that multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information is used by different decision makers.</p><p>Without loss of generality, denote the unbalanced linguistic term set used by d k by S (k) = {s k 0 , s k 1 , . . . , s k g(k) } and the numerical scale of each linguistic term s k t is denoted by N S (k) (s k t ), t = 0, 1, . . . , g(k). Also, let x k ij be the linguistic assessment over the i-th alternative provided by the k-th decision maker with respect to the j-th attribute, and H S (k) be the set of all HFLTSs defined on S (k) , k ∈ K, then we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">x k ij ∈ H S (k)</formula><p>, i ∈ I, j ∈ J, k ∈ K. Therefore, the decision matrix of each decision maker can be denoted by</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">X k = (x k ij ) n×m =      x k 11 x k 12 • • • x k 1m x k 21 x k 22 • • • x k 2m . . . . . . . . . . . . x k n1 x k n2 • • • x k nm      , k ∈ K.</formula><p>For the previous LGDM problem, it is needed to obtain a solution of the optimal alternative through aggregating the assessments provided by decision makers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. The proposed multiattribute LGDM method</head><p>In this subsection, it is developed an approach to deal with multiattribute LGDM problems with multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information with the use of LDAs. The framework of the proposed approach is demonstrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Specifically, the proposed approach consists the following processes: unification process, clustering process, aggregation and selection process and retranslation process. In what follows, these processes will be detailed. Eqs. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_75">32</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_82">36</ref>)</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. The framework of the proposed approach 1) Unification process: As HFLTSs provided by decision makers are defined on different unbalanced linguistic term sets and the LDA is used as the tool to aggregate decision makers' assessments, it is first needed to transform multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information into LDAs defined on a balanced linguistic term set. Herein, let us assume that the balanced linguistic term set be S (B) = {s B 0 , s B 1 , . . . , s B g }, which is also called the basic linguistic term set.</p><p>By Algorithm 2, each x k ij can be easily transformed into an LDA z k ij = {⟨s B t , α k ij,t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g}, i ∈ I, j ∈ J, k ∈ K. After unification, each initial decision matrix X k is transformed into an LDA decision matrix, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">Z k = (z k ij ) n×m =      z k 11 z k 12 • • • z k 1m z k 21 z k 22 • • • z k 2m . . . . . . . . . . . . z k n1 z k n2 • • • z k nm      , k ∈ K.</formula><p>2) Clustering process: For LGDM problems, it is usually necessary to cluster decision makers based on decision matrices such that decision makers in the same cluster are similar with each other while decision makers in different clusters are dissimilar with each other. In the literature, different clustering algorithms have been proposed. The fuzzy c-means clustering algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>, which assigns each object with a membership degree to each cluster by calculating the distance between each object and the corresponding cluster center, is one of the most widely used algorithm to detect clusters. In this paper, an LDA-based clustering algorithm is devised based on the FCM algorithm.</p><p>The basic process of the proposed clustering algorithm can be illustrated as follows.</p><p>First, let the iteration number l be 0 and generate the cluster centers of the l-th iteration (denoted by some LDA decision matrices) randomly. Assume that the number of clusters is N and let each cluster center's decision matrix be Z r,0 = (z r,0 ij ) n×m , then the following conditions should be satisfied: z r,0 ij = {⟨s B t , β r,0 ij,t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g} such that g t=0 β r,0 ij,t = 1, β r,0 ij,t ≥ 0, t = 0, 1, . . . , g, i ∈ I, j ∈ j, r = 1, 2, . . . , N . After that, the membership degree to which a decision maker belongs to a cluster is calculated by Definitions 15 and 16.</p><p>Definition 15. Let Z r,l = (z r,l ij ) n×m be the cluster center matrix for the cluster C r,l at the l-th iteration , where z r,l ij = {⟨s B t , β r,l ij,t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g} is an LDA defined on S B , then the Minkowski distance between Z k and Z r,l is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">dis(Z k , Z r,l ) = 1 mng n i=1 m j=1 |E(z k ij ) -E(z r,l ij )| λ 1/λ =   1 mng n i=1 m j=1 g t=0 t(α k ij,t -β r,l ij,t ) λ   1/λ , k ∈ K, r = 1, 2, . . . , N, (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_57">)</formula><p>where λ &gt; 0. In particular, if λ = 2, then dis(Z k , Z r,l ) is the Euclidean distance, which will be used in the LDA-based clustering algorithm.</p><p>Definition 16. Let Z k and Z r,l = (z r,l ij ) n×m be defined as before, then the membership degree to which d k belongs to the cluster C r,l at iteration l is calculated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">µ(d k , C r,l ) = (1/dis(Z k , Z r,l )) 1/(b-1) N u=1 (1/dis(Z k , Z r,l )) 1/(b-1) , k ∈ K, r = 1, 2, . . . , N, (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_59">)</formula><p>where b is the fuzziness degree of clusters, i.e., the larger the value of b, the fuzzier the cluster. Usually the value of b is set as 2.</p><p>Based on the membership degrees, the decision matrices of the updated cluster centers can be further calculated by Definition 17. Definition 17. Let Z k and µ(d k , C r,l ) be defined as before, then the decision matrices of the updated cluster centers are calculated as Z r,l+1 = (z r,l+1 ij ) n×m , where z r,l+1 ij = {⟨s B t , β r,l+1 ij,t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g} and</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">β r,l+1 ij,t = q k=1 µ(d k , C r,l )α k ij,t q k=1 µ(d k , C r,l ) , t = 0, 1, . . . , g, i ∈ I, j ∈ J, r = 1, 2, . . . , N. (<label>21</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_61">)</formula><p>Let l = l + 1, then the membership degree to which each decision maker d k belongs to the updated cluster center C r,l can be calculated by Definitions 15 and 16. Afterwards, the variation of membership degrees between two consecutive iterations can be further calculated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">var l = 1 N q q k=1 N r=1 |µ(d k , C r,l ) -µ(d k , C r,l-1 )|,<label>(22)</label></formula><p>where µ(d k , C r,l-1 ) and µ(d k , C r,l ) are the membership de- grees that d k belongs to C r,l-1 and C r,l , respectively, k ∈ K, r = 1, 2, . . . , N . If var l is larger than a predefined threshold ε, then the iteration will continue. Otherwise, the iteration will terminate and the decision maker d k will be assigned to the cluster C r such that µ(d k , C r,l ) = max r {µ(d k , C r,l )}. Based on the analysis, the LDA-based clustering algorithm is shown in Algorithm 4 and included in Appendix A of the supplementary materials.</p><p>By implementing Algorithm 4, each decision maker can be assigned to a cluster, denoted by C r , r = 1, 2, . . . , N .</p><p>3) Aggregation and selection process: After the clustering process, it is needed to aggregate decision matrices provided by decision makers into a collective one. First, we calculate the decision matrix of each cluster C r , r = 1, 2, . . . , N . For convenience, let Zr = (z r ij ) n×m be the decision matrix of the r-th cluster, where zr ij = {⟨s B t , ᾱr ij,t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g}, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">ᾱr ij,t = 1 |C r | d k ∈C r α k ij,t , t = 0, 1, . . . , g, i ∈ I, j ∈ J, r = 1, 2, . . . , N.<label>(23)</label></formula><p>In order to aggregate all clusters' decision matrices, it is needed to determine the weight of each cluster. In this section, a novel approach which considers both the size of each cluster and the accuracy of each cluster's decision matrix is proposed. The basic ideas are as follows: 1) If a cluster consists of more decision makers, then a larger weight should be assigned to the cluster; 2) If the accurate degree of a cluster's decision matrix is larger, then a larger weight should be assigned to the cluster.</p><p>First, the proportion of decision makers in a cluster C r is calculated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">P rop r = |C r | q , r = 1, 2, . . . , N.<label>(24)</label></formula><p>Moreover, the inaccuracy index of the r-th cluster's decision matrix is calculated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">Inacc r = 1 mn n i=1 m j=1 T (z r ij ) = - 1 log 2 (g + 1)mn n i=1 m j=1 g t=0 ᾱr ij,t log 2 ᾱr ij,t , r = 1, 2, . . . , N.<label>(25)</label></formula><p>Remark 6. In Eq. (25), T (z r ij ) denotes the inaccuracy degree of the LDA zr ij and the inaccuracy index Inacc r is the average of all T (z r ij ), i ∈ I, j ∈ J, r = 1, 2, . . . , N . It is easy to prove that Inacc r ∈ [0, 1], r = 1, 2, . . . , N . Based on each Inacc r , the normalized accuracy index of a cluster's decision matrix can be calculated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">Acc r = 1 -Inacc r N r=1 (1 -Inacc r ) , r = 1, 2, . . . , N.<label>(26)</label></formula><p>By considering the proportion and normalized accuracy index of each cluster C r , a collective index can be defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">P A r = ηP rop r + (1 -η)Acc r , r = 1, 2, . . . , N,<label>(27)</label></formula><p>where η ∈ [0, 1] denotes the compromise between P rop r and Acc r , r = 1, 2, . . . , N . Based on the above analysis, a cluster with a larger collective index should be assigned a larger weight. Keeping this idea in mind, in what follows, it is proposed a proportion and normalized accuracy index induced ordered weighted averaging operator (PA-IOWA) of balanced LDAs based on the induced ordered weighted aggregation (IOWA) operator <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>.</p><p>Definition 18. let Zr = (z r ij ) n×m be an LDA-based decision matrix, r = 1, 2, . . . , N , then the PA-IOWA operator of { Z1 , Z2 , . . . , ZN } is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">f (⟨z 1 ij , P A 1 ⟩, ⟨z 2 ij , P A 2 ⟩, . . . , ⟨z N ij , P A N ⟩) = DAWA v (z σ(1) ij , z σ(2) ij , . . . , z σ(N ) ij ),<label>(28)</label></formula><p>where v = (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v N ) T is the associated weighting vector such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">N r=1 v r = 1, v r ∈ [0, 1], and σ : {1, 2 . . . , N } → {1, 2, . . . , N } is a permutation such that P A σ(r) ≥ P A σ(r+1) , ∀r = 1, 2, . . . , N -1, i.e., ⟨z σ(r) ij , P A σ(r) ⟩ is a 2-tuple in which P A σ(r) is the r-th largest value in {P A 1 , P A 2 , . . . , P A N }.</formula><p>Here, P A r is the order-inducing variable and z r ij is the argument variable.</p><p>In order to aggregate decision matrices of the clusters using the PA-IOWA operator, the key problem to be solved is how to determine the associated weighting vector v = (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v N ) T . Keeping in mind the idea that a cluster with a larger P A r value will be assigned a larger weight and motivated by the quantifier guided linguistic OWA operators <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>, the weighting vector v = (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v N ) T can be determined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">v r = Q r h=1 P A σ(h) N h=1 P A h -Q r-1 h=1 P A σ(h) N h=1 P A h , r = 1, 2, . . . , N,<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where Q(x) = x γ (0 &lt; γ &lt; 1) is a regular increasing monotone quantifier.</p><p>It is obvious that when</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">Q(x) = x γ (0 &lt; γ &lt; 1), we have v 1 ≥ v 2 ≥ . . . ≥ v N .</formula><p>Usually, when the importance of the cluster with the largest P A r value is emphasized, γ should be set as a value that approximates 0. However, when the differences of the importance among different clusters are not too large, γ can be set a value that approximates 1.</p><p>Applying the PA-IOWA operator, each cluster's LDA decision matrix can be aggregated into a collective one, which is denoted by Z = (z ij ) n×m , where zij = {⟨s B t , ᾱij,t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g} is an LDA derived by Definition 18, i ∈ I, j ∈ J.</p><p>Once the collective decision matrix is derived, the selection process is implemented. By applying the DAWA operator, one can aggregate the attribute values to obtain the collective assessment of each alternative.</p><p>If the weighting vector of attributes is known, the col-lective assessment of the i-th alternative, denoted by zi = {⟨s B t , ᾱi,t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g}, can be calculated, where ᾱi,t = m j=1 w j ᾱij,t , t = 0, 1, . . . , g, i ∈ I. (</p><p>If the weighting vector of attributes is unknown, the maximum deviation approach proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> can be used to determine the weights, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">w j = n i=1 n l=1 g t=0 t(ᾱ ij,t -ᾱlj,t ) n j=1 n i=1 n l=1 g t=0 t(ᾱ ij,t -ᾱlj,t ) , j ∈ J. (<label>31</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_74">)</formula><p>Afterwards, by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_72">30</ref>), each z i can also be calculated, i ∈ I.</p><p>As each z i is an LDA which can also be considered as a discrete random variable, the dominance degree-based approach is used to rank alternatives <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. Let p ij be the dominance degree to which A i is preferred to A j , then</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">p ij = g t=0 t l=0 ᾱi,t ᾱj,l -0.5 g t=0 ᾱi,t ᾱj,t , i, j ∈ I. (<label>32</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_76">)</formula><p>One can prove that 0 ≤ p ij ≤ 1, p ij +p ji = 1 and p ii = 0.5, i, j ∈ I.</p><p>Based on the idea of the PROMETHEE II method <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>, a popular method for ranking in multicriteria decision making, it is defined the positive outranking flow Φ + (A i ) and the negative outranking flow Φ -(A i ) of each A i as</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">Φ + (A i ) = 1 n -1 j=1,j̸ =i p ij , i ∈ I,<label>(33)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_78">Φ -(A i ) = 1 n -1 j=1,j̸ =i p ji , i ∈ I. (<label>34</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_79">)</formula><p>Finally, the net outranking flow is calculated by calculating the difference between Φ + (A i ) and Φ -(A i ) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">Φ(A i ) = Φ + (A i ) -Φ -(A i ), i ∈ I (<label>35</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_81">)</formula><p>As p ij + pji = 1, then Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_80">35</ref>) can be further written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">Φ(A i ) = 1 n -1 j=1,j̸ =i 2p ij -1, i ∈ I. (<label>36</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">)</formula><p>By ranking each Φ(A i ) in descending order, the ranking of alternatives can be obtained, i.e., the larger the value of Φ(A i ), the better the alternative A i .</p><p>4) Retranslation process: For an MAGDM problem with multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information, if the purpose is for ranking alternatives, the procedure will terminate after ranking alternatives based on the net outranking flow of each alternative. However, for some practical decision making problems, decision makers may want to know the collective assessments over alternatives, i.e., it is necessary to provide interpretable results to decision makers. In order to do so, the collective assessments over alternatives should be retranslated to assessments defined on linguistic term sets used by each decision maker. In this paper we retranslate the collective assessments of alternatives to HLDs defined on linguistic term sets used by each decision maker.</p><p>For each decision maker d k , we can first transform each alternative's collective assessment zi = {⟨s B t , ᾱi,t ⟩|t = 0, 1, . . . , g} into an unbalanced LDA z k i defined on S (k) by Algorithm 3, i ∈ I, k ∈ K. For each z k i , the corresponding HLD H k i can be further obtained by Algorithm 1, i ∈ I, k ∈ K.</p><p>The procedure of the proposed approach is summarized below.</p><p>Step 1: Invite decision makers to provide their decision matrices X k , k ∈ K over each alternative with respect to all attributes.</p><p>Step 2: Transform all decision matrices X k into LDA decision matrices Z k by Algorithm 2.</p><p>Step 3: Use the LDA-based clustering algorithm (Algorithm 4) to cluster decision makers into N clusters {C 1 , C 2 , . . . , C N }.</p><p>Step 4: For each cluster C r , calculate its decision matrix Zr = (z r ij ) n×m by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_63">23</ref>). Afterwards, calculate the value of P A r by Eqs. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_64">24</ref>) -( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_67">27</ref>), r = 1, 2, . . . , N .</p><p>Step 5: Aggregate all clusters' decision matrices into a collective one Z = (z ij ) n×m by the PA-IOWA operator.</p><p>Step 6: If the weight of attributes is known, go to Step 7;</p><p>Otherwise, use Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_73">31</ref>) to determine the weight vector of attributes.</p><p>Step 7: Aggregate all attribute values to obtain the collective assessments of each alternative zi by Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_72">30</ref>), i ∈ I.</p><p>Step 8: Rank alternatives through calculating Φ(A i ) by Eqs. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_75">32</ref>) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref>, i ∈ I.</p><p>Step 9: If necessary, provide interpretable results H k i to each d k , k ∈ K, i ∈ I. In particular, for each d k , use Algorithm 3 to transform each zi into an LDA z k i defined on S (k) and then use Algorithm 1 to represent each z k i as an HLD H k i , i ∈ I, k ∈ K.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Comparisons and Discussions</head><p>In this subsection, the advantages of the proposed multiattribute LGDM approach are analyzed through comparisons with previous studies.</p><p>In the literature, some proposals have been devoted to deal with LGDM approach with linguistic information, which are further summarized as follows.</p><p>(1) In <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, Liu et al. proposed a two-layer weight determination method for large-scale MAGDM in linguistic environments based on the 2-tuple linguistic model. The core contribution of this study is the development of a minimized variance model and an entropy weight model to determine the expert weights in the cluster and the cluster weights, respectively. Liu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> developed an approach to LGDM in which decision makers from multiple groups were involved in the decision making problem. In this approach, a subjective and objective weighting method was proposed to determine the weights of each group and the alternatives were ranked using 1063-6706 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TFUZZ.2019.2949758, IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems the dominance degree-based approach. Moreover, Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> developed a method to address linguistic LGDM problems with multiple groups based on the concept of probabilistic linguistic term set. In this study, a consistency and consensusbased model was developed to objectively determine the weights of the groups, and the dominance degree-based approach was used to rank alternatives. Xiao et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref> developed a personalized individual semantics-based consensus model to handle LGDM problems with linguistic distribution preference relations, in which the numerical scales of each individual linguistic term set were first generated and some optimization models were then established to help decision makers reach consensus. For LGDM problems with probabilistic linguistic terms sets, Ma et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref> proposed an approach to model the reliability of decision makers based on evidential reasoning and the linguistic granulation optimization method.</p><p>(2) Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> developed an approach to manage multigranular balanced linguistic information in multiattribute LGDM problems, in which decision makers' multigranular balanced linguistic information were first represented by multigranular balanced LDAs. To obtain the collective decision matrix, multigranular balanced LDAs were further fused based on the linguistic computational model proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Finally, the collective assessments of alternatives were obtained by applying the DAWA operator on the collective decision matrix. Yu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> proposed an approach to LGDM with multigranular unbalanced linguistic information, in which multigranular unbalanced linguistic information were represented by an LDA defined on a virtual linguistic term set and then the TODIM method was extended to rank alternatives by considering the psychological behavior of decision makers.</p><p>(3) Wu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref> investigated linguistic LGDM problems under social network environment, in which linguistic information were first transformed into interval type-2 fuzzy sets, and then a social network analysis and TOPIS-based approach was developed to determine the weights of decision makers and to rank alternatives. and consensus in linguistic distribution large-scale group decision making Through comparison with the aforementioned studies, the proposed approach presents the following advantages.</p><p>(1) First, existing studies mainly focus on LGDM with linguistic expressions elicited by a simple linguistic term, which cannot be used to model the situations when decision makers may have some hesitancy when expressing their linguistic assessments. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study that deal with multiattribute LGDM problems with HFLTSs. Moreover, in most of previous studies, it is assumed that linguistic term sets used by decision makers to express linguistic information are balanced. However, the proposed approach can manage hesitant fuzzy linguistic information based on multigranular unbalanced linguistic term sets. As a result, the proposed approach provides a more flexible and general way for decision makers to express linguistic preferences in LGDM problems.</p><p>(2) In <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, the LDA is used as the tool to represent group assessments, which keeps the maximum information elicited by decision makers in initial stages of the decision process.</p><p>In a similar manner, this study transforms multigranular unbalanced HFLTSs into balanced LDAs, which also preserves the maximum information elicited by decision makers compared with the studies in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>. Although LDAs or probabilistic linguistic terms sets are used in Xiao et al and Ma et al's approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref>, these approaches are unsuitable for the LGDM problem considered in this paper. Moreover, all these approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref> cannot be used deal with LGDM problems with multigranular or unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information. Finally, in this paper, an LDA-based clustering algorithm is developed to cluster decision makers and the PA-IOWA operator is used to aggregate linguistic distribution decision matrices of different clusters, which takes into account both the proportion of decision makers in each cluster and the accuracy index of each cluster's decision matrix and can provide more information when determining the weights of clusters.</p><p>(3) Lastly, one can find that the approaches proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref> aim to obtain a ranking of alternatives, which cannot provide interpretable linguistic results to decision makers. However, the proposed approach represents the collective assessments of alternatives (balanced LDAs) by HLDs defined on each decision maker's initial linguistic term set, which are consisted of some disjointed HFLTSs and their support degrees to the LDAs. Therefore, the proposed approach follows the paradigm of CW, which can provide both ranking of alternatives and interpretable linguistic results to decision makers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. NUMERICAL EXAMPLE</head><p>In this section, a numerical example for subway line selection adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref> is provided to demonstrate the proposed approach.</p><p>Suppose that the government of a city in China intends to add a new subway line to the public transportation system. After initial discussions, four alternative plans x 1 , x  <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">III</ref>. Without loss of generality, the numerical scale of each linguistic term in S (k) (k = 1, 2, . . . , 20) is the corresponding canonical characteristic value (CCV) <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref>, which are also shown in Tables I -III.   Using these linguistic term sets, the hesitant fuzzy linguistic decision matrices are provided by the stakeholders as X k , k = 1, 2, . . . , 20. For instance, X 1 and X 7 are shown below and the others are included in Appendix B in the supplementary materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSISONS</head><p>In this paper, an approach to multiattribute LGDM with multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information is presented. The main contributions of the paper are as follows.</p><p>First, it is proposed an algorithm to represent an LDA using an HLD consisting of some disjointed HFLTSs, which can provide not only the overall assessment using some disjointed HFLTSs, but also the degree to which each HFLTS supports the LDA. Such representation offers a new way to provide intuitively interpretable results for an LDA.</p><p>Second, to facilitate the fusion of multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information, this paper develops an algorithm to transform an unbalanced HFLTS into a balanced LDA. To represent the aggregation result of multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information using the linguistic term sets used by decision makers, another algorithm is developed to transform a balanced LDA into an unbalanced LDA. The two algorithms lay good foundations for managing multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information in multiattribute LGDM problems.</p><p>Third, an approach to multiattribute LGDM with multigranular unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic information is proposed. In the proposed approach, an LDA-based clustering algorithm is devised to cluster decision makers and a PA-IOWA operator is proposed to fuse each cluster's decision matrix. The collective assessments of alternatives are represented by HLDs defined on each decision maker's initial linguistic term set to provide interpretable results.</p><p>Even though this paper proposes a novel approach to multiattribute LGDM with multigranular unbalanced HFLTSs, there are still some problems which need to be further studied:</p><p>1063-6706 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information. This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TFUZZ.2019.2949758, IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems 14 1) In the proposed LGDM approach, only selection process is discussed and consensus reaching process is not considered <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref>, which plays an important role in LGDM. As a result, it is essential to study consensus reaching process for multiattribute LGDM with multigranular unbalanced HFLTSs based on the results reported in this paper.</p><p>2) The type-2 fuzzy envelope was recently proposed to depict the uncertainty and fuzziness of an HFLTS <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref>. Therefore, utilizing the methodology of type-2 fuzzy sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[62]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">[66]</ref> to manage multigranular HFLTSs constitutes another interesting direction for future research.</p><p>3) The proposed approach is only compared with previous studies from a theoretical perspective, since previous studies cannot deal with the same type of decision making problems and a computational comparison is not fair. Therefore, it is necessary to carry out computational comparison with recent proposals in future.</p><p>4) Finally, it is also interesting to develop a decision support system to deal with practical LGDM problems.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>5 ) 6 × 3 :</head><label>563</label><figDesc>(0.7 -0.5) = 0. Therefore,α 2 = 0 + (1 -0) × 0.3 = 0.3, α 3 = 0 + 0 × 0.3 = 0.StepLet h = 4, then temp = 4 × (1 -0)/6 + 0 = 2/3. As N S (k) (s k 2 ) = 0.5 ≤ temp ≤ 0.7 = N S (k) (s k 3 ), we have i h = 2 and β k i h = 4 × (1 -0) + 6(0 -0.5) 6 × (0.7 -0.5) = 5/6.Therefore, α 2 = 0.3 + (1 -5/6) × 0.4 = 11/30, α 3 = 0 + 5/6 × 0.4 = 1/3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>By Eq. (8), we have that H = {s 0 , s 1 } has the largest support degree 0.59 (i.e., 0.24+0.35) to m. The collective support degree is 0.59, which is less than 1. Therefore, all HFLTSs which contain s 0 , s 1 are removed from H S N , and we have H S N = {{s 3 }, {s 4 }, {s 3 , s 4 }}. Again, by Eq. (</figDesc><table /><note><p>{s 1 }, {s 3 }, {s 4 }, {s 0 , s 1 }, {s 3 , s 4 }}.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>is calculated by Definition 13, h = 0, 1, . . . , g and w = (β B 0 , β B 1 , . . . , β B g ) T . According to Definition 14, Algorithm 3 is developed and included in Appendix A of the supplementary materials. Example 2. Let m = {⟨s B 3 , 0.3⟩, ⟨s B 4 , 0.4⟩, ⟨s B 5 , 0.3⟩} be an LDA defined on a balanced linguistic term set S B = {s B</figDesc><table /><note><p><p>0 , s B 1 , . . . , s B 6 } and S (k) = {s k 0 , s k 1 , . . . , s k</p>4 } be an unbalanced linguistic term set whose numerical scale is defined in Example 1.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TFUZZ.2019.2949758, IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Decision matrices expressed by unbalanced HFLTSs</cell></row><row><cell>Unification</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Process</cell><cell>Algorithm 2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Decision matrices represented by balanced LDAs</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Algorithm 4 and Eq. (23)</cell></row><row><cell>Clustering</cell><cell>Decision matrices for each cluster of decision makers represented by</cell></row><row><cell>Process</cell><cell>balanced LDAs</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PA-IOWA operator</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>The collective decision matrix represented by balanced LDAs</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Eq. (30)</cell></row><row><cell>Aggregation &amp; Selection Process</cell><cell>The collective assessments of alternatives represented by balanced LDAs</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Algorithms</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>The ranking of alternatives</cell><cell>1 and 3</cell></row><row><cell>Retranslation</cell><cell>The collective assessments of alternatives represented by unbalanced</cell></row><row><cell>Process</cell><cell>HLDs</cell></row></table><note><p>1063-6706 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TFUZZ.2019.2949758, IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</figDesc><table /><note><p>1063-6706 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2 , x 3 , x 4 are determined for further selection. A committee which consists of 20 stakeholders from different areas (d 1 , d 2 , . . . , d 20 ) are invited to select the best plan with respect to four attributes including U 1 : social impact, U 2 : environment impact, U 3 : project budget and U 4 : technical feasibility. Due to the fuzziness and imprecise of stakeholders' knowledge, the 20 stakeholders use HFLTSs to elicit their assessments over the four plans. Moreover, different linguistic term sets are used by the 20 stakeholders. In particular, the stakeholders d 1 , d 2 , . . . , d 6 use an unbalanced linguistic term set S (k) = {s k 0 , s k 1 , . . . , s k 8 }, k = 1, 2, . . . , 6 whose semantics are described by trapezoidal fuzzy numbers on [0, 1], as shown in Table I; The stakeholders d 7 , d 8 , . . . , d 12 use an unbalanced linguistic term set S (k) = {s k 0 , s k 1 , . . . , s k 4 }, k = 7, 8, . . . , 12 whose semantics are described by trapezoidal fuzzy numbers on [0, 1], as shown in Table II; The stakeholders d 13 , d 14 , . . . , d 20 use an unbalanced linguistic term set S (k) = {s k 0 , s k 1 , . . . , s k 6 }, k = 13, 14, . . . , 20, whose semantics are described by trapezoidal fuzzy numbers on [0, 1] shown in Table</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>TABLE I THE</head><label>I</label><figDesc>SEMANTICS AND NUMERICAL SCALES OF THE LINGUISTIC TERMS IN S (k) , k = 1, 2, . . . , 6</figDesc><table><row><cell>Linguistic terms</cell><cell>Semantics</cell><cell>NS</cell></row><row><cell>s k 0 : extremely poor s k 1 : very poor s k 2 : poor s k 3 : slightly poor s k 4 : fair s k 5 : slightly good s k 6 : good s k 7 : very good s k 8 : extremely good</cell><cell cols="2">T (0, 0, 0, 0) T (0, 0.05, 0.15, 0.2) T (0.15, 0.2, 0.25, 0.3) 0.225 0 0.1 T (0.25, 0.3, 0.4, 0.45) 0.35 T (0.4, 0.45, 0.55, 0.6) 0.5 T (0.55, 0.6, 0.7, 0.75) 0.65 T (0.7, 0.75, 0.8, 0.85) 0.775 T (0.8, 0.85, 0.95, 1) 0.9 T (1, 1, 1, 1) 1</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>TABLE II THE</head><label>II</label><figDesc>SEMANTICS AND NUMERICAL SCALES OF THE LINGUISTIC TERMS IN S (k) , k = 7, 8, . . . , 12</figDesc><table><row><cell>Linguistic terms</cell><cell>Semantics</cell><cell>NS</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">s k 0 : poor s k 1 : slightly poor T (0.2, 0.32, 0.38, 0.52) 0.35 T (0, 0, 0, 0) 0 s k T (0.3, 0.45, 0.55, 0.65) 0.5 2 : fair s k T (0.5, 0.6, 0.8, 0.95) 0.7 3 : slightly good s k 4 : good T (1, 1, 1, 1) 1</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>TABLE III THE</head><label>III</label><figDesc>SEMANTICS AND NUMERICAL SCALES OF THE LINGUISTIC TERMS IN S (k) , k = 13, 14, . . . , 20</figDesc><table><row><cell>Linguistic terms</cell><cell>Semantics</cell><cell>NS</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">s k 0 : very poor s k 1 : poor s k 2 : slightly poor T (0.2, 0.3, 0.35, 0.45) 0.325 T (0, 0, 0, 0) 0 T (0, 0.1, 0.2, 0.3) 0.15 s k T (0.35, 0.4, 0.6, 0.6) 0.5 3 : fair s k 4 : slightly good T (0.6, 0.65, 0.7, 0.75) 0.675 s k T (0.7, 0.8, 0.9, 1) 0.85 5 : good s k 6 : very good T (1, 1, 1, 1) 1</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Due to page limitation, the further detailed description of these algorithms are included in Appendix A of the supplementary materials</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) under Grant 71971039, Grant 71501023 and Grant 71771034, in part by the Funds for Creative Research Groups of China under Grant 71421001, in part by the Key Program of the NSFC under Grant 71731003, in part by the Scientific and Technological Innovation Foundation of Dalian under Grant 2018J11CY009 and Grant 2018JQ69, in part by the Research Funds for Young Scholars from the Education Department of Liaoning Province under Grant LN2017QN027, and in part by the Spanish Research Projects under Grants PGC2018-099402-B-I00 and TIN2015-66524-P.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>{s 1  5 } {s 1  2 , s 1  3 } {s 1  7 } {s 1  4 , s 1  5 , s 1  6 } {s 1  3 , s 1  4 } {s 1  4 } {s 1  7 } {s 1  6 } {s 1  6 , s 1  7 } {s 1  3 , s 1  4 } {s 1  4 , s 1  5 } {s 1  4 } {s 1  3 } {s 1  6 , s 1 7 } {s 1  2 } {s 1  5 }    </p><p>{s 7  2 , s 7  3 } {s 7 0 , s 7  1 , s 7  2 } {s 7  4 } {s 7  2 , s 7  3 } {s 7  1 , s 7  2 } {s 7  2 } {s 7  3 , s 7  4 } {s 7  3 } {s 7  3 , s 7  4 } {s 7  1 , s 7  2 } {s 7  2 } {s 7  1 , s 7  2 , s 7  3 } {s 7  1 , s 7  2 } {s 7  3 , s 7  4 } {s 7 0 , s 7  1 , s 7  2 } {s 7  2 , s 7  3 }</p><p>{s 15  4 } {s 15  1 , s 15  2 , s 15  3 } {s 15  1 } {s 15  6 } {s 15  5 , s 15  6 } {s 15  3 } {s 15  2 , s 15  3 } {s 15 0 , s 15  1 } {s 15  3 , s 15  4 , s 15  5 } {s 15  2 , s 15  3 } {s 15  5 , s 15  6 } {s 15  2 , s 15  3 } {s 15  3 } {s 15  3 , s 15  4 } {s 15  5 } {s 15  4 }</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>   </head><p>In what follows, the proposed approach is employed to select the best subway line plan.</p><p>Without loss of generality, let us assume that the basic linguistic term set is a balanced linguistic term set S (B) = {s B 0 , s B 1 , . . . , s B 9 }. By Algorithm 2, all decision matrices X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X 20 are transformed into LDA-based decision matrices Z 1 , Z 2 , . . . , Z 20 , respectively. Due to space limitation, only Z 1 , Z 7 and Z 15 are demonstrated in Tables IV -VI. Also, let us assume that the number of clusters is 3. By applying the LDA-based clustering algorithm on decision matrices    20 , the 20 stakeholders are clustered as follows:</p><p>By Eq. ( <ref type="formula">23</ref>), the decision matrix of the clusters C 1 , C 2 and C 3 can be calculated, as shown in Tables VII -IX.</p><p>The proportion of decision makers in each cluster C r can be calculated by Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> as P rop 1 = 0.4, P rop 2 = 0.25, P rop 3 = 0.35.</p><p>For each cluster C r , based on each decision matrix Zr , the normalized accuracy index of its decision matrix is calculated by Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> as Acc 1 = 0.3293, Acc 2 = 0.3503, Acc 3 = 0.3204.</p><p>Let the parameter η = 0.5, then the proportion and normalized accuracy index is further calculated as P A 1 = 0.3647, P A 2 = 0.3001, P A 3 = 0.3352.</p><p>Let Q(x) = x 1/2 . By Eq. ( <ref type="formula">29</ref>), the weighting vector v = (v1, v2, v3) T associated with the PA-IOWA operator is further calculated as v = (0.6039, 0.1634, 0.2327) T .</p><p>Applying the PA-IOWA operator yields the collective decision matrix Z, as shown in Table <ref type="table">X</ref>.</p><p>Here, the attribute weights are unknown. By Eq. ( <ref type="formula">31</ref>), the weight vector of attributes is obtained as w = (0.2636, 0.3492, 0.2254, 0.1618) T .</p><p>By Eq. ( <ref type="formula">30</ref>), the collective assessments of each plan are further calculated, as shown in Table <ref type="table">XI</ref>.</p><p>By Eq. ( <ref type="formula">32</ref>), the dominance degree to which Ai is preferred to Aj, i.e., pij is calculated. Let P = (pij)4×4, then we have P =    0.5 0.4481 0.4828 0.4577 0.5519 0.5 0.5364 0.5108 0.5172 0.4636 0.5 0.4693 0.5423 0.4892 0.5307 0.5    By Eq. ( <ref type="formula">36</ref>), the net outranking flow for each plan is calculated as Φ1 = -0.0743, Φ2 = 0.0660, Φ3 = -0.0332, Φ4 = 0.0415, which results in a ranking A2 ≻ A4 ≻ A3 ≻ A1. Therefore, the plan A2 should be selected as the optimal alternative.</p><p>Finally, let the maximum number of simple terms for an HFLTS be 3, then collective assessments of alternatives can be represented 1063-6706 (c) 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See http://www.ieee.org/publications_standards/publications/rights/index.html for more information.</p><p>This article has been accepted for publication in a future issue of this journal, but has not been fully edited. Content may change prior to final publication.      as some HLDs, as shown in Tables XII -XIV. For instance, for the decision maker d7, the collective assessment of A2 can be interpreted as two CLEs "at least fair" and "at most slightly poor", the support degree of "at least fair" is 0.8094, and the support degree of "at most slightly poor" is 0.1906. Clearly, these results are more interpretable to decision makers.    </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multi-Objective Group Decision Making. Methods, Software and Applications with Fuzzy Set Techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ruan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Imperial College Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A consensus model for group decision making with incomplete fuzzy preference relations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Herrera-Viedma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Alonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chiclana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="863" to="877" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A peer-to-peer dynamic adaptive consensus reaching model for the group ahp decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">250</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing the performance of classical consensus models in large scale group decision making: A comparative study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Labella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Soft Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="690" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Missing values estimation and consensus building for incomplete hesitant fuzzy preference relations with multiplicative consistency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consistency and consensus models for group decision-making with uncertain 2-tuple linguistic preference relations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Syst. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2572" to="2587" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus reaching in social network group decision making: Research paradigms and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fujita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chiclana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Herrera-Viedma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Knowl. Based Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">162</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A social network based approach for consensus achievement in multiperson decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ureña</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chiclana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Melançon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Herrera-Viedma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clusters in a group: Decision making in the vector space formulation of the analytic hierarchy process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zahir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Oper. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="620" to="634" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A partial binary tree DEA-DA cyclic classification model for decision makers in complex multi-attribute large-group interval-valued intuitionistic fuzzy decisionmaking problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="130" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sparse representation-based intuitionistic fuzzy clustering approach to find the group intra-relations and group leaders for large-scale decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="559" to="573" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A consensus model to detect and manage noncooperative behaviors in large-scale group decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Palomares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="516" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus model for multi-criteria large-group emergency decision making considering non-cooperative behaviors and minority opinions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-H</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-J</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Decis. Support Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A consensus model for large-scale linguistic group decision making with a feedback recommendation based on clustered personalized individual semantics and opposing consensus groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A large scale consensus reaching process managing group hesitation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Labella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Tré</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Knowl. Based Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A linguistic large group decision making method based on the cloud model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3314" to="3326" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A consensus model for large-scale group decision making with hesitant fuzzy information and changeable clusters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="231" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A two-layer weight determination method for complex multi-attribute large-group decisionmaking experts in a linguistic environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="165" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method for large group decisionmaking based on evaluation information provided by participators from multiple groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z.-P</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing multigranular linguistic distribution assessments in large-scale multiattribute group decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst. Man Cybern. -Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3063" to="3076" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lasca: A large scale group decision support system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Carvalho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vivacqua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Souza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P J</forename><surname>Medeiros</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Univers. Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="275" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MENTOR: A graphical monitoring tool of preferences evolution in large-scale group decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Palomares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Knowl. Based Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An analysis of symbolic linguistic computing models in decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Gen. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fuzzy logic = computing with words</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Zadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An overview on fuzzy modelling of complex linguistic preferences in decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Labella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The problem of linguistic approximation in clinical decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Degani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bortolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Approx. Reason</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uncertain linguistic aggregation operators based approach to multiple attribute group decision making under uncertain linguistic environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A 2-tuple fuzzy linguistic representation model for computing with words</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="746" to="752" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Type-2 fuzzistics for symmetric interval type-2 fuzzy sets: Part 1, forward problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="781" to="792" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computing the numerical scale of the linguistic term set for the 2-tuple fuzzy linguistic representation model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1366" to="1378" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hesitant fuzzy linguistic term sets for decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hesitant fuzzy linguistic term sets for linguistic decision making: Current developments, issues and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-J</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model based on linguistic 2-tuples for dealing with multigranular hierarchical linguistic contexts in multiexpert decision-making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst., Man, Cybern. B, Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="234" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information granule formation via the concept of uncertainty-based information with interval type-2 fuzzy sets representation and Takagi-Sugeno-Kang consequents optimized with cuckoo search</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sanchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Soft Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="602" to="609" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A generalized type-2 fuzzy granular approach with applications to aerospace</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cervantes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Soria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sanchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">354</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new linguistic computational model based on discrete fuzzy numbers for computing with words</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Massanet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Riera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Torrens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Herrera-Viedma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">258</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fuzzy linguistic methodology to deal with unbalanced linguistic term sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Herrera-Viedma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="370" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing the consensus in group decision making in an unbalanced fuzzy linguistic context with incomplete information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cabrerizo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pérez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Herrera-Viedma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Knowl. Based Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus-based group decision making under multi-granular unbalanced 2-tuple linguistic preference relations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Group Decis. Negot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A TODIM-based approach to largescale group decision making with multi-granular unbalanced linguistic information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 2017 IEEE Int. Conf. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<meeting>of the 2017 IEEE Int. Conf. Fuzzy Syst<address><addrLine>Naples, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="872" to="879" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Connecting the linguistic hierarchy and the numerical scale for the 2-tuple linguistic model and its use to deal with hesitant unbalanced linguistic information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">367</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">368</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extended TODIM for multicriteria group decision making based on unbalanced hesitant fuzzy linguistic term sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Ind. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="316" to="328" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consistency and consensus measures for linguistic preference relations based on distribution assessments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-granular unbalanced linguistic distribution assessments with interval symbolic proportions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Knowl. Based Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalizing linguistic distributions in hesitant decision context</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">70985</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Negation function based semantics for ordered linguistic labels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Torra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. of Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="975" to="988" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A group decision making model dealing with comparative linguistic expressions based on hesitant fuzzy linguistic term sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">241</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Group decision making based on linguistic distributions and hesitant assessments: Maximizing the support degree with an accuracy constraint</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pattern Recognition with Fuzzy Objective function Algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bezdek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Induced ordered weighted averaging operators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Yager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Filev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst. Man Cybern. Part B-Cybern</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifier guided aggregation using OWA operators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Yager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Note-a preference ranking organisation method (the PROMETHEE method for multiple criteria decisionmaking)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vincke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Manag. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="647" to="656" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel probabilistic linguistic approach for large-scale group decision making with incomplete weight information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2245" to="2256" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Managing personalized individual semantics and consensus in linguistic distribution large-scale group decision making</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Fusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A probabilistic linguistic group decision-making method from a reliability perspective based on evidential reasoning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TSMC.2018.2815716</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Syst. Man Cybern. -Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An interval type-2 fuzzy TOPSIS model for large scale group decision making problems with social network information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">432</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="392" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel consensus model for multi-attribute large-scale group decision making based on comprehensive behavior classification and adaptive weight updating</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Palomares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R.-X</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Knowl. Based Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new version of 2-tuple fuzzy linguistic representation model for computing with words</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="445" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">a hybrid group decision making framework for achieving agreed solutions based on stable opinions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">490</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus modelling on intervalvalued fuzzy preference relations with normal distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="706" to="715" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Type-2 fuzzy envelope of hesitant fuzzy linguistic term set: a new representation model of comparative linguistic expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Qin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TFUZZ.2019.2898155</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Fuzzy Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized type-2 fuzzy systems for controlling a mobile robot and a performance comparison with interval type-2 and type-1 fuzzy systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sanchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Expert Syst. Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5904" to="5914" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Type-2 fuzzy logic aggregation of multiple fuzzy controllers for airplane flight control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cervantes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">324</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparative study of type-1 fuzzy logic systems, interval type-2 fuzzy logic systems and generalized type-2 fuzzy logic systems in control problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Amador-Angulo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Garcia-Valdez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">354</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative analysis of noise robustness of type 2 fuzzy logic controllers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ontiveros-Robles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Melin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kybernetika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BBO optimization of an ekf for interval type-2 fuzzy sliding mode control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Medjghou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ghanai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chafaa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Comput. Intell. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="770" to="789" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
